<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par36">Beyond the mechanisms of the process, substantive questions about what flood protection for the neighborhood should look like, and tradeoffs about what to spend limited funding on were also seen as up for deliberation. Within funding constraints and supported by professional landscape architects, participants were able to discuss design alternatives among themselves. At the same meeting, Naomi reconstructed how the iterative design process of the Rebuild By Design competition shaped the expectations of activists on small and big issues, noting the open-endedness of the public deliberations in the style heralded by Habermasian<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn5">5</xref> democratic theorists:<disp-quote><p id="Par37">&#8220;And it was more than just a process to think about park programming, it was also a conversation about resiliency. So more than just how to re-design our 1939 Robert Moses park, and where to put playgrounds, and ballfields, and barbeque pits. But also to think about where should the flood protection be, and how should it work [&#8230;] So those were the expectations of that process.&#8221;</p></disp-quote>The input of participants is visible in scanned documents, pictures, and public reports from meetings and workshops produced during the design phase. A report of findings from a workshop in July 2015, for example, shows a large paper map of East River Park and depicts how workshop participants pasted post-it notes and wrote comments on the map. On the topic of &#8220;improving access to the park,&#8221; participants expressed, on colored post-it notes: &#8220;safe and inviting access to East River Park is the community&#8217;s number one priority,&#8221; &#8220;ensure entrances remain wheelchair accessible,&#8221; and &#8220;Build a new bridge at Grand Street and rehabilitate the Delancey Street bridge!&#8221; Four months later, in September, staff from the Mayor&#8217;s Office of Resilience presented a number of alternative designs of several different entrances to the park and sought the opinions of participants about which ones were preferred. A month after that, the official design included new park access points that reflected the input of participants. People involved in these workshops and meetings reported to be satisfied by how the city was carrying out the process.</p>