<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0030">Distributing the carbon budget using climate justice criteria has been proposed to address fairness in mitigation efforts (<xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Gach, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Bel and Rosell, 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Chakravarty et al., 2009</xref>). Nonetheless, distinct sectors are treated differently by mitigation policy. For example, deforestation and logging have been subject to decades of conservation efforts and increasingly strict regulation for emissions mitigation (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Garc&#237;a-L&#243;pez, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Osborne, 2015</xref>). Yet, given the relative size of the population involved, it is likely that their per capita emissions are less than the global elite who maintain high-emissions lifestyles with luxury activities like frequent air travel among others (<xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Schlosberg, 2019</xref>). A single flight could potentially emit more per person in a day than the average logger in Mexico might do in a year, whose livelihood is also at stake (<xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Jurjonas &amp; Seekamp, 2019</xref>). Therefore, new messaging is needed to appropriately value air travel relative to more commonly promoted green behaviors like recycling, plant-based diets, or driving an electric car (<xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Wynes &amp; Nicholas, 2017</xref>), while rural activities in developing countries need to be contextualized through fairness. In this opinion, per capita emissions of generally more regulated activities like forest use and logging (<xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Kashwan, 2017</xref>) are compared to the entirely unregulated behavior of air travel (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Higham et al., 2019</xref>), to raise questions about why the forest users of developing countries are subject to disproportionate regulation.</p>