<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par30">Superstorm Sandy in 2012 claimed the lives of 44 people, caused $33 billion in economic damages, and disproportionately cut off power, heat, and hot water to public housing (Graham et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2016</xref>; New York City Mayor&#8217;s Office, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2019</xref>; Schmeltz et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2013</xref>), As a response, the city triggered a long-term strategy to adapt its infrastructure &#8211; built in the twentieth century under the assumption of a stable climate &#8211; to future climate change impacts. The two mayors in office since the storm have committed to a vision of the city rebuilt stronger and tougher (New York City Mayor&#8217;s Office, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2019</xref>). Since then, the rhetoric of climate resilience has dominated New York climate politics. Mayor Bloomberg&#8217;s office rolled out over 200 initiatives under the label of resilience at a total price tag of nearly $20 billion (New York City Mayor&#8217;s Office, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2019</xref>), making New York the global leader in both spending (Georgeson et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2016</xref>) and number of planned initiatives (Araos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2016</xref>) to protect itself from climate impacts. At a 2013 press conference unveiling the city&#8217;s first flagship climate planning document, Mayor Bloomberg articulated his particular definition of resilience as armoring up the coast: &#8220;As New Yorkers we cannot abandon our waterfront [&#8230;] we must protect it, not retreat from it.&#8221; Since Bill de Blasio&#8217;s election, the new mayor maintained the same approach, while reframing all resilience initiatives through a &#8220;justice and equity&#8221; lens, reflecting his self-proclaimed emphasis on social justice (New York City Mayor&#8217;s Office, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2019</xref>). While Brash (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2011</xref>) characterized Bloomberg&#8217;s mayoralty ending in 2013 as containing a deep technocratic streak, the process of rebuilding after Sandy and the subsequent mayor&#8217;s administration centered public input in decision-making.</p>