<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par32">In 2013, the Danish design firm the Bjarke Ingels Group (BIG) joined the Rebuild By Design competition and carried out a collaborative, iterative, and stakeholder-intensive process, combining high-profile starchitect-led design expertise with an inclusive effort at community engagement in lower Manhattan. After a year-long design process, BIG designers and neighborhood groups agreed on a plan to redesign the Manhattan coastline to absorb floodwaters during storm surges, protecting the neighborhood from a 1-in-100&#160;year storm such as Sandy, relying on a series of protective walls that double as sloped parkland and recreational facilities such as walkways and sports fields. According to a BIG designer, participants overwhelmingly chose vulnerability-reducing and green-planted berms on the inside edge of the park that also increased neighborhood access to the water while protecting public housing, building a natural buffer that would absorb storm surges. A key feature of this design was the maintenance of existing trees and shrubs in the park &#8211; the use of natural infrastructure for protection as a sponge in the event of major coastal storms &#8211; rather than destroying and rebuilding the public amenity entirely. This proposal constituted an intentional departure from typical seawalls, that is, high riverside floodwalls that cut the neighborhood off from the waterfront (Collier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2016</xref>), an option an architect described as a &#8220;big dumb wall&#8221; (Goodell, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2016</xref>). Designers dubbed the resulting concept the &#8220;BIG U,&#8221; referencing both the architecture firm&#8217;s namesake and the U-shape of the lower Manhattan coastal tip. The proposal garnered significant international praise from the design and climate policy communities, as boosters highlighted both the collaborative design process and the natural infrastructure approach to protect the coast.</p>