<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0070">Gender differences shape food dynamics not only at the global and community level, but also at household level. Women around the world perform a disproportionate amount of reproductive work in addition to their productive work, almost two and a half times as much as men (<xref rid="bb0420" ref-type="bibr">OECD, 2014</xref>). This includes taking care of children and family members, cleaning, food gathering, collection of water and firewood, preparation of food, and feeding the family. UN-Women (<xref rid="bb0510" ref-type="bibr">UN, 2012</xref>) reports that women in sub-Saharan Africa spend up to 40 billion hours annually fetching water, which has a significant effect on their employment opportunities. It comes as no surprise it is reported that health conditions and the general wellbeing of children largely depend on the mother (<xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr">Halim et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bb0450" ref-type="bibr">Quisumbing et al., 1996</xref>). This already starts during women's pregnancy, as women's nutrition status during pregnancy and breastfeeding are critical factors in the nourishment and health of children. Besides, women, relative to men, tend to invest a higher proportion of their income on food, health and education of their family (<xref rid="bb0450" ref-type="bibr">Quisumbing et al., 1996</xref>). According to UN-Women (<xref rid="bb0510" ref-type="bibr">UN, 2012</xref>),&#8216;when more income is put into the hands of women, child nutrition, health and education improves&#8217;. It is estimated that at least 90% of women's income is reinvested back to their households and families (<xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">CGI, 2021</xref>). Paradoxically, even though women are the main caretakers and food providers for their households, they &#8216;too often eat last and least&#8217; (<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">CARE, 2020a</xref>).</p>