<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par19">The concept of the remaining carbon budget emerged around 2009 from modelling studies on the climate and carbon cycle system (see Lahn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2020</xref>). But it was the release of the IPCC&#8217;s Fifth Assessment Report (AR5) in 2013&#8211;2014 that firmly enacted the carbon budget as a new, central concept for guiding the climate policy debate (Lahn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2021</xref>). As Lahn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2021</xref>) noted, the IPCC provided an institutional infrastructure that enabled the group of scientists who first developed this concept to present it to policymakers with authority and legitimacy. The iconic figure in the Synthesis Report (SYR) of AR5 clearly shows how the idea of the carbon budget became the focal point connecting the risk assessment of climate change impacts to the emissions projection of climate change mitigation (see Fig.<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The relationship between risks from climate change, global temperature change, cumulative CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and changes in annual greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions by 2050 (Source: IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2014</xref>). The figure combines three graphics: the burning embers graphic (<bold>a</bold>); a graphic that shows the near-linear relationship between global temperature increase and cumulative CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (<bold>b</bold>); and the projection of annual GHG emissions in 2050 relative to 2010 levels (<bold>c</bold>). The amount of cumulative CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (carbon budget) fulfils the intermediary function of linking the risk assessment of climate impacts with the emission projection of climate mitigation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10584_2021_3185_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>