<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Historically, social workers, in general, play a critical role in actively responding to extreme events by highlighting that the systemic inequities are root causes, exposing increasing individuals and communities to potential risks and hazards [<xref rid="B36-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. These inequities result in extreme events being more devastating to vulnerable and marginalized groups (e.g., children and youth, older adults, Indigenous, refugees, people experiencing homelessness, and people living with disabilities). Supporting these under-represented groups has been the core component of social work practice and the foundation for community development principles [<xref rid="B37-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. At the same time, as argued above, extreme events increase the complexity of committing to this mandate. Responsively, GSW interventions will fulfill this mission by contributing to the building of equal, inclusive, and diverse communities. In fact, social workers have been leading a bottom-up approach to coordinate various community-based stakeholders and agencies, collectively identify the different types of vulnerabilities (e.g., access to healthcare and social services and unorganized community resources), and develop community-driven solutions [<xref rid="B38-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. These social workers&#8217; micro-and mezzo-level interventions, as community builders and organizers, not only accelerate the affected individuals&#8217; and communities&#8217; reconstruction and recovery [<xref rid="B39-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], but also promote community development. Although community development is one of the major streams in the social work profession, social work students and trainees might not fully understand the importance of community development in the GSW stream. </p>