<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par14">Since its creation in 2015, SBTi has approved targets for more than 1,000 companies (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Each company typically has two or three individual SBTs that differ according to emission scopes covered and use of absolute or intensity-based targets and timeframe. As of October 2020, according to SBTi, companies with approved targets &#8220;were collectively responsible for 1.2 billion tonnes of scope 1 and scope 2 greenhouse gas emissions in their most recent reporting years, which is approximately 3.6% of global greenhouse gas emissions from energy and industry&#8221; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Assuming a linear relationship between the number of companies with approved targets and share of global emissions suggests this has increased to 8.3% of global emissions (452 companies had SBTs in October 2020 and 1039 in November 2021). However, this may be an overestimate given the increase in SMEs with SBTs approved in 2021 (166 compared to 29 in 2020, two in 2019, and none in the preceding years). Company uptake was modest at first, but more companies had SBTs approved in the 12&#160;months before November 2021 than the initial 62&#160;months of the SBTi (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, the recent rate of increase in SBT uptake shown in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> is somewhat inflated because companies with revised targets are counted at the timing of their latest target approval<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn5">5</xref>. In addition to companies with approved SBTs, more than 800 companies (not included in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) have made commitments to setting an SBT in some (unspecified) future date. This indicates that the recent acceleration in target approval may continue. However, as of November 2021, 136 companies that announced commitments between 2015 and 2019 do not yet have an approved SBT<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn6">6</xref>, indicating that not all commitments lead to approved SBTs. There has also been a shift in the temperature alignment of SBTs. While SBTs commonly aligned with a 2&#160;&#176;C scenario well into 2019, two-thirds of targets currently in place align with a more ambitious 1.5&#160;&#176;C scenario (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>SBT approval for 1039 companies by temperature goal through November 2021. Data extracted from SBTi dataset on 2 December 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Companies who have only committed to setting SBTs are not included. Companies with revised targets are only counted at the timing of their latest target approval</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40641_2022_182_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>