<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par42">My own feeling is that hope and radical care can coexist in our pastoral theology if (and I realize this can sometimes be a very big <italic>if</italic>) it is the <italic>active</italic> hope put forward by Macy and Johnstone, a hope that is similarly grounded in a radical and less anthropocentric care of all people, all living things, of the planet itself. To cultivate active hope and radical care may sometimes seem futile, given the anxiety and uncertainty that many of us, including care providers, are feeling. Indeed, the uncertainty, as Macy and Johnstone make clear, is &#8220;normal&#8221; given the present circumstances: &#8220;We can no longer take it for granted that the resources we&#8217;re dependent on&#8212;food, fuel, and drinkable water&#8212;will be available&#8221; or &#8220;even that our civilization will survive or that conditions on our planet will remain hospitable for complex forms of life&#8221; (Macy &amp; Johnstone, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2012</xref>, p. 1). Once again, uncertainty is normal for the era of rapid climate change, a fundamental and &#8220;pivotal psychological reality of our time&#8221; (Macy &amp; Johnstone, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2012</xref>, p. 1). This, of course, assumes that we can &#8220;go there,&#8221; in this case as pastoral theologians and as pastoral and spiritual care providers&#8212;that we can work within the uncertainty and ambiguity without feeling compelled to change the subject or interject optimistic platitudes because it is too difficult or &#8220;depressing&#8221; to talk about the situation. It also assumes that we can refrain from automatically diagnosing or pathologizing the uncertainty about climate change as an intrapsychic and/or religious issue, an underlying psychological disorder, a personal problem, a lack of faith. In so doing, we send a clear message to those in our care that we are unable or unwilling to &#8220;go there.&#8221; But, as we have learned from mindfulness- and acceptance-based approaches to therapy, this form of &#8220;experiential avoidance,&#8221; even in the face of a climate emergency, becomes &#8220;an obstacle to personal and collective growth and development&#8221; as well as &#8220;an obstacle to the effective care of clients and congregants&#8221; (Bingaman, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2018</xref>, p. 50). For Macy &amp; Johnstone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2012</xref>,) when we avoid or do not talk about the seriousness of the climate emergency, &#8220;[T]his blocked communication generates a peril even more deadly, for the greatest danger of our times is the deadening of our response.&#8221; They continue:<disp-quote><p id="Par43">We often hear comments such as &#8220;Don&#8217;t go there, it is too depressing&#8221; and &#8220;Don&#8217;t dwell on the negative.&#8221; The problem with this approach is that it closes down our conversations and our thinking. How can we even begin to tackle the mess we&#8217;re in if we consider it too depressing to think about? Yet when we do face the mess, when we do let in the dreadful news of multiple tragedies unfolding in our world, it can feel overwhelming. We may wonder whether we can do anything about it anyway. So, this is where we begin&#8212;by acknowledging that our times confront us with realities that are painful to face, difficult to take in, and confusing to live with. Our approach is to see this as the starting point of an amazing journey that strengthens us and deepens our aliveness. The purpose of this journey is to find, offer, and receive the gift of Active Hope.. .. Whatever situation we face, we can choose our response. When facing overwhelming challenges, we might feel that our actions don&#8217;t count for much. Yet the kind of responses we make, and the degree to which we believe they count, are shaped by the way we think and feel about hope. .. so that we can best play our part, whatever that may be, in the healing of our world. (pp. 2&#8211;4)</p></disp-quote></p>