<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par29">I well realize that this is not the easiest information to reflect on, theologically and/or psychologically, let alone digest; doing the research has been nothing less than a reality check for me. That said, I want to encourage us as pastoral theologians and pastoral and spiritual care providers to take the data very seriously and in so doing avoid the conclusion that runaway climate change is simply one issue among all the others. The environmental threat is all too real, and with it the beginnings of a great climate migration. As LaMothe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2016</xref>) noted earlier, with the extinction crisis in mind, there is a real possibility that we are in the midst of a &#8220;final tragic story,&#8221; which might be difficult for us to get our minds around given the overt anthropocentric emphasis of so much of our Western theology. Human beings, from a Christian theological perspective, occupy a privileged place in the created order and therefore have dominion over <italic>all</italic> the earth. The historical views of anthropocentric progress and having dominion over nature have therefore coalesced into a unified &#8220;Christian progressive dominion theology,&#8221; which has produced &#8220;anthropogenic climate change (with its catastrophic dangers) in the present&#8221; (Tyson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2021</xref>, p. 8). Said another way, the theological view of human exceptionalism, with the natural world always subordinate to us in rank and value, has now put all of life, including ourselves, at significant risk. Thus, &#8220;We need structural and pastoral changes in religious practices and worship,&#8221; and, as Ilia Delio (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2019</xref>) rightly adds, &#8220;essentially a renewal of religion for a planet in crisis. . a new religion of the earth, one that celebrates interdependency, divine immanence, mutuality, and shared future.&#8221; It will not be easy, given the epistemological foundations of Western theology, which have always been, and still are to this day, decidedly anthropocentric. If there was ever a time to put forward pastoral practices and worship, grounded in a robust pastoral theology that takes very seriously a planet and all of life in crisis, that moment is now.</p>