<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par32">Here is where a pastoral theology of climate change, and with it a pastoral response to the crisis, must include a clear understanding of, in the words of Washington (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2019</xref>), the reality of &#8220;environmental racism.&#8221; As &#8220;people of color&#8221; are suffering disproportionately due to climate change, it is therefore not surprising that they are more concerned about its effects than white people. And yet, those responding to the issues of climate change and the concept of climate anxiety are disproportionately and overwhelmingly white (Ray, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2021</xref>). I am aware of my own whiteness as I write this paper, living and working in a place of privilege that is not, at least not yet, on the &#8220;fringe,&#8221; outside the niche required to sustain human life. So, while I, like the collapsology researchers, are more than a little concerned that civilization is at increasing risk, that there is the distinct possibility that we are witnessing the end of the world as we have known it, I want to be careful that my concern is more for humanity as a whole, in particular those who are most vulnerable and at risk, and less about any &#8220;anxiety&#8221; that what we are witnessing is the passing away of a world of privilege. Ray (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2021</xref>) writes:<disp-quote><p id="Par33">I am deeply concerned about the racial implications of climate anxiety. If people of color are more concerned about climate change than white people, why is the interest in climate anxiety so white? Is climate anxiety a form of white fragility or even <italic>racial</italic> anxiety? Put another way, is climate anxiety just code for white people wishing to hold onto their way of life or get &#8220;back to normal,&#8221; to the comforts of their privilege.. .. ? The prospect of an unlivable future has always shaped the emotional terrain for Black and brown people, whether that terrain is racism or climate change. Climate change compounds existing structures of injustice, and those structures exacerbate climate change. Exhaustion, anger, hope&#8212;the effects of oppression and resistance are not unique to this climate moment. What <italic>is</italic> unique is that people who had been insulated from oppression are now waking up to the prospect of their own unlivable future.</p></disp-quote></p>