<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<italic toggle="yes">Many Happy Returns</italic> is a large, multidisciplinary project funded by UK Research and Innovation (UKRI), specifically as part of the UKRI&#8217;s Enabling Research competition in its Smart Sustainable Plastic Packaging Challenge. The aims of this funding initiative are &#8220;to find solutions to existing issues with plastic packaging, reduce plastic pollution and unlock barriers to create fundamental changes in the industry&#8221; (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_087" ref-type="bibr">UKRI 2020</xref>), and MHR&#8217;s proposed contribution, as mentioned in <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_s_001" ref-type="sec">Section 1</xref>, is to innovate and encourage reusable plastic packaging systems as a means of reducing single-use plastic waste. To this end, it has five research teams, each covering one of the work packages (Language, Change, Willingness, Technology, and Life Cycle), and represents seven departments (English, Geography, Psychology, Mechanical Engineering, Chemical and Biological Engineering, the Management School, and Chemistry) across four faculties at the University of Sheffield. Beyond the University, the project has external partners ranging from non-profit organizations such as OPRL (On-Pack Recycling Label),<fn id="j_jwl-2022-0017_fn_005"><label>5</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.oprl.org.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.oprl.org.uk/</ext-link> (accessed 6 May 2021).</p></fn> City to Sea,<fn id="j_jwl-2022-0017_fn_006"><label>6</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.citytosea.org.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.citytosea.org.uk/</ext-link> (accessed 6 May 2021).</p></fn> and WRAP,<fn id="j_jwl-2022-0017_fn_007"><label>7</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://wrap.org.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://wrap.org.uk/</ext-link> (accessed 6 May 2021).</p></fn> to major UK supermarkets such as Morrisons, Co-op, and Marks &amp; Spencer, as well as larger, multinational corporations including Nestl&#233;, Unilever, and Berry Global.</p>