<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The cross-disciplinary relevance of (eco)linguistics is not always obvious to all stakeholders, however. Of the ten university-led projects participating in this UKRI challenge, MHR is the only one to include a work package dedicated specifically to language. Reasonably, one might ask where linguists, with little to no background in plastics research, fit when it comes to research on packaging technology and polymer science. We would argue that our limited background in plastics is not only acceptable, for linguistic analysis, but in fact preferable. To be new to a subject can be an advantage for linguists, according to Stibbe, as &#8220;the stories that a discipline are based on may be so ingrained within the discipline that they go unnoticed&#8221; (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_082" ref-type="bibr">Stibbe 2021a</xref>: 80). Drawing on <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_050" ref-type="bibr">Meyer and Land&#8217;s (2005)</xref> work on &#8220;threshold concepts&#8221;&#160;&#8211; the concepts that, once understood, irreversibly change one&#8217;s outlook and can even lead to shifts in disciplinary identity&#160;&#8211; Stibbe proposes that it may be better for discourses to be analyzed by those who have not yet crossed such thresholds (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_082" ref-type="bibr">Stibbe 2021a</xref>: 80). Another central argument in his discussion is that ecolinguistics is not a subject or a methodology but can be considered a <italic toggle="yes">transdisciplinary movement</italic> that is not to be confined to the linguistic; to do ecolinguistic work is to be engaged in the &#8220;real world&#8221; and to have an &#8220;ethical and practical dimension&#8221; (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_082" ref-type="bibr">Stibbe 2021a</xref>: 84). It makes sense, as we see it, to try to use (eco)linguistic research to transcend the disciplinary boundaries in a project as broad and complex as this one, and we recognize the general lack of linguistics in plastic research as a significant disciplinary gap.</p>