<abstract xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">This paper investigates the determinants of environmental degradation in Australia from 1990 to 2017, using ecological footprint analysis and the well-established logarithmic mean Divisia index (LMDI) decomposition method. Additionally, decoupling factor analysis was performed to examine the link between environment related variables (CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and ecological footprint) and their determinants such as real income and population. The decomposition analysis considered the impact of five different factors on CO<sub>2</sub> emissions: income effect, population, energy intensity, energy structure, and carbon intensity. For decoupling factor analysis, the link between ecological footprint and its two determinants, real income and population, was examined. Furthermore, the possible decoupling between CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and these determinants was also analyzed, because CO<sub>2</sub> emissions are the main cause of the country&#8217;s increasing ecological footprint. The present study has a more comprehensive approach because it analyzes the factors affecting environmental degradation in Australia by assigning two proxies (CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and ecological footprint) as dependent variables. The results confirmed that Australia&#8217;s ecological reserve substantially declined over the past three decades due to deforestation and energy industries. The LMDI results demonstrated that income effect, population, and carbon intensity were the main factors that raised Australia&#8217;s CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, whereas the energy intensity factor substantially curbed them. The reducing impact of energy structure on CO<sub>2</sub> emissions was minimal; thus, Australia was not able to prevent an upward trend in CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. Lastly, an analysis of Australia&#8217;s CO<sub>2</sub> emissions according to economic activities was conducted for the period between 1990 and 2017 in order to understand other factors that may have affected environmental sustainability.</p></abstract>