<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par31">As experiences in the Covid crisis have shown, decisions taken by way of expertocratic shortcuts will ultimately lack compliance because the reasons behind them are not transparent to and shared by those subjected&#160;to them: democratic citizens. If reasons are not publicly justified and critically assessed, they cannot be translated into motives to accept and comply with decisions. As numerous authors have convincingly argued, the <italic>epistemicization</italic> of democratic politics through expertocratic shortcuts fertilizes a resonance base for authoritarian populists, who draw on perceptions of irresponsiveness, especially among disadvantaged groups (Sch&#228;fer and Z&#252;rn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2021</xref>; Lafont <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>; Bogner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2021</xref>). Does this mean that expertise and experts are a problem for contemporary democracies and that their influence on policy-making should be limited? On the contrary: the demand for information increases in an ever more complex world and citizens rightly expect representatives to take decisions on the basis of a thorough assessment of the best available evidence. More importantly, the ideal of democracy not only entails a promise of egalitarian self-determination but also one of rationality. Citizens do expect legislatures and governments to solve societal problems and do, on the whole, expect democracies to promote liberty, welfare and justice to a higher degree than autocracies can. The central question is thus: <italic>How can democracy live up its promise of rationality without betraying its promises of self-determination and equality?</italic> In light of the challenges ahead, we see three necessary, but not sufficient requirements democratic government has to meet to base decisions on necessary expertise without sacrificing legitimacy and sustainability:</p>