<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par34">In times of greater demand for legal services, clinics will face pressures from clients, governments, and others to extend the services they offer. This needs to be done in sustainable ways that do not place unrealistic burdens on clinic staff. There may be calls to offer services and self-help resources intended to help clients take greater responsibility for addressing their own legal needs. Clinics need to recognise the limitations of models that are predicated on people helping themselves in complex legal situations. Three key variables impact on the utility of services designed to foster legal self-help:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par35">The <italic>context</italic> in which that legal self-help takes place. The attitudes towards self-helpers demonstrated by officials and other personnel involved in the legal system will be important, as will be the circumstances in which the legal self-help is undertaken (e.g., a matter of choice or of necessity) and any emotional dimensions of the legal task involved (whether it is purely administrative or highly personal).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par36">The <italic>complexity</italic> of the relevant law and legal process. The potential for effective self-help is framed by the degree of difficulty of the legal work that needs addressing. The level of complexity varies enormously according to the nature of the legal tasks involved.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par37">The personal <italic>characteristics</italic> of the self-helper who is undertaking their own legal work. As well as the legal skills and knowledge required, self-helpers need a range of non-legal skills and abilities (such as literacy and numeracy skills). Self-helpers need the ability to make informed decisions and complexity may mean they do not have the skills and knowledge they need and are presumed to possess.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn37">37</xref></p></list-item></list></p>