<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">As the nursing profession addresses the complexity of SARS&#8208;CoV&#8208;2 also known as the novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID&#8208;19), public health concerns regarding the intersection of climate change and emerging pandemics are an urgent problem in the 21st century. As noted by Rosenbloom and Markard (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>), the climate crisis as well as COVID&#8208;19 are global and unprecedented disruptors and require comprehensive and coordinated responses by policy&#8208;makers, businesses, broader society&#8212;and to this, we urge the inclusion of public health professionals. Ivanova et&#160;al.&#160;(<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) has suggested that climate change and pandemics may individually and collectively amplify a cascade of global challenges and potential economic collapse. Further Rosenbloom and Markard (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) suggested that the pandemic directly threatens individuals, populations, and health systems, while climate change undermines broader natural, ecological, human systems, and populations. From a global perspective, it is well established that climate change represents a looming health emergency with Lancet and Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change reports on climate change and health contributing to our current state of the science and understanding of the deleterious health consequences associated with climate change (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Watts et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0037" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). There is a pressing need for health professionals to galvanize the response to both of these challenges for the health of the world's people. The purpose of this integrative review is to examine the intersection of climate change and COVID&#8208;19.</p>