<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par29">It seems that after the success of containing the first Covid wave, political communication highlighting the risks of infection and numbers of potential fatalities could no longer induce the same level of fear as in the early days of the pandemic. Messages that promoted compliance in the first wave now sparked reactance, especially among groups that perceived politics as neglecting their interests and concerns&#8212;but doing so in the name of science and morals that were presented as uncontestable. In consequence, not so much the selection of containment measures, but the very diagnosis of an emergency justifying these was contested. The resulting politicization of expertise and scientific findings meant that scientific judgments used by the government to justify their policies were confronted with counter-judgments. Counter-judgments came partly from renowned experts arriving at different risk assessments or advocating different measures as effective and partly from outright science deniers and conspiracy theorists. As Alexander Bogner has pointed out, the science denial movement should not be dismissed as one of lunatics, but tells us something about the dark sides of the knowledge society, as it gains salience where an epistemicization of the political denies the existence of alternatives (Bogner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2021</xref>, pp. 97&#8211;98). Where expertise and science become politicized, the differences between facts and opinions and between dissenting experts and conspiracy theorists are blurred on both sides of the struggle. Whereas science deniers shared &#8216;alternative facts&#8217;, those advocating a &#8216;zero-Covid&#8217; strategy in the name of science did no longer recognize the difference between reasonably disagreeing voices and those of outright Covid and science deniers. Disregarding scientific uncertainty and legitimate disagreement can thus give way to both, expertocratic governance and science denial (Moore and MacKenzie <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>).</p>