<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">The two questions stated above are distinct but linked and offer a stepwise approach for understanding the impact of engagement, states of mental health and wellness, and factors that link the two in ways that produce positive outcomes for children/youth who participate in eco-social health research. Of additional importance is the practice of researchers engaging with and supporting those who work with youth and children. In particular, those using age-appropriate ways to empower children/youth to lead interventions, identify and work on local responses to climate change, and address issues of climate change and its relation to their personal experiences, health and wellbeing. Children and youth do best when the information they are taught and the challenges they are asked to address are presented in age and stage appropriate ways. Using &#8216;hearts, hands and heads&#8217; requires that projects be local and tangible in order for children/youth to be able to observe a problem and identify the factors that could be manipulated to affect positive change. It is also important that their change-making efforts produce a positive and measurable outcome that engenders a sense of achievement. The older children and youth become, the more complexity they can manage, and therefore the tasks and goals they may decide to tackle can have both a local element and a larger system dimension [<xref rid="B1-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. However, even teenagers, particularly in the context of climate change, benefit developmentally from the experience of making a positive difference [<xref rid="B1-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Further steps can also be developed, such as cultivating new conversations, inspiring others to act, teaching friends and family members about new strategies, and/or connecting projects with each other to build capacity or scale up an initiative. Projects particularly suited to children/youth include arts-based activities [<xref rid="B47-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], gardening, nature-based projects [<xref rid="B48-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], or solving a discrete planning problem in a local environment, such as in relation to an issue at a school or in a neighborhood [<xref rid="B37-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p>