<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0115">Work along these lines begins to understand transport justice not as a state of affairs but in terms of ongoing process, power relations and struggles over praxis, meaning and values that are actively shaped by the places and spatial configurations as part of which they unfold. Critical scholarship beyond feminist theory has also been mobilised to conceptualise transport (and mobility) justice in this manner. <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Golub et al. (2013)</xref>, for instance, have drawn on thinking about environmental racism in their work on bus use by African-Americans in the eastern part of the San Francisco Bay Area, whereas <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Inwood et al. (2015)</xref> draw on the thinking of Martin Luther King Jr. and the activist-researchers of the Untokening collective work with critical race theory to contribute to greater transit, cycling and walking justice (<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">L&#243;pez et al., 2018</xref>). The work of Henri Lefebvre, David Harvey, and others on the right to the city &#8211; the right of its inhabitants to produce, appropriate, rework, and use urban space and life (<xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Lefebvre, 1996</xref>) &#8211; is perhaps the most widely used resource from critical theory in relation to transport justice, either directly (see e.g. <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Attoh, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Attoh, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">Prytherch, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bb0370" ref-type="bibr">Verlinghieri and Venturini, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Casta&#241;eda, 2020</xref>) or via Ed Soja's related concept of spatial justice (see e.g. <xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr">Soja, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Enright, 2019</xref>). Focusing on the Bay Area Rapid Transit (BART) system around San Francisco, <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Enright (2019)</xref> discusses how public transport systems are sites both of racial oppression and dispossession and of resistance and re-imagination by Black Lives Matter in 2014&#8211;2015. Justice in this context means reworking BART into a &#8220;crucial &#8230; life support system&#8221; (page 673) that also offers greater equity and freedom to marginalised Black and Latinx populations through radical transformation of the transport planning, urban regeneration, racial politics and other socio-spatial processes that shape this public transport system.</p>