<p>Our community development pedagogy employs authentic assessment processes, thus ensuring that
students develop practical skills that they can utilize post-university. Authentic assessment
processes ensure students connect theory and practice through presenting them with real-world
challenges and standards of performance that professionals typically face in the field. This
requires students to demonstrate higher-order thinking and complex problem solving (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Koh, 2017</xref>). For example, in the community development
course at the University of the Sunshine Coast, students undertake a &#8216;practice
review&#8217;. Students take a &#8216;first person&#8217; stance and write to the community
development practitioner/s of a published case study; this helps students to critically reflect
on practice with a theory-informed analysis. Another example is an assessment piece called a
&#8216;Community Development Process Plan&#8217; where students write a plan for a piece of
community development work they intend to undertake. Based on the community development theory
which takes &#8216;private concerns into public action&#8217; (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Kelly and Westoby, 2018</xref>, p. 90), students identify a personal concern. This
could be related to their local neighbourhood or community, or something about the state of the
world in general. Using the participatory developmental method (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Kelly and Westoby, 2018</xref>), they demonstrate their structural analysis of the
root causes of the situation and identify with whom they intend to build relationships for
collective action. These analyses range from activist type actions such as neighbours banding
together to lobby local government for better community infrastructure, to creating their own
community infrastructure where none currently exists, such as community gardens or actions to
clean up a creek. For other students who develop an analysis about their own sense of
&#8216;community&#8217; and the impact of declining social capital, their process plan can
simply be to connect with their neighbours for a street barbecue or other social event to start
the process of building relationships. In many instances, student groups have followed through
with these planned activities, supporting the practical action component of the pedagogy.</p>