<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par27">The Lower East Side (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) is a dense neighborhood in downtown Manhattan built over an in-filled tidal marsh next to the East River. Originally settled by Lenape people before being displaced by Dutch colonizers, the LES has a history as an immigrant destination and developed in proximity to the financial district, producing one of the most racially and economically diverse neighborhoods in Manhattan. The shifting character of the neighborhood is evident in the mixed built environment: Public housing developments, tenement houses, and new luxury high-rise developments are anchored by a dense network of local community organizations addressing youth engagement, education, employment, and equity issues in the neighborhood. This neighborhood-level diversity, however, belies stark racial and economic segregation at the block scale. While the neighborhood has some of the highest rent prices in the city (around $200 a month higher than the Manhattan average), median income is low and the rate of families below the poverty line is high &#8211; 27.3% of LES residents live below the poverty line compared to the Manhattan average of 16.2% (NYU Furman Center, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2018</xref>). Apartments in public housing account for 23% of all rental units, housing more than 30,000 of the neighborhood&#8217;s 163,277 residents. Over the last few decades, waves of luxury redevelopment have squeezed the availability of low-cost housing in the neighborhood. As a consequence, local activists and other residents have been left feeling besieged by Manhattan&#8217;s real estate industry and distrustful of a city government they perceive as complicit (Brash, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2011</xref>). Superstorm Sandy disproportionately affected public housing residents, as a 13-ft storm surge flooded the eastern blocks of the LES and nearby East Village, causing many buildings to lose electricity, heating, and hot water, in some cases for weeks. Beyond high-density housing, public institutions such as a cluster of hospitals, transportation and utility infrastructure, as well as small businesses were damaged and stopped functioning for weeks after Sandy, and today remain at risk in the low-elevation floodplain.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Community District 3 in Manhattan</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11186_2021_9459_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>