<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par29">As a neighborhood ravaged by disaster in a city spending billions to protect it from future catastrophe with the promise of input from its residents, the Lower East Side of Manhattan is not a typical neighborhood exposed to climate impacts. Yet this distinction is precisely what makes New York and the LES a powerful case study. As Zussman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2004</xref>) writes, &#8220;successful case studies look at extremes, unusual circumstances, and analytically clear examples, all of which are important not because they are representative but because they show a process or a problem in particularly clear relief.&#8221; New York is a city with strong political willingness, tremendous resources, and an intention to democratize climate planning, representing a &#8220;pointy case&#8221; (Pacewicz, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2020</xref>) wherein the phenomenon of interest &#8211; the controversy between democratic decision-making and technical expertise in climate planning &#8211; is unusually pronounced. If New York&#8217;s government faces problems pursuing democratic planning for climate impacts, it is likely that other less-resourced or less-participatorily inclined cities around the world may face similar difficulties, perhaps even in an exaggerated manner. Tensions between participation and technical expertise have been well-documented globally (e.g. Easterly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2014</xref>; Li &amp; Zhong, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2020</xref>), giving us reason to believe that in other cities around the world, governments are likely to wield authority relying on technical expertise, with negative impacts on the procedural justice dimensions of climate adaptation and potentially creating resistance to large-scale projects. While we can expect that the specific empirical findings presented in this article will not appear in the same way across all other contexts, the controversies over climate infrastructure in New York show us generalizable social processes, as well as particular conditions under which these processes are likely to arise.</p>