<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par13">One indicator of the lack of post-disaster support for renters is the level of aid going to renters in comparison to homeowners for specific historic events. Using both disaster record number data and FEMA Individual Assistance Program Data, which includes the Individuals and Households Program (IHP) and the Housing Assistance (HA) and Other Needs Assistance (ONA) programs, for both homeowners and renters<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn4">4</xref>, a significantly smaller percentage of individual assistance funding goes to renters. This may be due to many factors including renters lack of knowledge of how to apply for assistance, social or cultural barriers such as those faced by undocumented immigrants that are fearful of government authorities, or the fact that repairs to building structures (homeowner assistance) are typically more costly than replacement of the contents (which is the assistance that renters qualify for). In Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, we compare five events in recent US history and the amount of individual assistance for the two groups. As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, the amount of total assistance granted to homeowners is much higher than to renters, as would be expected due to the cost of structure repair or replacement. Moreover, the rental amount column represents FEMA assistance for temporary housing, which is only available in presidentially declared disaster areas. The total dollars flowing to homeowners in that category is much higher than to renters for all events with the exception of one event, the Salem Virginia flooding in 2004. As noted, there is at least one very large apartment complex that has had extensive and repeated flood damage (Hammack <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2019</xref>), which may have contributed to the large rental amount assistance in that case. Interestingly, the amount of assistance per valid registrant for rental assistance is at least 1.4 times higher for renters than for homeowners (with the exception of Hurricane Harvey), potentially indicating that the homeowner&#8217;s need for temporary housing is shorter or less significant than that of renters following the events considered here. It should be noted, however, that the repair and replacement amounts for assistance to homeowners would also include funds to owners of rental properties to restore dwellings to habitability.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of renter vs. homeowner individual assistance, post-disaster</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Event</th><th>Housing status</th><th>Number of properties inspected<sup>5</sup></th><th>Valid registrations</th><th>Approved for FEMA assistance</th><th>Repair-replace amount<sup>6</sup></th><th>Rental amount (temporary housing assistance per valid registrant)<sup>7</sup></th><th>Total approved Ihp amount</th><th>Percentage of total assistance for event</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">2010 Flood - TN Disaster Number 1909</td><td>Homeowner</td><td>34,329</td><td>34,230</td><td>22,172</td><td>$122,115,341</td><td>$374</td><td>$142,709,669</td><td>93.00%</td></tr><tr><td>Rental</td><td>5386</td><td>7060</td><td>2705</td><td>$53,469</td><td>$699</td><td>$10,743,502</td><td>7.00%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Hurricane Harvey - TX Disaster Number 4332</td><td>Homeowner</td><td>301,473</td><td>444,037</td><td>209,106</td><td>$896,762,907</td><td>$515</td><td>$1,309,260,437</td><td>80.16%</td></tr><tr><td>Rental</td><td>279,447</td><td>443,735</td><td>163,781</td><td>$311,072</td><td>$241</td><td>$323,997,036</td><td>19.84%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Boulder Flood - CO Disaster Number 4145</td><td>Homeowner</td><td>17,406</td><td>21,043</td><td>13,460</td><td>$41,176,568</td><td>$470</td><td>3,026,899</td><td>85.97%</td></tr><tr><td>Rental</td><td>5214</td><td>6618</td><td>3090</td><td>$15,429</td><td>$860</td><td>$8,651,481</td><td>14.03%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Sandy - NJ Disaster Number 4086</td><td>Homeowner</td><td>70,507</td><td>87,635</td><td>39,578</td><td>$174,890,114</td><td>$753</td><td>$318,291,459</td><td>75.39%</td></tr><tr><td>Rental</td><td>46,707</td><td>60,918</td><td>21,736</td><td>$36,047</td><td>$1084</td><td>$103,912,209</td><td>24.61%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Salem - VA 2004 Disaster Number 1570</td><td>Homeowner</td><td>203</td><td>219</td><td>167</td><td>$384,312</td><td>$336</td><td>$491,618</td><td>37.54%</td></tr><tr><td>Rental</td><td>177</td><td>205</td><td>147</td><td>$0</td><td>$804</td><td>$817,912</td><td>62.46%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>5</sup>Renters do not receive a full home inspection because they do not own the property. For renters, this is a count of the number of valid registration renters who received an inspection of the damages to their contents</p><p><sup>6</sup>Renters are not eligible for repair/replacement assistance because they do not own the property. Yet, for multiple events, data does exist, indicating that some funding was provided to renters in this category</p><p><sup>7</sup>Renters may receive some temporary housing assistance through FEMA&#8217;s Individual Assistance program if the individual is in a declared state and county and has registered within the FEMA designated registration period. Rental amount listed under the homeowner&#8217;s category refers to the total amount of rental assistance for temporary housing, approved in dollars, for Housing Assistance (HA) under FEMA&#8217;s IHP program</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>