<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par15">The burdens of historical housing policies also created disadvantaged minority renters while their white counterparts became homeowners. Implementation of the federal housing laws noted above included &#8220;red-lining,&#8221; the express drawing of boundaries around geographic areas of city, typically with predominantly black or Latino residents, considered at high risk of default and for which no mortgage lending would occur. Accordingly, homeownership and economic development was much more difficult or impossible in these redlined areas, and they tended to be located in areas at higher risk to extreme weather (i.e., floods) or even industrial accidents. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> is an example of one of these early 1940s &#8220;redlined&#8221; maps for the city of Nashville, TN, showing the areas near the river (except the immediate business district downtown) as areas where home loans could not easily be secured (Nelson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">n.d.</xref>). Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows this redlined area with current and possible<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn5">5</xref> rental properties indicated, demonstrating a legacy of higher flood risk and lack of homeownership that endures to this day, with several rental properties located within the floodplains.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Early 1940s map of Nashville with &#8220;redlining&#8221; (Nelson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">n.d.</xref>), where home mortgages could not easily be obtained, in higher-risk areas (near the river) that were often in predominately black communities</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13412_2021_691_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>&#8220;Redlined&#8221; areas from early 1940s maps with high-risk flood zones and current rental properties identified. The 1933 Home Owners&#8217; Loan Corporation (HOLC) color-coded map areas based on risk for mortgage lending, often identifying black neighborhoods in &#8220;red&#8221; (high risk) and making it difficult for homeownership to occur in those areas. Current rental properties are indicated in relation to the old redlined areas. Flood plains are indicated as hatched areas</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13412_2021_691_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>