<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0025">In recent years, energy transition research in the U.S. and globally has expanded to explore a range of economic and policy mechanisms necessary to achieve a just transition. Some have suggested that fossil fuel divestment presents a viable way to center issues of energy justice upstream, prompting the consideration of injustices related to supply-side analysis and decision-making in various energy sectors <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Just transition frameworks have been explored through the lens of political economy, advancing the notion that beyond worker protections, addressing energy access and poverty and adopting climate justice goals are necessary to ensure transition is equitable <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Just transition frameworks have also been leveraged to argue for the need for a socially equitable approach to sustainable design in a post-carbon future <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Likewise, there have been efforts to map and align environmental policy goals with anticipated levels of investment in renewables in conjunction with the implementation of adequate worker support systems and recommended public policy <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. <italic>Energy Research and Social Scienc</italic>e has had numerous articles touching on various aspects of a just energy transition. Tvinnereim et al. (2017) look at the issues from a national perspective in Norway, while Biresselioglu et al. (2020) consider the wider European issues for individuals and collectives <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Johnstone et al. (2020) explore some of the non-technical issues of energy transitions <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Crowe and Li (2020) explore the issues of just transitions in certain US states for both coal and solar <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Sovacool and Brisbois (2019) explore the role of &#8220;elite power&#8221; in these transitions, while Schwarz (2020) considered the role of citizen power as did Thombs (2019) <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Both Bayulgen (2020) and Seidl (2019) looked as socio-economic aspects of specific energy transitions <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Prinz and Pegels (2018) considered the role of labor organizations in energy transitions, and Oselik (2019) used an advocacy coalition framework <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Li and Strachan (2019) used socio-economic modelling to explore transitions, and Hess (2019) viewed the issues through a local democracy lens <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p>