<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par22">Second, the assumption that scientific methods can provide answers to political questions is mistaken. When it comes to weighing benefits of disease control against social and economic damages, it is clear that no &#8216;scientific&#8217; calculus could do the job: political decisions require societal and democratic value judgments to trade off conflicting interests and concerns. They regularly produce winners and losers since they deal with the fair distribution of specific goods and burdens. Scientific claims cannot constitute answers to the normative questions political decisions have to address. Moreover, an authority of experts in the decision-making process on such normative questions would undermine the democratic legitimacy of the respective decision. This applies not only to the formulation of societal aims, but also to the choice of instruments with which these aims are to be achieved. Even assuming that there was a societal consensus on the desired aims and that experts were only entrusted with the task of determining the right means to achieve them, there are often functionally equivalent ways with diverging practical implications to achieve the same goal (Saretzki <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2011</xref>, p. 61). One might ask, for example, what proportions of the Paris Agreement&#8217;s 1.5&#8211;2&#160;&#176;C target should be achieved by consistently shutting down coal-fired power plants, banning individual passenger transport, eliminating factory farming, or applying geoengineering technologies. While a consideration of such options must in principle be informed by scientific evidence about their effects, it involves questions that are, in J&#252;rgen Habermas&#8217; typology, in their essence ethical&#8211;political ones (Habermas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1992</xref>, p. 198). Whether one prefers, for example, to leave natural resources untouched or to manipulate the climate system by technical means in order to achieve the same quantitative goal of a limited temperature increase is also an expression of one's own moral orientation toward the world. Scientific expertise alone simply cannot provide definitive answers to questions that concern society as a whole and ultimately aim at moral issues and ethical&#8211;political questions of a shared good life (Fischer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>, p. 272). Answering these questions cannot be done from an objective point of view, but requires a democratic discourse in which, on the one hand, there is no normative justification for a special position of experts (ibid.), and on the other hand, no better answers can be expected epistemically unless all relevant perspectives are taken into account.</p>