<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par24">An epistemic conception of democracy and expertocratic government strategies therefore offer no answers to political distribution conflicts between different actors, which are often at the heart of the problem. This omission of distributional issues, however, does not make conflicts disappear, but only obscures them, thus reinforcing existing power structures in the most problematic way. This becomes clear when state actors themselves blur the boundaries between science and politics in their global climate policy efforts: In 2009, the Copenhagen Accord set the goal of limiting the global temperature increase to 2&#160;&#176;C. According to the Accord, it is &#8216;the scientific view that the increase in global temperature should be below 2&#160;&#176;C&#8217; (UNFCCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2010</xref>, p. 5). However, this statement is problematic in two respects: First, there was and is no scientific consensus on a very concrete number (Blue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>, p. 158), and second, every number in this context represents a normative target, which in its consequences produces winners and losers. The mode for formulating such a common goal can therefore not be a scientific one at all, but is always a political one that faces competing interests and values. Conflicting interests were only disguised in the case of the 2&#160;&#176;C target, hiding an imbalance of power in the decision-making process: the target in fact expressed the interest of the richer countries in the more northern latitudes, which are less likely to experience the immediate effects of climate change, while many Pacific Island Countries see their literal demise cemented in a 2&#160;&#176;C rise in global temperatures (Fletcher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2009</xref>). By politicizing the target, the latter eventually managed to get the 1.5&#160;&#176;C target included as a more ambitious aspiration in the 2015 Paris Agreement (Falkner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2016</xref>, p. 1114).</p>