<contrib-group xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>Zack</given-names></name><address><email>zack.walsh@iass-potsdam.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><bio><sec id="d30e186"><title>Zack Walsh</title><p>is a Research Associate at the Institute for Advanced Sustainability Studies (IASS) in Potsdam, Germany. He co-leads the A Mindset for the Anthropocene (AMA) project which is a transdisciplinary research project and emerging network of change agents integrating personal and socio-ecological transformations to sustainability. He has completed doctoral coursework in Process Studies at Claremont School of Theology, and he frequently collaborates with the Institute for Ecological Civilization and the Courage of Care Coalition in the United States.</p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>B&#246;hme</surname><given-names>Jessica</given-names></name><address><email>jessica.boehme@iass-potsdam.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><bio><sec id="d30e201"><title>Jessica B&#246;hme</title><p>is a Research Associate at the Institute for Advanced Sustainability Studies (IASS) in Potsdam, Germany, and is a doctoral candidate at Leuphana University, L&#252;neburg, in cooperation with Lund University Centre for Sustainability Studies (LUCSUS). She co-leads the A Mindset for the Anthropocene (AMA) project which is a transdisciplinary research project and emerging network of change agents integrating personal and socio-ecological transformations to sustainability. Her research interest is the intersection of sustainable lifestyles and personal transformation.</p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wamsler</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><address><email>christine.wamsler@lucsus.lu.se</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><bio><sec id="d30e216"><title>Christine Wamsler</title><p>is Professor of Sustainability Science at Lund University Centre for Sustainability Studies (LUCSUS), Sweden. She is an internationally renowned expert in sustainable development and associated (material and cognitive) transformation processes, with more than 20 years of working experience, both in theory and practice. Her work has shaped international debates and knowledge on personal, social, organisational and policy transformations in a context of climate change. She has led many international projects and published over 150 academic papers, book chapters, and books on these issues. Since 2016, she is also leading the Contemplative Sustainable Futures Program at LUCSUS.</p></sec></bio></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.464582.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0409 4235</institution-id><institution>Institute for Advanced Sustainability Studies e.V, </institution></institution-wrap>Berliner Strasse 130, 14467 Potsdam, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10211.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9130 6144</institution-id><institution>Leuphana University of L&#252;neburg, </institution></institution-wrap>Universit&#228;tsallee 1, 21335 L&#252;neburg, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4514.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0930 2361</institution-id><institution>Lund University Centre for Sustainability Studies, </institution></institution-wrap>Box 170, 221 00 Lund, Sweden </aff></contrib-group>