<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0160">Integration is widely regarded as the core process underpinning interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary research <xref rid="b0900" ref-type="bibr">[180]</xref>, enabling scientists to combine different disciplinary theories, methods and perspectives with an overarching aim of arriving to common ground. It includes insights, practices, frameworks, or concepts shared by multiple or all participants in different phases of a research process <xref rid="b0905" ref-type="bibr">[181]</xref>. There is no universal model of how integration should be developed because interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary projects vary in purpose, scale and scope, and because it depends on the problems and questions at hand, the mix of expertise, and the degree of coordination <xref rid="b0910" ref-type="bibr">[182]</xref>. Through integration, the framework proposed in this study goes beyond the spatial disaggregation of where we are, where we want to go and how we get there <xref rid="b0915" ref-type="bibr">[183]</xref>. It rather makes a case of reinstating science in society and legitimising different types of knowledge <xref rid="b0900" ref-type="bibr">[180]</xref> towards exploring the broad spectrum of the potential for and impacts of behavioural changes, based on individual, community, national and global action for climate change. In understanding the desirability of sustainability, transitions research can employ an agenda fuelled by knowledge co-produced by scientists and citizens alike from a transdisciplinary lens, one that bridges different disciplines and agendas in an interdisciplinary setting, and one that can explore and provide holistic insight into the interplay between individual behaviours and macro-level changes, and with factors such as language, culture and economy setting the drivers toward this change (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
).<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>A holistic framework for capturing behavioural and societal transitions in energy modelling.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>