<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0120">While this methodology thus involved listening in the courtroom and taking notes, at times it explored the creativity of people mobilising against the pipeline expansion. I interacted with defendants, observers, and defence lawyers, as well as reviewed transcripts; these included statements prepared for the judge &#8211; some delivered only in part or not at all in the hearings. The evidence that mattered most to the judge was never evidence about conscientious objections or greenhouse gases but rather what members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police (RCMP) showed on the stand &#8211; &#8216;evidence&#8217; such as news articles or Facebook posts citing defendants' words, indicating that they engaged in &#8220;calculated defiance&#8221; or an &#8220;organised&#8221; plan to be on the road. My task evolved to include revisiting these sources, too, venturing into some of the voluminous legal cases referenced (several thousand pages of which were circulated by the many lawyers involved; a single defendant recounted being given more than 600 pages when charged). Conversations in the gallery during breaks and elsewhere in the courthouse, and beyond, explored experiences in hundreds of trials and sentencing hearings. I spoke with courtroom observers and defendants in coffee shops, over meals and on the street, exploring testimonies and meanings around them &#8211; and also what it means to witness. In being there in the courtroom, day after day, a courtroom ethnographer becomes not merely an observer but inescapably part of the proceedings &#8211; at times making unavoidable eye contact with judge and prosecutors as well as becoming part of the camaraderie of the gallery itself. At times the ethnography became a process of reflecting, in an awkward courthouse setting and, if only partially, on urgent needs for geographers &#8211; efforts toward more meaningful engagement with Indigenous ontologies of place, relations with place and legal practices of place (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Daigle, 2019</xref>).</p>