<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0130">Separate from but concurrent to the courtroom ethnography work, I also collaborated on a project with members of the Tsleil-Waututh Nation focused on life within Tsleil-Waututh territory (<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Spiegel et al., 2020</xref>), which informs engagement on wider inter-relating issues of knowledge production with Indigenous youth and elders dialoguing in solidarity. My positionality <italic>vis-&#224;-vis</italic> this courtroom over the August 2018&#8211;January 2020 period thus had various dimensions that inflected my learning. As someone who conducts environmental justice-oriented research projects with Indigenous communities locally and internationally, I approached this courtroom &#8211; and the TMX issues at stake &#8211; as a locally and globally important space of contention. As someone who grew up in Canada in schooling systems that utterly lacked proper education on Indigenous histories or on the brutality of colonization, I found being part of the courthouse solidarity group to offer particular vantage points for critical learning; my positionality was also as one who participated in raising legal funds to support those being disproportionately affected by state/corporate violence, while encountering a range of methodological tools for critical learning including interviewing artists on their experiences and histories of social justice work. Over time, I went from being a courtroom novice to a &#8216;regular&#8217; attendee, allowing appreciation of the sensitive ways in which diverse positionalities were embraced in the group, regardless of whether a person was arrested, or whether one person chose to plead a certain way, or how the &#8216;lead&#8217; concerns about the TMX were framed; this also allowed for attentiveness to inconsistencies in the logics mobilised by prosecutors. Methodologically, courtroom ethnography can be challenging as it is a time-consuming method (see also <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Walenta, 2020</xref>); for me, the returning time and again to the court allowed for not just keeping a diary but more importantly, relationship building that is crucial to this methodology, at times sharing notes (and drafts of this article) with defendants and supporters who also then offered further insights.</p>