<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">In the current historical moment, a contradiction is arising where generally people are living longer and healthier lives; however, for the youngest generations, the assumptions of unending economic growth, social stability, and increasing health and wellbeing across the life-course are not experienced ubiquitously. At an early age, children (defined by the Canadian Census as individuals between the ages of 0&#8211;14) and youth (defined as individuals between the ages of 15&#8211;24) who have always lived under the specter of climate change are facing a barrage of information which suggests that the planet as we know it is already, and will increasingly, change for the worst. A significant, and growing impact, on children and youth&#8217;s mental health, therefore, is climate change. Globally, children/youth are exhibiting deepening distress around climate change, and will be disproportionately burdened by it across their life-course [<xref rid="B1-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Whether due to direct impacts from climate events or as a result of growing up in a discursive space infused with climate anxiety, children/youth in Canada and around the world are showing increasing levels of mental health distress from climate change [<xref rid="B2-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Furthermore, it is predicted that without accelerated intervention, climate change will impact the health of people at every stage of their lives and in both short- (e.g., health care visits) and long-term (e.g., lost potential) ways [<xref rid="B3-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These concerns are further exacerbated given that children/youth are developing both psychologically and physically and more susceptible to environmental elements than adults [<xref rid="B4-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], in part due to the time they spend playing outside in close contact with nature [<xref rid="B3-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Additionally, their physiological and mental development can slow down or be halted by the unpredictable consequences of increased climate impacts [<xref rid="B3-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. It is posited that impacts from climate change events start before birth when birthing bodies are exposed to environmental stressors that impact the baby in utero [<xref rid="B4-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. As a result, this phenomenon raises significant questions in relation to childhood development and precipitates a new set of considerations that must be attended to when considering the causes and consequences of mental health disorders on society.</p>