<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">While the Social Determinants of Health (SDoH) are increasingly well understood as socio-economic, cultural, and environmental conditions that affect health outcomes, lesser known are the Ecological Determinants of Health (EDoH). These are distinct from the field of environmental health and extend beyond the limits of the &#8216;environmental&#8217; determinants to the earth system. Within the context of ecosystem services, fundamental needs like water, food, and natural resources are impacted by global environmental changes like biodiversity loss, pollution, resource depletion and climate change. An eco-social approach grasps the holistic nature of public health as it impacts the most basic necessities for health and shows that they are underrecognized at all levels of government [<xref rid="B6-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. For topics that arise in the interplay between the social and natural world, the EDoH offer an important complement to the SDoH as together they form crucial components to environmental and social health and wellbeing [<xref rid="B7-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. An &#8216;eco-social&#8217; approach centers the idea that social and ecological factors are key components of the health and wellbeing of current and future populations. While environmental and ecological approaches are complementary, the EDoH strengthens attention to how ecosystems and ecologies are intrinsically linked to both human and animal health. Examining the determinants of children/youth&#8217;s mental health illuminates the limits to knowledge that would occur if genetic, biological and family factors, or a focus on individual&#8217;s exposures to emotional or physical adversity or abusive conditions alone were used to study contemporary socio-environmental issues and their impacts on children/youth&#8217;s mental health [<xref rid="B8-ijerph-18-04573" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>