<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par4">The interconnected and cascading nature of loss and damage in the Pacific has emerged in other studies. Ecosystem and biodiversity losses have, for example, been observed to have inherent cascading effects on people and livelihoods (Goulding et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2016</xref>; Sattler <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2017</xref>; Pearce et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2018</xref>; Thomas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2019</xref>; van der Geest et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2020</xref>). C&#225;mara-Leret et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2019</xref>) also refer to the impact of climate change on &#8216;biocultural heritage&#8217;, illustrating how climate change diminishes the wellbeing and cultural integrity of Indigenous peoples by affecting endemic plant species. Damage to the relationship between people and their customary lands from climate change also has severe implications for the material, cultural and social security as well as emotional and spiritual wellbeing of Pacific Islander people (Campbell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2019</xref>). In this way, NELD affects the interlinked socio-ecological system with embedded cultural, social and ecological structures, rather than affecting people and ecosystems separately. McNamara et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2021b</xref>) argue that, in the Pacific, NELD can undermine entire socio-ecological systems, and are understood, perceived and experienced through the lens of intangible values, identity and cultural landscapes. Works by Epeli Hau&#8217;ofa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2008</xref>) that traverse the breadth of Oceania remind us that this interconnectivity transfers to regional scales as there is a deep connection between everything. The &#8216;sea of islands&#8217; are a conglomeration of islands not restricted by geopolitical boundaries but connected by the sea and seafarers (Hau&#8217;ofa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1998</xref>).</p>