<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">We examine the role of technical wind potential, institutional factors (business acumen and administrative capacity as proxied by tribal casinos, Department of Energy support through the wind energy grants), and the political environment (RPS and concerns about tribal sovereignty) in which the tribes are located. The key variable of interest is the tribe&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">technical potential for wind power</italic> at the utility-scale (there is very little distributed scale, below 1 megawatt, wind power). To harness wind energy for electricity generation, the tribal land must have sufficient wind flow or technical potential. Therefore, we expect that tribes with more renewable energy potential are more apt to pursue renewable energy projects. These data are drawn from the Tribal Energy Atlas, which researchers at the National Renewable Energy Laboratory (NREL) developed to provide geospatial data on assessed technical renewable energy potential. The applied methodologies are provided in Milbrandt et al. [<xref rid="pone.0261752.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] Energy potential may not automatically translate into energy generation capacity&#8212;institutions and expertise matter. Actors must have the economic and business expertise to recruit outside investors, select appropriate technologies, and oversee the construction project. We do not control for solar energy in our model. The reason is that to date, only 4 tribes have installed utility-level solar projects. Hence, there is insufficient variation on this variable for it to be included in our model. We expect tribes with business experience have an advantage in this regard. Hence, we consider the <italic toggle="yes">size of tribal casinos</italic> logged. Revenues from specific casinos are not publicly available, as they are proprietary information. Following Walker and Jackson [<xref rid="pone.0261752.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], we consider the square footage of tribally-owned casinos as a proxy for casino revenue [<xref rid="pone.0261752.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The average gaming operation is 71,151 square feet. Thirty-five percent of tribal governments in the sample do not have a casino.</p>