<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0045">Indeed, women play a crucial role in food security, both as primary producers of food and as primary caretakers of the household. Women are important contributors to different activities that support agricultural development (<xref rid="bb0540" ref-type="bibr">UNDP, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0365" ref-type="bibr">Karl, 2009</xref>). Based on data from the World Bank, women in developing countries produce 60&#8211;80% of the household food (<xref rid="bb0440" ref-type="bibr">Palacios-Lopez et al., 2017</xref>). Women's role in food production varies from direct producers on their own account, wageworkers, to unpaid labour on family farms (<xref rid="bb0540" ref-type="bibr">UNDP, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0455" ref-type="bibr">Raney et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bb0370" ref-type="bibr">Kotz&#233;, 2003</xref>). In developing countries, for instance, they account for more than 43% of the labour force (<xref rid="bb0510" ref-type="bibr">UN, 2012</xref>), much of which they are poorly or not at all compensated for. Evidently, &#8216;[&#8230;] if these women had the same access to productive resources as men, they could increase yields on their farms by 20 to 30 percent, raising total agricultural output in these countries by 2.5 to 4 percent&#8217; (ibid). Presently, it is estimated that only less than 13% of the agricultural land globally is owned by women because of discriminatory laws and practices (<xref rid="bb0520" ref-type="bibr">UN, 2020</xref>). Consequently, for their lack of tenure security, women are often excluded from farming opportunities, such as modern contract farming arrangement (<xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2011</xref>). Men also play an important role in food production, but their role is usually more focused on the production of cash crops. The production of food crops, which often has a more direct influence on local households food security level, is usually attended to and managed by women (<xref rid="bb0540" ref-type="bibr">UNDP, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Garc&#237;a, 2013</xref>).</p>