<notes xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><fn-group><fn fn-type="participating-researchers"><p><?igo-nc?><?igo-nc?>Contributors and sources: A-SJ, VH, and HL-Q conceived and designed the analysis paper. A-SJ, VH, RN, SMA, and HL-Q collected the data. A-SJ, VH, RN, and HL-Q analysed the data and drafted the manuscript with input from all authors. All authors contributed to revising the manuscript. This analysis was part of the work commissioned by the Independent Panel for Pandemic Preparedness &amp; Response, which reviewed the national responses of 28 countries. Data used for the analysis were collected through three complementary methods: (1) literature review of peer-reviewed papers, policy documents, public reports, and articles that examined national and sub-national policy responses; (2) semi-structured interviews with country experts and national government written submission of selected countries about their own account of the measures implemented to contain covid-19; (3) validation of country specific data by experts through written consultation and round table discussion.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Patient involvement: No patients were involved in this analysis.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Competing interests: We have read and understood the BMJ policy on declaration of interests and have the following interests to declare: All authors declare no conflict of interest. The Secretariat of the Independent Panel for Pandemic Preparedness and Response is independent.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Provenance and peer review: Commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>This collection of articles was proposed by The Independent Panel for Pandemic Preparedness and Response; open access fees were funded by WHO and Singapore's National Medical Research Council (NMRC/CG/C026/2017_NUHS). <italic toggle="yes">The</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic> commissioned, peer reviewed, edited, and made the decision to publish these articles. Kamran Abbasi was the lead editor for <italic toggle="yes">The</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic>. </p></fn></fn-group></notes>