<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">There are three conceptual building blocks that, together, serve as the spine of our argument. First, the term &#8216;land politics&#8217; is used here to refer to the land-based social relations between social classes and groups within society, and between the state and society, that are structured by formal and informal, state and non-state rules, procedures or norms, and the degrees of autonomy and capacity of actors to understand their situation and take actions to maintain or change it. State land policies are thus a small fraction of land politics; institutions through which working people access land are diverse: state and non-state, formal and informal, and the degree of autonomy and capacity of access land and derive benefit from it varies based on class, ethnicity, gender and generation (Ribot &amp; Peluso, <xref rid="CIT0086" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). In land politics the concept of &#8216;land tenure security&#8217; is highly contested: whose tenure and whose security, tenure security for what end? For example, the Vacant, Fallow and Virgin (VFV) Land Management Law of Myanmar calls for ordinary villagers to formally register their land claims purportedly to provide land tenure security. There are two less publicly spoken about implications of this process: (a) villagers who engage in shifting agriculture are unlikely to get registration for his/her full range of land, and at best, may get a small parcel suitable only for sedentary farming; (b) all lands that are not or cannot be claimed by the villagers are then claimed by the state, deemed as virgin, fallow and vacant land, and are then reallocated to corporate investors; or that, only the remaining lands after corporate investors took over vast tracts of lands were then opened up to land registration for ordinary villagers. So, the question is: whose tenure is it that was secured in this process? Land grabbing in Myanmar has been carried out through this legal mechanism loosely billed as a &#8216;land tenure security&#8217; instrument by the government, and in constrast, labelled by autonomous civil society groups as the &#8216;land grabbing law&#8217; (Franco &amp; Borras, <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Ra et al., <xref rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p>