<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par22">The significant publicity of &#8220;Climategate,&#8221; the story about the IPCC&#8217;s error regarding Himalayan glacier futures, its subsequent mitigation of the situation, and the wide range of responses the event elicited, highlights the complicated politics of climate change. While laying bare north-south relations, organizational culture, and the role of science in state-building, the event also highlights the nomination of certain subjects, worldviews, and scales as more important than others. IPCC&#8217;s errors were seen by some to support a historical global north agenda to transfer an unequal share of the climate crisis burden onto the global south. The response to prevent future events was the creation of institutional mandates meant to reduce the space for epistemic and ontological plurality within the process of knowledge production. The credibility of the IPCC was seen restored despite unanswered questions around the negotiations of science and state when reasoning is tied to local political and subjective priorities. In all these conversations the solutions remain biased to the scale of the nation-state, claiming more stringently expert controlled knowledge production processes that avoid engaging with seemingly unquantifiable accounts while retaining the IPCC as the foremost arbitrator of climate futures (Beck, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2012</xref>; Mahony, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2014</xref>). The aftermath of &#8220;Climategate&#8221; resulted in significant public scrutiny and fueled a coalition of a diverse ensemble of climate deniers. To counter these attacks, the IPCC mobilized a powerful response highlighting their credibility through unfatigued allegiance to the scientific method (Hajer, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2012</xref>). This management ideology was echoed in the work of important Himalayan scholars who proposed that more quantifiable, more expert assessed, more technical research programs, harnessing the labor power of regional inhabitants (as citizen scientists), could address the controversies in knowledge production (Seidler and Bawa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2016</xref>; Singh and Thadani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2015</xref>). However, in such contestations around legitimacy and control, the questions of representation, plurality, and co-design/production are conspicuously absent and with it the voices of many like Ekta, Dawa, and Sunil. Himalayan people and places still shackled by environmental determinist renditions of risk denied their complicated stories of social-ecological transformation. It is these stories that confront tropes of precarity which are functions of temporally linear changes in biogeochemical cycles.</p>