<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par26"><italic>Second, we need to situate climate change within a social and historical context</italic>. Climate change as a concept wields immense power in the Himalayan region (Chakraborty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2019</xref>; Gergan, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2017</xref>; Satyal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>). However, as Sunil understands it, the intersections of oppression he occupies are all inseparable from each other. Accusing erratic rainfall or lack of winter snow as the main perpetrator is a &#8220;way of hiding our sins.&#8221; The ongoing impacts of colonial land management and capitalism mimic the impacts of climate change. We need to be aware of this and not&#160;divorce the process of finding &#8220;fixes&#8221; to the climate problem from existing socio-political inequalities, which often lead our decision-making into the &#8220;technical trap&#8221; (Nightingale et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2019</xref>). The production of vulnerability to climatic events is co-emergent with the existing inequities around caste, gender, class, age, religion, and political affiliations (Bhattarai <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2019</xref>; Brown et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>; Goodrich and Namchu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2019</xref>; Kovacs et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2016</xref>; Nagoda and Eriksen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2014</xref>). The detection and attribution of climatic change need to be reimagined using boundary objects that resemble the entangled social and ecological domains that, according to most Himalayan communities, are inseparable. Flash floods devastating a village are caused not simply by increasing monsoonal intensity, but also represent the hubris of top-down industrial infrastructure, the commodification of natural resource management, and the ebbing presence of communally managed land (Huber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2019</xref>; Huber et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2017</xref>). In this retelling, the boundary object is not simply safe precipitation values but a socionatural one: the mobile village of remittance households.</p>