<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par27"><italic>Third, we need to address the politics of scale</italic> (Ahlborg and Nightingale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2012</xref>; Barrett and Bosak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2018</xref>; Bergmann et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>; Harris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2013</xref>; Ojha et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">b</xref>). The Himalayas straddle two important socio-spatial processes that reveal how cultural, political, and ecological transformations are regionally woven together. First, colonial and post-colonial territorial politics were and are a product of ethnic, racial, and developmental insecurities. This has led to contentious encounters between regional governments around territorial autonomy and control, usually at the cost of social-ecological systems that defy political borders. Second, state-making has proceeded in most regional countries through the unveiling of hegemonic versions of nationalism. The corralling and subjugation of multicultural Himalayan people and places through tools such as national language imposition and widespread Anglophone instruction in educational institutions pose a significant threat to ecological and cultural wellbeing (see Davis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2020</xref>). This prominence of the national scale, its political aspirations, and specific limitations pose a significant roadblock to equitable climate change-related decision-making. National plans to address climate-related issues foreground themselves in international political maneuvering between different collectives of state actors discussing national accountability, respective policies of carbon management, and the viability of a functional regulatory framework given outstanding issues of monitoring and evaluation (Nightingale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2018</xref>). Addressing this bias will require a move towards decentralization and polycentricity in governance. This can serve to improve the existing lack of stakeholder engagement in most top-down intergovernmental scenarios while providing a plurality of climate-society narratives that are brought forth by diverse scalar realities of regional communities. The inclusion of scholars working with feminist theories of science, political ecology, environmental history, human geography, environmental sociology, and anthropology among others can help with such a mobilization. Additionally, <italic>boundary making</italic> institutions like the IPCC can also facilitate this process by actively engaging with such polycentricity through an engagement with the fairly fragmented climate governance landscape of the Himalayas which is populated with all manner of hybrid institutions (e.g., public, private, civil society, community-based organizations).</p>