<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par14">This brings us to collapsology, or <italic>la collapsologie</italic> in French, an emerging field of research that focuses directly on the future of human civilization via the intersectionality of overlapping crises, including the climate emergency, the vast loss of biodiversity and living species, the widening social and racial divide, the rapid advance of machine intelligence, pandemics, and the increasing frequency of natural disasters. It is telling that in France, where collapsology has taken hold with force, two out of every three people surveyed (65%) believe there will be a significant decline if not collapse of human civilization in the next 20 years, and in Italy it is an even higher percentage, with almost three of four Italians (71%) answering the question in the affirmative (McIntyre, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>). The percentage is not quite as high in the United Kingdom and the United States, 56% and 52% respectively, but still indicates a fairly substantial level of pessimism. When the numbers are adjusted for age, for example for those under the age of 35 in the United States, almost two of every three people surveyed (63%) believe that a collapse of civilization will occur in the not-too-distant future. Whether there will be a civilizational collapse or more of a steady decline, what is important to note about the poll is the &#8220;mood&#8221; it has tapped into in the West, a pessimistic mood about the future of humanity. This mood has been captured not only in polling research but more popularly in the domain of contemporary cinema and television. Around a decade ago, many of us watched the intriguing documentary series <italic>Life after People</italic>, which was the <italic>most watched program ever</italic> on the History Channel. It was extraordinary to ponder, with a team of scientific experts, what would happen to the planet if and when we became extinct, which seemed like an inevitability as we watched the series. And what was the consensus, in terms of what would become of the earth when we are no longer here? The earth, again invoking the words of R.E.M., will be fine.</p>