<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par15">More recently, the mood has been captured in the dystopian melodrama <italic>Fear the Walking Dead</italic>, which, if the ratings are any indication, taps into the same wave of pessimism, anxiety, and <italic>fear</italic> about the future of human civilization. And, while the ratings are not what they used to be during the first few seasons of the series when it was <italic>The Walking Dead</italic>, there is still considerable interest in the show. On the surface, it seems rather far-fetched and fantastical, with post-apocalypse humans trying to maneuver around wave after wave of zombies. But if we take a closer look at the series, we begin to see that the zombies are little more than a plot device, a sideshow for what surviving humans most need to fear in the event of a civilizational collapse: <italic>other humans</italic>. The zombies, in other words, are the least of everyone&#8217;s worries as humans, friend and foe, revert to more primal form in the midst of dire circumstances. While there are still glimpses of love and compassion in the surviving human communities, still glimpses of, in a word, <italic>humanity</italic>, the show makes it clear that if there is a collapse of human civilization, all bets are off as to whether human compassion or rather human incivility or worse will win out. As David Sims (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2015</xref>), the insightful television critic for <italic>The Atlantic</italic>, noted in his review of the updated show, <italic>Fear the Walking Dead</italic>:<disp-quote><p id="Par16">Viewers know from the get-go that society is going to collapse. But as leaden as it sounds, the show&#8217;s title has proven thematically apt: Like any great dystopian drama, it&#8217;s about how fear of death and the unknown make people behave in terrible ways. Much as in <italic>The Walking Dead</italic>, the encroaching zombies are just window dressing for the threats humans pose to each other as the rule of law crumbles.. .. The villains of the show aren&#8217;t the zombies, who rarely appear, but the U.S. military, who sweep into an L.A. suburb to quarantine the survivors. Zombies are, after all, a recognizable threat&#8212;but <italic>Fear</italic> plumbs drama and horror from the betrayal by institutions designed to keep people safe.</p></disp-quote></p>