<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par17">A central focus of French researchers Pablo Servigne and Raphael Stevens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2020</xref>), who introduced the term collapsology, most notably in their book <italic>How Everything Can Collapse: A Manual for Our Times</italic>, is the question: &#8220;Can we live more or less peacefully through a &#8216;civilized&#8217; collapse&#8221; or &#8220;will the outcome inevitably be entirely negative?&#8221; (p. 6). From the standpoint of <italic>Fear the Walking Dead</italic>, we can say that even if the outcome post-collapse is not entirely negative, it is anything but a civilized transition. While the term collapsology is reminiscent of Jared Diamond&#8217;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2005</xref>) earlier book <italic>Collapse</italic>, Servigne and Stevens extend the research much further by way of robust interdisciplinary science and extensive meta-analyses of <italic>current</italic> crises. And what is their conclusion? &#8220;In recent decades, humans (or at least many of them, in growing numbers), have become capable of upsetting the large biogeochemical cycle of the earth system, thereby creating a new era of profound and unpredictable change&#8221; (Servigne &amp; Stevens, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2020</xref>, p. 4). Given the scale of the problem, the fundamental altering of the planet&#8217;s biogeochemical cycling caused by human-induced climate change, we now find ourselves in the midst of an <italic>unprecedented</italic> crisis. While it is true that humans have faced many crises before, including war and plagues and natural disasters, the problem, at least for modern humans of the past 12,000 years, has never been so large-scale and global, with <italic>all</italic> of humanity now at risk. Servigne and Stevens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2020</xref>) make clear that we are not simply dealing with a &#8220;one-off disaster that we can forget about after a few months, like a tsunami or a terrorist attack&#8221; (p. 2), as if it were relegated to a single region or empire or population of the world. Rather, the present crisis is more of a &#8220;large scale, irreversible process&#8212;just like the end of the world, admittedly, except that it&#8217;s not the end&#8221; (p. 2).</p>