<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par21">We are, however, cautioned not to overstate the signs of progress that have been made lest we cling to the illusion of perpetual human advancement, whether material and/or technological. Notwithstanding our well-meaning efforts to reduce our carbon footprint, the reality is that it is much too little, too late, as global carbon emissions continue to rise five years after the Paris Agreement. &#8220;Neither &#8216;sustainable development,&#8217;&#8221; write Servigne et al., (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2021</xref>), &#8220;nor &#8216;green growth,&#8217; nor promises of wealth redistribution will be able to stop the disasters from happening, should business-as-usual prevail&#8221; (p. xix). We are, in no uncertain terms, encouraged to stop the madness, not only the madness of runaway climate change, rising carbon emissions, and biodiversity loss but also the madness of clinging to the illusion that the progress of our minimal efforts, in comparison to the enormity of the crisis, can and will stave off the inevitable from happening. At a moment when human beings need to have an adult conversation about something that is very much unprecedented on a global scale, at least within the last 12,000 years, we find ourselves reverting at times to familiar default settings as a means of coping. Or, it might simply be that the unprecedented nature of the current situation is in many ways unrecognizable, for when we encounter something as unprecedented as the possibility of an uninhabitable <italic>world</italic> &#8220;we automatically interpret it through the lenses of familiar categories, thereby rendering invisible precisely that which is unprecedented&#8221; (Zuboff, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2019</xref>, p. 12). For Servigne and Stevens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2020</xref>), the familiar categories or default settings include a variety of religious and social &#8220;myths&#8221;:<disp-quote><p id="Par22">In media and intellectual circles, the question of collapse is not taken seriously. The notorious computer bug that threatened to strike in 2000, and the &#8220;Mayan event&#8221; of 21 December 2012, [ended] the possibility of any serious and factual argument. Anyone who publicly mentions a &#8220;collapse&#8221; is seen as announcing the Apocalypse, and relegated to the narrow category of those &#8220;credulous believers&#8221; in the &#8220;irrational&#8221; who have &#8220;always existed.&#8221; End of story. Time to change the subject! The process of automatically dismissing such talk&#8212;a dismissal which, as it happens, itself appears truly irrational&#8212;has left public debate in such a state of intellectual disrepair that it is no longer possible to express oneself without adopting one of two simplistic standpoints which often border on the ridiculous. On the one hand, we are subjected to apocalyptic, survivalist or pseudo-Mayan language; on the other hand, we have to endure the &#8220;progressive&#8221; denials.. .. These two postures, both frenziedly clinging to their respective myths (the myth of the Apocalypse vs the myth of progress), reinforce each other, view each other as a scarecrow and share a phobia for dignified and respectful debate. All of this just reinforces the attitude of uninhibited collective denial that is such a prominent feature of our times. (pp. 4&#8211;5)</p></disp-quote></p>