<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par22">Next, a psychological perspective highlights the implications of knowledge about how people learn for the process of changing teaching and learning for students, teachers and others supporting instruction (Reimers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2020</xref>). This means that education programs need to be purposefully designed, with specific behavioral changes targeted from the outset. It is not enough for students to acquire theoretical&#160;concepts but also to be prepared to act, based on sensible decisions for real-world and complex situations (Vega-Marcote and Varela-Losada <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2016</xref>). This implies that the educational actions should seek the development of specific skills that foster sustainable actions. Wiek et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2011</xref>) illustrates five basic competencies of education for sustainable development (ESD) that should be combined to reach this aim:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par23"><bold>Systems-thinking competence:</bold> the ability to collectively analyze complex systems across different domains (society, environment, economy, etc.) and across different scales (local to global), thereby considering cascading effects, inertia, feedback loops and other systemic features related to sustainability issues and problem-solving frameworks.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par24"><bold>Anticipatory competence:</bold> the ability to collectively analyze, evaluate, and craft rich visions of the future related to sustainability issues and problem-solving frameworks.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par25"><bold>Normative competence</bold>: the ability to collectively map, specify, apply, reconcile, and negotiate sustainability values, principles, goals, and targets.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par26"><bold>Strategic competence:</bold> the ability to collectively design and implement interventions, transitions, and transformative governance strategies toward sustainability.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par27"><bold>Interpersonal competence:</bold> the ability to motivate, enable, and facilitate collaborative participatory sustainability research and problem solving.</p></list-item></list></p>