<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">The movement <italic>Comitato No Grandi Navi</italic> has taken on a&#160;central role as an active agent of urban change. In its symbolic actions, it conspicuously blocks the passageways used by cruise ships and casts them as transnational symbols of profound ecological, economic, social, and cultural imbalances. The Venice protests attracted significant media attention both in Europe and the rest of the world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn5">5</xref> A&#160;heterogeneous network of activists, associations, and citizen campaigners, united in their mobilization against the cruise industry in Venice and the lagoon, has expressed its dissent toward the implementation of infrastructures which exclusively support tourism and thereby subject large parts of urban space and urban governance to tourist needs. By connecting their spatial knowledge to contested infrastructural developments, they have become an important voice on cruise tourism in Venice. I&#160;will discuss the ways in which protesters share, spread, and apply their knowledge to reappropriate these spaces and reclaim their voice. Yet the structures surrounding the cruise ship are more complex than the dominant discourse on big ships suggests. Venice is not only a&#160;central destination for cruise tourism, but Marghera, the industrial part of the lagoon located on the mainland, is also home to one of the production sites of the Italian shipbuilding company Fincantieri, which has been one of the world leaders in the manufacture of cruise ships since the 1980s. In the public perception, however, Marghera and its manufacturing capabilities remain invisible.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn6">6</xref> Thus, the local field of tension is situated between the limits of popular discourses about the city, the spatialization of the industry, and the governance of these processes. In my contribution, I&#160;want to retrace these interdependences, depict the production and circulation of knowledge by the network, shed light on how protests address and perform these entanglements, and analyze the counter-narrative the <italic>Comitato</italic> initiated to challenge hegemonic political accounts and actions through the symbol of the big ship.</p>