<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">This is where this paper ties in with current debates about infrastructure projects and the demand for social participation, and where it reveals the transnational elements of infrastructure studies. Cultural analysis of infrastructures focuses on the connections between the tangible and intangible dimensions of artifacts and technical systems, as well as their social and cultural effects (Strang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2016</xref>; Flitner, Lossau, M&#252;ller <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2017</xref>). The concept of infrastructure also includes power constellations (van Laak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2001</xref>) and can be understood as &#8220;a mixture of political rationality, administrative techniques, and material systems&#8221; (Larkin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2013</xref>: 331). Dirk van Laak highlights the symbolic value of infrastructures and emphasizes their significance as &#8220;lifelines of a&#160;community&#8221; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2018</xref>: 69). However, this raises the question of who belongs to a&#160;certain community and who has a&#160;stake in infrastructure projects. Hence, analyzing the &#8220;processes of infrastructurisation focuses decidedly on the political, economic and social decisions that are inscribed in infrastructure&#8221; (Niew&#246;hner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2015</xref>: 492), and it shifts the focal point from the artifact to the &#8220;everyday translation processes between materiality and normativity&#8221; (Ibid.). To grasp the structures and actors involved in protests against cruise infrastructures, I&#160;draw on the concept of relational infrastructure that sheds light on the &#8220;relation to organized practices&#8221; (Star &amp; Ruhleder <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1996</xref>: 113) by focusing on the connection between the system and the actors involved. A&#160;relational approach to infrastructures emphasizes the linkages &#8220;between formalized knowledge, social interaction and organizational structure&#8221; (Niew&#246;hner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2014</xref>: 343), and touches upon the tacit knowledge of individuals or groups and their practices.</p>