<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0360">We are now at the crossroads toward or away from a sustainable development trajectory, depending on how we collectively decide how we want to emerge from this pandemic. For illustrative purposes, we can broadly envision two alternatives that embody distinct views on how to respond to the current global disruption (see <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
). On the one hand, strategic decisions made during the recovery could focus on pathways to rebuilding society and the economy as we know it, that is, reverting to a business-as-usual scenario. On the other, a recovery path could be chosen to harness the disruption caused by COVID-19 and catalyze a broader transformation toward resilient and green economies. The first alternative places a single focus on recovery from the specific shock caused by COVID-19. The second is guided by a systems thinking approach to strategic decision making, seeking integrated solutions able to strengthen society's general preparedness for a variety of shocks and looming threats. It is currently unclear which of these contrasting alternatives will predominate, that is, the extent to which the international community will succeed in coupling near-term responses to COVID-19 with longer-term transformations of human systems toward sustainability, which is also informed by more comprehensive risk management efforts across scale. Before moving to key considerations and recommendations in section 5, it is worth also highlighting some potential challenges and pitfalls involved in the transformation process.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Illustrative narratives for alternative futures.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>COVID-19 and the global lockdown have led to a global recession, undermined long-term development progress, and exacerbated inequalities within and across countries. As countries transition from crisis management to a focus on socioeconomic recovery, we illustrate here two contrasting narratives for future development paths, which would also have consequences for building more resilient food systems.</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Resilient and Sustainable Futures:</bold> Fiscal stimulus packages seek to couple recovery with targeted transformation toward more equitable, circular, green, and inclusive economies. Strong emphasis is placed on strengthening social safety nets and access to basic services. International development cooperation is recognized as an essential tool to help narrow economic and technological gaps between countries. This is reflected in a sustained increase of ODA contributions by developed countries to facilitate a collective international response to the crisis. These ODA commitments are coupled to fiscal and institutional reforms in developing countries toward greater accountability and transparency. Great emphasis is placed on education and training, helping to build endogenous research capacities in developing countries. A balanced approach of technological innovation and upscaling of available sustainable agricultural practices allows agricultural productivity to be improved, while also helping to regenerate degraded lands. Recognizing and rewarding farmers as stewards of ecosystem services through targeted incentive and payment schemes, coupled with strengthened regulations and enforcement mechanisms further contribute to maintaining carbon stocks and protecting biodiversity. The international push toward healthy and affordable diets, which is supported through targeted government programs and awareness campaigns, reduces the prevalence of non-communicable diseases while also reducing the pressure on land. The world is moving toward integrated collaboration and integration to address global challenges, maintaining a collective focus on SDG targets in 2030 and carbon neutrality by 2050.</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Disordered recovery to business as usual.</bold> Emphasis in the recovery is placed on saving and restoring existing economic structures as fast as possible without strategizing investments. Country capacity with respect to issuance of fiscal stimulus packages differs greatly: growth returns to the richest parts of the world, but development in low- and middle-income economies stalls. Greenhouse gas emissions continue to increase, as several countries dilute their national climate change targets and environmental regulations. The objectives of the Paris Agreement appear to be out of reach, and multilateral cooperation weakens as official development assistance (ODA) and investments from developed countries are reduced. Devaluation of currencies, loss of remittances, depression of prices for primary commodities, and absence of social safety nets further exacerbate the poverty and food insecurity in developing countries, while obesity levels continue to rise globally. The technological gap between developed and developing countries widens. Developing countries struggle to improve agricultural and livestock productivity, as they are also confronted with managing climate variability and change, land degradation, and other environmental changes. The multilateral system is weak, countries putting national priorities first. While some countries are thriving economically, other countries are falling behind. The world becomes divided into regional blocks with limited cooperation among them.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Source: Authors.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>