<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0365"><italic>The timing and speed of the socioeconomic recovery are uncertain</italic>. While there were some initial signs of improvement early in 2021, global infection numbers continue to be at high levels. By the end of December 2020 over 79.2 million cases of COVID-19 and over 1.7 million deaths had been reported globally since the start of the pandemic (<xref rid="bb0655" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020</xref>). The confirmed cases of COVID-19, which are reported on a weekly basis by WHO, peaked at close to 5 million people in early January (<xref rid="bb0660" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2021a</xref>) and the numbers started to drop to about half this amount by mid-February before increasing again, reaching again over four million cases in early April 2021 (<xref rid="bb0665" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2021b</xref>). This fluctuation between global drops and increases in weekly case numbers has continued throughout 2021, as situations in some countries improved only to deteriorate in others again. While China, Australia, New Zealand, and a few other countries appear to have largely contained the virus, the number of infections continue to be high in several other parts of the world. In autumn 2021, Europe is confronted with another surge of Covid-19 cases (<xref rid="bb0670" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2021c</xref>). There is concern that the extent of infections and fatalities particularly in developing regions may be higher than reported due to limited testing and healthcare capacities, as has been explored in the Nepal (<xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Giri and Rana, 2021</xref>). However, other factors may also be at play, such as demographics, geography, past experiences with epidemics, level of urbanization and connectivity, which been explored as arguments for explaining the comparatively and unexpectedly low Covid-19 cases numbers in most African countries (e.g. <xref rid="bb0405" ref-type="bibr">Nguimkeu and Tadadjeu, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0715" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2021</xref>). As of early November 2021, the number of confirmed COVID-19 cases across the globe reached over 249 million and over 4.9 million deaths had been reported since the start of the pandemic (<xref rid="bb0665" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2021b</xref>).</p>