<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0120">Land conflicts are particularly prominent in the context of MR with contestations involving the disappearance of cultural land and heritage (<xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">Huang, 2018</xref>), valuation of land solely in financial terms (<xref rid="b0455" ref-type="bibr">Marino, 2018</xref>), inadequate compensation for loss of land (<xref rid="b0580" ref-type="bibr">Siders, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">Flavelle, 2020</xref>), elite capture and enclosure of land (<xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Ajibade, 2019</xref>), demographic pressure in resettlement sites (<xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">Hanna et al., 2019</xref>) and uncertainty about land tenure in receiving communities (<xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Donner, 2015</xref>). Related to these issues are the unmaking and remaking of place and the role of MR in land-use and spatial planning within wider adaptation governance. For example, some MR programs have led to the <italic>un</italic>making of land where the withdrawal of a community has resulted in land abandonment as a means of creating a sacrificial buffer zone for future flooding events (<xref rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr">Maly and Ishikawa, 2013</xref>). Other cases involve the <italic>re</italic>making of land where vacated areas are repurposed for new uses. Positive examples include ecological restoration in Mongolia (<xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Dickinson and Webber, 2007</xref>), wetlands in China (<xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Du, 2012</xref>) and recreational uses such as community parks and gardens in the US (<xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Brady, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0645" ref-type="bibr">Zavar and Hagelman, 2016</xref>). Negative examples can be found in Lagos and Manila where retreat incentivized new development of at-risk coastal lands following the forced displacement of the poor (<xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Ajibade, 2019</xref>).</p>