<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0040">The first goal of bridging disciplines to tackle climate change lies in scaling up low-carbon innovation, from individual to community and then to wider society, and developing characteristics of user profiles based on various economic, political, and socio-cultural backgrounds. This helps to acquire a more disaggregated understanding of the diffusion of technological innovation, including product and services <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, and social innovation <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Understanding individual behaviours and preferences, and how these aggregate up to group and society levels leading to fundamental change across the entire economy and society <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, is vitally important, as it allows an understanding of the acceptance and viability of different policies and measures. But it is also a critical step in designing models of technological and behavioural transitions to reflect real-life conditions more realistically. Attention must be paid to how people&#8217;s social relations influence energy demand <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, while aspects of &#8216;energy sufficiency&#8217; <xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, &#8216;downscaling&#8217; and &#8216;energy descent&#8217; <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref> must be explored, as drivers of behaviour change through direct and embodied energy use that cuts across electricity and heat, buildings, transportation, the food system, and as drivers of degrowth with potential impacts on industry. At the end of the day, framing energy as a social relation is crucial given that the political nature of nature&#8211;society relations can arguably be best manifested over energy decisions and the social power constellations these give rise to <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>.</p>