<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In addition to imposing climate reparations based on countries&#8217; historical emissions, we propose levying reparations in accordance with countries&#8217; current levels of emissions. In this regard, we propose that a scheme of global carbon taxation or other financial contribution be levied in accordance with each country&#8217;s current annual total CO<sub>2</sub> emission levels (see <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), balanced with current per capita emissions (see <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This dual source would complement the levy based on countries&#8217; historical emissions (see <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). We think that such a measure is appropriate for assessing climate reparations because, as noted above, countries with large populations should not be unduly penalized for their numbers. A country&#8217;s total annual CO<sub>2</sub> emissions are also relevant for assessing climate reparations since this figure reflects public policies that result in excessive energy consumption, including both a lack of initiatives to reduce per capita emissions and decisions about the kind of energy sources to promote. Here, the fact that China is currently the biggest annual CO<sub>2</sub> emitter (9.5 billion metric tons) is due both to its population size and to its continuous construction of coal-fired power plants&#8212;currently outnumbering those in the rest of the world combined&#8212;in order to drive its economy.<sup><xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> The United States is in second place (4.9 billion metric tons), followed by India, Russia, Japan, Germany, South Korea, Iran, Canada, and Indonesia. The imposition of a global carbon tax would provide additional financial resources to the climate reparations fund, while encouraging countries to lower their CO<sub>2</sub> emissions by cutting their fossil fuel consumption.</p>