<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0205">In this study, we set out to investigate why WNV outbreaks have become so frequent in Europe over the past decade. If we consider the findings of this work, together with other important research in this area, we can start to build a picture of why the virus has become so prevalent in Europe. We hypothesize that:<list list-type="simple" id="list0005"><list-item id="listitem0005"><label>(1)</label><p id="p0210">Rising winter temperatures, or rather the creation of optimal temperature conditions allowed the virus to overwinter with <italic>Culex pipiens</italic>. Given current trends, we can also expect to see regions that have previously been too cold for <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> to survive over winter become viable locations and cause further havoc in regions that are currently experiencing just a few annual cases. On the contrary, regions which currently have optimal conditions for overwintering mosquitoes may become too warm in the future.</p></list-item><list-item id="listitem0010"><label>(2)</label><p id="p0215">Warmer summer temperatures are benefiting mosquitoes, influencing their hatching rate and development time, and shortening the extrinsic incubation period (EIP) of WNV.</p></list-item><list-item id="listitem0015"><label>(3)</label><p id="p0220">Shrinking water resources are increasing WNV prevalence in birds and mosquitoes during some seasons. It may be the case that this phenomenon is also acting at a macro-scale in Europe and is a significant driver of recent outbreaks, especially given that meteorological and hydrological droughts are becoming more frequent and extreme <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>. These changes also occurred during an economic crisis and subsequent austerity, where government institutions were severely weakened and had to limit spending on key sectors, and segments of the human population were exposed to increased financial hardship.</p></list-item></list></p>