<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Another limitation is that data on HIV transmission risk were self-reported in the DHS data set, which may be influenced by recall and social desirability biases, as well as the level of community stigma. Nonresponse bias may have affected results because HIV prevalence was based on population-based laboratory HIV testing. However, extensive analyses by studies that have used DHS data have not shown clear patterns in nonresponse rates by various risk or protective factors.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> Although our use of data spanning 12 years captures a greater number of participants and a wider range of weather variability, the large range of survey years may have led to variations in the observed effect estimates. The use of survey-level fixed effects may account for some of this variability and we do not hypothesize that the association between heavy rainfall and HIV prevalence would change over time. Although the measurements of rainfall are highly precise in the IRI/LDEO Climate Data Library,<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> the distribution of satellite data and ground stations and the level of accuracy of the resultant data may not be consistent among countries, leading to the potential for misclassification of heavy rainfall in certain locations. However, by using the SPI, which categorizes heavy rainfall relative to the region-specific climatologic average, rather than an absolute threshold, we reduced the potential for misclassification. Residual confounding is a possibility, but deviations from long-term trends may be mostly independent of other potential confounding variables. In addition, our analysis only extends to 2017, excluding more recent HIV and rainfall data that may be influenced by progress in response to the UNAIDS 90-90-90 and 95-95-95 targets, and worsening climate change.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup></p>