<p xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">While issues of climate justice have traditionally focused on urban populations, the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS) identifies serious concerns for vulnerable populations within rural regions in the U.S. because climate change health threats are not expected to affect all populations equally [<xref rid="B20-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Lal <italic>et al.</italic> assert that &#8220;the literature specifically related to how climate change will affect rural communities, their resilience, and adaptive capacity in the United States is scarce&#8221; [<xref rid="B8-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] (p. 819). Further, the literature suggests that vulnerability differs not only among nations and regions but also across demographic divides (<italic>i.e.</italic>, race, ethnicity, age, income level, and gender) [<xref rid="B21-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B23-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Beyond the well-established disparities in health between Caucasians and racial and ethnic minorities, rural minorities are at an even greater disadvantage for health status and health care [<xref rid="B24-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B26-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. NIEHS also identifies people living in poverty and outdoor workers (<italic>i.e.</italic>, farmers and farmworkers) as vulnerable populations for climate change effects [<xref rid="B20-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Rural and underrepresented populations, such as those inhabiting the Southeastern U.S., represent some of the most vulnerable of demographic and occupational groups. </p>