<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Young people have led efforts to advocate for and achieve deliberate and meaningful engagement in the global dialogue about the Paris Agreement on climate change and its implementation.<sup><xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> These efforts are driven by the collaborative work of youth-led organizations from the local to the international level, where they are formally recognized as YOUNGO, the official youth constituency of UNFCCC, which participates as an observer in the COPs. Despite their observer status, these organizations are advancing various programs to augment young people&#8217;s participation and attempt to influence international negotiations and conferences, including through the organization of annual Conferences of Youth. From our experience, the engagement of young people at these negotiations has amplified advocacy efforts and put pressure on states to meet their commitments on emission reductions. During the 2019 UNFCCC COP25 in Madrid, young activists drafted the Intergovernmental Declaration on Children, Youth and Climate Action, which acknowledges young people&#8217;s right to a healthy environment and their role as agents of change.<sup><xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> With the COVID-19 pandemic moving advocacy efforts online, young people have been actively engaging in online events for climate action. For instance, in February 2021, the Children&#8217;s Environmental Rights Initiative organized an online Tweetstorm event on Twitter, urging governments to sign the intergovernmental declaration.<sup><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Moreover, in recent years, universities have become a growing platform for youth participation in international climate decision-making.<sup><xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Students are participating in university observer delegations to the COPs, often as part of the Research and Independent Nongovernmental Organizations (RINGO) constituency. Significant networks have emerged to amplify student voices in climate advocacy and leverage partnerships with academia to raise global awareness, for example through the COP26 Universities Network and the University Climate Change Coalition.<sup><xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup></p>