<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?OLF?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sustain Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sustain Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Sustainability Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1862-4065</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1862-4057</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Japan</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8786589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35096181</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1091</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-022-01091-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Special Feature: Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Envisioning just transformations in and beyond the EU bioeconomy: inspirations from decolonial environmental justice and degrowth</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3209-545X</contrib-id><name><surname>Ramcilovic-Suominen</surname><given-names>Sabaheta</given-names></name><address><email>sabaheta.ramcilovik-suominen@luke.fi</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.22642.30</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4668 6757</institution-id><institution>Natural Resources Institute Finland, </institution></institution-wrap>It&#x000e4;inen Pitk&#x000e4;katu 4 A, 20520 Turku, Finland </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The European Union (EU) is adhering to decarbonization of its economy to tackle what is narrowly framed as &#x02018;environmental issues&#x02019; of our socioecological and civilizational crises&#x02014;including, but not limited to, climate change and biodiversity loss. A shift to bio-based economy (bioeconomy) is an important component of this effort. This paper applies theoretical ideas from decolonial environmental justice and degrowth, placed in the wider context of transformations, to analyse the EU bioeconomy policy within the global context, and to draw lessons and recommendations for just transformations in the EU bioeconomy policy. I identify five dominant logics and approaches in the EU bioeconomy that act as barriers for just transformations and propose alternative ones that can support such transformations. Barriers and alternatives include (1) framing &#x02018;nature&#x02019; as a resource and service provider for humans, who are seen as separate from nature, and the need to abandon human&#x02013;nature duality; (2) dominance of economic green growth and technoscientific policy solutions, and the need to place planetary justice at the centre of tackling socioecological crises; (3) a limited approach to justice, and the need to act upon climate and epistemic justice, including self-determination and self-governing authority; (4) the EU&#x02019;s ambition for global leadership and competitiveness in global bioeconomic markets and governance, and the need to redefine global governance towards partnerships based on the principles of solidarity, mutual respect, reconciliation and redistribution of power and wealth; (5) hegemonic politico-economic structures and actor coalitions in charge of the EU bioeconomy, and the need for decentralized bottom-up leadership coalitions that promote direct democracy, local autonomy and sovereignty beyond state. I conclude with reflections on the politics of change and risks of co-optation, with a hope to inspire decolonial and just socioecological transformations in and beyond bioeconomy.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>EU bioeconomy</kwd><kwd>Degrowth</kwd><kwd>Decoloniality</kwd><kwd>Decolonial environmental justice</kwd><kwd>Transformations</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002341</institution-id><institution>Academy of Finland</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>332353</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ramcilovic-Suominen</surname><given-names>Sabaheta</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Natural Resources Institute Finland (LUKE)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by Natural Resources Institute Finland (LUKE).</p></open-access></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Socioecological emergencies, global inequalities, the pandemic, decarbonization, bioeconomy, degrowth, environmental justice: what common threads?</title><p id="Par2">The bleak findings from global assessments and literature showing the rapidly degrading state of socioecological systems continue to fill our newsfeeds. Figures and scenarios related to climate change and biodiversity loss are alarming and are among the most highlighted in policy discourses and public debates. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) report of 2018 estimated that to have a 50&#x02013;66% chance to stay within 1.5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C of the pre-industrial level, global carbon emissions need to be reduced to around 50% from the current levels by 2030, and eliminated by 2050 (Masson-Delmotte et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2018</xref>). The IPCC report of 2019 shows an accelerating rate of species extinction and suggests that we are approaching a tipping point of global biodiversity beyond which a more dramatic and faster biodiversity decline is inevitable (Tucker et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">2018</xref>). The IPCC report of 2021 echoed these messages, with higher clarity and precision than before, removing any doubts of the alarming state of the global climate, suggesting that nothing short of an immediate and complete cessation of CO<sub>2</sub> and other greenhouse gas emissions can stabilise the climate (IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2021</xref>). Each year is warmer than the preceding one, with the last 7&#x000a0;years being the hottest years ever recorded in the last 140&#x000a0;years (NASA Global Climate Change&#x000a0;database). The year 2020, the hottest ever recorded, also became the turning point in history when human-made materials outweigh the living biomass (Elhacham et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR900">2020</xref>). The Earth Overshoot Day, the point of time when human resource extraction exceeds the capacity for regeneration of those resources, indicates that collectively we humans require the equivalent of 1.75 planets to sustain our lifestyles (Gills and Morgan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2020</xref>). This figure is much larger in GDP-rich countries (Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2020b</xref>).</p><p id="Par3">These socioecological and existential crises, including climate change, are increasingly recognized as a global injustice problem due to (neo)colonial and imperial relations of extraction of labour and resources in the GDP-poor countries (many of which are in the &#x02018;Global South&#x02019;) to foster economic growth in the GDP-rich countries (&#x02018;Global North&#x02019;) (Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">b</xref>; Hickel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2021</xref>; Martinez-Alier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2020</xref>). The resulting socioecological crises have disproportionately benefited and harmed different countries and regions of the world and different segments of society (genders, ethnicities, races) (Gore and Alestig <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2020</xref>; Harcourt and Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">b</xref>; Hickel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2021</xref>; Sultana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">2021</xref>). Those least responsible for the crises are, however, the most vulnerable and unprotected, importantly as a result of the continued marginalization and dispossession enabled by colonialism and the coloniality that followed it.</p><p id="Par4">In the wake of the global COVID-19 pandemic, the multiple and interrelated crises that humanity is facing, even if with significant differences in urgency and severity depending on the societal groups and class (Sultana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">2021</xref>), have gained renewed attention and a new dimension of interconnectedness with planetary health (Leach et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">2021</xref>; IPBES <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2020</xref>). The COVID-19 pandemic has provided momentum for questioning the current ways of doing and being in the world, and with that more focus on the viability of our current economic and environment protection systems (B&#x000fc;scher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2021</xref>). Not only have the cavities of our global economic and health systems been exposed (Gereffi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2020</xref>) but so have also the moral cavities upon which these are based (Sultana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par5">This increased focus relates to the concepts and initiatives for transitions and transformations, the literature on which has flourished over the last decade (Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2015</xref>; Feola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2021</xref>; H&#x000f6;lscher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2018</xref>). Discussions range from a need to shift our economic model towards one that prioritizes people and wellbeing over economic growth and profit (Raworth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">2012</xref>) to the need for a civilizational shift and the rise of a new era (Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>; Kothari&#x000a0;et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>). Taking into account the distinction between transitions and transformations elaborated in the next section, I join the scholars who argue that transformations and transformative approaches rather than transitions and reformist approaches are needed to tackle the concurrent global socioecological and inequality crises (Gills et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2021</xref>; Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>; Martin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2020</xref>). Social movements have a key role to play in transformations by providing alternative ways of relating to one another and to more-than-human worlds, and by outlining alternative modes of economic and governing systems (Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>; Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>). Degrowth and environmental justice are prominent fields of study and constitute the agenda of many social movements that call for a shift in our imaginaries, mentalities and economies, with justice at the heart of transformation processes (Akbulut et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2019</xref>; Gerber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2020</xref>; Martin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2020</xref>, Martinez-Alier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2012</xref>).</p><p id="Par6">The dominance and assumed universality of western knowledge, which justified its imposition on different hemispheres ever since the European colonial project, is part of the problem as it continues to shape development theory and practice (Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>; Sh&#x000f6;neberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2019</xref>). The environmental governance field represents a good example where Eurocentric ideas of environment and nature are exclusively used as a basis for designing global policy problems and solutions, dismissing indigenous knowledge systems as subjective and/or situated cultural knowledge (Biermann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020</xref>; Rodr&#x000ed;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>). The EU has a multitude of environmental policies with direct and indirect implications for the Global South, where issues such as global deforestation, climate change and biodiversity are tackled. The EU bioeconomy policy is one of the EU policies which, even if not directly implemented or imposed on Global South countries, has direct impacts on them owing to the EU&#x02019;s role in imports and trade as well as corporate investments in developing the green economy in those countries (Fuchs et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2020</xref>; Hickel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2021</xref>; Zografos and Robins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par7">The EU bioeconomy policy is embedded within and relies on the long-standing constellation of policy actors and institutions, similar policy problems and solutions defined by the global and EU political and economic elite (T&#x000f6;ller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">2021</xref>; Vogelpohl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">2021</xref>). To build more ecologically sound and socially just bio-based societies and economies, the EU needs to look beyond affirmative reformist approaches that rely on the existing political and economic institutions, rules, roles, knowledge and relations, which have contributed to socioecological degradation and inequalities (B&#x000fc;scher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2021</xref>; Gills and Morgan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2020</xref>; Martin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2020</xref>; Nightingale et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2019</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>), and seek to embrace a decolonial and pluralist approach to justice, environment and development more broadly.</p><p id="Par8">The paper proceeds as follows: first I review the EU bioeconomy policy in terms of dominant bioeconomy visions and changes in the new revised bioeconomy strategy (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>). Second, to emphasize the importance of global socioecological justice implications in the context of the EU bioeconomy policy, I review some of the more recent empirical findings that emphasize the socioecological costs and creation of green sacrifice zones associated with transition to green and renewable resources and energy systems. Third, I outline the theory that informs this research&#x02014;decoloniality, decolonial environmental justice and degrowth&#x02014;followed by main results, consisting of dominant and alternative logics and approaches that act as barriers to vis-&#x000e0;-vis enablers of just transformations. Finally, I reflect on the politics and the process of transformations and change.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>From a policy of green growth to a practice of green sacrifice zones</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Dominant EU bioeconomy visions and the revised EU bioeconomy strategy</title><p id="Par9">In the 1970s Romanian economist Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen introduced the term &#x02018;bioeconomics&#x02019;, which directed attention to the physical, material and energy boundaries to economic growth, based on the principle of entropy described by the second law of thermodynamics (Georgescu-Roegen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2011</xref>). His ideas are considered by many as foundational for the discipline of ecological economics and degrowth alike (Asara et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2015</xref>; Vivien et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2019</xref>), even if contemporary debates on degrowth, as I will show later, draw on a host of other disciplines and therefore extend beyond Georgescu-Roegen&#x02019;s notion of bioeconomics. Georgescu-Roegen&#x02019;s original concept of bioeconomics and the new idea of bioeconomy launched and promoted by the EU and Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), despite the illusion of similarity in wording and despite the many existing visions related to the latter idea (Bugge et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>; P&#x000fc;lzl, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">2014</xref>; Vivien et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2019</xref>), can hardly be farther apart (Vivien et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2019</xref> for details).</p><p id="Par10">My concern is with this &#x0201c;new&#x0201d; bioeconomy as framed in the EU bioeconomy policy. I start with the most commonly cited definition where bioeconomy is defined as &#x0201c;an economy where the basic building blocks for materials, chemicals and energy are derived from renewable biological resources&#x0201d; (McCormick and Kautto <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2013</xref>). This definition is in line with the one used by the European Commission (EC), which further emphasizes the primary production sectors (such as forestry, agriculture and bioenergy), as well as services (including knowledge and innovations) as part of EU bioeconomy (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>, p.&#x000a0;4). The focus is on bioeconomy in relation to terrestrial ecosystems, sectors and forms of land use that relate to it, including forestry, agriculture and bioenergy.</p><p id="Par11">There are different visions and narratives of the EU bioeconomy (Bugge et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>; P&#x000fc;lzl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">2014</xref>; Vivien et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2019</xref>). Importantly, however, they differ in terms of the lobbying and support they receive from stakeholders, which makes it possible to distinguish fewer dominant visions (L&#x000fc;hmann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2020</xref>; Korhonen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2018</xref>; Vivien&#x000a0;et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2019</xref>). The dominant EU bioeconomy visions and discourses are closely associated with industry, private sector, intensified biomass harvest, technological innovations, and production of novel bio-based materials. The EU dominant bioeconomy visions tend to overlook the ecological, social and cultural sustainability dimensions, which remain marginally covered (Ramcilovic-Suominen and P&#x000fc;lzl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2018</xref>). Consequently, the bioeconomy policy as a whole has been framed as technology-driven and biomass-based green growth bioeconomy (Bugge et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>; Levidow et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2019</xref>), elite-driven neoliberalization of nature, which remains silent on the politics of bioeconomy (Birch et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2010</xref>; Levidow et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2019</xref>). Most recently, the policy has also been framed as a novel form of extractivism (Boyer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2019</xref>). These framings and critical analyses expose the gaps between the EU bioeconomy policies and the planetary boundaries and holistic sustainability (Gawel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2019</xref>; Ramcilovic-Suominen and P&#x000fc;lzl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2018</xref>). I next shortly outline the evolution of EU bioeconomy policy and analyse the revised EU bioeconomy strategy (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par12">On the basis of the efforts to develop biotechnology research and innovation in 1980&#x02013;90s, and from there the attempts at knowledge-based bioeconomy (KBBE) during 2000&#x02013;2010, the EC adopted its first bioeconomy strategy entitled &#x0201c;Innovating for Sustainable Growth: a Bioeconomy for Europe&#x0201d; in 2012 (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>). While the strategy was an influential political tool that led to individual EU member states developing their own strategies (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2021</xref>), it faced severe criticism among the civil society and research community (for a summary of critiques, see Kurki and Ahola-Launonen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2021</xref>). Consequently, in late 2018, after a stakeholder consultation process (L&#x000fc;hmann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2020</xref>), the EC presented the revised bioeconomy strategy for Europe entitled &#x0201c;A Sustainable Bioeconomy for Europe: Strengthening the Connection Between Economy, Society and the Environment&#x0201d; (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par13">As the name suggests, the revised strategy aims to respond to some of the critiques ascribed to the EU strategy of 2012, including the assumption of biomass sufficiency to satisfy the present level of consumption, and the socioecological damage and conflicts associated with increased production and imports of biomass (Kurki and Ahola-Launonen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2021</xref>). The revised EU bioeconomy strategy responded to these critiques in several ways. First, it diversifies the challenges at hand, which now include finite biological resources and planetary boundaries, climate change, biodiversity loss, land degradation and deforestation. Second, it highlights sustainability as the key principle, adopting the term &#x02018;sustainable bioeconomy&#x02019;. Looking beyond introductory sections and into policy measures and actions, however, sustainability is reduced to economic sustainability only, where green economic growth and green jobs have a key role. Third, locally sourced bioeconomy is encouraged, but policy measures and actions are limited to assessment, measuring, monitoring and only voluntary actions. Fourth, the solutions remain limited to technoscientific solutions, where modernised industries and green jobs for innovative production and consumption, including cascading and circular use of materials and energy, dominate. Fifth and final, the green growth and the EU global competitiveness and prosperity of its citizens are highlighted or framed as ultimate goals.</p><p id="Par14">While the changes in the revised EU bioeconomy strategy are a step in the right direction, the revised strategy remains problematic in two major ways: first, the framing of challenges vis-&#x000e0;-vis solutions; second, the ignorance of justice and inequalities. Concerning the former, all socioecological emergencies are approached as challenges or bottlenecks that need to be addressed so that the ultimate goals (green growth, jobs, the EU&#x02019;s competitiveness) may be realized, rather than something that needs to be addressed and tackled in its own right. This is evident in the closer analyses of policy measures and actions, where policy actions concerning climate change, biodiversity loss, ecosystem degradation and deforestation are limited to the need for their better understanding, assessing, measuring, and in some cases their <italic>voluntary</italic> addressing. On the contrary, the proposed actions concerning all aspects related to growth and the EU&#x02019;s competitiveness (e.g. bio-based industry, innovation, green jobs) are elaborated more concretely and include non-voluntary policy packages. Concerning justice and equality, the revised strategy is devoid of concerns and issues related to climate justice, carbon inequality, and different carbon footprints and resource use between different sectors of society in the EU, let alone EU ecological footprint and global extraction. This is despite the growing scientific and political debates on carbon inequality and climate injustice within the EU (Gore and Alestig <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2020</xref>). The reference to equality in the revised strategy is limited to &#x0201c;equal exploitation of bioeconomy opportunities across the EU coastal, rural and urban areas&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;equitable job creation to ensure European competitiveness&#x0201d; (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>, p.&#x000a0;71). The idea of sufficiency rather than substitution alone and the need for and actions towards reducing production and consumption are also absent. The centrality of growth, the reliance on biomass and the framing of nature as a resource whose function is to serve humans and their economy remain unquestioned in the revised strategy (see also, Eversberg and Holz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2020</xref>; Kurki and Ahola-Launonen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Displacement of socioecological costs and creation of green sacrifice zones</title><p id="Par15">Global socioecological implications and justice implications are central to the EU bioeconomy for several reasons. The first concerns the EU colonial resource accumulation and contemporary vast carbon footprints (Gore and Alstig <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2020</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">b</xref>; UNDP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">2020</xref>). The second, the lack of domestic biocapacity in most EU countries and their reliance on imports (Hoff et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2018</xref>; Fuchs et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2020</xref>; Proskurina <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">2018</xref>; Hickel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2021</xref>). The third and final reason is the transition to bio-based, green, or low-carbon energy and economic systems, which in more than one way, and similarly to non-renewable counterparts, can and do contribute to extraction, extractivism, socioecological conflicts and various kinds of injustices. Building on Lerner&#x02019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2010</xref>) &#x02018;sacrifice zones&#x02019;, scholars have used the concept &#x02018;green sacrifice zones&#x02019; (Scott and Smith <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">2017</xref>; Zografos and Robbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>) to conceptualise situations where transition to green and renewable energy and economic systems leads to green grabbing, displacement, dispossession, exploitation and a range of other injustices towards marginalized groups and local indigenous and non-indigenous communities. Such sacrifice zones are reproduced in the process of developing green and renewable infrastructure (e.g. Brock et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2021</xref>; Dunlap and Arce <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2021</xref>; Sovacool et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2021</xref>), as well as in the process of implementing Eurocentric &#x02018;green&#x02019; policy solutions; the latter tend to favour scientific over local or indigenous knowledge systems, and elite groups over disadvantaged societal groups who are marginalized across various identity lines, from race to gender to class, etc. (Zografos and Robbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>). This leads to various forms of violence and injustices, including epistemic injustice (Harcourt and Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>; Rodr&#x000ed;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par16">Shifting to bio-based materials does not imply fewer socioecological conflicts, unless the sources of environmental and social injustices, such as extractive mentalities, exploitive human&#x02013;nature relations, economic and cultural domination and power asymmetries are addressed. An emerging body of literature documents the harms and conflicts over extraction of resources needed for decarbonization of our economies and for growth of green and bio-economies (Huff and Orengo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2020</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">2020</xref>; Zografos and Robins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>), which in some cases have led to murder of those resisting extraction (Butt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>; Le Tran et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2020</xref>; Menton and Le Billon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">Some of the most serious examples of violence and extraction are associated with biomass for production of biofuels (Bastos-Lima and Gupta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2014</xref>; Backhouse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2021</xref>), hydropower (Del Bene et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>) and wind energy (Dunlap and Arce <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2021</xref>), which lead to food insecurity, forced displacement, loss of livelihoods, oppression, dispossession and loss of rights and access to land and resources. Temper et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">2020</xref>) show that globally conflicts associated with biomass and hydropower extraction are comparable to those of extraction of non-renewables. Yet, the political momentum of decarbonization, bioeconomy and transition to green energy have helped reframe energy sources such as biomass and hydropower as &#x02018;green&#x02019; (Zarfl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">2014</xref>). Wind energy is argued to produce &#x02018;infrastructural violence&#x02019;, where communities are relocated or otherwise affected by heavy infrastructure (Dunlap and Arce <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2021</xref>). When locals resist the land grabs and dispossession this has led to physical violence, intimidation and in the worse cases death of activists (Butt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>; Menton and Le Billon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2021</xref>). Local resistance movements have nonetheless been effective in slowing down extractive projects worldwide (Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">2020</xref>). While conflicts and violence tend to be more severe in cases where indigenous and politically and socially marginalized groups are involved (Butt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>; Menton and Le Billon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2021</xref>), they occur across different geographies, including in EU countries (Brock et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2021</xref>; Sovacool et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par18">This short overview reveals the political nature of bioeconomy and decarbonization projects, where issues of justice and power and creation of winners and losers appear to be inevitable. Considering that some of the key actors in the bioeconomy and in GDP-rich EU member states are agribusinesses and the pharmaceutical industry (e.g. Korhonen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2018</xref>), the risks and concerns only increase (FFRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>). Considering the path dependency, power relations and institutions embedded in the global environmental governance, it is highly unlikely that the local dispossession and violence associated with many of such policies (Huff and Orengo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2020</xref>; Milne and Mahanty <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2019</xref>; Ramcilovic-Suominen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2021</xref>) are to subside in the case of bioeconomy. On the contrary, given the importance of market-based and technoscientific solutions in the EU bioeconomy, the same actor coalitions and the path dependencies (Vogelpohl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">2021</xref>), there are numerous reasons to be concerned about the impacts of the EU bioeconomy policy in the Global South and global peripheries elsewhere (Sovacool <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2021</xref>; Sovacool et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2021</xref>; Zografos and Robins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Decoloniality, decolonial environmental justice and degrowth as tenants of transformations</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>Transformations</title><p id="Par19">While the literature on transformations has flourished and different strands have emerged (Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2015</xref>), some common trends can be observed. Those include (1) reference to the Anthropocene and planetary boundaries (Gills and Morgan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2020</xref>; Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2015</xref>; Steffen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">2007</xref>) and (2) need for fundamental shift, as opposed to minor or incremental changes (Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2015</xref>) and (3) radical and widespread societal changes as opposed to changes in a certain sector or policy domain (Holscher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2018</xref>). Beyond these generic features, there is little agreement about what transformation is, what ends it should achieve, or how (Bluwstein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2021</xref>; Gram-Hanssen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2021</xref>). The uncertainty about the <italic>what</italic> and the <italic>how</italic> of transformations, I argue, is part of the definition of transformations as an uncertain, emergent, heterogenic and multifaceted process which is not managed and instituted under the existing structures, forms of knowledge and definitions. This again sets transformations aside from the more structured and managed processes of transitions that are expected to lead societies towards known and desired ends and futures (Holscher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2018</xref>; Pelenc et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2019</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par20">I highlight in particular the politics or power dimensions (Martinez-Alier et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2016</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>; Scoones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">2016</xref>) and justice dimensions (Martin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2020</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>) as central features of what Temper et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>, p.&#x000a0;5) term &#x02018;radical transformations&#x02019;. The word &#x0201c;radical&#x0201d;, originating from the Latin<italic> radix</italic> meaning roots (Pugh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">2009</xref>), in this context means changing the root causes, as opposed to symptoms of a problem. Radical transformations therefore focus on addressing the underlying structural root causes that (re)produce ecological destruction and societal injustices, many of which boil down to the politics, power, intersectionality, and the multiple justice dimensions. The power/politics and justice dimensions, as central elements of transformations, are mutually connected and in practice reproduce one another. For instance, power configurations such as capitalism, patriarchy, and state reproduce injustices against certain sections of society and identities defined through gender, race, ethnicity or caste (Le Tran et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2020</xref>; Kojola and Pellow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2020</xref>; Sakshi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">2021</xref>; Sultana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">2021</xref>). From the plethora of fields offering visions concerning transformations, I focus on decolonial environmental justice and degrowth.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Decoloniality</title><p id="Par23">Decoloniality is theorized in different contexts and approached from different perspectives. There is a general agreement, however, that decoloniality represents a critique of modernity (Quijano <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">2007</xref>), and of modern notions of development, which reproduce various forms of violence and oppression, including extractivism, racism, patriarchy, and cultural domination (Maldonado-Torres <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">2007</xref>; Lugones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143">2010</xref>). Building on Fanon&#x02019;s decoloniality of mind (Fanon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144">1967</xref>) various scholars have focused on decoloniality of imaginary and being (Latouche <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2015</xref>; Maldonado-Torres <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">2007</xref>; Mignolo and Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">2018</xref>). Decoloniality is also discussed in the context of human-nature duality (Rodr&#x000ed;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>; Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>), power relations and forms of knowledge (Santos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">2008</xref>).&#x000a0;Unlike decoloniality of mind perspectives, indigenous perspectives frame decoloniality in more material and concrete terms and aims, which include ending structural systemic oppression and violence of colonialism, as well as repatriation or restitution of indigenous land (Tuck and Young <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2012</xref>).</p><p>Hence, an important scholarly debate on decoloniality concerns the questions of what is to be decolonized (i.e. the object of decolonialisation) and whether decoloniality should be used as a means to address a range of socio-political issues (i.e. decoloniality as a means), or an end in itself (i.e. decoloniality as an end) have emerged among decolonial, postcolonial and degrowth scholars (see for example D&#x02019;Alisa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>; Deschner and Hust <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2019</xref>; Garcia-Arias and Sch&#x000f6;neberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2021</xref>; Tuck and Yang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2012</xref>). Concerning the object of decoloniality, as noted above, the debate revolves around decoloniality of material (i.e. land and colonial structures of domination), and of immaterial, including mind and imaginary (i.e. knowledges, worldviews, significations). Decoloniality of mind, originally introduced by Fanon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">1965</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144">1967</xref>), has since been used by many decolonial and some postcolonial and degrowth scholars. For example, Latouche (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2015</xref>) frames decoloniality of imaginary as decolonizing of culture, meanings, and significations. Even if he discusses decolonizing imaginary directly in relation to a range of societal, structural and political issues, arguing especially against economic growth, some degrowth scholars criticize Latouche for engaging only slightly with the questions of power and conflicts (Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2019</xref>). Decolonial and post-colonial scholars, in contrast, problematize decoloniality of imaginary as defined by Latouche as an appropriation of the term that takes decoloniality away from its core and intended objectives, which should be repatriation of indigenous land and life (Deschner and Hurst <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Tuck and Yang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2012</xref>). Similarly, some scholars argue for a use of decoloniality strictly in relation to undoing colonial histories and injustices (decoloniality as an end in itself), while others approach it in the context of, and for addressing a range of socio-political issues, including justice and education for example (decoloniality as a means).</p><p>Acknowledging that tensions between the different positions on the object of decoloniality can emerge, I am inclined to suggest that the two are not necessarily mutually exclusive. In fact, decolonizing the immaterial, that is the mind and imaginary, can act as a precondition for decolonizing the material, since to decolonize land and structures of colonial oppression requires, decolonizing the imaginary and mind is necessary. Such synergies are, however, less certain when it comes to framing decoloniality as a means (i.e. using decoloniality for and in the context of tackling various social and ecological issues) versus framing it as an end (i.e. decoloniality as undoing the colonially rooted systemic oppression and the aim of repatriation and restitution of indigenous lands). While the former may not directly obstruct the latter, it does not by default support it either. As Tuck and Young (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2012</xref>) convincingly argue, using decoloniality argument for advancing various societal and political agendas and aims&#x02014;regardless how benevolent they might be&#x02014;can be harmful as it shifts the attention from the key point and aim, that is ending the colonial oppression and violence and repatriation of indigenous lands. In this context, the importance of remaining vigilant to numerous attempts to co-opt and reduce the radical ideas and political agendas of decoloniality cannot be overstated. Strengthening alliances among decolonial, postcolonial and degrowth scholars and activists is an important step towards the right direction, providing that dismantling the system of cultural and political violence of colonialism is an important part of their political projects and ideas.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Decolonial environmental justice (DEJ)</title><p id="Par24">Decolonial environmental justice (DEJ) draws on the ideas of decoloniality and emphasizes the need to decolonize concepts, meanings and epistemologies embedded within the environmental justice literature (Menton et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2020</xref>; Ramcilovic-Suominen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2021</xref>). DEJ emerges as a response to critiquing &#x0201c;mainstream&#x0201d; environmental justice (EJ) (Menton et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2020</xref>), which proposes three and sometimes four dimensions of justice, including participation, distribution, recognition (Fraser <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1998</xref>; Schlosberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">2007</xref>) and capabilities (Nussbaum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">2011</xref>). The critiquing of the EJ framework refers to its western or Eurocentric worldviews, imaginaries and politics, which do not fit those in many countries in the Global South where Eurocentric EJ is commonly applied (Alvarez and Coolseat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2018</xref>; Rodr&#x000ed;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>; Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">Seminal works on DEJ (Alvarez and Coolseat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2018</xref>; Rodr&#x000ed;guez and Inturias <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2018</xref>; Rodr&#x000ed;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>; Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>) highlight three central aspects. The first concerns the need to move <italic>beyond human&#x02013;nature dichotomy</italic>. This aspect builds on indigenous cosmologies (i.e. theories of the world), but is increasingly used as a framework for rethinking the human place and relations to other forms of life in other contexts (Biermann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020</xref>; Gebara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>). In this view, humans are an intrinsic and embedded part of the natural world and the underlying cause for socioecological crises relates to humans dominating nature, rather than living <italic>with</italic> nature. The notion of distributional justice is challenged because the very idea of distributing nature assumes that humans are separate from nature and can distribute it more equally between themselves (Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>). Imposing distributional justice is a form of epistemic injustice to indigenous and non-indigenous local groups, given that in so doing their worldviews and epistemologies are ignored and dominant Eurocentric ones imposed (Rodr&#x000ed;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>). DEJ calls for a breaking of the human&#x02013;nature dichotomy, which degrowth scholars term reciprocal and regenerative human&#x02013;nature relationalities (Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>).</p><p id="Par26">The second aspect, <italic>epistemic justice and the right to self-determination</italic>, concerns the imposition and domination of one particular way of knowing the world at the expense of other ways, which is termed as epistemic domination or violence. &#x02018;Speaking for others&#x02019; and assuming that other knowledge systems are subordinate and therefore need to adopt the &#x02018;supreme&#x02019; western Eurocentric one creates cultural and political oppression and slow violence (Tuhiwai Smith <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">1999</xref>). Temper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>) argues that recognitional justice (Fraser <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2000</xref>) can lead to inclusion of other onto-epistemological orientations within the dominant colonizing ones. Consequently, DEJ requires going beyond recognition and towards cultural and political self-determination, where people rely on their own sociocultural and political norms and structures (Rodr&#x000ed;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>; Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">The third aspect, <italic>self-governance and self-governing authority</italic>, while tightly linked to the other two, concerns the procedural EJ element (i.e. participation). The argument is for the need to go beyond participation and towards the self-governing authority of informal indigenous or other customary structures and authorities, which exist in parallel with formal state systems (Lund <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2011</xref>). The implication is that indigenous and other traditional authorities have the right to govern their own territories within their own indigenous and/or customary governing structures. This aspect is opposed to procedural justice which argues for participation <italic>within</italic> the existing domineering political and legal structures and which can lead to cultural and political assimilation (Sakshi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">2021</xref>; Rodr&#x000ed;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Degrowth</title><p id="Par28">While there are different perspectives on degrowth, there are also some well-agreed key propositions, including that degrowth is not simply about descaling the economy and current practices but about changing them altogether, together with their underlying logics (Asara et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2015</xref>). Hence defining degrowth as a society with a smaller metabolism (energy and material throughput an economy) only portrays one side of the coin (Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>). Degrowth signifies a society with different structures that serve different functions, needs and relations. The emphasis is on a good life, care, wellbeing, community and living well with less for all, implying redistribution and more equal sharing of resources globally (O&#x02019;Neill <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">2020</xref>; Raworth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">2012</xref>). The relevance of direct democracy and local autonomy is central (Parrique <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2019</xref>) as is the need to define our limits autonomously, collectively, and democratically (Kallis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2013</xref>). Finally, the degrowth perspective also calls for radical change in infrastructure, technologies and monetary system, with the aim of strengthening sharing and communing, direct democracy, wealth and power redistribution (Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>), and of paving the way for more democratic and decentralised technologies and financial systems (Douthwaite <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2012</xref>; Pensera and Fressoli <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par29">Degrowth builds on critiquing growth-oriented paradigms, including green growth, green economy and sustainable development (D&#x02019;Alisa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>; Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>). Degrowth scholars argue that such frameworks and paradigms have been co-opted and reoriented from their original ideas, towards serving economic growth at the cost of nature or environment, society and cultures (D&#x02019;Alisa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>). An important feature with direct implications for the policies such as the EU bioeconomy is the degrowth&#x02019;s focus on sufficiency (rather than substitution, for example) and affinity for voluntarily limiting our consumption and accumulation (Kallis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2013</xref>). Degrowth&#x02019;s focus on global environmental justice, care and reciprocity, which are increasingly articulated in the literature through the feminist and decolonial perspectives on degrowth (Dengler and Seebacher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2019</xref>; Mehta and Harcourt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2021</xref>; Nirmal and Roscheleau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR901">2019</xref>; Singh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2019</xref>), is also vital to EU bioeconomy. Kallis et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>) outline a number of strategies which they argue offer alternatives to the current capitalist extractivist economy. These strategies include carbon and wealth taxes, debt cancelation of the former colonies and GDP-poorer countries, redistribution of economic and political power across countries and regions of the world and scaling down environmentally polluting sectors and industries while promoting locally sourced production and consumption economies. While these measures are not exhaustive, especially when it comes to onto-epistemological aspects and decolonial justice, they hold tremendous potential for informing and inspiring EU bioeconomy policy to embrace socially and ecologically just approaches in building European bio-based societies.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Drawing on DEJ and degrowth to identify barriers to and alternatives for socioecological justice and transformations</title><p id="Par30">Applying the theoretical framework outlined above to the EU bioeconomy policy described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">From a policy of green growth to a practice of green sacrifice zones</xref>&#x0201d;, I first identify the dominant approaches and logics in the EU bioeconomy that act as barriers to socioecological justice and transformations, and then propose alternative ways and logics to support just transformations within the EU bioeconomy in its global context. More attention is given to the alternatives, rather than the better-known barriers and problems. The barriers include:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p id="Par31">Framing the web of life (nature) as a resource and service provider for humans, which is based on and strengthens extractive and &#x02018;rent-seeking&#x02019; behaviour and relations to nature and at best promotes market-friendly nature-based solutions, such as carbon sequestration and trading. Responding to this framing calls for reimagining the dominant Eurocentric human&#x02013;nature relationality and for abandoning human&#x02013;nature and other forms of duality (Biermann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020</xref>; Gebara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>; Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>). Relationality concerns the broader way we humans view, live and relate to the world around us. It refers to an idea that humanity is embedded and relationally constituted within it (Gebara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>, p.&#x000a0;238).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="Par32">Dominance of green growth logic and technoscientific policy solutions that promote large-scale economic and industrial activities at the expense of socioecological burdens and small-scale technologies and activities. This approach does not question the current production and consumption levels and prioritizes industrial development that comes at the expense of small-scale, community-based and local economic activities, and the sociocultural and socioecological sustainability (O'Neill <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">2020</xref>; Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p id="Par33">A limited approach to socioecological justice, where only procedural and distributive justice elements are visible, but limited to key stakeholder participation (i.e. European businesses, industry, policymakers and research institutions) and to equitable distribution of job opportunities. Global socioecological injustices, historical, colonial and current exploitation and inequalities related to climate change responsibility and ecological footprints between different societal groups and countries are ignored in the EU bioeconomy.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iv)</label><p id="Par34">EU global leadership and competitiveness in globalized bioeconomic markets as a goal, which motivates relocation of socioecological burdens of EU bioeconomy to its domestic and global peripheries. This furthers reproduction of neo-imperial and neo-colonial relations with the countries in the Global South in the name of European competitiveness, development and carbon-neural economy.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(v)</label><p id="Par35">Hegemonic politico-economic structures and actor coalitions in charge of EU bioeconomy, including international economic organizations, such as OECD, and transnational businesses. These actor coalitions and their policy initiatives and decisions cooperate with state structures, overlooking the legal plurality and indigenous structures as well as state coercion and violence. Recentralization and state-centred initiatives are reproduced in the countries where international policies are implemented, which can lead to further marginalization and violence (Harcourt and Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>; Ramcilovic-Suominen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2021</xref>).</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par36">The proposed alternatives are intended to strengthen justice and plurality and to discourage discrimination against and violations of other knowledge, practices, and actor constellations. These barriers and alternatives are organized in three groups, as shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Barriers to just transformations and alternatives: the case of EU bioeconomy with its global implications</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Barriers to just transformations in the EU bioeconomy with global implications</th><th align="left">Alternative ways and logics to support just transformations within the EU bioeconomy</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"><italic>Barriers and alternatives concerning relationalities and ways of being</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1. Framing of nature as a resource and service provider for humans</td><td align="left">1. Beyond human&#x02013;nature dualism and extractive relations towards reciprocal and regenerative relationality</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"><italic>Barriers and alternatives most specifically linked to bioeconomy</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2. Dominance of (green) growth and technoscientific policy solutions that favour industrial activities at the expense of socioecological burdens</td><td align="left">2. Beyond the logic of growth and technoscientific solutions towards institutionally supported, sufficiency-oriented lifestyles and means of production that respect planetary limits and planetary justice</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3. Limited approach to socioecological justice, where procedural justice is limited to &#x0201c;key stakeholder participation&#x0201d; and distributive justice is limited to equitable distribution of economic opportunities</td><td align="left">3. Beyond stakeholder participation and equitable distribution of economic opportunities towards decoloniality, plurality, climate and epistemic justice, and full recognition for cultural and political self-determination and self-governing authorities</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"><italic>Barriers and alternatives that concern the politics of change</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">4. EU global leadership and competitiveness in globalized bioeconomic markets as a goal in itself</td><td align="left">4. Beyond global competitiveness and harmful competition towards partnerships based on principles of local autonomy, solidarity, mutual respect, reconciliation and redistribution of power and wealth</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5. Hegemonic politico-economic structures and actor coalitions in charge of EU bioeconomy</td><td align="left">5. Beyond dominant actor coalitions, top-down initiatives and state coercion towards decentralized bottom-up leadership that promotes direct democracy, local autonomy and sovereignty</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Alternative ways and logics to support just transformations within the EU bioeconomy</title><p id="Par37">In what follows we present the alternative approaches to the identified barriers, elaborating also on the barriers in further detail.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p id="Par38">Beyond human&#x02013;nature dualism and extractive relations towards reciprocal and regenerative relationalities with more-than-human &#x02018;natures&#x02019;</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par39">&#x0201c;Bio-based products go far beyond biomass processing. They capitalize on the unprecedented advances in life sciences and biotechnology&#x02026; that, coupled with the digital revolution, allow [one] to use nature&#x02019;s &#x0201c;biological assets&#x0201d; (its biochemicals and biomaterials) and its &#x0201c;biomimetic assets&#x0201d; (its functions and processes) to generate significant new sources of economic value and future revenue&#x0201d; (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>, p.&#x000a0;42). This citation from the revised EU bioeconomy strategy is a common example of human&#x02013;nature duality where humans and nature are seen as separate from one another, with the former dominating the latter.</p><p id="Par40">Human&#x02013;nature dualism and the associated extractivist logics position human species as supreme to other species and forms of life, which justifies human domination, extraction, and exploitation of other forms of life for the benefit of humans. Human&#x02013;nature dualism was consolidated in the process of European enlightenment and was instrumental in justifying European colonialism, dispossession and enslaving of colonized non-Europeans and capitalist endeavours that began some 500&#x000a0;years ago (Sch&#x000f6;neberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2019</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>). This duality persists and helps maintain domination of humans over more-than-humans (animal and plant species), reducing them to mere resources and/or service providers to one supreme species.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1">1</xref> For instance, concepts such as &#x02018;ecosystem services&#x02019; effectively reproduce such logics (Sullivan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">2010</xref>).</p><p id="Par42">Facing unprecedented socioecological breakdown, the time is ripe for Europe to re-examine its epistemologies (knowledge systems) and ontologies (philosophies of life) concerning human relations with the wider ecology. Indigenous cosmologies or philosophies of life are known for positioning all forms of life&#x02014;animals, plants, trees, bacteria, viruses&#x02014;as part of one whole biosphere or ecology (Gebara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>; Gram-Hanssen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2021</xref>). Beyond indigenous cosmologies, modern and western science and scholars also increasingly question the human&#x02013;nature duality, stressing the importance of epistemic plurality (Biermann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020</xref>; Pascual et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par43">Once we see ourselves as interconnected, embedded in, and dependent on other forms of life and species, and accept the sentiency of other forms of life (i.e. that they are morally equal to us), not only our relations with them but also our policy goals are more likely to shift from dominance, extraction and competition to those of care, respect, reciprocity, responsibility and nourishment (Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">b</xref>). But how do we get there? My argument is not for the EU bioeconomy and EU societies to adopt animism, but for human&#x02013;nature narrowly framed relations to be re-examined (Gebara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>). I also do not suggest that European or any other society ceases to use other forms of life, as this contradicts the (co)existence and the very existence of societies in question. Besides, examples from Latin America, where the neoliberal grab and commodification of nature have continued despite indigenous ontologies being recognized and given space in the countries&#x02019; laws and constitutions, suggest the need for radical change in practice as well. Yet, I argue that rethinking the ways we relate and interact with and use other forms of life, by embracing reciprocal relationality, is the first and necessary step to radical change. Reciprocity here implies taking not more than you need and returning the favour. Returning can be done by regeneration or replenishing the forms of life that we interact with (e.g. forest, land), which ensures continuity of their regenerative capacities; an example would be regenerative agroecological practices (Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>). Any efforts aiming to support a transition to a post-fossil economy that can be sustained in the long run, as the EU bioeconomy strategy and other similar policies claim to intend to, must go beyond colonising, exploiting and extracting other forms of life. Such attempts and policies need to urgently rethink and abolish human&#x02013;nature duality, promote reciprocal relationality between humans and other species and forms of life.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="Par44">Beyond green growth and technoscientific solutions, towards institutionally supported, sufficiency-oriented lifestyles and means of production that respect and prioritize planetary limits and planetary justice</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par45">The EU bioeconomy recognizes the degraded states of life cycles and proposes a circularity of energy and materials and a decoupling of economic growth from use and degradation of &#x02018;nature&#x02019;. Both circularity and decoupling are vital, but unattainable at the rate and within the timeframe needed. The scale of technological readiness and particularly the level of economic and political readiness lag significantly behind the urgency of socioecological crises, climate change and biodiversity loss (Hickel and Kallis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2019</xref>; Parrique et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2019</xref>). Regarding circularity, only a portion of the materials and energy sources that we use can be recycled, as a large share of primary materials is degraded through use and recycling itself is energy intense (Giampietro <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2019</xref>; Parrique et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par46">Hence there is a need for strategies which focus on living within planetary boundaries and planetary justice as a precondition for curbing CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and inequalities. One such strategy is the principle of <italic>sufficiency and voluntary frugality</italic> (Kallis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2013</xref>). Sufficiency is opposed to excess and accumulation and can be explained using Raworth&#x02019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">2012</xref>) idea of &#x02018;living within the doughnut&#x02019; or living within a safe and just space for humanity, where everyone has a solid social foundation without overshooting the ecological ceiling or limits. Embracing sufficiency in GDP-richer EU countries can lead to faster reductions of throughput of energy. Since the wealth accumulation by GDP-richer countries and economic elites relocates social and ecological damage to global peripheries, adopting sufficiency in the GDP-rich countries also directly advances global socioecological justice.</p><p id="Par47">Supporting local(ized) production and consumption of resources and services is also important because such local and small-scale activities perform better ecologically owing to their shorter value chains. Being embedded within sociocultural and socioecological systems, local(ized) systems of economic exchange are potentially more sustaining and regenerating of socioecological systems (Parrique <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2019</xref>), and for the same reason of place embeddedness, they are also likely to be more democratic (Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>; Parrique <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2019</xref>). However, such local initiatives require policy and institutional support that a bioeconomy policy can provide. Such support includes, for example, reforming and democratising the monetary system and tax relief to support public goods, local producers and livelihoods (Douthwaite <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2012</xref>; Mellor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2017</xref>). Examples of alternative and local initiatives and cooperatives for providing collective goods and services exist throughout Europe (Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>) and the world (Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>). Promotion and support of cooperatives and community-led projects for provision of food, clothes, cosmetics, shared transportation and housing, and renewable energy is needed in the EU bioeconomy policies and discourses as a complement to the narrow focus on innovation and technologies. This in turn implies more self-reliance and local autonomy to decide, and less dependence on private and industry-led provision of new materials and technologies.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p id="Par48">Beyond stakeholder participation and equitable distribution of economic opportunities, towards climate and epistemic justice, local autonomy, self-determination, and self-governing authority</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par49">As discussed in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">From a policy of green growth to a practice of green sacrifice zones</xref>&#x0201d;, the EU bioeconomy policy adopts a rather narrow focus when it comes to procedural and distributive justice that is limited to participation of stakeholders and distribution of economic opportunities. Recognitional justice, which deals with marginalization and cultural identities (Fraser <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2000</xref>), is the least reflected in the bioeconomy policy. This may partly be because it is seen to be part of other Directorate-Generals (DG) and their policies and regulations (e.g. DG for justice and consumers). Proposing a decolonial justice approach is crucial if the EU is to ensure plurality and justice and to address inequalities, both globally and domestically (Sch&#x000f6;neberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par50">At a global level, it is crucial that the EU countries and the block as a whole acknowledge and address the injustices associated with the historic colonial past, as well as with the contemporary and non-proportional burdens and injustices associated with its high living standards, and its environmental, nature protection and development policies more broadly. This is necessary for starting to imagine a decolonial turn in the EU development approach and policies. This also concerns and requires a shift from policies that rely on technoscientific and market-based solutions and which go beyond the rhetoric of participation and selling &#x02018;good governance&#x02019; packages to &#x02018;developing countries&#x02019;. Taking a decolonial turn means (1) embracing and acting upon climate and epistemic justice, (2) embracing plurality of knowledge and epistemologies, and (3) recognising local autonomy of indigenous people, their cultural and political self-determination and self-governing authority, their territorial rights and practices of living with and within the web of life (Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>; Temper, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>).<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(iv)</label><p id="Par51">Beyond global competitiveness and harmful competition, towards partnerships based on the principles of local autonomy, solidarity, mutual respect, reconciliation and redistribution of power and wealth</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par52">The EU bioeconomy, like the green economy to which it is closely associated, is embedded within the global trade, power and economic relations, which are in turn embedded within colonial and neo-colonial legacies of racially driven domination, extraction of labour and &#x02018;natural resources&#x02019; and exploitation and dispossession of people in the Global South (Harcourt and Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">b</xref>). If the EU leadership is to respond to growing pressure including from its own especially younger and increasingly protesting citizens and civil society organizations, demanding climate justice and an end to fossil capitalism, it is not the global competitiveness the EU should be concerned about. Rather efforts should be made towards recognition of responsibilities and commitment to reparations for the wrongdoing of the past and change of the current trends and politics. Yet not only is there a shortage of such commitments and change but policies like the EU bioeconomy signals continuity and escalation of neo-colonial domination and plunder in the Global South (Fuchs et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2020</xref>; Hickel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2021</xref>; Zografos and Robbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>). It is not sufficient to promote use of &#x0201c;domestically available sustainable renewable resources&#x0201d; if they are not defined or elaborated upon (Kurki and Ahola-Launonen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2021</xref>). To avoid reproduction of green sacrifice zones (Zografos and Robbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>), EU policies with relations to and implications for the Global South need to change course radically, and here are just a few suggestions: (1) reinvent EU relations with and role in the world, with the humility of a former coloniser, where responsibilities for historical/colonial and modern/neo-colonial debt, burdens and injustices are acknowledged and acted upon; (2) reform EU policy and institutional framework with an aim to fostering reconciliation, reciprocity, respect, care and solidarity with the Global South and marginalized groups across the peripheries, as opposed to exploitation and violence; (3) abandon the &#x02018;imperial mode of living&#x02019; by tackling non-proportional and wasteful consumption and extraction and thus alleviate pressure on lands, peoples, and &#x02018;natures&#x02019; at home and elsewhere; (4) implement reforms for redistribution of wealth and power in a way that addresses current inequalities and repairs historic, as well as contemporary injustices and violence associated with the EU corporate extraction and dispossession; (5) implement policy reforms that allow the EU to operate in full recognition of domestic and, where relevant, local indigenous and customary territorial rules and rights, including cultural and political self-determination and self-governing authority. Relying on the state as the only legitimate actor tends to reinforce marginalization and violence against indigenous and/or rebellious groups (Dunlap <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2021a</xref>; Pellow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">2018</xref>; Ramcilovic-Suominen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2021</xref>).<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(v)</label><p id="Par53">Beyond dominant actor coalitions, top-down initiatives and state coercion towards decentralised bottom-up leadership that promotes direct democracy, local autonomy and sovereignty</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par54">Owing to the European colonial project, spaces and territories in the Global South remain characterized by parallel existence of formal/state and informal/customary structures, which compete for power and authority (Lund <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2011</xref>). This remains one of the major causes for conflicting relations between the state and sections of society that do not always recognize the state authority but rely on traditional norms and political authority. Contrary to this reality, the EU institutions and global governance organizations (World Trade Organization, World Bank, International Monetary Fund, OECD) collaborate exclusively with state organs, while ignoring the evidence that the state does not always represent all citizens equally (Kojola and Pellow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2020</xref>; Sakshi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">2021</xref>) and plays an important part in oppression, violence and coercion (Dunlap <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2021a</xref>). This leads to consolidation of state control of people and territories that previously operated more independently, fostering thus state-sponsored dispossession and violence (Ramcilovic-Suominen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2021</xref>; Menton&#x000a0;and Le Billon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par55">Systemic and structural shifts in global governance structures, discourses and power relations are required to allow for direct representation of indigenous people and other marginalized groups, by their own elected authorities, norms and structures, including direct democracy. There is a need to decentralize power and authority and encourage bottom-up leadership for transformations that can offer a safe political space for marginalized or oppressed groups (Stephens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">2020</xref>). Local and bottom-up leadership examples across the world show an affinity for direct democracy, local autonomy and non-violence (Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>). Examples of people-centred bottom-up leadership where people come together to organize and govern their political, economic and ecological affairs exist across the world. Such leaderships challenge state oppression, racism, casteism, sexism, patriarchy and other forms of social injustice and marginalization, including those rooted in their own culture (e.g. tackling discrimination related to gender, ethnicities, caste etc.). Examples include, but are not limited to, the Kurdish Rojava women&#x02019;s movement for autonomy and direct democracy (Gills and Hosseini <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2021</xref>) and various movements for ecological stewardship, food and seed sovereignty, economies of caring and sharing, self-determination and autonomy (Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par56">Progressive political leadership in the EU and the USA alike needs to embed itself within the anti-racist, feminist political leadership to a greater extent as to defend their rhetoric and commitment to social justice, security, race and housing (Stephens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">2020</xref>). We can see signs of hope on the streets, where youth protesting for new climate policies have had significant impacts.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Transformations, co-optation, and politics of change: EU bioeconomy and beyond</title><p id="Par57">The EU bioeconomy policy primarily aims to advance economic sustainability, green growth, and EU global competitiveness, by substituting non-renewables for renewables, modernizing production and consumption, boosting technology, research and innovation, and promoting circular and cascade use of materials and products. Socioecological emergencies and existential crises, such as climate change, biodiversity loss, deforestation and ecosystem degradation, are framed as challenges to achieving these goals. Based on the decolonial environmental justice and degrowth perspectives, the agenda proposed in the bioeconomy policy and the revised strategy is insufficient in several ways. The EU&#x02019;s ecological and climate debt are left unaddressed. Global inequalities and responsibilities for the EU&#x02019;s historical colonial and current neo-colonial extraction and appropriation of resources from the Global South are sidelined. Sufficiency or decreases of EU production and consumption levels, which fuel domestic and global socioecological burden and injustices, are not among suggested policy measures. Economic sustainability, creation of &#x02018;green jobs&#x02019;, circular economy approaches and the focus on participation of stakeholders and equal economic opportunity within Europe are insufficient to tackle the socioecological crises at hand. The same holds for substitution of non-renewables with renewables, coupled with technology, research and innovation, and EU global competitiveness.</p><p id="Par58">A significant part of this paper deals with the need to go beyond certain approaches and logics, identified as the key barriers to just transformations in the EU bioeconomy, and with alternative approaches and logics to facilitate such transformations (&#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec10" ref-type="sec">Drawing on DEJ and degrowth to identify barriers to and alternatives for socioecological justice and transformations</xref>&#x0201d;). Rather than proposing far-fetched policy recommendations for more transformational and more just politics in the EU bioeconomy policy domain, in what follows I reflect upon the process of change and risks of co-optation, with a hope to inspire decolonial and just socioecological transformations in and beyond bioeconomy.</p><p id="Par59">The concepts and processes of decoloniality, degrowth and transformations are crucial for the radical changes, as argued above. Yet, each of these concepts and political agendas is highly susceptible to co-optation that leads to dilution of their radical ideas, followed by their absorption into the &#x02018;ordinary&#x02019;. This co-optation can, and usually happens from the outside&#x02014;by actors who favour status quo (Coy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2013</xref>; Katz-Rosene and Paterson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2018</xref>; Stephens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">2020</xref>). Co-optation can also happen from the inside, and by the proponents themselves, when faced with a temptation for proliferating and mainstreaming their concepts and political agendas. While co-optation from the outside is the most dominant across all three concepts and political agendas, it currently appears to be the most extreme in the case of transformations, where the term is used to describe and therefore legitimize sociotechnical and eco-modernist solutions as &#x02018;transformative&#x02019; (Kruus and Hakala <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2017</xref>; Tome Valencia Hamilton and Ramcilovic-Suominen forthcoming; UNECE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">2012</xref>). Decoloniality, inter alia, appears to be prone to co-optation by often well-intended group of actors, including scholars, who may use the term without properly engaging the theory and previously published literature, and may end up reducing the term to a buzzword or a metaphor (Deschner and Hust <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Tuck and Yang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2012</xref>). Internal co-optation is highlighted as a potential risk to degrowth. As degrowth ideas start to gain wider popularity, including among policymakers, they tend to reduce degrowth to a toolbox for &#x0201c;broadening the sustainability debate (and for meeting EU&#x02019;s) sustainability ambitions&#x0201d; (EEA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2021</xref>; p.&#x000a0;2), largely omitting the sociocultural and justice dimensions of degrowth. Some scholars have noted that degrowth proponents in some cases flirt with policy approaches that can be considered rather reformist, statist, and non-heterodox, risking internal co-optation (Deschner and Hust <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Dunlap <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2021b</xref>; Garcia-Arias and Sch&#x000f6;neberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par60">As Tome Valencia Hamilton and Ramcilovic-Suominen (forthcoming in this Special Feature) argue, whether a certain political process or agenda is to result in radical transformations or not will depend not only on their foci and even outcomes but also on the nature of the process of change. Concerning the focus and outcomes, in this paper I have argued for a need of an all-encompassing change and reinvention across all dimensions&#x02014;from onto-epistemological, to material, to political. The focus should be firmly on justice, race, colonial histories, inequalities, gender, class, and it should ensure that marginalized and colonised voices and concerns are not only attended to but are at the centre of the processes where problems are defined, and solutions designed and implemented. Such focus is a prerequisite not only for co-creating just alternatives and solutions, knowledge, and technologies but also a precondition for safeguarding against co-option by elite interests and actors. Concerning the process of change, as decoloniality, transformations and degrowth imply reshuffling and redistribution of power, wealth and privilege, the process ought to be messy, flexible, deeply democratic and locally owned. Direct democracy, local ownership, local autonomy, collective action and solidarity should be fiercely defended. As the protests for climate justice associated with the COP26 climate change conference in Glasgow bear witness to, it is becoming clear to an increasing number of people that, in the words of the COP26 Coalition for Climate Justice: &#x0201c;The transformative solutions that we need in order to survive and build a more just and fairer world can only be brought about through collective action, solidarity and coordination, from our local communities to international levels&#x0201d; (@COP26_Coalition twitter account, tweet 6.11.2021).</p><p id="Par61">At a more practical level, I wish to highlight the role of social movements and activism, including science and research activism, as a counteraction to socioecologically and socioeconomically harmful and unjust policies and practices (Caniglia et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2021</xref>; Stephens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">2020</xref>), but also as a force to help reimagine the &#x02018;ordinary&#x02019; and to co-create the &#x02018;alternative&#x02019;. Scholars, especially those in the Global North, have a moral responsibility to make space for their colleagues from the Global South to tell their truths, as well as to be allies of the marginalized and oppressed societal groups and voices. Building coalitions and synergies between different initiatives and movements for change, which are based on different knowledge and aim to unmake the current structures and status quo together with the underlying logics, are crucial for co-designing alternative ways forward&#x02014;ways forward where justice, plurality, solidarity, resilience and resistance are both the means and the ends of the processes of change.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="Fn1"><label>1</label><p id="Par41">In this part the focus is only on the inter-species level, leaving out the dynamics and violence within the human species, such as enslavement, unequal extraction and appropriation of labour and other &#x0201c;resources&#x0201d;, which continue in different forms and with different justifications to the present day.</p></fn><fn><p>Handled by Dennis Eversberg, Friedrich Schiller University, Jena, Germany.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>2/26/2022</p><p>A Correction to this paper has been published: 10.1007/s11625-022-01122-1</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by Natural Resources Institute Finland (LUKE). Academy of Finland (Grant no. 332353).</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akbulut</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Demaria</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Alier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Who promotes sustainability? Five theses on the relationships between the degrowth and the environmental justice movements</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2019</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>106418</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2019.106418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Coolsaet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decolonizing environmental justice studies: perspective</article-title><source>Cap Nat Soc</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10455752.2018.1558272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asara</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Otero</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Demaria</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Socially sustainable degrowth as a social&#x02013;ecological transformation: repoliticizing sustainability</article-title><source>Sustain Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-015-0321-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Backhouse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;hmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Puder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tittor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bioeconomy and inequalities. Socio-ecological perspectives on biomass sourcing and production across South America, Asia and Europe</source><year>2021</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastos-Lima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The extraterritorial dimensions of biofuel policies and the politics of scale: live and let die?</article-title><source>Third World Q</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01436597.2014.893484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biermann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The future of &#x02018;environmental&#x02019; policy in the anthropocene: time for a paradigm shift</article-title><source>Environ Polit</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644016.2020.1846958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Levidow</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Papaioannou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable capital? The neoliberalization of nature and knowledge in the European &#x0201c;knowledge-based bio-economy&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2898</fpage><lpage>2918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su2092898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bluwstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transformation is not a metaphor</article-title><source>Polit Geogr</source><year>2021</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>102450</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.polgeo.2021.102450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmalz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternativen zum Extraktivismus oder alternative Extraktivismen? &#x000bb;Gr&#x000fc;ne&#x000ab; Strategien und der Streit um die Kontrolle nat&#x000fc;rlicher Ressourcen</article-title><source>Extraktivismus</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>M&#x000fc;nchen</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lateinamerika nach dem Ende des Rohstoffbooms. oekom verlag</publisher-name><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sovacool</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile photovoltaics: green industrialization, sacrifice zones, and the political ecology of solar energy in Germany</article-title><source>Ann Am Assoc Geograph</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/24694452.2020.1856638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bugge</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Klitkou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is the bioeconomy? A review of the literature</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>691</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su8070691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;scher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Feola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Harcourt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholtens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Spierenburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walstra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiskerke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Planning for a world beyond COVID-19: five pillars for post-neoliberal development</article-title><source>World Dev</source><year>2021</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>105357</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34548744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambrick</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Menton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The supply chain of violence</article-title><source>Nat Sustain</source><year>2019</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-019-0349-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caniglia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Luederitz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>von Wirth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hondrila</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;nig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>von Wehrden</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;pke</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laubichler</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pluralistic and integrated approach to action-oriented knowledge for sustainability</article-title><source>Nature Sustain</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-020-00616-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Coy PG (2013). Co-optation. 10.1002/9780470674871.wbespm054</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">D&#x02019;Alisa G, Demaria F, Kallis G (2015) Degrowth vocabulary for a new era. ISBN 9781138000773</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del Bene</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheidel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Temper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>More dams, more violence? A global analysis on resistances and repression around conflictive dams through co-produced knowledge</article-title><source>Sustain Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-018-0558-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dengler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Seebacher</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What about the global south? Towards a feminist decolonial degrowth approach</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2019</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2018.11.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Deschner C, Hust E (2018) Decolonisation and degrowth. Degrowth blog dated 1 Feb 2018. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.degrowth.info/blog/decolonisation-and-degrowth">https://www.degrowth.info/blog/decolonisation-and-degrowth</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Douthwaite</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degrowth and the supply of money in an energy-scarce world</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2012</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2011.03.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The politics of ecocide, genocide and megaprojects: interrogating natural resource extraction, identity and the normalization of erasure</article-title><source>J Genocide Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14623528.2020.1754051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dunlap A (2021b) Degrowth care: two commentaries worth mentioning. Terra Nullis: repossessing the existent. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sum.uio.no/forskning/blogg/terra-nullius/">https://www.sum.uio.no/forskning/blogg/terra-nullius/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arce</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x02018;Murderous energy&#x02019; in Oaxaca, Mexico: wind factories, territorial struggle and social warfare</article-title><source>J Peasant Stud</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03066150.2020.1862090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">EEA (European Environmental Agency) (2021) Growth without economic growth. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/growth-without-economic-growth">https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/growth-without-economic-growth</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR900"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elhacham</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Uri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grozovski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global human-made mass exceeds all living biomass</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>588</volume><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-3010-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33299177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degrowth, postdevelopment, and transitions: a preliminary conversation</article-title><source>Sustain Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-015-0297-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Designs for the pluriverse: radical interdependence, autonomy, and the making of worlds</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Durham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Commission (EC)</collab></person-group><source>Innovating for sustainable growth: a bioeconomy for Europe</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Luxembourg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Publications Office of the European Union</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Commission (EC) (2018) A sustainable bioeconomy for Europe: strengthening the connection between economy, society and the environment. Updated Bioeconomy Strategy</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Commission (EC) (2021) The bioeconomy in different countries database. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://knowledge4policy.ec.europa.eu/visualisation/bioeconomy-different-countries_en">https://knowledge4policy.ec.europa.eu/visualisation/bioeconomy-different-countries_en</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eversberg D, Holz J (2020) Empty promises of growth: the bioeconomy and its multiple reality checks (No. 2). Working Paper der BMBF-Nachwuchsgruppe &#x0201c;flumen.&#x0201d; Friedrich-Schiller-Universit&#x000e4;t, Jena</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR145"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fanon F (1965) L&#x02019;An Cinq, de la R&#x000e9;volution Alg&#x000e9;rienne. Paris: Fran&#x000e7;ois Maspero, 1959 (Published in English as A Dying Colonialism, trans. Haakon Chevalier. Grove Press, New York, 1965)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR144"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fanon F (1967) Peau Noire, Masques Blancs. Paris: Editions du Seuil, 1952 (Published in English as Black Skin, White Masks, trans. Charles Lam Markmann. Grove Press, New York, 1967)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Societal transformation in response to global environmental change: a review of emerging concepts</article-title><source>Ambio</source><year>2015</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13280-014-0582-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25431335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degrowth and the unmaking of capitalism: beyond &#x02018;decolonization of the imaginary&#x0201d;</article-title><source>ACME Int J Crit Geograph</source><year>2019</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>997</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Koretskaya</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>(Un)making in sustainability transformation beyond capitalism</article-title><source>Glob Environ Change</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2021.102290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FFRC (Finland Futures Research Centre) (2019) Precarious resources to a &#x02018;good&#x02019; bioeconomy in 2125: making sense of bioeconomy and justice horizons. First Foresight Report of the BioEcoJust Project. FFRC eBooks 2/2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social justice in the age of identity politics: redistribution, recognition and participation</article-title><source>Tanner Lect Hum Values</source><year>1998</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rethinking recognition: overcoming displacement and reification in cultural politics</article-title><source>New Left Rev</source><year>2000</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>120</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rounsewell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Europe&#x02019;s Green Deal offshores environmental damage to other nations</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>586</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-020-02991-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33106645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia-Arias</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;neberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urgencies and imperatives for revolutionary (environmental) transitions: from degrowth and postdevelopment towards the pluriverse?</article-title><source>Environ Polit</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644016.2021.1911443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gawel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pannicke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagemann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A path transition toward a bioeconomy&#x02014;the crucial role of sustainability</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>3005</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su11113005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gebara</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ioris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossotto Ioris</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shubin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thinking beyond human-nature dichotomy: on the cosmopolitics of the Amazon</article-title><source>Frontiers of development in the Amazon: riches, risks and resistance</source><year>2021</year><publisher-loc>Lanham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lexington Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgescu-Roegen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><source>The entropy law and the economic process</source><year>1971</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge/London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harvard UP</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgescu-Roegen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><source>From bioeconomics to degrowth: Georgescu&#x02013;Roegen's' new economics' in eight essays</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degrowth and critical agrarian studies</article-title><source>J Peasant Stud</source><year>2020</year><volume>47</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03066150.2019.1695601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gereffi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What does the COVID-19 pandemic teach us about global value chains? The case of medical supplies</article-title><source>J Int Bus Policy</source><year>2020</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1057/s42214-020-00062-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giampietro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the circular bioeconomy and decoupling: implications for sustainable growth</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2019</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2019.05.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gills B, Hosseini H (2021) Beyond the Pluriverse: consolidating radical alternatives. Conference of the Westermarck Society 2021, March 11&#x02013;12, 2021. University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sosiologipaivat.fi/in-english/2021-annual-conference/">http://sosiologipaivat.fi/in-english/2021-annual-conference/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gills</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global climate emergency: after COP24, climate science, urgency, and the threat to humanity</article-title><source>Globalizations</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14747731.2019.1669915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gore T, Alestig M (2020) Confronting carbon inequality in the European Union: why the European Green Deal must tackle inequality while cutting emissions. Oxfam policy papers. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.oxfam.org/en/research/confronting-carbon-inequality-european-union">https://www.oxfam.org/en/research/confronting-carbon-inequality-european-union</ext-link>. Accessed 26 Jan 2020</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gram-Hanssen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafenacker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decolonizing transformations through &#x02018;right relations&#x02019;</article-title><source>Sustain Sci</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-021-00960-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harcourt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Practising feminist political ecologies: moving beyond the &#x0201c;green economy&#x0201d;</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Zed</publisher-name><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Less is more: how degrowth will save the world</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Penguin Random House</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying national responsibility for climate breakdown: an equality-based attribution approach for carbon dioxide emissions in excess of the planetary boundary</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>e404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30196-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is green growth possible?</article-title><source>New Polit Econ</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01436597.2018.1535895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoomkawala</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plunder in the post-colonial era: quantifying drain from the global south through unequal exchange, 1960&#x02013;2018</article-title><source>New Politi Econ</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13563467.2021.1899153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hoff H, Johnson FX, Allen B, Biber-Freudenberger L, F&#x000f6;rster JJ (2018) Sustainable bio-resource pathways towards a fossil-free world: the European bioeconomy in a global development context. Policy Paper produced for the IEEP Think2030 Conference 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holscher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittmayer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loorbach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transition versus transformation: what&#x02019;s the difference?</article-title><source>Environ Innov Soc Trans</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eist.2017.10.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Orengo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resource warfare, pacification and the spectacle of &#x02018;green&#x02019; development: logics of violence in engineering extraction in southern Madagascar</article-title><source>Polit Geogr</source><year>2020</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>102195</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.polgeo.2020.102195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IPBES (2020) Workshop report on biodiversity and pandemics of the intergovernmental platform on biodiversity and ecosystem services. In: Daszak P, das Neves C, Amuasi J, Hayman D, Kuiken T, Roche B, Zambrana-Torrelio C, Buss P et al (eds). Bonn. 10.5281/zenodo.4147317</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IPCC</collab></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Masson-Delmotte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;an</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Caud</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldfarb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomis</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitzell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonnoy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>JBR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maycock</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterfield</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yelek&#x000e7;i</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Summary for policymakers</article-title><source>Climate change 2021: the physical science basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the sixth assessment report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source><year>2021</year><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kallis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Societal metabolism, working hours and degrowth: a comment on Sorman and Giampietro</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2013</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2012.06.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kallis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Alisa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Demaria</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><source>The case for degrowth</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz-Rosene</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological transformations and co-optations</article-title><source>Thinking ecologically about the global political economy</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kojola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New directions in environmental justice studies: examining the state and violence</article-title><source>Environ Polit</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644016.2020.1836898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korhonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Giurca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockhaus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toppinen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actors and politics in Finland&#x02019;s forest-based bioeconomy network</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>3785</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su10103785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salleh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Demaria</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pluriverse: a post-development dictionary</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Tulika Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kruus K, Hakala T (2017) The making of bioeconomy transformation. VTT Technical Research Centre of Finland. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cris.vtt.fi/en/publications/the-making-of-bioeconomy-transformation">https://cris.vtt.fi/en/publications/the-making-of-bioeconomy-transformation</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahola-Launonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Koukios</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacio-Szyma&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioeconomy in maturation: a pathway towards a &#x0201c;Good&#x0201d; bioeconomy or distorting silence on crucial matters?</article-title><source>Bio#Futures</source><year>2021</year><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Latouche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>D&#x02019;Alisa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Demaria</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decolonization of imaginary</article-title><source>Degrowth: a vocabulary for a new era</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Abingdon</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>120</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Tran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Alier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Navas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mingorria</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gendered geographies of violence: a multiple case study analysis of murdered women environmental defenders</article-title><source>J Polit Ecol</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1212</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>MacGregor</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scoones</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-pandemic transformations: how and why COVID-19 requires us to rethink development</article-title><source>World Dev</source><year>2021</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>105233</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33100478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lerner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Sacrifice zones: the front lines of toxic chemical exposure in the United States</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levidow</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieddu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivian</surname><given-names>F-D</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;fort</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Allaire</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Daviron</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transitions towards a European bioeconomy: life sciences versus agroecology trajectories</article-title><source>Ecology, capitalism and the new agricultural economy: the second great transformation</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>203</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR143"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lugones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards decolonial feminism</article-title><source>Hypatia</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1527-2001.2010.01137.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000fc;hmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whose European bioeconomy? Relations of forces in the shaping of an updated EU bioeconomy strategy</article-title><source>Environ Dev</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>100547</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envdev.2020.100547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fragmented sovereignty: land reform and dispossession in Laos</article-title><source>J Peasant Stud</source><year>2011</year><volume>38</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03066150.2011.607709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR142"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maldonado-Torres</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the coloniality of being</article-title><source>Cult Stud</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09502380601162548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Armijos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Coolsaet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>GAS</given-names></name><name><surname>Few</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross-Camp</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tebboth</surname><given-names>MLG</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental justice and transformations to sustainability</article-title><source>Environ Sci Policy Sustain Dev</source><year>2020</year><volume>62</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00139157.2020.1820294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Alier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental justice and economic degrowth: an alliance between two movements</article-title><source>Cap Nat Soc</source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Alier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A global environmental justice movement: mapping ecological distribution conflicts Disjuntiva</article-title><source>Cr&#x000ed;tica De Les Ci&#x000e8;ncies Socials</source><year>2020</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14198/DISJUNTIVA2020.1.2.6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Alier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Temper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Bene</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheidel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is there a global environmental justice movement?</article-title><source>J Peasant Stud</source><year>2016</year><volume>43</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03066150.2016.1141198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Masson-Delmotte V, Zhai P, Portner HO, Roberts D, Skea J, Shukla PR, Pirani A, Moufouma-Okia W, Pean C, Pidcock R, Connors S (2018) Special report on global warming of 1.5 &#x000b0;C. Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kautto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bioeconomy in Europe: an overview</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2589</fpage><lpage>2608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su5062589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Harcourt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond limits and scarcity: feminist and decolonial contributions to degrowth</article-title><source>Polit Geogr</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.polgeo.2021.102411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mellor M (2017) Money for the people. Great Transition Initiative. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://greattransition.org/publication/money-for-the-people">https://greattransition.org/publication/money-for-the-people</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Menton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Billon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Environmental defenders deadly struggles for life and territory</source><year>2021</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Alier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Temper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental justice and the SDGs: from synergies to gaps and contradictions</article-title><source>Sustain Sci</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-020-00789-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mignolo</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><source>On decoloniality: concepts, analytics, praxis</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Durham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahanty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Value and bureaucratic violence in the green economy</article-title><source>Geoforum</source><year>2019</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoforum.2018.11.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NASA Global Climate Change Data. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://climate.nasa.gov/vital-signs/global-temperature/">https://climate.nasa.gov/vital-signs/global-temperature/</ext-link>. Accessed 1 May 2021</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nightingale</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksen</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsyth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Newsham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Beyond technical fixes: climate solutions and the great derangement</article-title><source>Clim Dev</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17565529.2019.1624495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR901"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nirmal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocheleau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decolonizing degrowth in the post-development convergence: questions, experiences, and proposals from two Indigenous territories</article-title><source>Environ Plann E Nat Space</source><year>2019</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2514848618819478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Creating capabilities</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond green growth</article-title><source>Nat Sustain</source><year>2020</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-020-0499-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parrique T (2019) The political economy of degrowth. Economics and finance. Stockholm University, 2019. English. ffNNT : 2019CLFAD003ff. fftel-0249946</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parrique T, Barth J, Briens F, Kerschner C, Kraus-Polk A, Kuokkanen A, Spangenberg JH (2019) Decoupling debunked. Evidence and arguments against green growth as a sole strategy for sustainability. A study edited by the European Environment Bureau EEB. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://eeb.org/library/decoupling-debunked/">https://eeb.org/library/decoupling-debunked/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lele</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnhout</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity and the challenge of pluralism</article-title><source>Nat Sustain Perspect</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-021-00694-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelenc</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallenborn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Milanesi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e9;bastien</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vastenaekels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lajarthe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cervera-Marzal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carimentrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Merveille</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative and resistance movements: the two faces of sustainability transformations?</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2019</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2019.01.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Political prisoners and environmental justice</article-title><source>Cap Nat Soc</source><year>2018</year><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10455752.2018.1530835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pensera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fressoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovation without growth: technological change in a post-growth era</article-title><source>SSRN</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3486805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Proskurina S (2018) International trade in biomass for energy production: the local and global context. Acta Universitatis Lappeenrantaensis 806. PhD Thesis, Lappeenranta University</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR106"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>What is radical politics today? What is radical politics today?</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR107"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000fc;lzl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleinschmit</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Arts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioeconomy e an emerging meta-discourse affecting forest discourses?</article-title><source>Scand J for Res</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02827581.2014.920044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR108"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quijano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coloniality of power and Eurocentrism in Latin America</article-title><source>Int Sociol</source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0268580900015002005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR141"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quijano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coloniality and modernity/rationality</article-title><source>Cult Stud</source><year>2007</year><volume>2001</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09502380601164353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR109"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramcilovic-Suominen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000fc;lzl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable development&#x02014;a &#x02018;selling point&#x02019; of the emerging EU bioeconomy policy framework?</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2018</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>4170</fpage><lpage>4180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2016.12.157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR110"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramcilovic-Suominen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carodenuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiedanp&#x000e4;&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental justice and REDD+ safeguards in Laos: lessons from an authoritarian political regime</article-title><source>Ambio</source><year>2021</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>2256</fpage><lpage>2271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13280-021-01618-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34519956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR111"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Raworth K (2012) A safe and just space for humanity. Can we live within the doughnut? Oxfam Discussion Paper, February 2012</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR112"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rodriguez I (2020) The Latin American decolonial environmental justice approach. In: Coolsaet B (ed) Environmental justice: key isues earthscan</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR113"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Inturias</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conflict transformation in indigenous peoples&#x02019; territories: doing environmental justice with a &#x02018;decolonial turn&#x02019;</article-title><source>Dev Stud Res</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21665095.2018.1486220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR114"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakshi</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Denying indigenous environmental justice: Experiences from Australia, Brazil and Canada</article-title><source>Fourth World J</source><year>2021</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR115"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Another knowledge is possible: beyond northern epistemologies</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR116"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlosberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Defining environmental justice: theories, movements, and nature</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR117"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scoones</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The politics of sustainability and development</article-title><source>Annu Rev Environ Resour</source><year>2016</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-environ-110615-090039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR118"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Sacrifice zones&#x0201d; in the green energy economy: toward an environmental justice framework</article-title><source>McGill Law J</source><year>2017</year><volume>62</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>861</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7202/1042776ar</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR119"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sh&#x000f6;neberg J (2019) Imagining postcolonial-development studies: refections on positionalities and research practices. In: Baud I et al (eds) Building development studies for the New Millennium. Part of the EADI global development series book series. 10.1007/978-3-030-04052-9_5</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR120"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental justice, degrowth and post-capitalist futures</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2019</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2019.05.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR121"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sovacool</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Who are the victims of low-carbon transitions? Towards a political ecology of climate change mitigation</article-title><source>Energy Res Soc Sci</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.erss.2021.101916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR122"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sovacool</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnheim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martiskainen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dispossessed by decarbonisation: reducing vulnerability, injustice, and inequality in the lived experience of low-carbon pathways</article-title><source>World Dev</source><year>2021</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>105116</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR123"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Crutzen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anthropocene: are humans now overwhelming the great forces of nature?</article-title><source>Ambio</source><year>2007</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1579/0044-7447(2007)36[614:TAAHNO]2.0.CO;2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18240674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR124"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Diversifying power, why we need antiracist, feminist leadership on climate and energy</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Island</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR125"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>'Ecosystem Service Commodities'&#x02014;a new imperial ecology? Implications for animist immanent ecologies, with Deleuze and Guattari</article-title><source>New Form</source><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3898/NEWF.69.06.2010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR126"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change, COVID-19, and the co-production of injustices: a feminist reading of overlapping crises</article-title><source>Soc Cult Geogr</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14649365.2021.1910994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR127"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Temper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blocking pipelines, unsettling environmental justice: from rights of nature to responsibility to territory</article-title><source>Local Environ</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13549839.2018.1536698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR128"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Temper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A perspective on radical transformations to sustainability: resistances, movements and alternatives</article-title><source>Sustain Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-018-0543-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR129"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Temper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Movements shaping climate futures: a systematic mapping of protests against fossil fuel and low-carbon energy projects</article-title><source>Environ Res Lett</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>123004</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/abc197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR130"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>T&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelpohl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;cher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is bioeconomy policy a policy field? A conceptual framework and findings on the European Union and Germany</article-title><source>J Environ Policy Plan</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1523908X.2021.1893163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR131"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tome Valencia Hamilton R, Ramcilovic-Suominen S. Hegemony and radical socioecological transformation: horizons of possibility and strategies of escape. Forthcoming in Sustainability Science</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR132"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decolonization is not a metaphor</article-title><source>Decolon Indig Educ Soc</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR133"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;hning-Gaese</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fryxell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Moorter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Moving in the anthropocene: global reductions in terrestrial mammalian movements</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>359</volume><issue>6374</issue><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aam9712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29371471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR134"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuhiwai Smith</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><source>Decolonizing methodologies: research and indigenous peoples</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Zed</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR135"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNDP (2020) Human development report. The next frontier. Human development and the anthropocene. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdr.undp.org/en/2020-report">http://hdr.undp.org/en/2020-report</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR136"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNECE (United Nations Economic Commission for Europe) (2012) From transition to transformation, sustainable and inclusive development in Europe and Central Asia. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/index.php?page=view&#x00026;type=400&#x00026;nr=795&#x00026;menu=1515">https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/index.php?page=view&#x00026;type=400&#x00026;nr=795&#x00026;menu=1515</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR137"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vivien</surname><given-names>F-D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieddu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Befort</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Debref</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Giampietro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hijacking of the bioeconomy</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2019</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2019.01.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR138"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogelpohl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Perbandt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>T&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;cher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of European bioeconomy policy. Insights from a cross-case study of three policy areas</article-title><source>Environ Polit</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644016.2021.1917827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR139"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarfl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumsdon</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Berlekamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tydecks</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tockner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A global boom in hydropower dam construction</article-title><source>Aquat Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00027-014-0377-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR140"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zografos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green sacrifice zones, or why a green new deal cannot ignore the cost shifts of just transitions</article-title><source>One Earth</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oneear.2020.10.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>