<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par34">Second, building data is sourced from the National Structure Inventory (NSI) of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, and represents every structure in Harris County as a point. The NSI was constructed by combining information from many datasets&#8212;including Census data, Microsoft building footprints, CoreLogic parcels, and ESRI business layers&#8212;to produce the most accurate possible inventory for assessing natural hazard risk<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. The data includes information on occupancy type, first-floor elevation (including foundation type and whether the structure was built before or after the area was mapped as part of the 100-year floodplain), and the replacement value in order to link them to depth-damage functions and assess their flood vulnerability. We only include structures flooded above a 20&#8201;cm threshold; as very shallow flood depths are unlikely to cause much damage from surface water or pluvial flooding. Since it is composed of proprietary data, this dataset is not publicly available. Further details can be found in refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Our damage estimates are somewhat lower than another recent study: we estimate residential damages at $6.42 billion compared to $11.1 billion in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. We attribute these differences primarily to our calculation of building damages using replacement value instead of market value (as the latter also includes the value of the land), as well as possible differences in the depth-damage functions we use, in the modeling of riverine networks, and in the study&#8217;s spatial domain. Further, we believe our use of replacement value instead of market value as a depth-damage function is justified for a few reasons. First, replacement value directly estimates impacts on residential structures and contents from flooding. This differs from approaches using a market value which includes the land value that has characteristics (such as neighborhood desirability or how the land use of the building affects the value of the land) that are not easily measured. While economic models exist that could describe the damage as a function of market value such as hedonic property value modeling for cost-benefit analyses relating to environmental impacts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>, our use of depth-damage functions is favored because of the closer focus on the replacement value of estimated damages. Second, there are large disparities in market value based on the racial composition of neighborhoods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> meaning that a depth-damage function for market value could undercount damages in minority and/or low-income neighborhoods. Still, future research might consider other approaches such as hedonic models that take into account market value because the present approach with replacement value does not measure the land value of the parcel or how the land value of the parcel may be affected by damages to the buildings in the parcel.</p>