<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0035">Migration, as documented throughout human history, involves the mobility of people, usually <italic>towards</italic> a new location due to pull (e.g., work and livelihood) or push factors (e.g., drought, flood, political instability, poverty, and violent conflicts) or a combination of both (<xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Boustan et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Bowman and Henquinet, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">Hansen and Oliver-Smith, 2019</xref>). Retreat, on the other hand, refers to the <italic>withdrawal</italic> from a place because of a perceived or real threat of danger. Historically, military forces retreat from war zones when overpowered by enemy forces (<xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">Eyre, 1843</xref>). Some people view such withdrawal as a defeat (<xref rid="b0585" ref-type="bibr">Sides, 2018</xref>) but others see it as a victory by saving thousands of lives (<xref rid="b0610" ref-type="bibr">Thompson, 2009</xref>). Over the last two decades, climate change scholars and disaster experts have focused on <italic>retreat</italic> as one of several adaptation options in response to climate change. There are multiple definitions of retreat (<xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Agyeman et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Ferris, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">Hanna et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0575" ref-type="bibr">Scott et al., 2020</xref>) as well as contestations as to which &#8220;R&#8221; word (retreat, relocation, resettlement, realignment) is acceptable to different actors (<xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">Esteves, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr">Koslov, 2016</xref>) or commonly used in different geographic regions (<xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">Hammond, 2008</xref>, <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Betzold, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Arnall, 2019</xref>). In this paper, we use the word &#8216;managed retreat&#8217; because of its emerging but controversial appeal to scholars working on the subject.</p>