<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0040">We define MR as a deliberate and strategic &#8216;move from climate-induced harm&#8217; - this encompasses moving people and the resources they value such as homes, businesses, infrastructure, ecosystems, and other assets from areas of risk and resettling them in safer locations (<xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Alexander et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Bowman and Henquinet, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">Hino et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Ajibade, 2019</xref>). For some people, retreat may mean creating new setbacks (<xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Abel et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0540" ref-type="bibr">Pilkey et al., 2016</xref>), revoking building permits (<xref rid="b0505" ref-type="bibr">Nalau et al., 2015</xref>), re-zoning and land acquisition (<xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Dyckman et al., 2014</xref>) or outright relocation from hazardous zones (<xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr">Herrmann, 2017</xref>). MR is considered an alternative to sudden displacement (<xref rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr">Johnson, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr">Koslov, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0575" ref-type="bibr">Scott et al., 2020</xref>) and typically involves government and/or community participation (<xref rid="b0590" ref-type="bibr">Sipe and Vella, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Ferris, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0495" ref-type="bibr">Mortreux et al., 2018</xref>). For example, Taro, the capital of Choiseul Province in the Solomon Islands, is set to become the first capital globally to relocate residents and services due to the threat of SLR (<xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Albert et al., 2016</xref>). Indonesia has also announced the relocation of its capital city Jakarta to another location due to rising seas and sinking land (<xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Chappell, 2019</xref>). Other examples include the relocation of national treasures such as lighthouses in Denmark (The <xref rid="b0595" ref-type="bibr">Guardian, 2019</xref>) and North Carolina (<xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Allen, 2019</xref>).</p>