<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par63">The poor quality of national adaptation strategies and plans, the existence of a multiplicity of such plans and disconnects between the NDC and National Adaptation Planning (NAP) from broader national economic development planning are some of the challenges that Murphy and Parry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2020</xref>) identify in aligning developing country adaptation priorities and financing with the Paris Agreement objectives and MDB financing. MDBs can and have played a key role in improving the quality of the plans and aligning them with national economic development goals as well as objectives and financing of the Paris Agreement through technical assistance to NDC planning as well as adaptation policy-making (Murphy &amp; Parry, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2020</xref>). The example of IFAD&#8217;s involvement in the Kyrgyzstan NDC development illustrates how this may work. At the request of the Kyrgyz government, IFAD provided technical assistance in revising the country&#8217;s NDC via grant funding from ASAP. One of the main inputs to the revised NDC from the IFAD technical assistance was the addition of the livestock sector which was absent from the initial NDC, despite its importance in the national economy as well as a source of livelihood for a large share of the population &#8211; many of whom are poor (IFAD, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2021</xref>). The assistance included an analysis livestock emission and strategies for low-carbon livestock development, as well adaptation measures for sustainable livestock and pasture management. It also included detailed mapping of pastures and support for the strengthening and expansion of community based livestock and pasture management groups and plans. The assistance also included support to the development of a proposal to the Adaptation Fund for financing (IFAD, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2021</xref>).</p>