<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par2"> Normativity defines a significant research field within sustainability science, where scientific knowledge and normative orientations are intrinsically linked (Carnau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>; Miller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2014</xref>; Ziegler and Ott <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2011</xref>). However, it is still unclear how we can understand, or even model, normativity similarly to how we understand and model knowledge about complex biosocial or earth systems (Grunwald <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2011</xref>, p. 26). In this paper, we suggest ways to understand and model norms in sustainability discourses based on the analysis of three documents: the Pope&#8217;s Encyclical <italic>Laudato Si&#8217;</italic>, the <italic>Sustainable Development Goals</italic> (SDGs) and the <italic>Paris Agreement</italic> (PA) (see Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Synopsis of the three 2015 documents analyzed in this paper</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">UN Development Group <italic>Transforming our world: the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development (SDGs)</italic>
<break/>A/RES/70/1<break/>Adopted by the General Assembly: September 25, 2015<break/>Start: January 1, 2016</td><td align="left">UN Framework Convention on Climate Change<break/>
<italic>Paris Agreement (PA)</italic>
<break/>FCCC/CP/2015/L.9/Rev.1<break/>Sealed: December 12, 2015<break/>Signed: April 22, 2016&#8211;April 21, 2017.<break/>Start: November 4, 2016</td><td align="left">Encyclical<break/>Pope Francis<break/>
<italic>Laudato Si&#8217;, on the Care for Our Common Home</italic>
<break/>Published: June 18, 2015</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Authorship</td><td align="left">Directed by the United Nations through a deliberative process involving its 193 Member States, as well as global civil society, in order to provide a diversity of perspectives and experience</td><td align="left">Drafted during the 21st Conference of the Parties (COP21), November 30, 2015&#8211;December 12, 2015 in Paris; France&#8217;s foreign minister Laurent Fabius on behalf of the COP21</td><td align="left">Pope Francis, drafted by Cardinal Peter Turkson. Precursor summit on April 28, 2015 at the Vatican: &#8220;Protect the Earth, Dignify Humanity. The Moral Dimensions of Climate Change and Sustainable Development&#8221;&#8212;summoned the world religions&#8217; leaders, political leaders, and leading scientists</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Words</td><td align="left">~ 15.000</td><td align="left">~ 16.200</td><td align="left">~ 40.500</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Languages</td><td align="left">Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian, Spanish (official languages of the United Nations)</td><td align="left">Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian, Spanish (official languages of the United Nations)</td><td align="left">Arabic, English, French, German, Italian, Polish, Portuguese and Spanish, later Latin and Chinese</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Addressee</td><td align="left">&#8220;[T]his Agenda is a plan of action for people, planet and prosperity; as we embark on this collective journey, we pledge that no one will be left behind&#8221; (Preamble); &#8220;the future of humanity and of our planet lies in our hands&#8221; (&#167; 53)</td><td align="left">Parties of the UNFCCC (member states of the UN)</td><td align="left">&#8220;[E]very person living on this planet&#8221; (p. 4); &#8220;enter into dialogue with all people about our common home&#8221; (p. 4); &#8220;Future generations&#8221; (p. 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Performance</td><td align="left">A resolution is a non-binding intergovernmental agreement &#8220;setting out a supremely ambitious and transformational vision&#8221; (&#167; 7). Implementation of: &#8220;nationally owned sustainable development strategies&#8221;, &#8220;enabling international economic environment, including coherent and mutually supporting world trade, monetary and financial systems, and strengthened and enhanced global economic governance&#8221;, &#8220;availability of appropriate knowledge and technologies globally&#8221;, &#8220;capacity-building&#8221;, &#8220;global partnership&#8221;.(&#167; 63)</td><td align="left">The Agreement is not legally binding but aims at: &#8220;strengthening the global response to the threat of climate change, in the context of sustainable development and efforts to eradicate poverty&#8221; (Art. 2.1); &#8220;common but differentiated responsibilities and respective capabilities, in the light of different national circumstances&#8221; (Art. 2.2);<break/>&#8220;Facilitative dialogue&#8221; (&#167; 20); &#8220;global stocktake&#8221; &#8220;to assess the collective progress&#8221; (Art. 14)</td><td align="left">&#8220;[A] conversation which includes everyone, since the environmental challenge we are undergoing, and its human roots, concern and affect us all&#8221; (p. 14); &#8220;act of cooperation with the Creator&#8221; (p. 80);<break/>&#8220;critique of the &#8220;myths&#8221; of a modernity grounded in a utilitarian mindset (individualism, unlimited progress, competition, consumerism, the unregulated market)&#8221; (p. 154); dialogues on &#8220;the environment and the international community&#8221; (p. 121ff), &#8220;new national and local policies&#8221; (p. 129ff), &#8220;transparency in decision-making&#8221; (p. 134ff); &#8220;ecological education&#8221; (p. 155f)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Time horizons addressed</td><td align="left">2016&#8211;2030; &#8220;seek to build on the Millennium Development Goals&#8221; 2000&#8211;2015 (Preamble); &#8220;decision of great historic significance&#8221; (&#167; 50)</td><td align="left">Recalling the UNFCCC in 1992 (Art. 1); first global stocktake in 2023, then every five years (Art. 14); holding the increase in the global average temperature to well below 2&#160;&#176;C above pre-industrial levels (Art. 2); projecting emissions levels for 2030 (&#167; 17)</td><td align="left">&#8220;Genesis&#8221; (p. 47ff); &#8220;the last two hundred years&#8221; (p. 39);<break/>&#8220;future generations&#8221; (p. 118ff)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Values</td><td align="left">Sustainable development; education; cooperation; capacity-building; universalism; empowerment; the &#8220;Goals and targets are integrated and indivisible, global in nature and universally applicable&#8221; (&#167; 55)</td><td align="left">&#8220;[N]oting the importance for some of the concept of &#8216;climate justice&#8217; [&#8230;] of education, training, public awareness, public participation, public access to information and cooperation at all levels&#8221; (Annex, p. 21); &#8220;environmental integrity&#8221;, &#8220;transparency&#8221;, &#8220;accuracy&#8221;, &#8220;completeness&#8221;, &#8220;comparability and consistency&#8221; (Art. 4)</td><td align="left">&#8220;Human development&#8221; (p. 14), &#8220;justice&#8221; (p. 10), &#8220;universal solidarity&#8221; (p. 13), &#8220;common good&#8221; (p. 40), &#8220;scientific consensus&#8221; (p. 18), &#8220;ecological debt&#8221; (p. 36), &#8220;differentiated responsibilities&#8221; (p. 38), &#8220;ecological ethics&#8221;, &#8220;ecological citizenship&#8221; (p. 154)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>