<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Climate change is expected to adversely affect human health through direct and indirect paths. Direct effects of global environmental change include increased exposure to extreme weather and temperature events, comprising heat waves, cold spells, storms, and floods [<xref rid="B1-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Indirect effects are mediated through natural and social systems [<xref rid="B1-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Natural systems mediate changes in disease vector distribution, increased air pollution, and pollen distribution, as well as a higher frequency of food- and water-borne infections. Social systems, on the other hand, influence indirect climate effects on crop production and distribution, mental health, and occupational health and safety [<xref rid="B1-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Worldwide and within societies, exposure risks and vulnerability to negative health effects of climate change are unequally distributed [<xref rid="B1-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B4-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Beyond the natural distribution patterns of climate-related hazards, humans&#8217; abilities to withstand shocks and the extent of damages caused by these hazards are determined by social, cultural, and economic capital and power [<xref rid="B7-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], making climate change and its related policies&#8212;beyond other concerns&#8212;an ethical issue [<xref rid="B4-healthcare-04-00065" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p>