<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0130">At the same time Sheller's conceptualisation of mobility justice has been criticised. <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Davidson (2020)</xref>, for instance, points out that the operationalisation of the mobility as commons that <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Sheller (2018b)</xref> proposes still approaches mobility as a resource that can be owned and distributed with states required to regulate transnational firms and excessive levels of mobility and speed whilst minimising the harms and cost of mobility. Sheller's mobile ontology is still significantly oriented towards distributive justice. Drawing in particular on feminist and black feminist thought (e.g. <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Grosz, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0330" ref-type="bibr">Ferreira da Silva, 2017</xref>), Davidson proposes to move further away from questions about distribution through two moves. The first of these is to understand mobility as a material-semiotic process of energetic transformation through death and/or the foregoing of forms of life: the movement of humans hinges on metabolisms, either of those humans themselves when they eat or drink organic matter in some form to move themselves through their physical environments, or of the &#8220;organisms that died millions of years ago&#8221; (<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Davidson, 2020</xref>, page 15) and so enabled the formation of fossil fuels. This energetic transformation is not merely biophysical (material) but also entangled with ideas, ranging from the notion that it is perfectly fine to extract oil &#8216;resources&#8217; for human movement, even at high environmental or geopolitical risk, to the belief that active travel should be encouraged because of its benefits to individual health. The second move is to understand justice in terms of an immanent ethics that is not premised on universal, abstract and externally specified rules but on a collective and impersonal ethos &#8211; a set of self-imposed limits and emergent and likely place-specific ways of living that &#8220;define a purpose, values, targets for change, and potential techniques for change&#8221; (<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Grosz, 2017</xref>, page 134). Davidson's interest is particularly, though not exclusively, concerned with the material-semiotics of extraction and burning of fossil fuels. It thus complements Sheller's conceptualisation of mobility justice by refusing any separation of justice and sustainability of mobility and extends Sheller's approach by focusing attention on the very formation of the energetic socio-technical processes that make mobility possible, how and to what effect (something <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Henderson, 2020</xref> also does, albeit in a significantly different manner). Davidson's move is significant for various reasons, not least because it challenges the idea that, say, walking is inherently just. If this practice becomes for some people in certain situations &#8211; e.g., in unfamiliar neighbourhoods or on streets deemed &#8216;risky&#8217; because of who might be encountered&#8211; heavily dependent on smartphone apps tethered to near-planetary digital systems, is it still &#8216;good&#8217; or desirable given its connection to carbon consumption and the socio-spatial coding of bodies in terms of, for instance, physical strength, gait or skin colour?</p>