<p xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Involving all stakeholders in mitigation and adaptation efforts can create sustainable community development [<xref rid="B97-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. It is common for mitigation strategies to be presented as a win-win scenario, often referred to as co-beneficial, in order to attract the interest of all organizations and individuals affected by the policy [<xref rid="B113-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. For example, through building a solar farm in a community, energy service costs could be minimized for the individual, and local companies who create and then install the solar panels would benefit economically as well. In addition to initiating preventative measures to combat current and future climate change, &#8220;a comprehensive approach that considers all stakeholders within different levels, and the availability of resources&#8221; is recommended for communities and individuals [<xref rid="B97-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>] (p. 290). The authors indicate that the best adaption and mitigation strategies for addressing climate change in low- and middle-income communities must focus not only on specific environmental issues but also social and economic issues. Ebi <italic>et al.</italic> suggest that the capacity to adapt to climate change includes population awareness of the issues; option availability and availability of knowledge, skills, and technology; political drive; human and financial investment capital; and institutional capacity [<xref rid="B19-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The literature underscores that continual efforts must be made to provide particularly vulnerable populations with the knowledge, skills, and capital to empower individuals and communities to develop and support local and regional co-beneficial mitigation and adaptation strategies.</p>