<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para0005">To study environmental justice of land surface temperature, this article provides six types of data aggregated at the scale residential zones (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;1</xref>): (1) land surface temperature during summer; (2) economic status of residents; (3) ethnic composition of residents; (4) presence of different age groups; (5) gender composition; (6) housing tenure and value. To do so, the following datasets are used, processed, and provided.<list list-type="simple" id="celist0002"><list-item id="celistitem0004"><label>1.</label><p id="para0006">LST_Summer_Rasters_2014.gdb: geodatabase of the raw MODIS satellite imagery in the format of GIS raster. The name coding is as follows: <italic>MOD_Day</italic> refers to MODIS Terra day (10:30 a.m.); <italic>MOD_Night</italic> refers to MODIS Terra night (10:30 p.m.); <italic>MYD_Day</italic> refers to MODIS Aqua day (1:30 p.m.); <italic>MYD_Night</italic> refers to MODIS Aqua night (1:30 a.m.). The numbers in the rasters' name refer to the starting day of the eight days the images represent. For instance, <italic>MOD_Day_153</italic> is MODIS Terra day (10:30 a.m.), representing the average land surface temperature values of the days number 153 to 161 in 2014 <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0005"><label>2.</label><p id="para0007">Wijk_2014: the statistical bureau of the Netherlands' published data over the residential zones (Wijk) in 2014, in GIS polygon shapefile format.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0006"><label>3.</label><p id="para0008">Buildings_DEM: the raw data over the buildings' height in the format of 25&#160;m&#8239;&#215;&#8239;25&#160;m GIS raster (given the sheer size of the original file in polygons, the raster version is stored).</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0007"><label>4.</label><p id="para0009">Buildings_Age: the raw data over the buildings' age in the format of 25&#160;m&#8239;&#215;&#8239;25&#160;m GIS raster (given the sheer size of the original file in polygons, the raster version is stored).</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0008"><label>5.</label><p id="para0010">Aggregated_data: SPSS file with summer surface temperature and socioeconomic data of the residential zones of the Netherlands. Using the zones code (WK_Code), the data can be joined to the GIS file titled Wijk_2014.</p></list-item></list><fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Case study areas: The residential zones of the Netherlands -the so-called Wijken (left), and a zoom-in preview of the zones (left).</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p>