<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11094178</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">61044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-61044-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mechanisms upholding the persistence of stigma across 100&#x000a0;years of historical text</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5048-3088</contrib-id><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>Tessa E. S.</given-names></name><address><email>tessa.charlesworth@kellogg.northwestern.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hatzenbuehler</surname><given-names>Mark L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/000e0be47</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16753.36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2299 3507</institution-id><institution>Kellogg School of Management, </institution><institution>Northwestern University, </institution></institution-wrap>2211 Campus Dr, Evanston, IL 60208 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03vek6s52</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.38142.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 754X</institution-id><institution>Department of Psychology, </institution><institution>Harvard University, </institution></institution-wrap>33 Kirkland St, Cambridge, MA 02138 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>11069</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Today, many social groups face negative stereotypes. Is such negativity a stable feature of society and, if so, what mechanisms maintain stability both within and across group targets? Answering these theoretically and practically important questions requires data on dozens of group stereotypes examined simultaneously over historical and societal scales, which is only possible through recent advances in Natural Language Processing. Across two studies, we use word embeddings from millions of English-language books over 100&#x000a0;years (1900&#x02013;2000) and extract stereotypes for 58 stigmatized groups. Study 1 examines aggregate, societal-level trends in stereotype negativity by averaging across these groups. Results reveal striking persistence in aggregate negativity (no meaningful slope), suggesting that society maintains a stable level of negative stereotypes. Study 2 introduces and tests a new framework identifying potential mechanisms upholding stereotype negativity over time. We find evidence of two key sources of this aggregate persistence: within-group &#x0201c;reproducibility&#x0201d; (e.g., stereotype negativity can be maintained by using different traits with the same underlying meaning) and across-group &#x0201c;replacement&#x0201d; (e.g., negativity from one group is transferred to other related groups). These findings provide novel historical evidence of mechanisms upholding stigmatization in society and raise new questions regarding the possibility of future stigma change.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Stigma</kwd><kwd>Stereotypes</kwd><kwd>Historical change</kwd><kwd>Text analysis</kwd><kwd>Word embeddings</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Human behaviour</kwd><kwd>Health policy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Stigma&#x02014;defined as the co-occurrence of labeling, stereotyping, separation, status loss, and discrimination in a context in which unequal power is exercised<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>&#x02014;is a central topic throughout social science<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Robust evidence indicates that stigmatization affects the distribution of life outcomes (e.g., health, employment, educational attainment) for a diverse range of statuses, such as race, ethnicity, sexuality, disability, religion, immigration, and mental (e.g., schizophrenia) and physical (e.g., HIV) health conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Both the number of targeted groups and the adverse consequences of stigmatization have motivated extensive efforts to understand whether, when, and how stigma might be reduced<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Social science theories suggest that such efforts to reduce stigma might face serious challenges because stigmatization serves multiple evolutionary, psychological, and social functions&#x02014;including to avoid perceived pathogens<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, to justify and maintain the status quo<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, and to exploit and dominate others for political and economic gains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. These theories raise the provocative hypothesis that societies maintain a relatively stable level of stigmatization, in which the aggregate level of stigma across many groups remains flat over time. By aggregate, we mean the average level of stereotype negativity in society, observed by averaging trends across a diverse sample of stigmatized groups. Moreover, if aggregate persistence is observed, it raises new questions regarding the mechanisms underlying such stability. The current project provides the first historical test of both questions. Specifically, we ask: Is stigmatization&#x02014;as revealed through aggregating trends in collective stereotypes towards 58 diverse groups&#x02014;a stable feature of society? And if so, what mechanisms maintain stability of negativity both within and across groups?</p><p id="Par4">Existing research on questions of stigma stability or change, as well as the underlying mechanisms upholding such patterns, typically relies on archival data capturing components of stigma (e.g., stereotypes) that scientists happened to collect in past surveys and experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. While such approaches have provided important insights, they nevertheless remain limited to understanding stigma change as it unfolds: (a) towards one group target (or, in rare cases, a small subset of groups) studied in isolation; (b) over a short timescale, typically days or weeks; and (c) at the individual level of analysis (e.g., respondents measured pre/post interventions).</p><p id="Par5">Yet to address whether and how stigma is stable on aggregate in society, we require a very different approach. First, because our question is about the aggregate level of stigma, it can only be examined by averaging the trends in stereotypes across <italic>dozens</italic> of stigmatized groups that represent a wide sample space of group targets. Additionally, as we elaborate below, a wide sample space of group targets is also critical for testing whether and how stereotype negativity may transfer or generalize between groups over time to uphold aggregate negativity across groups. Second, by definition, examining persistence requires a long-term, historical dataset that studies these diverse groups simultaneously over a sufficiently long period (ideally, multiple decades) to allow for the detection of any reasonable change, should it exist. And finally, our question about stigma at a societal level necessitates methods that explicitly seek to examine collective, shared representations rather than a single individuals&#x02019; endorsed attitudes.</p><p id="Par6">Drawing on recent advances in Natural Language Processing (NLP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, the current work created a new historical dataset that meets these requirements to address multi-group, long-term, societal-level change in stigma. Specifically, as elaborated in <italic>Methods</italic> below, we use word embeddings trained on Google Books from 1900 to 2000<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> (and replicate all analyses in the Corpus of Historical American English). Word embeddings utilize word co-occurrences to quantitatively represent word meaning as vectors. The result is that words that tend to co-occur in similar contexts (e.g., &#x0201c;woman&#x0201d; co-occurs with &#x0201c;home&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;kind&#x0201d; more than &#x0201c;office&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;assertive&#x0201d;) will have vectors that are closer together in space. Thus, relationships between vectors can be used to identify stereotypical associations (e.g., between &#x0201c;woman&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;home&#x0201d;)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Already, researchers have demonstrated the validity of studying stereotype change in word embeddings, showing that the embeddings capture known changes in gender stereotypes alongside the Women&#x02019;s movement<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> as well as shifts in Asian stereotypes following immigration waves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Most recently, these approaches have also been used to provide insights into <italic>which</italic> groups may change over time in historical text. Specifically, comparing stereotypes towards 36 stigmatized groups (and 36 non-stigmatized contrast groups), sociodemographic identities (i.e., demographic characteristics that are imbued with strong social significance such as race, religion, or ethnicity) were found to change more over 115&#x000a0;years than body-related identities (i.e., identities that are visible and physical such as body weight or disability)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">Still, none of these projects have used a multi-group perspective focused on negatively stigmatized groups to test <italic>aggregate</italic> stereotypes at a societal level. Nor has any project yet considered the mechanisms upholding aggregate negativity both within groups (i.e., towards the same target) as well as across groups (i.e., towards multiple targets simultaneously). The novel contributions of the current manuscript are thus to: (1) examine patterns in aggregate negative stereotypes in society (Study 1); and (2) introduce and test a new theoretical framework that organizes a set of mechanisms underlying these trends (Study 2).</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Study 1: examining aggregate negative stereotypes across 100 years of text</title><p id="Par8">Study 1 examines whether the aggregate negativity in stereotypes of stigmatized groups has either generally decreased, increased, or remained stable in English-language book text from 1900 to 2000. Past work would suggest that any of these three patterns are empirically and theoretically possible. First, a <italic>decrease</italic> in negativity might be expected given results from repeated cross-sectional surveys of explicit and implicit attitudes showing slow but steady drops in negative representations for some target groups between the early 2000s&#x02013;2020<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Alternatively, <italic>increasing</italic> negativity might be expected, based on findings that as the number and visibility of several stigmatized groups increased over the past century, so too has the perceived threats of those groups, perhaps prompting negative backlash<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Indeed, recent history has seen rising hate crimes and legislation targeting stigmatized groups<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Finally, negativity may have remained <italic>persistent</italic> throughout the past 100&#x000a0;years. As reviewed above, some social science theories<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> posit that stigmatization serves multiple evolutionary, psychological, and social functions. Thus, societies may maintain a relatively stable level of stigmatization because it allows individuals and groups to attain relevant goals.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Results</title><p id="Par9">For each of the 58 groups (represented by group label lists from historical thesauruses; <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref>), we ranked cosine similarities between the group and a list of 414 traits available across the 100&#x000a0;years (from a larger list of&#x02009;~&#x02009;600 traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>). We then identified the top ten traits associated with each of the 58 groups in each decade. From these top-associated traits we also extract our primary metric of interest&#x02014;stereotype <italic>negativity&#x02014;</italic>by taking the historically-contextualized (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref>) valence scores of these traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. For example, in 1900, the group <italic>Homeless</italic> was most associated with traits including <italic>helpless, heartless, lonely, disorderly,</italic> and <italic>thoughtless</italic>, which had an average valence score of &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.10 (corresponding to the 18th most negative group); in 1950, the group was associated with traits including <italic>helpless, careless, inquisitive, impetuous,</italic> and <italic>cruel</italic>, with an average valence score of &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.11 (the 17th most negative). In this way, each of the 58 groups ends up with a timeseries of 11 valence scores (all decades from 1900 to 2000). Additionally, to have a measure of whether the stereotype was stable in latent semantic meaning, we transformed the top-associated traits into scores of stereotype <italic>warmth</italic> and <italic>competence</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, a widely used typology of stereotype content. We again&#x000a0;did so using historically-contextualized scores (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref>) of each trait along these latent semantic dimensions. In summary, our analyses focus on the 58 timeseries (one for each group) of latent valence, warmth, and competence, in addition to changes in the top-associated traits themselves (i.e., the top-10 trait content).</p><p id="Par10">For our first result, we inspect the average stereotype negativity aggregating across the 58 stigmatized groups over 100&#x000a0;years of English-language books. Bayesian mixed-effects models (<italic>Methods</italic>) showed an aggregate slope that was close to zero, <italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0030, 95% credible interval (CI) [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0042, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0017] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), indicating only a slight movement towards more negative representations of stigmatized groups over the past century. Indeed, inference using the Region of Practical Equivalence (ROPE)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> showed 100% of the posterior estimates for the aggregate slope fell within a region that would be reasonably said to be a &#x0201c;null&#x0201d; effect. Thus, over 100&#x000a0;years of English-language text, negative stereotypes of stigmatized groups have remained, on aggregate, remarkably stable.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Trajectories of stereotype valence (positivity/negativity) towards 58 stigmatized groups. The dark black line indicates the aggregate (averaged) trajectory from raw values, showing stability in aggregate trends of stereotype negativity across 58 stigmatized groups over the past century. Individual colored lines show the individual group trajectories. Y-axis indicates the stereotype valence score (historically-contextualized valence scores averaging across the top 10 traits in each decade), with higher scores indicating more positive trait representations and lower scores indicating more negative trait representations. X-axis indicates the decade of the Google Books text.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61044_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec4"><title>Robustness checks</title><p id="Par11">We ensured that central conclusions were robust to various methodological choices (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref>). First, because the Google Books corpus changed over time in the proportion of non-fiction scientific texts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, we replicate all analyses with word embeddings trained on the smaller, genre-balanced (i.e., consistent balance of fiction and non-fiction texts over time) Corpus of Historical American English<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Although COHA is substantially smaller (&#x0003c;&#x02009;1% the size of Google Books), we still find consistent conclusions with both corpora, ruling out concerns that the observed stability in stereotype negativity is due merely to changes in genre composition. Second, we ensured robustness across frequentist modeling approaches, finding identical conclusions regardless of model specifications.</p><p id="Par12">Third, for a subset of groups we had scores on (1) how much the meaning of the group labels (e.g., changes in the meaning of <italic>Gay</italic>) had changed across time (known as semantic drift), (2) how many meanings the group labels had other than non-group related meanings (known as polysemy), and (3) the frequency of these labels. For groups with these available data, we computed an additional regression that directly controlled for drift, polysemy, and frequency of group labels, and the main conclusions of aggregate stability remained. Further, none of these three variables showed significant interactions with change, indicating that these covariates did not moderate the conclusions of how groups are changing. Fourth, because the current methods rely on choices of how to represent the social groups in question, we tested whether changing the lists of group labels altered the key results. Even when using only the four most central and frequent group labels to represent a sample of the groups, we again found aggregate stability.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Study 2: mechanisms upholding aggregate negativity over 100&#x000a0;years of text</title><p id="Par13">Study 1 showed that aggregate stereotype negativity was relatively stable over 100&#x000a0;years of English-language book text, raising the question of what societal mechanisms might maintain such stigmatization. Here, we introduce and test the <italic>Stigma Stability Framework</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) to propose two complementary mechanisms of reproducibility (within groups) and replacement (transfer across groups), each enacted in three empirical patterns.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Visual overview of the Stigma Stability Framework. The framework proposes two complementary classes of mechanisms&#x02014;replacement and reproducibility&#x02014;to explain aggregate (averaged) persistence of negative stereotypes towards stigmatized groups at a societal level. The general mechanisms are, in turn, empirically enacted in six empirical patterns, as described in the figure. Gray numbers and percentages indicate the number of groups, in the current sample and with the current methods, that followed each empirical pattern.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61044_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec6"><title>Reproducibility</title><p id="Par14">We refer to the first mechanism as <italic>reproducibility</italic>, in which stereotype negativity is reproduced (repeated) towards a single target group. The idea of reproducibility emerges from the theory of stigma as a fundamental cause<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, which posits that, if the underlying motivations to stigmatize (e.g., to dominate) have not been addressed, advantaged groups will continually reproduce stigma, often by developing new means to stigmatize the same group via interchangeable, mutually reinforcing mechanisms. For example, historical analyses show the changing means used to sustain stigmatization of Black people in the United States, moving from slavery to explicit forms of discrimination (e.g., Jim Crow laws) to more covert expressions, such as aversive<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> and &#x0201c;laissez faire&#x0201d; racism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par15">Empirically, reproducibility can be enacted through three patterns. First, a pattern we term &#x0201c;deep stability&#x0201d; occurs when a stereotype is repeated across time (e.g., a group is &#x0201c;lazy&#x0201d; in 1900 and &#x0201c;idle&#x0201d; in 2000), with the same underlying negativity, latent semantic meaning (i.e., warmth and competence dimension), and semantically-similar top associated traits (i.e., near synonyms with high cosine similarities). A second pattern, which we term &#x0201c;valence&#x02009;+&#x02009;semantic stability&#x0201d;, occurs when the same underlying negativity and semantic meaning is reproduced but new traits emerge; for example, a group is &#x0201c;lazy&#x0201d; in 1900 but &#x0201c;helpless&#x0201d; in 2000, with &#x0201c;helpless&#x0201d; being similar to &#x0201c;lazy&#x0201d; in average warmth and competence but not a direct semantic synonym as in the first pattern (i.e., they have lower cosine similarities), thereby reflecting change in the top trait associates. In a third pattern that we term &#x0201c;valence stability&#x0201d;, the same underlying negativity is reproduced, but the source of the negativity shifts as new semantic meanings become associated with the group (e.g., &#x0201c;lazy&#x0201d; in 1900 but &#x0201c;ugly&#x0201d; in 2000, where &#x0201c;lazy&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;ugly&#x0201d; are both negative but are different in latent warmth and competence).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Replacement</title><p id="Par16">The second complementary mechanism upholding aggregate stereotype negativity is stigma <italic>replacement,</italic> in which the negativity towards one group is transferred across group lines such that, on aggregate, patterns of change may &#x0201c;cancel out&#x0201d;. As one historical example, replacement is seen in increasing negativity towards Black Americans following the Great Migration into the Northern US in 1915&#x02013;1930 that occurred alongside <italic>decreasing</italic> negativity towards European immigrant groups into those same areas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. That is, negativity historically held towards immigrants was transferred to more newly-arrived Black Americans. More broadly, the idea of replacement is also conceptually supported by the theory of stigma as a fundamental cause<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>: if underlying stigma motivations remain, but the permissibility of stigmatizing a given target changes (e.g., it is no longer permissible to stigmatize immigrant groups), then advantaged groups may seek a new target for their negativity (e.g., Black Americans).</p><p id="Par17">Replacement, understood as the transfer or generalization of negativity, can similarly follow three empirical patterns. First, replacement could occur by transferring stereotype negativity across groups that share some semantic relationship, essentially in a hydraulic manner. For example, lessening negativity towards <italic>Asexual</italic> people may be transferred towards a group that shares similar semantic meanings of warmth and competence (i.e., is represented close in semantic space)<italic>,</italic> such that a group like <italic>Infertile</italic> experiences a corresponding strengthening in negativity. In this case, groups that are more semantically similar in the 1900s would have very different (and, perhaps in some cases, even opposing) slopes from 1900 to 2000, resulting in a negative correlation between semantic similarity between groups and similarity in their change.</p><p id="Par18">Second, the transferal of negativity could occur through other, non-semantic processes. Empirically, this would be observed if the semantic similarity between groups did not significantly predict the similarity of negativity slopes across groups. Indeed, the above example of transferring prejudice between immigrant groups and Black Americans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> is less about shared semantics than it is other shared characteristics, such as geographic location. Further explanations for why negativity is transferred between groups could include the relative prevalence of the groups (e.g., when a group switches from the second to the first most prevalent minority group in society it could &#x0201c;acquire&#x0201d; the brunt of prejudice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>) or the shared functions of the groups (e.g., both satisfy the need for exploitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>).</p><p id="Par19">Finally, also within the general umbrella of replacement is a pattern that we term &#x0201c;generalization&#x0201d;, which is the idea that some semantically-related groups may experience similar patterns of lessening negativity; in short, a pattern of change in one group &#x0201c;generalizes&#x0201d; to a similar second group, such that there would be a negative correlation between the semantic similarity between groups and their differences in change. To be clear, this pattern is not a hydraulic relationship (i.e., one group lessens, another group strengthens) like the other two empirical patterns of replacement, and thus it is not strictly a means of maintaining aggregate stable negativity. In fact, observing &#x0201c;generalization&#x0201d; would result in an aggregate <italic>change</italic> in the societal-level of negativity because multiple groups are changing in similar ways and similar directions. Nevertheless, we include this last empirical pattern under the umbrella of a &#x0201c;replacement&#x0201d; mechanism, because it conceptually also involves a transfer or generalization of negativity across groups.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><p id="Par20">Study 2 used the same data and general methods as Study 1 to provide initial empirical tests of the prevalence of mechanisms in the Stigma Stability Framework, looking across all 58 groups and 100&#x000a0;years of English-language book text. A group is classified as showing <italic>reproducibility</italic> if the random slope estimates from the Bayesian regression model are null (i.e., the Highest Density Interval includes zero). Conversely, a group is classified as showing <italic>replacement</italic> if the random slopes are not null, since replacement requires that the target group be changing in stereotype negativity for some transfer to occur.</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Overall prevalence of mechanisms</title><p id="Par21">Using these criteria, we found that over half of the individual group-level slopes (33/58 groups; or 57%; Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) revealed little meaningful change, a result consistent with the reproducibility mechanism. The remaining groups showing change (25/58; or 43%) suggest replacement (transfer) of stereotype negativity.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Estimated change in latent valence and identified top traits for 58 stigmatized groups across 100&#x000a0;years of book text.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Group</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Mechclass</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Change in latent valence <italic>b</italic> [95% HDI]</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Top 10 traits</th></tr><tr><th align="left">1900</th><th align="left">2000</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Bipolar</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0019 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0055, 0.0015]</td><td align="left">Depressed, nervous, despondent, melancholy, intellectual, irritable, intense, moody, restless, emotional</td><td align="left">Depressed, compulsive, antisocial, severe, emotional, patient, unstable, persistent, temperamental, aggressive</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Blind</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.0005 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0028, 0.0038]</td><td align="left">Stupid, dull, superstitious, foolish, careless, relaxed, melancholy, ignorant, irritable, conceited</td><td align="left">Lustful, dull, sloppy, gullible, listless, spiteful, suave, scornful, stingy, glum</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Depressed</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.0009 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0027, 0.0045]</td><td align="left">Melancholy, gloomy, depressed, despondent, listless, lonely, moody, fearful, irritable, helpless</td><td align="left">Depressed, gloomy, angry, fearful, melancholy, listless, lonely, anxious, dull, helpless</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gang</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.0010 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0025, 0.0045]</td><td align="left">Noisy, disorderly, unruly, ruthless, fanatical, reckless, greedy, spiteful, dishonest, hostile</td><td align="left">Spiteful, disrespectful, bossy, glum, inconsiderate, stingy, lustful, sloppy, suave, opinionated</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heartattack</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0023 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0058, 0.0012]</td><td align="left">Nervous, sympathetic, superficial, irritable, severe, perceptive, patient, tense, excitable, persistent</td><td align="left">Severe, patient, spontaneous, nervous, unstable, sympathetic, persistent, compulsive, moderate, abrupt</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Homeless</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.0002 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0032, 0.0038]</td><td align="left">Helpless, heartless, lonely, disorderly, thoughtless, conceited, reckless, adventurous, unruly, greedy</td><td align="left">Spiteful, sloppy, opinionated, despondent, suave, insolent, bossy, headstrong, rebellious, disrespectful</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mute</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0015 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0049, 0.0019]</td><td align="left">Silent, despondent, helpless, meek, submissive, timid, listless, melancholy, lifeless, dull</td><td align="left">Silent, listless, dull, easygoing, suave, fussy, argumentative, spiteful, amiable, disrespectful</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prostitute</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0014 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0048, 0.0020]</td><td align="left">Conceited, headstrong, immoral, moody, heartless, enterprising, crafty, thoughtless, resentful, disorderly</td><td align="left">Stingy, lustful, bossy, sociable, spiteful, suave, opinionated, disrespectful, indiscreet, envious</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ret*</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0029 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0065, 0.0005]</td><td align="left">Stupid, cowardly, unsympathetic, ignorant, mischievous, intellectual, impressionable, timid, sluggish, immoral</td><td align="left">Stupid, opinionated, fussy, easygoing, temperamental, immature, abusive, spiteful, listless, compulsive</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Scarred</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.0002 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0033, 0.0036]</td><td align="left">Helpless, lifeless, cruel, weak, heartless, despondent, spiteful, tender, clumsy, irritable</td><td align="left">Dull, superstitious, clumsy, careless, insolent, rude, helpless, listless, spiteful, easygoing</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Short</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0015 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0050, 0.0020]</td><td align="left">Intolerant, arrogant, thoughtless, shy, timid, fickle, conceited, mischievous, touchy, fearful</td><td align="left">Spiteful, listless, suave, sloppy, headstrong, envious, scornful, gloomy, lustful, opinionated</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Stroke</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0020 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0054, 0.0014]</td><td align="left">Nervous, severe, patient, irritable, impressionable, relaxed, perceptive, intense, passive, cold</td><td align="left">Severe, nervous, patient, spontaneous, compulsive, rash, irritable, persistent, progressive, depressed</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unattractive</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.0005 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0031, 0.0041]</td><td align="left">Clumsy, despondent, rude, vulgar, disagreeable, stupid, gloomy, coarse, pompous, shy</td><td align="left">Spiteful, listless, easygoing, stupid, opinionated, inept, gloomy, suave, greedy, headstrong</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Abortion</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0023 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0060, 0.0012]</td><td align="left">Impressionable, spontaneous, immature, artificial, inventive, rash, patient, perceptive, rebellious, rational</td><td align="left">Cruel, immoral, prudent, impolite, incompetent, spontaneous, considerate, pompous, fearful, antisocial</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Alcoholic</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0023 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0059, 0.0012]</td><td align="left">Cold, impulsive, sensual, irritable, weak, haphazard, nervous, sober, sluggish, greedy</td><td align="left">Compulsive, antisocial, irritable, reckless, disorderly, abusive, negligent, temperamental, emotional, severe</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Black</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.0005 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0030, 0.0042]</td><td align="left">Fanatical, spiteful, cultured, greedy, belligerent, coarse, reckless, helpless, honest, irresponsible</td><td align="left">Bossy, squeamish, talented, thoughtless, insolent, aloof, belligerent, respectable, sloppy, disrespectful</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cancer</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0018 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0051, 0.0016]</td><td align="left">Superficial, patient, nervous, irritable, progressive, severe, spontaneous, perceptive, intense, passive</td><td align="left">Cultured, spontaneous, patient, nervous, superficial, immature, severe, inactive, blunt, soft</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Divorced</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0028 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0064, 0.0008]</td><td align="left">Detached, unruly, independent, immature, dependent, unkind, helpless, dominant, respectable, aloof</td><td align="left">Detached, abusive, incompetent, dependent, unkind, resentful, respectable, jealous, mature, fussy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Herpes</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0027 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0061, 0.0008]</td><td align="left">Nervous, bright, impressionable, irritable, severe, bland, patient, cold, coarse, erratic</td><td align="left">Severe, antisocial, cultured, nervous, persistent, compulsive, unconventional, patient, rash, spontaneous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Molestor</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.0001 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0035, 0.0036]</td><td align="left">Lenient, obnoxious, vindictive, disorderly, cruel, severe, unjust, unfair, ruthless, reasonable</td><td align="left">Disorderly, antisocial, discriminating, abusive, inept, aggressive, manipulative, temperamental, impulsive, compulsive</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Muslim</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0005 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0040, 0.0033]</td><td align="left">Hostile, fanatical, ruthless, arrogant, rebellious, daring, insolent, stubborn, belligerent, irresponsible</td><td align="left">Religious, bossy, belligerent, aloof, suave, opinionated, inconsiderate, stingy, benevolent, superstitious</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Schizophrenic</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0030 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0064, 0.0004]</td><td align="left">Sophisticated, immature, impressionable, irritable, squeamish, perceptive, nervous, feminine, spiteful, severe</td><td align="left">Compulsive, antisocial, temperamental, depressed, patient, severe, emotional, spontaneous, immature, spiteful</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Wheelchair</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0007 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0043, 0.0028]</td><td align="left">Helpless, patient, irritable, weak, depressed, inactive, severe, nervous, inefficient, unsympathetic</td><td align="left">Helpless, incompetent, abusive, patient, emotional, severe, negligent, irritable, depressed, immature</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Atheist</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0026 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0009, 0.0062]</td><td align="left">Fanatical, intolerant, cowardly, vulgar, arrogant, obstinate, rebellious, superstitious, fickle, cruel</td><td align="left">Spiteful, bossy, stingy, opinionated, argumentative, disrespectful, fickle, headstrong, sloppy, insolent</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Criminal</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0025 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0011, 0.0061]</td><td align="left">Disorderly, immoral, cruel, obnoxious, dishonest, vindictive, heartless, cowardly, negligent, ruthless</td><td align="left">Disorderly, incompetent, negligent, dishonest, reckless, prejudiced, unethical, cruel, suspicious, conscientious</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Deaf</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0006 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0030, 0.0042]</td><td align="left">Dull, articulate, depressed, harsh, irritable, despondent, resentful, melancholy, weak, noisy</td><td align="left">Severe, spontaneous, depressed, abusive, argumentative, thoughtless, listless, temperamental, emotional, spiteful</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Disabled</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0023 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0011, 0.0058]</td><td align="left">Helpless, cowardly, inefficient, incompetent, negligent, irritable, resentful, inactive, weak, cruel</td><td align="left">Abusive, helpless, incompetent, negligent, inept, opinionated, thoughtless, fussy, argumentative, discriminating</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Infertile</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0014 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0020, 0.0049]</td><td align="left">Lonely, helpless, envious, heartless, arrogant, cruel, mischievous, fickle, lifeless, harsh</td><td align="left">Inept, abusive, listless, immature, unruly, vindictive, incompetent, irresponsible, easygoing, helpless</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Middleeastern</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0024 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0011, 0.0062]</td><td align="left">Hostile, ruthless, cruel, fanatical, rebellious, insolent, belligerent, irresponsible, crafty, ignorant</td><td align="left">Belligerent, diplomatic, bossy, hostile, indecisive, despondent, fanatical, spiteful, inconsiderate, loyal</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Molested</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0018 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0016, 0.0053]</td><td align="left">Ruthless, worried, insolent, disorderly, cruel, prejudiced, vindictive, dishonest, fanatical, hostile</td><td align="left">Jealous, angry, abusive, disagreeable, suspicious, prejudiced, impetuous, shrewd, unethical, incompetent</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Polygamous</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0002 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0031, 0.0035]</td><td align="left">Cooperative, aggressive, immoral, dominant, illogical, optimistic, religious, spontaneous, superstitious, unfriendly</td><td align="left">Stingy, spiteful, suave, bossy, disrespectful, temperamental, inconsiderate, glum, gullible, opinionated</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Poor</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.0012 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0024, 0.0049]</td><td align="left">Helpless, heartless, ignorant, weak, cowardly, conceited, lazy, stupid, envious, cruel</td><td align="left">Helpless, stupid, ignorant, easygoing, lazy, hardworking, envious, greedy, opinionated, rebellious</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unemployed</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0009 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0043, 0.0025]</td><td align="left">Inactive, listless, lazy, frivolous, restless, noisy, helpless, inefficient, silent, aloof</td><td align="left">Inactive, lazy, ignorant, helpless, depressed, inefficient, weak, restless, immature, listless</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Asexual</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0121 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0160, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0085]</td><td align="left">Strict, conventional, meek, submissive, feminine, conscientious, dignified, modest, religious, compassionate</td><td align="left">Opinionated, spiteful, suave, sloppy, squeamish, inconsiderate, easygoing, argumentative, disrespectful, fickle</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Aboriginal</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0046 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0081, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0011]</td><td align="left">Hostile, crafty, adventurous, ruthless, fanatical, rebellious, rude, belligerent, devious, fickle</td><td align="left">Bossy, sloppy, stingy, spiteful, carefree, devious, squeamish, touchy, disrespectful, egotistical</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Asian</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0043 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0079, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0006]</td><td align="left">Crafty, dominant, belligerent, hostile, traditional, diplomatic, irresponsible, cultured, adventurous, cooperative</td><td align="left">Bossy, belligerent, diplomatic, religious, traditional, peaceful, social, unconventional, concise, devious</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Christian</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0055 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0091, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0018]</td><td align="left">Religious, fanatical, tolerant, dominant, spiritual, hostile, cultured, intolerant, ethical, loyal</td><td align="left">Bossy, religious, conservative, spiritual, benevolent, loyal, philosophical, argumentative, stingy, moral</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dealer</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0071 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0108, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0036]</td><td align="left">Talkative, smart, haphazard, shrewd, skillful, crafty, sly, cunning, dishonest, possessive</td><td align="left">Compulsive, gullible, unethical, disorderly, nonchalant, unscrupulous, inept, antisocial, fickle, negligent</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fat</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0056 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0091, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0020]</td><td align="left">Tough, soft, strong, weak, clumsy, coarse, jolly, earthy, neat, sluggish</td><td align="left">Easygoing, coarse, moderate, soft, immature, listless, lazy, fussy, bright, witty</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gay</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0095 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0132, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0060]</td><td align="left">Spiteful, squeamish, jolly, curious, humorous, pompous, sentimental, bashful, touchy, clumsy</td><td align="left">Lustful, bossy, spiteful, opinionated, argumentative, suave, easygoing, temperamental, disrespectful, fussy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HIV</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0132 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0170, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0095]</td><td align="left">Spiritual, ethical, indirect, artistic, efficient, intellectual, rational, artificial, helpful, inventive</td><td align="left">Severe, patient, antisocial, persistent, nervous, temperamental, inactive, abusive, capable, compulsive</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indian</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0043 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0078, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0008]</td><td align="left">Ignorant, superstitious, traditional, crafty, hostile, abusive, religious, intelligent, friendly, polite</td><td align="left">Bossy, stingy, belligerent, squeamish, religious, sloppy, spiteful, inconsiderate, glum, concise</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Jewish</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0044 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0079, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0008]</td><td align="left">Religious, traditional, spiritual, ethical, fanatical, materialistic, cultured, dominant, intolerant, tolerant</td><td align="left">Religious, bossy, spiritual, benevolent, conservative, superstitious, uncompromising, loyal, traditional, hostile</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Laborer</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0117 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0153, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0081]</td><td align="left">Honest, skillful, intelligent, diligent, respectable, talented, jolly, ingenious, cooperative, practical</td><td align="left">Respectable, suave, opinionated, diligent, benevolent, ignorant, spiteful, gullible, talented, bossy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Latino</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0052 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0087, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0017]</td><td align="left">Belligerent, hostile, diplomatic, adventurous, loyal, rebellious, friendly, indecisive, crafty, uncompromising</td><td align="left">Belligerent, bossy, diplomatic, social, squeamish, opinionated, bland, spiteful, disrespectful, devious</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Old</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0080 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0116, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0041]</td><td align="left">Respectable, impressionable, affectionate, discreet, helpless, amiable, thoughtful, mature, proud, considerate</td><td align="left">Affectionate, respectable, proud, talented, jealous, amiable, charming, compassionate, fussy, submissive</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Paroled</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0044 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0079, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0011]</td><td align="left">Evasive, rash, flattering, satisfied, unfair, unjust, negligent, responsible, indiscreet, belligerent</td><td align="left">Incompetent, dishonest, negligent, unscrupulous, cruel, competent, indiscreet, spiteful, compulsive, impartial</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pierced</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0060 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0094, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0026]</td><td align="left">Clumsy, blunt, lifeless, tough, spiteful, bright, deep, coarse, soft, expressive</td><td align="left">Suave, glum, sloppy, spiteful, easygoing, stingy, listless, squeamish, bossy, untidy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Psoriasis</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0039 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0075, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0005]</td><td align="left">Nervous, irritable, severe, soft, superficial, patient, bright, tense, relaxed, harsh</td><td align="left">Rash, severe, compulsive, nervous, excitable, irritable, persistent, cultured, spontaneous, touchy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Server</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0091 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0128, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0055]</td><td align="left">Jolly, touchy, smart, haphazard, tidy, fickle, neat, merry, lazy, charming</td><td align="left">Suave, easygoing, fussy, cheerful, jolly, noisy, glum, merry, disrespectful, sly</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Std</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0042 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0076, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0008]</td><td align="left">Nervous, perceptive, impressionable, immature, helpful, severe, competitive, patient, artificial, direct</td><td align="left">Antisocial, patient, cultured, severe, nervous, persistent, compulsive, unconventional, inactive, rash</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Transgender</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0091 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0128, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0056]</td><td align="left">Methodical, philosophical, original, analytical, devious, outgoing, argumentative, constructive, ethical, impersonal</td><td align="left">Bossy, argumentative, squeamish, egotistical, suave, gullible, sloppy, indiscreet, spiteful, philosophical</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Uneducated</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0048 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0084, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0014]</td><td align="left">Ignorant, vulgar, stupid, conceited, intelligent, careless, submissive, inquisitive, indifferent, thoughtless</td><td align="left">Ignorant, glum, opinionated, suave, bossy, easygoing, spiteful, intelligent, stingy, inept</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetic</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0044 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0079, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0009]</td><td align="left">Severe, patient, sophisticated, nervous, analytical, impressionable, progressive, irritable, bright, immature</td><td align="left">Severe, temperamental, compulsive, spontaneous, dependent, patient, immature, nervous, depressed, progressive</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Drugaddict</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0042 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0077, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0007]</td><td align="left">Earthy, crude, discriminating, weak, disagreeable, coarse, bitter, cold, fickle, sluggish</td><td align="left">Compulsive, antisocial, abusive, inept, temperamental, rebellious, spiteful, irritable, heartless, opinionated</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Immigrant</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0058 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0093, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0024]</td><td align="left">Hostile, unfriendly, ignorant, adventurous, dominant, enterprising, greedy, irresponsible, rebellious, disorderly</td><td align="left">Abusive, hostile, belligerent, aloof, heartless, ruthless, ignorant, prejudiced, casual, headstrong</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Multiracial</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0053 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0089, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0016]</td><td align="left">Tidy, spiteful, greedy, spirited, shy, bashful, immature, benevolent, indiscreet, fearless</td><td align="left">Social, bossy, argumentative, disrespectful, benevolent, temperamental, sloppy, feminine, religious, insolent</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smoker</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0060 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0096, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0026]</td><td align="left">Sly, listless, sociable, coarse, bland, neat, scornful, jolly, sarcastic, lazy</td><td align="left">Compulsive, antisocial, soft, nonchalant, persistent, listless, irritable, refined, spontaneous, disagreeable</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#x0201c;Mech. class&#x0201d; indicates the class of mechanism for each group, with codes as follows (see also Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>): &#x0201c;1&#x0201d;&#x02009;=&#x02009;reproducibility via &#x0201c;deep stability,&#x0201d; with all metrics showing stability over time; &#x0201c;2&#x0201d;&#x02009;=&#x02009;reproducibility via &#x0201c;valence&#x02009;+&#x02009;semantic stability,&#x0201d; despite change in the top traits; &#x0201c;3&#x0201d;&#x02009;=&#x02009;reproducibility via &#x0201c;valence stability,&#x0201d; despite changing semantic sources of the valence; &#x0201c;4&#x0201d;&#x02009;=&#x02009;replacement via &#x0201c;shared semantics&#x0201d;; &#x0201c;5&#x0201d;&#x02009;=&#x02009;replacement or transfer via other, &#x0201c;non-semantic&#x0201d; means; &#x0201c;6&#x0201d;&#x02009;=&#x02009;the only empirical pattern that might produce change, by producing &#x0201c;generalization&#x0201d; via shared semantics, where a change in one group cascades to similar changes among semantically-related groups. Estimated change in latent valence are the group-level random slopes, from the Bayesian mixed-effects model predicting valence from the fixed effect of time. 95% HDI&#x02009;=&#x02009;95% Highest Density Interval. Top traits are the top-10 traits ranked as the most associated with the group target (i.e., have the highest average cosine similarities), within the listed example years.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Empirical patterns of stability through reproducibility</title><p id="Par22">Starting with the 33 groups indicating reproducibility, we find evidence for all three proposed patterns, each occurring in approximately equal proportion. The first pattern (&#x0201c;deep stability&#x0201d;) is descriptively the most common, observed in 13/33 groups (39%). For example, negative stereotypes of the group <italic>Mute</italic> had top traits including [<italic>silent, listless, dull</italic>] in 1900 and 2000, with both timepoints reflecting near-identical negative representations (with traits that had high cosine similarities) and reflecting the same latent stereotype meanings of coldness and incompetence across time.</p><p id="Par23">A second set of groups, 10/33 (30%), followed the &#x0201c;valence&#x02009;+&#x02009;semantic stability&#x0201d; pattern in which the actual top-associated traits turned over across time (i.e., traits had low cosine similarities) but latent valence and warmth and/or competence were stable. The negative stereotypes towards <italic>Black</italic> illustrate this empirical pattern: top traits in 1900 included [<italic>coarse, reckless, irresponsible, helpless, honest</italic>] but in 2000 included [<italic>sloppy, belligerent</italic>, <italic>thoughtless</italic>, and <italic>respectable</italic>]. Although the traits themselves changed, the negativity was reproduced via stable latent sources (i.e., the average latent warmth was stable, <italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0024 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0001, 0.0050], as was average competence <italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0002 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0031, 0.0026]).</p><p id="Par24">The final set of groups, 10/33 (30%), followed the &#x0201c;valence stability&#x0201d; pattern, wherein latent valence was stable and reproduced across time, but the source of that valence varied (i.e., the latent semantics of warmth and competence shifted, possibly also with changes in the top traits). For example, stereotypes of <italic>Criminal</italic> were persistent in negative valence (<italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0025 [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0011, 0.0061]) but the traits also showed an increase in latent warmth (<italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0036 [0.0009, 0.0063], see <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref>. That is, although the new top-associated traits were (relatively) warmer (e.g., no longer <italic>harsh</italic> and <italic>cruel</italic> but now <italic>inept</italic> and <italic>immature</italic>), they continued to reproduce negative valence through other meanings, such as by increasing in negative competence, negative morality, and assertiveness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. In sum, for these latter groups we find that, when a new trait does emerge, it likely brings new meaning along latent axes of warmth/competence or some other dimension, but always reproducing the underlying negative valence.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Empirical patterns of stability through replacement</title><p id="Par25">Twenty-five groups (43%) changed meaningfully in stereotype negativity, prompting the next investigation on which empirical patterns of replacement they follow (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The first possibility is a &#x0201c;transfer&#x0201d; of stigma via shared semantics, in which a strengthening negativity towards one target group corresponds to diminishing negativity in secondary groups that are semantically related. Such a pattern was notably rare in the groups we examined. Indeed, using our current empirical operationalization (<italic>Methods, Appendix</italic>), only one group, <italic>Asexual</italic>, suggested transfer via shared semantics (i.e., warmth/competence) with other groups: <italic>Asexual</italic> showed a strong negative slope, <italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.012, while semantically-similar groups including <italic>Infertile</italic> (<italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0014) and <italic>Atheist</italic> (<italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0026) had slopes that were null but trended towards more positivity over time. In short, the initial tests appear to suggest transfer via shared semantics is a relatively rare mechanism in historical patterns of stigma negativity, although it could be observed more widely for other groups using different empirical criteria.</p><p id="Par26">In contrast, most of the changing groups (19/25, or 76%) suggested other processes of transferring negativity that were not predicted by simple semantic relationships. For instance, the increasing negativity towards the group target <italic>Aboriginal</italic> did not correspond to lessened negativity towards semantically-related groups of <italic>Indian</italic> or <italic>Middle-eastern</italic>, suggesting that many changing groups may be sharing/transferring negativity through processes not reducible to shared semantics.</p><p id="Par27">Finally, we found that a handful of the changing groups (5/25, or 20%) showed &#x0201c;generalization&#x0201d; of negativity, in which semantically-similar groups are changing in similar ways (e.g., similar strengthening in negativity). For instance, increasing negativity towards <italic>Smoker</italic> (<italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0060) was similar and shared across semantically-similar groups including <italic>Alcoholic</italic> (<italic>b</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0023). Such a finding could help explain why the overall, aggregate trend showed a slight movement towards more negative representations in general. We nevertheless emphasize that this empirical pattern of generalization is uncommon (only 5 groups out of the possible 58), thereby underscoring that mechanisms prompting widespread change in societal negativity are rare in the current set of stigmatized groups.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>General discussion</title><p id="Par28">Using 100&#x000a0;years of English-language book text and the largest sample of negatively stigmatized groups studied via NLP methods to date, the current research contributes new understanding to the persistence of aggregate negativity in social group stereotypes. Study 1 shows that, over the past 100&#x000a0;years, societies have maintained a relatively stable level of stereotype negativity, as revealed from the aggregate trend across 58 stigmatized groups. A key contribution of the current work is going beyond this aggregate persistence to also consider what societal mechanisms may uphold such negativity. Study 2 provided a first attempt at conceptualizing and empirically testing a novel theoretical framework for addressing this question. We propose two overarching classes of mechanisms&#x02014;reproducibility of negativity towards individual group targets, and replacement (or transfer) of negativity across group lines&#x02014;as a framework to understand how stereotype negativity persists on aggregate. The initial empirical tests of this framework suggest three key take-aways.</p><p id="Par29">First, the reproducibility mechanism is relatively more prevalent than replacement, with 57% of groups showing individual stable slopes, suggesting that negativity itself is reproduced towards individual group targets. Within these stable groups, approximately one-third showed &#x0201c;deep stability&#x0201d; (i.e., all metrics we investigated were stable), as in the case of several disability-related stigmas. The remaining two-thirds of stable groups showed patterns of reproducibility that suggested shifting sources of negativity. For instance, for groups such as <italic>Alcoholic</italic> or <italic>Black</italic>, the top-associated traits might have shifted over time, but the underlying latent valence was always the same general level of negativity. Such dynamic reproducibility suggests that society may be inventing new means (e.g., new words or new meanings) to repeatedly stigmatize the same groups across time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par30">At the same time, a handful of groups did show some meaningful change in stereotype negativity, underscoring that change for some groups is possible, if far from assured. Such change in negativity suggests the operation of a complementary <italic>replacement</italic> mechanism, in which negativity is transferred across group lines. Notably, however, we found little evidence that the transfer of stigma was falling along predictable lines of semantically-similar groups (e.g., there was no evidence of a transfer between <italic>Gay</italic> and <italic>Transgender</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>). Instead, the data suggest that transfer of stigma is more likely to occur through means other than simply semantic relations. These findings set the stage for future research to identify non-semantic replacement mechanisms, such as groups that appear in the same geographic locations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, that fulfill the same function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, or that switch their relative ranking in terms of numerical prevalence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par31">Finally, for a small handful of changing groups, we found that increasing negativity towards one target group appeared to cascade through semantically-related groups, an empirical pattern that could help explain the slight aggregate trend towards increasingly negative representations over time. That is, while the current work focuses on the mechanisms upholding stigma stability, we also show the utility of the current methods for uncovering means by which society may, in the future, show aggregate change in stigmatization. Although such generalization of stigma is obviously concerning in the case of increasing <italic>negativity</italic>, it could be possible that, for other groups not studied here (e.g., groups that are not as ubiquitously stigmatized), generalization mechanisms could operate to cascade <italic>positivity</italic> throughout the network (e.g., as in the &#x0201c;secondary transfer effects&#x0201d; of intergroup contact<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>).</p><p id="Par32">Of course, there are limitations to using text analysis for social science inquiries. For instance, when it comes to the words used to operationalize groups, factors such as semantic drift, polysemy, and frequency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> can confound inferences. In the <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref>, we show that the primary conclusions are not altered after controlling for the drift, polysemy, or frequency of group labels, or after using shorter lists of only four central group words. Additionally, when it comes to the underlying text, the current study focused on the (limited) Google Books English corpus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Although conclusions were robust in a complementary book text source, variation is likely to arise in different media sources or languages. For instance, stigma may be more persistent in some societies than others, such as those with stronger collective norms that require more conformity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. We look forward to testing such questions following continued innovations in natural language processing and the availability of archived text data across cultures, geographic locations, and diverse languages.</p><p id="Par33">Finally, the current work was limited in focusing on only one dimension of stigma&#x02014;negativity in stereotypes&#x02014;leaving open the question of how other aspects of stigma, such as the initial act of labeling or behavioral dimensions of discrimination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, might persist or change over time. Although labeling and behavior are more difficult to address using historical language, researchers may successfully merge the current data with other indicators of stigmatization such as the persistence of discrimination in audit experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> or human attitude data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> to better understand the persistence and change of interacting components of stigma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par34">The results reported here fall between the hopes of optimists that we might gradually increase in positivity towards all groups<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and the fears of pessimists that society will continue to grow in hostility and negativity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Instead, the current data seem to suggest a stasis, in which the aggregate negativity of today is not so different from that of the past. Most critical, by expanding beyond traditional social science methods to consider stereotype negativity towards a large, diverse set of stigmatized groups across an unprecedented timespan of 100&#x000a0;years of books, we can also newly observe <italic>how</italic> stigmatization persists in society. Our hope is that introducing the Stigma Stability Framework, alongside a methodological toolkit to test its predictions, will provide a clearer path to explore the mechanisms (specifically, reproducibility and replacement) upholding persistent negativity. Only by understanding the pernicious ways that stigma endures both within and across groups can we, as researchers and societal actors, be equipped to durably reduce the multifaceted processes of stigmatization.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Text data sources</title><p id="Par35">We used word embeddings trained using the <italic>word2vec</italic> algorithm (a neural network method to compute vector representations of word meaning<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>) on book text obtained from Google Books and the Corpus of Historical American English (COHA) text data <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Standard hyperparameters were used (e.g., 300-dimensions, a context window size of 4 words on either side of the target training word), and only words appearing at least 500 times were included in training. The entirety of the Google Books corpus (across 200&#x000a0;years available, from 1800 to 2000) consists of&#x02009;~&#x02009;850 billion tokens and 500 million books, while the COHA corpus is much smaller, consisting of&#x02009;~&#x02009;410 million tokens, but it is balanced in the composition of text genres across history (equivalent balance of fiction and non-fiction texts).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Selecting and representing stigmatized groups in text</title><p id="Par36">A study of whether stigma is stable or changing in society requires the best approximation of a large, diverse set of stigmatized groups. To that end, we selected an established list of 93 stigmatized identities, characteristics, and statuses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Because we use single word embeddings, a subset of these 93 groups were indistinguishable from one another with the current methods. Thus, we collapsed these into a single identity&#x02014;for example, both &#x0201c;symptomatic&#x0201d; (e.g., <italic>bipolar symptomatic</italic>) and &#x0201c;remitted&#x0201d; identities (e.g., <italic>bipolar remitted</italic>) were combined, as were various forms of cancer (e.g., <italic>breast cancer current, breast cancer remitted, colorectal cancer current</italic>, and so on). We recognize this as a limitation of the current methods, since these groups do indeed differ in how they are perceived in society as well as in their social, health, and economic consequences.</p><p id="Par37">To identify group stereotypes in text, we need to use multiple terms to represent a single group and thereby ensure that the representation of a group triangulates on the group-specific meaning rather than some other polysemous meaning of a single term (e.g., &#x0201c;Alien&#x0201d; alone could refer to aliens from outer space, rather than to the intended meaning of a non-citizen or immigrant). Thus, for each of the stigmatized groups, we generated lists of single word synonyms using both historical and contemporary thesauruses (e.g., <italic>Oxford Historical Thesaurus, Thesaurus.com</italic>). Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> in the <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref> lists the chosen synonyms for each group. Using only the uniquely distinguishable groups, and those groups that could be represented in a list of single word synonyms available across all decades of text, ultimately left us with a final list of 58 stigmatized groups (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Extracting stereotype content and valence</title><p id="Par38">To compute stereotype valence (positivity/negativity), we begin by extracting the stereotype content (top-ten traits associated with each group). Using a list of 414 traits, all available traits in the corpus of text<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, we computed the average cosine similarity between a given target trait (e.g., &#x0201c;untrustworthy&#x0201d;) and a group representation (e.g., <italic>Dealer</italic>), by averaging across the pairwise cosine similarities between the trait and all group synonyms (e.g., &#x0201c;untrustworthy&#x0201d;-<italic>dealer,</italic> &#x0201c;untrustworthy&#x0201d;-<italic>peddler,</italic> &#x0201c;untrustworthy&#x0201d;-<italic>narcotic,</italic> &#x0201c;untrustworthy&#x0201d;-<italic>supplier,</italic> and so on). Then, all traits were ranked according to how strongly associated they were with the group, and the top-ten traits were used as the stereotype content for that group in a given decade. Additional details are provided in the <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref>.</p><p id="Par39">After identifying the top-10 trait associates for each group in each decade, we replaced the traits with their corresponding valence rating that was contextualized to that specific decade. Specifically, rather than assume that a single rating of valence (e.g., from valence rating norms) was applicable across 100&#x000a0;years, we allowed the valence of traits to vary across time. To do so, we first created lists of 25 words that strongly (and stably) signaled positivity/negativity, drawn from the lists used for the Implicit Association Test and the Word Embeddings Association Test. Then, we took each of the traits and looked at its relative cosine similarity to these positive and negative words within each decade of text. We used these historically-contextualized valence scores of each trait within a decade of text and took the average across all the top-10 traits within a decade. For example, imagine the top ranked traits for <italic>Aboriginal</italic> include [hostile, rebellious, adventurous, superstitious]. The corresponding historically-contextualized valence ratings for each of these traits in 1900 are [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.13, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.18, 0.05, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.19] and in 2000 are [&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.14, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.11, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.02, &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.15]. Taking the average across these traits returns an average valence for <italic>Aboriginal</italic> of &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.11 in 1900 and &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.11 in 2000. We repeat this computation for all 11 decades (1900&#x02013;2000) resulting in an 11-decade long timeseries of average historically-contextualized valence scores for each stigmatized group.</p><p id="Par40">We followed a similar process to create the timeseries for the average historically-contextualized latent warmth and competence scores for each stigmatized group. We use a set of &#x0201c;anchor&#x0201d; words (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Appendix</xref>) from automated dictionaries that represent poles of warmth/coldness and competence/incompetence <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, and score each of the 414 traits in terms of its relative warmth/coldness or competence/incompetence within each decade of text. Then, for each decade, we replace the top-10 traits with its warmth (competence) score and calculate the average warmth (competence) score for the 11 decades.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Modeling aggregate and individual group persistence or change</title><p id="Par41">We fit a Bayesian mixed effects model (i.e., allowing each group to start at a different valence and change at a different rate) to the data frame of the 58 timeseries trajectories (for valence and, separately, for latent warmth and competence). Model specifications used a uniform prior, random intercepts and random slopes for each group, and all other default parameters and model specifications (e.g., 2000 iterations, 4 chains) using <italic>brms</italic> (package version 2.17.0) in R<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. For inference, we focus on the region of practical equivalence or ROPE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, which is a pre-specified range of values that would reasonably be seen as indicating a &#x0201c;null effect.&#x0201d; Following convention, we set the ROPE to&#x02009;+&#x02009;/&#x02212; 0.1*SD<sub>y</sub> (with more conservative thresholds of 0.05*SD<sub>y</sub> tested for robustness) and compute the percentage of the model&#x02019;s posterior inside the ROPE to quantify evidence in favor of the null for the fixed effect of time (the overall population effect).</p><p id="Par42">Additionally, we use the random effects of the individual group slope estimates to identify those groups that have meaningfully changed (and thus suggest replacement) or remained stable (suggesting reproducibility). For random effects, we use the 95% Highest Density Intervals (HDIs) and determine those changing groups as any group with an HDI not including zero in the estimated random effect; stable groups are any group with an HDI that includes zero.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec19"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2024_61044_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-024-61044-z.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was supported by the Hao Family Inequality in America Support Grant, the Foundations of Human Behavior Initiative, and the Harvard Mind Brain Behavior Interfaculty Initiative awarded to Tessa Charlesworth.</p><sec id="FPar2"><title>Disclaimer</title><p id="Par43">This manuscript contains references to offensive slurs used to refer to groups in the past and present.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>T.E.S.C. and M.L.H. conceptualized the research, T.E.S.C. performed all analyses, T.E.S.C. and M.L.H wrote and edited the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data and R code are made publicly available at the project&#x02019;s OSF page: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/8p7s5/">https://osf.io/8p7s5/</ext-link>.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par44">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conceptualizing stigma</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Sociol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.soc.27.1.363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The social psychology of stigma</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Psychol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.psych.56.091103.070137</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15709941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15709941</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggleton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV and AIDS-related stigma and discrimination: A conceptual framework and implications for action</article-title><source>Soc. Sci. Med.</source><year>2003</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0277-9536(02)00304-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12753813?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753813</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullainathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are Emily and grEg more employable than Lakisha and Jamal?: A field experiment on labor market discrimination</article-title><source>Am. Econ. Rev.</source><year>2004</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>1013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1257/0002828042002561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AIDS: From social history to social policy</article-title><source>Law Med. Health Care</source><year>1986</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-720X.1986.tb00990.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3302549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3302549</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pescosolido</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The stigma complex</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Sociol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-soc-071312-145702</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26855471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26855471</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stigma and its public health implications</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2006</year><volume>367</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(06)68184-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16473129?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473129</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of multi-level stigma interventions: State of the science and future directions</article-title><source>BMC Med.</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-018-1244-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30651111</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schaller, M. &#x00026; Neuberg, S. L. Danger, Disease, and the Nature of Prejudice(s). in <italic>Advances in Experimental Social Psychology</italic> vol. 46 1&#x02013;54 (Academic Press, 2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of stereotyping in system justification and the production of false consciousness</article-title><source>Br. J. Soc. Psychol.</source><year>1994</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8309.1994.tb01008.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dovidio</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stigma and prejudice: One animal or two?</article-title><source>Soc. Sci. Med.</source><year>2008</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2008.03.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18524444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18524444</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paluck</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Porat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prejudice reduction: Progress and challenges</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Psychol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-psych-071620-030619</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32928061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32928061</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>TES</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dehghani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Word embeddings reveal social group attitudes and stereotypes in large language corpora</article-title><source>Handbook of Language Analysis in Psychology</source><year>2022</year><publisher-name>Guilford Publications</publisher-name><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>608</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hamilton, W. L., Leskovec, J. &#x00026; Jurafsky, D. Diachronic Word Embeddings Reveal Statistical Laws of Semantic Change. <italic>Proceedings of the 54th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)</italic> 1489&#x02013;1501 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caliskan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Semantics derived automatically from language corpora necessarily contain human biases</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>1979</volume><issue>356</issue><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>TES</given-names></name><name><surname>Caliskan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Historical representations of social groups across 200 years of word embeddings from google books</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>e2121798119</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2121798119</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35787033?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35787033</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in gender stereotypes over time: A computational analysis</article-title><source>Psychol. Women Q.</source><year>2021</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0361684320977178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiebinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurafsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Word embeddings quantify 100 years of gender and ethnic stereotypes</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>E3635</fpage><lpage>E3644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1720347115</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29615513?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29615513</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>TES</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanjeev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatzenbuehler</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying and predicting stereotype change in large language corpora: 72 groups, 115 years (1900&#x02013;2015), and four text sources</article-title><source>J. Pers. Soc. Psychol.</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/PSPA0000354</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 37616081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37616081</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marsden, P. V, Smith, T. W. &#x00026; Hout, M. Tracking US social change over a half-century: The general social survey at fifty. in <italic>Annual Review of Sociology</italic> vol. 46 109&#x02013;134 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pescosolido</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Halpern-Manners</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in Public Stigma of Mental Illness in the US, 1996&#x02013;2018</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e2140202</fpage><lpage>e2140202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.40202</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34932103?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34932103</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>TES</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of implicit and explicit attitudes: IV: Change and stability From 2007 to 2020</article-title><source>Psychol. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1347</fpage><lpage>1371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/09567976221084257</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35895290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35895290</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Richeson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>More diverse yet less tolerant? How the increasingly diverse racial landscape affects white Americans&#x02019; racial attitudes</article-title><source>Pers. Soc. Psychol. Bull.</source><year>2014</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0146167214524993</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24625658?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24625658</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Branigin, A. &#x00026; Kirkpatrick, N. Anti-transgender laws are on the rise. Here&#x02019;s where and what kind. <italic>The Washington Post</italic> (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cikara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouka</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabellini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hate crime towards minoritized groups increases as they increase in sized-based rank</article-title><source>Nat. Hum. Behav.</source><year>2022</year><volume>2022</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41562-022-01416-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatzenbuehler</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stigma as a fundamental cause of population health inequalities</article-title><source>Am. J. Public Health</source><year>2013</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2012.301069</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23488505?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23488505</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peabody</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selecting representative trait adjectives</article-title><source>J. Pers. Soc. Psychol.</source><year>1987</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-3514.52.1.59</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive stereotype content dictionaries using a semi-automated method</article-title><source>Eur. J. Soc. Psychol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejsp.2724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuddy</surname><given-names>AJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model of (often mixed) stereotype content: Competence and warmth respectively follow from perceived status and competition</article-title><source>J. Pers. Soc. Psychol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>878</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-3514.82.6.878</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12051578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12051578</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruschke</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rejecting or accepting parameter values in bayesian estimation</article-title><source>Adv. Methods Pract. Psychol. Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2515245918771304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pechenick</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Danforth</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the Google Books corpus: Strong limits to inferences of socio-cultural and linguistic evolution</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0137041</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26445406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26445406</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davies, M. Corpus of Historical American English. (2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dovidio</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaertner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aversive racism</article-title><source>Adv. Exp. Soc. Psychol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2601(04)36001-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kluegel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tuch</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laissez-faire racism: The crystallization of a kinder, gentler, antiblack ideology</article-title><source>Racial Attitudes in the 1990s: Continuity and Change</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fouka</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazumder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabellini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From immigrants to Americans: Race and assimilation during the great migration</article-title><source>Rev. Econ. Stud.</source><year>2022</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/restud/rdab038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidanius</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><source>Social Dominance: An Intergroup Theory of Social Hierarchy and Oppression</source><year>1999</year><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A spontaneous stereotype content model: Taxonomy, properties, and prediction</article-title><source>J. Pers. Soc. Psychol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/pspa0000312</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35511560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35511560</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dovidio</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaertner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reducing prejudice: Combating intergroup biases</article-title><source>Curr. Dir. Psychol. Sci.</source><year>1999</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-8721.00024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Charlesworth, T. E. S. &#x00026; Banaji, M. R. Research: How Americans&#x02019; biases are changing (or not) over time. <italic>Harv. Bus. Rev.</italic> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vezzali</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Bernardo</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cocco</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stathi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Capozza</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reducing prejudice in the society at large: A review of the secondary transfer effect and directions for future research</article-title><source>Soc. Pers. Psychol. Compass</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>e12583</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/spc3.12583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muthukrishna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are collectivistic cultures more prone to rapid transformation? Computational models of cross-cultural differences, social network structure, dynamic social influence, and cultural change</article-title><source>Pers. Soc. Psychol. Rev.</source><year>2020</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1088868319855783</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31253070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31253070</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quillian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in racial and ethnic discrimination in hiring in six Western countries</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>e2212875120</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2212875120</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 36719918?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36719918</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quillian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pager</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hexel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Midtb&#x000f8;en</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meta-analysis of field experiments shows no change in racial discrimination in hiring over time</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>10870</fpage><lpage>10875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1706255114</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28900012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28900012</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>TES</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of implicit and explicit attitudes: I: Long-term change and stability from 2007 to 2016</article-title><source>Psychol. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0956797618813087</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30605364?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30605364</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mikolov, T., Chen, K., Corrado, G. &#x00026; Dean, J. Efficient Estimation of Word Representations in Vector Space. in <italic>International Conference on Learning Representations</italic> (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pachankis</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The burden of stigma on health and well-being: A taxonomy of concealment, course, disruptiveness, aesthetics, origin, and peril across 93 stigmas</article-title><source>Pers. Soc. Psychol. Bull.</source><year>2018</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0146167217741313</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29290150?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29290150</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;rkner</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>brms: An R package for bayesian multilevel models using Stan</article-title><source>J. Stat. Softw.</source><year>2017</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v080.i01</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>