<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par3">Addressing such concerns is critical for the pursuit of multi-scalar and multi-temporal representation and justice within the contentious narratives defining nature-society relationships. Scholarship on the history, politics, and philosophy of science has challenged the value-neutral conceptualizations of climate science, arguing that the IPCC is an organization involved in <italic>boundary work</italic> and is a <italic>boundary organization</italic> (Hoppe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2013</xref>; Livingston and Rummukainen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2020</xref>; De Pryck and Wanneau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2017</xref>). Boundary work can be understood as the efforts of the various subjects and institutions of the science and policy spheres to characterize the lines separating them while also trying to form a collaborative work culture to address the complicated issues that span across such lines. In its most fundamental definition, it relates to the actions and processes that create, maintain, and destroy boundaries for the production and management of knowledge (Bremer and Meisch <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2017</xref>). In climate science, boundary work has often been performed to satisfy the empirical aspirations of biophysical scientists and the political aspirations of various nation-states. Therefore it encompasses the wielding of power to define who or what is legitimate (knowledge, stakeholder) and belongs within a certain group (e.g., climate change experts, historical national emission responsibilities). Ultimately, the boundary separating science and politics is frequently negotiated and renegotiated. The IPCC as a boundary organization sits at the edges of diverse socio-material positions and exhibits very specific versions of accountability towards each. And it employs boundary objects&#8212;items or artifacts of knowledge that can be adjusted and utilized across different socio-political contexts for different goals (e.g., temperature targets like 2 &#176;C or 1.5 &#176;C). Over the years, the IPCC&#8217;s role as a boundary organization and its attempts at managing the plural aspirations of its stakeholders has led to its conceptual positions around scientific objectivity, socio-political positions around formalization and standardization of procedure, and a spatial position skewed towards the global north reflecting existing geopolitical power discrepancies. Such an institutional culture creates a significant set of issues concerning just and democratic knowledge production across the world (Beck and Mahony <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>; Carey et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2014</xref>; Minx et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2017</xref>; Pearce et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2018</xref>).</p>