<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par4">In the Himalayas, questions of representation and justice have marred science and policy regarding climate change (Ensor et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2019</xref>; Nightingale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2016</xref>; Ojha et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">b</xref>; Satyal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>; Sherpa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2014</xref>). Such critiques are rooted in a rich vein of critical and radical social science and humanities scholarship on nature-society relations that seek to interrogate environmental determinist narratives of risk, techno-managerial decision-making pathways, hegemonic state development policies, geopolitical contentions at multiple borderlands, and the active marginalization of the plurality of worldviews that constitute the region (Campbell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2017</xref>; Davis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2020</xref>; Drew, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">b</xref>; Gergan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2017</xref>; Huber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2019</xref>; Joshi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2014</xref>; Lord et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2020</xref>; Ojha <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2020</xref>; Poudel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2018</xref>; Sapkota et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2016</xref>). This scholarship reveals the insidious nature of the theory of environmental degradation (THED), which still informs critical policy positions and has morphed into a regional narrative of the Anthropocene. It also highlights the complicated manifestations of state power and energy politics through haphazard industrialization which include the construction of a widespread network of dams in the region, and how such infrastructure engages with assessments of risk and vulnerability. Finally, it highlights how transnational climate change management initiatives like the REDD+ program have marginalized historic needs of justice within natural resource governance, through a simplistic focus on carbon and its reduction. This optimization of dynamic human-nature relationships for the removal, capture, and trade of carbon has threatened more participatory and locally rooted management aspirations and cosmologies while ushering in a wide variety of powerful international entities. Most regional climate science and policy emerge from this intersection of risk theory, modern state-building, and algorithm-driven market-orchestrated transnational environmental governance.</p>