<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par5">In response, in recent years, national governments have attempted to create more inclusive attempts to address the diverse manifestations of climate change within their governance spaces, and intergovernmental initiatives such as the International Centre for Integrated Mountain Development (ICIMOD) have mobilized to explore the place-based, multi-dimensional narratives of social-ecological change (Awasthi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2016</xref>; Mishra et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2017</xref>). However such attempts are rare, and most climate change knowledge production in the region exhibits biases very similar to those witnessed in the IPCC. Additionally, attempts to address the data poverty and lack of reliable projections advocate for the wide operationalization of the scientific model with very little focus on the powerful historical and political processes that produce regional (transnational) nature-society relationships (Gerlitz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2015</xref>; Singh and Thadani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2015</xref>). At present, the plurality of Himalayan voices is marginalized both by the political aspirations of the nation-state which fails to represent the aspirations and experiences of its diverse citizens, especially when they threaten its developmental and geopolitical goals, and by the hegemonic narrative of the Anthropocene that erases historical inequities and injustices and replaces them with an overarching &#8220;risk society&#8221; which afflicts all individuals and communities and can only be resolved through expert-driven initiatives (Chakraborty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2021</xref>; Mathur <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2015</xref>; Nightingale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2017</xref>; Ojha et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2016</xref>).</p>