<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par7">The lake covers a total mean surface area of 28,760 km<sup>2</sup>, total basin area of 150,000 km<sup>2</sup>, volume of 7725 km<sup>3</sup>, 560 km long, maximum width of 75 km, maximum depth of 695 m, and mean depth of about 474 m and is Africa&#8217;s third largest lake (Drayton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1984</xref>; Neuland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1984</xref>; Jury <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2014</xref>; Sene et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2017</xref>). About a quarter of the total global freshwater is held by Lake Malawi together with Lakes Tanganyika and Victoria (Bootsma and Hecky <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1993</xref>). The Lake Malawi basin experiences a tropical climate with a strongly seasonal rainfall pattern. Over 80% of the total annual rainfall occurs during the Austral summer months from November to April when the Intertropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ) and the Congo Air Boundary (CAB) are active in the region. The mean annual rainfall ranges from less than 800 mm/year on the southern lake shore to more than 2400 mm/year in the northern highlands. On the eastern shore of the lake, the Ruhuhu River basin in Tanzania with a catchment area of 14,070 km<sup>2</sup> is the sole major inflow and contributes about 20% of the total annual lake inflow, whereas the other major inflows each account for less the 10% of the inflows (Lyons et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2011</xref> and references within). The second largest inflow is South Rukuru in Malawi with a total catchment area of 12,110 km<sup>2</sup>. The Bua and Linthipe rivers, all in Malawi, are also significant tributaries with respective catchment areas of 10,700 km<sup>2</sup> and 8560 km<sup>2</sup>. The mean annual temperature during 1992 to 2007 is 22.4 &#176;C over the land part of the basin and 24.8 &#176;C over the water (Lyons et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2011</xref>). Over many parts of Malawi, Ngongondo et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2015</xref>) reported of rainfall declines that were not statistically significant, coupled with significant increases in mean temperature during 1960 to 2007 and 1971 to 2001, respectively. The lake provides a mean annual discharge of about 480 m<sup>3</sup>s<sup>&#8722;1</sup> flows to the Shire River at Mangochi, the only outlet from the lake (Jury <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2014</xref>). Over 90% of Malawi&#8217;s hydropower installation is located at a series of rapids in the middle Shire River basin, downstream of the outlet. The Kamuzu Barrage at Liwonde, about 72 km from the outlet, regulates flows to the hydropower stations. There are also plans for a major water abstraction project from the lake for supply to Lilongwe City.</p>