<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Third, the pilot study takes place amidst the COVID-19 pandemic, potentially affecting response rates due to, inter alia, non-attendance of students following mandatory quarantine measures or COVID-19 infections, thus limiting the generalisability of our findings. However, we anticipate that more students will attend schools during non-pandemic times, therefore rendering response rate estimations from the pilot study conservative. Forth, we acknowledge that no formal programme theory has been developed a priori to guide expectations how the PCS may be related to outcomes or interact with contextual factors. For programmes primarily developed by practitioners, however, recent guidance on the evaluation of complex interventions suggests that programme theory in these cases is often developed in parallel with the evaluation cycle [<xref rid="B28-ijerph-19-08039" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. We therefore plan to explore the applicability of the SIMPEA as programme theory for the PCS in a formative qualitative study comprising semi-structured interviews with students, teachers, school principals and members of the implementation team followed by transdisciplinary workshops. If suggested by interview and workshop results, we will develop the programme theory further by, inter alia, proposing outcomes not currently considered in the SIMPEA [<xref rid="B36-ijerph-19-08039" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], mechanisms linking the PCS to outcomes and contextual factors at the level of students, teachers and schools that hinder or promote PCS implementation and potentially moderate intervention effectiveness. However, given the strong alignment of the SIMPEA with the objectives of the PCS, we anticipate that relatively minor adaptations to the original model will be necessary. Last, we acknowledge that different approaches may have been used at several points in designing this study. Given that the current understanding of issues explored in this study is limited and that our goal was to lay the groundwork for future work, we focused on foundational, yet methodologically important operationalisations of study processes, such as the proportion of students completing both baseline and follow-up surveys, providing a measure of participant retention, and the proportion of missing data and basic psychometric properties of scales, highlighting potential problems with data quality as well as floor and ceiling effects, respectively. We consider this pilot study as a learning opportunity for gauging the feasibility and potential implications of several methodological decisions made at this stage, potentially guiding the design and implementation of related research projects in Germany and internationally.</p>