<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para300">Reducing zoonotic disease emergence risks posed by the trade and consumption of wildlife is obviously a crucial element of any approach that seeks to limit opportunities for cross-species pathogen transmission and zoonoses outbreaks. SARS-CoV-2 has understandably highlighted the trade and consumption of wild animals and their products as a risk factor for future spillover events with pandemic potential.<xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr"><sup>107</sup></xref> Although scientists, international leaders, and others have called for blanket bans on wildlife trade, these could sometimes have unintended consequences of non-subsistence wildlife trade bans and mass shutdowns of wildlife markets, and debate around whether such actions would be effective.<sup>63,108&#8211;110</sup> Even though the banning of wildlife trade activities could address problems, including population declines in trafficked species, ecosystem disruption, and risks for zoonotic pathogen spillover events, the complexities of the trade must be considered. These complexities include the trade's existence in both legal and illegal forms, the multiple scales at which it occurs (from local to global), its sustainable and unsustainable elements, the multiple ways in which its actors depend on it (including for economic and food security),<xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>, <xref rid="bib111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref> and the disproportionate effects bans could have on low-income populations in regions such as Africa and Asia compared with high-income countries.<xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>, <xref rid="bib111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref> Historically, shutting down legal wildlife trade in response to zoonotic disease outbreaks has often driven increases in illegal trade,<xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr"><sup>109</sup></xref> as prices for illegal goods rise.<xref rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr"><sup>112</sup></xref> Such unintended outcomes have resulted in trade with less regulation and surveillance, not necessarily less trade activity, and a loss of community trust in both conservation and the outbreak response.<xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr"><sup>109</sup></xref>
</p>