<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para310">One Health approaches to addressing wildlife trade could deliver more robust threat-alleviation results, with increased cost-effectiveness and better socioeconomic outcomes and health outcomes for people.<xref rid="bib113" ref-type="bibr"><sup>113</sup></xref> Approaches should include multiscale collaboration targeting both supply and demand, careful regulation, and a high level of surveillance, particularly around activity that is illegal or carries higher risks for zoonotic spillover and conservation.<xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>, <xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref> Strategies by governments and international bodies to address the risks of wildlife trade, such as the Vietnamese Government's July 2020 directive mandating increased enforcement of wildlife protection legislation,<xref rid="bib115" ref-type="bibr"><sup>115</sup></xref> should without doubt be encouraged. However, it is crucial that such strategies be developed and implemented in a collaborative, diversified context, with the involvement of local communities and stakeholders in decision making.<xref rid="bib111" ref-type="bibr"><sup>111</sup></xref> Ensuring this can minimise the trade-offs and negative consequences often associated with strategies, such as loss of subsistence livelihood for people involved in the trade, which could feed into increased illegal trade and undermine intended aims. Wildlife Enforcement Networks approach enforcement of the wildlife trade on the basis of single-nation or single-agency approaches often being inadequate, due to the complex multiactor and cross-boundary nature of the trade. Networks such as the Association of Southeast Asian Nations&#8217; Wildlife Enforcement Network aim to enable stronger cooperation on wildlife law enforcement between countries, contributing to overcoming the geographical and economic barriers to approaches of single nations or entities.<xref rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr"><sup>116</sup></xref>
</p>