<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0170">Systems analysis is used by the scientific community to inform strategic decision making, as it helps to anticipate the complex interactions between human and natural systems and thus the challenges for sustainable development across different scales (<xref rid="bb0420" ref-type="bibr">OECD and IIASA, 2020</xref>). Shared Socioeconomic Pathways (SSPs) represent quantified scenarios of socioeconomic trends, which can be used to project secondary indicators in domains related to food and land use (<xref rid="bb0440" ref-type="bibr">Popp et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0450" ref-type="bibr">Riahi et al., 2017</xref>). Alternative projection scenarios, from the most optimistic (SSP1 &#8220;Sustainability&#8221;) to the most pessimistic (SSP3 &#8220;Regional Rivalry&#8221;), allow for the exploration of consistent representations of the future of the agricultural and food systems (<xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Fricko et al., 2017</xref>). For example, under SSP2, a &#8220;middle-of-the-road&#8221; scenario, the global population grows from 7.8 billion people today to over 9.2 billion people by 2050, while GDP per capita increases by 140%. Under SSP2, cropland would expand globally by 137 million hectares (Mha) between 2020 and 2050 and pasture by an additional 112 Mha, while agricultural GHG emissions would increase by 19% (<xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Fricko et al., 2017</xref>). Mitigating climate change will require radical changes to our economies that also imply deep transformations for food systems. According to estimates, an achievable global emission-reduction target for agriculture alone would be 1 Gt CO<sub>2</sub>-equivalent (<xref rid="bb0685" ref-type="bibr">Wollenberg et al., 2016</xref>). However, such mitigation policies need to be suitably designed to minimize potential adverse impacts on other development outcomes and to ensure a positive overall outcome (<xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Havl&#237;k et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Frank et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Hasegawa et al., 2018</xref>). For example, nature-based solutions for climate change mitigation would involve large transformations of land-use, including afforestation programs, deployment of bioenergy, and soil organic carbon sequestration, all of which have consequences for agriculture, food systems and biodiversity (<xref rid="bb0470" ref-type="bibr">Roe et al., 2019</xref>).</p>