<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">New Media Soc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">New Media Soc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NMS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>New Media &#x00026; Society</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1461-4448</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1461-7315</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9669507</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/14614448221135632</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_14614448221135632</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Predicting COVID: Understanding audience responses to predictive
journalism via online comments</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9211-4598</contrib-id><name><surname>Allaham</surname><given-names>Mowafak</given-names></name><xref rid="corresp1-14614448221135632" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5005-6123</contrib-id><name><surname>Diakopoulos</surname><given-names>Nicholas</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff1-14614448221135632">Northwestern University, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-14614448221135632">Mowafak Allaham, Computational Journalism
Lab, Northwestern University, Frances Searle Building, Room 1-269, 2240 Campus
Drive, Evanston, IL 60208, USA. Email:
<email>mowafakallaham2021@u.northwestern.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><elocation-id>14614448221135632</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/"/><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for
unrestricted re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with
acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for
the duration of the COVID-19 pandemic or until permissions are revoked in
writing. Upon expiration of these permissions, PMC is granted a perpetual
license to make this article available via PMC and Europe PMC, consistent
with existing copyright protections.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The COVID-19 pandemic triggered a global health crisis that stimulated
journalists to frame their stories around predictive models and forecasts aiming
to predict the future trend of the pandemic. This article examines the audience
response to predictive journalism by qualitatively analyzing readers&#x02019; comments
to articles covering COVID that were published in a small sample of mainstream
media. Based on a thematic analysis of readers&#x02019; comments, this research
contributes a typology of audience response types to the models incorporated in
such predictive journalism. We elaborate on each of three primary
themes&#x02014;reflecting affective, action-oriented, and evaluative responses&#x02014;and
discuss the implications of our findings and the importance of expanding
research to answer questions related to the role of predictive journalism in
shaping affective response, encouraging action-oriented responses and collective
planning around responsibility for taking future actions, and considering the
ways in which supportive and critical comments triggered by the models may be
harnessed to improve communication.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>data journalism</kwd><kwd>online comments</kwd><kwd>predictive journalism</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>edited-state</meta-name><meta-value>corrected-proof</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-14614448221135632"><title>Introduction</title><p>Predictive journalism is an emerging genre within data journalism that incorporates
predictive information such as estimations, forecasts, or nowcasts into news
production processes (e.g. reporting, publication, distribution) by using or relying
on data-driven computational techniques such as predictive analytics or computer
simulations (<xref rid="bibr10-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Diakopoulos,
2022</xref>). One potential application of predictive journalism is to assist
the public in reasoning under uncertainty about possible future events and outcomes.
For example, in 2008, FiveThirtyEight began to popularize this genre of journalism
in election predictions to answer the question of who is leading the elections and
who is likely to win. The accessibility of big data paired with advancements in
computational power has also enabled journalists to cover stories beyond election
forecasts and political polling (<xref rid="bibr42-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Toff, 2019</xref>) such as weather forecasts as
well as entertainment (<xref rid="bibr13-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Franck
and Wilson, 2020</xref>) and sports predictions (<xref rid="bibr29-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Pentzold and Fechner, 2020</xref>) and more
recently projecting the number of COVID-19 cases in the future.</p><p>Throughout the COVID-19 pandemic, journalists utilized epidemiological and
forecasting models to offer reports and infographics informing the public about the
scale and pace of the health crises amid a wave of muddled information (<xref rid="bibr31-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Pentzold et al., 2021</xref>).
Yet despite the prominFranckence of this type of journalism throughout the course of
the pandemic, little is known about how such predictions, themselves full of
uncertainty, are received by audiences and might influence public attitudes and
emotions toward the pandemic. Accordingly, our research primarily focuses on
answering the following question: <italic toggle="yes">How did the public respond to COVID-19
models conveyed in predictive journalism articles published in US-based news
media?</italic></p><p>This research aims to understand the impact of predictive journalism on audiences by
qualitatively analyzing the comments section of a sample of such news articles from
three US-based news outlets: The New York Times, The Washington Post, and
FiveThirtyEight. The digital medium of predictive journalism combined with the
deliberate and thoughtful engagement from readers via online comments offers a
unique opportunity to understand how people respond to predictive models and
forecasts in news media (<xref rid="bibr19-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Hullman et al., 2015</xref>). Because comments are generally unsolicited and
reflect readers&#x02019; raw reactions to news content, they provide a rich and ecologically
valid window into how <italic toggle="yes">some</italic> people in the audience are responding to
the predictions. In this work, we analyze 885 comments made in response to six
articles, applying an iterative qualitative thematic analysis approach to uncover
patterns and themes in user reactions.</p><p>Our findings contribute a typology of responses to predictive journalism that
articulates three main themes (<italic toggle="yes">affective, action-oriented</italic>, and
<italic toggle="yes">evaluative</italic> responses) as well as several subthemes which
emerged from the thematic analysis of readers&#x02019; comments in our sample. We found that
the focal point of readers&#x02019; comments was largely on the predictive models described
in the sampled articles; thus, these themes reflect readers&#x02019; responses that are
specific to the models. <italic toggle="yes">Affective response</italic> reflects the emotions
expressed as a result of analyzing and interpreting the models.
<italic toggle="yes">Action-oriented response</italic> includes all comments requesting or
demanding an action to be taken based on the numbers conveyed by the models.
<italic toggle="yes">Evaluative response</italic> comprises a variety of supporting and
critical comments that are relevant to the models.</p><p>Building on these findings, our discussion offers further insights into the
emotionality in public response to predictive models in journalism, how these models
can encourage action-oriented responses and collective planning around
responsibility for taking future actions, and the type of supportive and critical
comments that these models trigger among commenters. Predictive journalism has an
apparent capacity for impacting public emotions, attitudes, and behavior, which are
consequential to the ways in which the public makes sense of news information.
Developing this typology of responses is an important initial contribution toward
understanding the range of responses to predictive journalism that can inform future
research in operationalizing such responses as well as suggest ways for journalistic
practice to better communicate predictions and forecasts about the future. This work
thus outlines a first step in a larger research program examining the role of
predictive journalism in the news media, and how this genre of journalism may shape
public attitudes and opinions about future events and public policy for a variety of
social processes that are predicted in the news.</p></sec><sec id="section2-14614448221135632"><title>Background: predictive journalism in the COVID-19 pandemic</title><p>The COVID-19 pandemic triggered broad intolerance of uncertainty around policy
responses and when life would return to &#x0201c;normal&#x0201d; as well as other emotions such as
fear, stress, depression, and anxiety (<xref rid="bibr8-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Coelho et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bibr27-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Pakpour and Griffiths, 2020</xref>). Media
exposure, health anxiety, and risk for loved ones were predictors of fear of the
coronavirus (<xref rid="bibr6-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al.,
2022</xref>; <xref rid="bibr25-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Mertens et
al., 2020</xref>). Traumatic stress symptoms and fear of economic factors were
also associated with the coronavirus (<xref rid="bibr20-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Jacmin-Park et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>COVID-19 thus created a public need for orientation and information seeking due to
the high uncertainty about the future and its relative impact on peoples&#x02019; lives.
Research by <xref rid="bibr23-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">McCombs and Weaver
(1973)</xref> on the need for orientation suggests that people&#x02019;s motivation to
learn about their social environment increases with uncertainty and relevance.
Accordingly, it is plausible for the public to seek information from the news during
crises.</p><p>During the COVID-19 crisis, journalism acted as a facilitator and a communication
channel between public officials and experts and the broader public (<xref rid="bibr32-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Perreault and Perreault,
2021</xref>). In the United States, for example, early news coverage of the
COVID-19 pandemic communicated to the public constant updates about prevention
policies (<xref rid="bibr2-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Basch et al.,
2020</xref>). Nevertheless, a large degree of uncertainty and speculation
remains in news making (<xref rid="bibr26-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Neiger,
2007</xref>; <xref rid="bibr38-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Spiegelhalter,
2017</xref>), especially when predicting the future. As more data, technologies,
and computational power become accessible to journalists, <xref rid="bibr24-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">MayCotte (2015)</xref> foresaw the potential of
predictive journalism in news making: &#x0201c;journalists will be able to orchestrate
predictions and write tomorrow&#x02019;s headlines and stories&#x0201d;. News organizations ventured
into predictive journalism after recognizing the ability of predictive analytics to
generate &#x0201c;pre-emptive knowledge&#x0201d; about the future and shape the formulation of
knowledge claims in newsmaking (<xref rid="bibr30-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Pentzold and Fechner, 2021</xref>).</p><p>In response to the coronavirus outbreak, many news outlets developed their own
data-driven predictive models and simulations to report on the possible impact of
preventive policies and health measures on case counts and mortality rates (<xref rid="bibr10-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Diakopoulos, 2022</xref>).
Readers were given the opportunity to engage with these models through exploring
different possible future outcomes and scenarios by modifying some of the underlying
assumptions and configurations of these models. Journalists have also incorporated
third-party predictive models into their news reporting (e.g. the IHME model) when
thinking about the future and imaging tradeoffs between short-term decisions and
long term effects (<xref rid="bibr9-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Colglazier
and Diakopoulos, 2022</xref>). For instance, The New York Times published an
article entitled &#x0201c;What 5 Coronavirus Models Say the Next Month Will Look Like&#x0201d;
(<xref rid="bibr5-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Bui et al., 2020</xref>)
comparing five different predictive models forecasting case counts,
hospitalizations, and deaths and how these models are guiding current public
policies. It is evident from the title of this article that the focus of predictive
journalism is on informing the public about possible and predicted future outcomes
and how such outcomes could possibly have an impact on society.</p><p>The majority of prior academic research on predictive journalism has been focused on
either interpreting model outcomes, describing journalistic practices in this genre
of data journalism, or the way models were presented to the public (<xref rid="bibr31-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Pentzold et al., 2021</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr44-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Westwood et al.,
2020</xref>). Westwood et al. focused on the consequences of misinterpreting
projections in predictive journalism articles on demobilizing the public in election
forecasts (2020). In the context of COVID, Pentzold et al. looked at how predictive
models in the news were presented and discussed in news products and whether such
models did a good job casting away uncertainty and ambiguity around COVID-19 (2021).
Moving beyond these prior studies, the present research focuses on describing
<italic toggle="yes">the public response to predictive models</italic> covering the COVID-19
pandemic by elaborating themes that reflect the types of responses found in online
news comments</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section3-14614448221135632"><title>Methods</title><p>In this section, we describe the data collection and analytic approach to the
qualitative analysis of the comments section of news articles published in three
news outlets: The New York Times, The Washington Post, and FiveThirtyEight.</p><sec id="section4-14614448221135632"><title>Data</title><p>Our data here consist of news comments made in response to predictive journalism
articles about COVID-19. We chose to focus on news comments as they contribute
to the deliberative public discourse and offer a rich stream of data for
understanding public reactions (<xref rid="bibr12-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Eisele et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bibr22-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Lee and McElroy,
2019</xref>). At the same time, comments do not reflect all news readers (<xref rid="bibr14-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Friemel and D&#x000f6;tsch,
2015</xref>), and therefore, our analysis of comments should not be
interpreted as some reflection of public opinion or the general population but
rather reflects only the population of commenters studied. Although there are
sometimes issues with the quality of news comments (<xref rid="bibr34-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Santana, 2014</xref>) including issues of
incivility, hate speech, and rude language (<xref rid="bibr7-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Coe et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bibr18-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Hughey and Daniels, 2013</xref>), prior
research has shown that people tend to conform to standards of thoughtfulness
set by others in online commenting communities (<xref rid="bibr16-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Han and Brazeal, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr40-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Sukumaran et al.,
2011</xref>). In addition, in comparison to comments on social media, research
has found that comments on news websites have more deliberative quality than
those on social media outlets (<xref rid="bibr33-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Rowe, 2015</xref>). As our results here show,
we did not encounter substantive quality issues with the data we collected.</p><p>To construct our dataset, we draw on a corpus of previously collected news
articles that incorporate predictive information (<xref rid="bibr10-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Diakopoulos, 2022</xref>) and identify a
subset related to COVID-19, which could be in the present or the future (e.g.
projecting the number of COVID-19 cases next month). We specifically sought
articles related to COVID-19 that showed evidence of some computational
technique (i.e. a model that can predict a value, score, or category) or
computer simulation. A total of 27 articles were identified, coming from various
sources including: The New York Times (11), The Economist (6), Washington Post
(3), NPR (2), Time (2), Bloomberg (1), FiveThirtyEight (1), and Reuters (1).
Articles that did not have a comment section or did not allow readers to comment
on the article were excluded from further analysis. Accordingly, only six
articles remained, three articles from The New York Times,<sup><xref rid="fn1-14614448221135632" ref-type="fn">1</xref></sup> two articles
from the Washington Post,<sup><xref rid="fn2-14614448221135632" ref-type="fn">2</xref></sup> and one article from FiveThirtyEight<sup><xref rid="fn3-14614448221135632" ref-type="fn">3</xref></sup> that fit the
search criteria and enabled readers to comment. All six articles were published
between 19 February 2020 and 28 May 2021 at a time when the world was still
learning about the virus and vaccine efficacy (<xref rid="table1-14614448221135632" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-14614448221135632"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Articles used in the data analysis, the date those articles were
published on, their source, and the number of comments analyzed from
each article.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_14614448221135632-table1" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Title</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date Published</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Comments Analyzed</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How epidemics like COVID-19 end (and how to end them
faster)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 February 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Washington Post</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How Much Worse the Coronavirus Could Get, in Charts</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 March 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The New York Times</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">341</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">What 5 Coronavirus Models Say the Next Month Will Look
Like</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 April 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The New York Times</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How a sluggish vaccination program could delay a return to
normal and invite vaccine-resistant variants to emerge</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 February 2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Washington Post</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Just How Big Could India&#x02019;s True Covid Toll Be?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 May 2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The New York Times</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Where The Latest COVID-19 Models Think We&#x02019;re Headed&#x02014;And Why
They Disagree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 May 2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FiveThirtyEight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>All of the articles in our dataset followed a relatively similar structure where
journalists pose a question related to COVID-19 that is relevant to the public,
then attempt to answer this question using either computer simulations,
mathematical, or epidemiological models that convey to the public possible
future outcomes. For example, on 13 March 2020, 2 days after the declaration of
COVID-19 as a global pandemic by the WHO and prior to any public conversation
about rolling out the vaccine, Nicholas Kristof and Stuart Thompson published in
collaboration with infectious disease epidemiologists an online opinion article
titled &#x0201c;How Much Worse the Coronavirus Could Get, in Charts.&#x0201d;<sup><xref rid="fn4-14614448221135632" ref-type="fn">4</xref></sup> The discourse
in this article was mainly focusing on potential policies and actions that could
help in curbing the number of infections due to COVID-19. The article showcases
an interactive simulation tool that allows readers to visualize how swift
actions by U.S officials could make a difference in controlling the pandemic.
The interactive tool starts by displaying simulated numbers of COVID-19
infections and fatalities in the United States from April 2020 until July 2021
if no action was taken by U.S officials to control the pandemic (<xref rid="fig1-14614448221135632" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>). As the reader
scrolls down through the article, different scenarios were displayed to
demonstrate that implementing interventions is not only important, but the
timing and immediacy of when these interventions are implemented could have
consequences on the number of infections and fatalities. For example, based on
results from the interactive tool for one of the shown scenarios, implementing
intervention measures (e.g. ending public gatherings, closing workplaces and
schools, and mass testing) as early as June 2020 could reduce the number of
infections in July 2020 from 9.4 million, if no action was taken, to 4.5 million
cases and reduce the number of fatalities from 1 million, if no action was
taken, to 475,000 deaths by July 2021 (<xref rid="fig1-14614448221135632" ref-type="fig">Figure 1b</xref>). Readers can modify the
timing and level of aggressiveness in implementing additional measures to better
understand the impact of these factors on the course of the pandemic (<xref rid="fig2-14614448221135632" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-14614448221135632"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(a) and (b) Predictions generated by the model developed at the New York
Times. (a) The predicted number of infections and total deaths due to
COVID if no intervention or action is taken. (b) The relationship
between early interventions and the model&#x02019;s forecasts and the impact of
early interventions on the forecasted number of infections and total
deaths.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_14614448221135632-fig1" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig2-14614448221135632"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Illustrates how the audience can interact with the model by changing when
interventions can begin and their level of severity. There are three
levels of severity that the model accounted for: mild, moderate, and
aggressive. The audience can visualize the impact of each level of
intervention severity on the number of infections and total deaths due
to COVID.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_14614448221135632-fig2" position="float"/></fig><p>Next, we used The New York Times API<sup><xref rid="fn5-14614448221135632" ref-type="fn">5</xref></sup> to collect online news
comments for all articles in our sample that are published on the New York Times
website. For the remaining news sources, we used a custom web scraper to scrape
the comments section of the Washington Post and FiveThirtyEight articles. A
total of 1851 comments were collected, 1239 comments from articles published in
The New York Times, 328 comments from articles published in the Washington Post,
and 284 comments from FiveThirtyEight. Since we were only interested in
understanding the direct public response to predictive information in these
articles, and not commenters&#x02019; responses to each other&#x02019;s comments, we excluded
comment replies (i.e. comments to other readers&#x02019; comments) before conducting our
analysis. Out of the 1851 comments originally collected, only 885 direct
comments were left for analysis (603 comments from The New York Times, 165
comments from the Washington Post, and 117 comments from FiveThirtyEight). A
small subset of uninformative comments were further excluded from the analysis
because they were lacking clear relevance to the article (e.g. &#x0201c;Trends are your
friends&#x0201d;). In the end, the remaining comments did not exhibit the quality issues
sometimes observed in online news comments (<xref rid="bibr34-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Santana, 2014</xref>) but rather reflected an
overall courteous (i.e. not rude, obscene, or trolling) discourse.</p></sec><sec id="section5-14614448221135632"><title>Analysis</title><p>All of the collected comments were analyzed using a qualitative thematic analysis
approach (<xref rid="bibr4-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Braun and Clarke,
2006</xref>). The authors started with the earliest published article to
sequentially open code all comments. The objective was to allow themes to emerge
from the data while following the method of constant comparison to continuously
assess the fit and organization of comments into stable conceptual groupings
across comments. To code the comments, the authors read comments while
summarizing and pulling excerpts that could be grouped together to fit into an
evolving set of possible thematic clusters of comments or potentially be the
basis for new themes. Throughout the coding process, the authors wrote memos to
articulate and clarify the evolving definitions of concepts that the themes
represent. The authors also periodically discussed and assessed the conceptual
organization of themes, a process often referred to as analyst triangulation
(<xref rid="bibr28-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Patton, 2014</xref>).
This contributed to the refinement of the overall organization of the emerging
themes. Per the constant comparison process in qualitative research, all
emerging themes and their definitions were continuously revised and assessed
throughout the coding process to ensure that the themes made conceptual sense
and decide whether they needed to be reorganized, merged, or further broken into
more themes (<xref rid="bibr39-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Strauss and
Corbin, 1990</xref>). After coding 768 comments on five articles, the themes
were largely saturated and stable with small amounts of new information still
being added depending on the specific context of the article being coded.
However, this new information did not require any reorganization or revisions of
the concepts that defined the saturated themes. To be sure that the authors
reached a suitable level of thematic saturation, an additional article from the
list of sampled articles (described in <xref rid="table1-14614448221135632" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), titled &#x0201c;Where The Latest
COVID-19 Models Think We&#x02019;re Headed&#x02014;And Why They Disagree,&#x0201d; was coded bringing
the total number of coded comments to 885. The newly coded comments did not
contribute to the formation of new themes or necessitate the revision of the
conceptual organization of themes, but rather supported the already existing
themes and how they were organized. As a qualitative analysis, we focus our
results on describing and elaborating themes rather than on considering the
salience or prevalence of those themes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section6-14614448221135632"><title>Results</title><p>Throughout the qualitative thematic analysis of the comments, we found that the focal
point of readers&#x02019; comments was on the models described in the sampled articles. All
emerging themes resulting from the qualitative thematic analysis were also
descriptive of the attitudinal responses to the models in the sampled predictive
journalism articles in the context of the pandemic. In the following subsections, we
describe the three themes and corresponding subthemes and codes, which are also
summarized in <xref rid="fig3-14614448221135632" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3-14614448221135632"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Typology of responses to predictive journalism articles grouped by the three
main themes (shaded in dark gray) and their corresponding sub-themes (shaded
in light gray) and codes constituting those themes (white).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_14614448221135632-fig3" position="float"/></fig><sec id="section7-14614448221135632"><title>Affective response</title><p>All comments that include clear expressions of negative emotional responses after
interpreting the models described in the sampled predictive journalism articles
were grouped under the broad <italic toggle="yes">affective response</italic> theme. Comments
in this theme conveyed rising levels of concern about the future of the virus.
Predominantly, comments consistently expressed fear as one of the emotions
triggered by the models&#x02019; depictions and forecasts of the worst-case scenario
(e.g. &#x0201c;the worst-case scenario [as described in the model] does nothing but
promote anxiety and fear&#x0201d;). Such comments were grouped into a single subtheme
named <italic toggle="yes">negative emotional response.</italic> Throughout the qualitative
analysis of the comments, we also observed a few commenters communicating other
types of emotions such as anxiety, nervousness, and frustration in response to
the models. For instance, one commenter wrote, &#x0201c;I don&#x02019;t find articles like these
helpful; it just accelerates anxiety and panic&#x0201d; and another stated that &#x0201c;Every
evening I get into a state of fear and frustration when I come here to see the
updates [of the model].&#x0201d;</p><p>Another observation we found in readers&#x02019; comments is their utilization of the
model to mentally simulate future events about the possible trends of COVID.
This, however, could yield a worrying perspective and negative sentiment about
the future as one commenter puts it &#x0201c;There is no way to eradicate this virus and
other viruses. Everybody will be afraid to engage in sports, travel and even
work. Life as we know has been dramatically diminished forever.&#x0201d; Even in the
presence of optimistic news such as the vaccine development, readers expressed
their negative outlook of the future outcome of COVID based on their
interpretation of the models &#x0201c;I think a vaccine is at least a year away and that
is super optimistic. By then, Covid might well have run its course, killing
millions.&#x0201d; Other commenters used information from the models to compare it to
the present state of the virus at the time. This mental process could have
created negative emotions and perception of the uncertain future as readers
interpreted results of the model. For example, a commenter in their seventies
shared: &#x0201c;all outcomes are uncertain and trend towards the dire, towards the non
flattened curve on your chart [referring to the model]. My husband and I are
both in our seventies. We&#x02019;re not panicking, but are definitely afraid.&#x0201d;</p><p>Negative emotions evoked by interpreting the models, as shown in the previous
examples, were also in some instances a catalyst for readers to take action.
This was evident in a comment shared by a teacher in a community college
discussing the shift to online learning due to their concern about safety: &#x0201c;I
work at a rural community college. These charts [referring to the model] make it
look like the entire summer, fall, and even next spring might be too unsafe,
resulting in maybe a year or more of online instruction.&#x0201d; In the next section,
we will further elaborate on this type of action-oriented response by focusing
on the numerous actions that were taken or demanded by the readers as expressed
in their comments.</p></sec><sec id="section8-14614448221135632"><title>Action-oriented response</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Action-oriented response</italic> is the main theme which amasses all
comments requesting or demanding action as a result of understanding and
interpreting the models; as one comment illustrates, &#x0201c;The model easily
understandable and illustrates the impact of practical changes in our behavior
on the peak severity and cumulative fatalities, The good news is that an
aggressive approach can save thousands of lives. Lets get underway today!&#x0201d;.
Throughout the qualitative analysis of readers&#x02019; comments that gave rise to this
theme, commenters were encouraging domestic (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">government, collective
society</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">individual/personal</italic>) and global (i.e.
<italic toggle="yes">global community</italic>) actors to take political, economic, or
health-related actions.</p><p>In the <italic toggle="yes">action-oriented response</italic> theme, commenters referenced the
model in their comments to justify when, why, and by whom an action needs to be
taken to curb the spread of the virus. For example, commenters ascribed to the
government the task of implementing aggressive measures as early as possible to
slow down the spread of the virus, one commenter wrote &#x0201c;As shown on the graphs
very early intervention is absolutely essential. Everything possible to do must
be done if that means closing schools, public gatherings, etc..&#x0201d; Other
commenters also proposed that society should take the necessary measures moving
forward to avoid infecting more people. For example, a commenter suggests,
&#x0201c;Great article and the model helps to explain what is going on. Work from home
if you can. Clean your hands-a lot. Go out just once a day, if needed, to get
supplies.&#x0201d; It is worth noting that irrespective of the type of ascribed
responsibility or action, models in the sampled predictive journalism articles
remain the main focal point of the comments requesting to take action in
response to the pandemic. Next, we elaborate on the types of actions commenters
ascribed to domestic and global actors.</p><p>Our analysis revealed three main types of actions referenced in readers&#x02019;
comments: political, economic, and health-related actions.
<italic toggle="yes">Political</italic> actions are best described in terms of comments
requesting actions that are political in nature such as voting the president out
(e.g. &#x0201c;Call them out on it . . . and vote them out on it.&#x0201d;) or calling for
collective action (e.g. &#x0201c;It&#x02019;s up to the people to organize and demand action&#x0201d;).
<italic toggle="yes">Economic</italic> actions include comments calling for the
distribution of economic relief packages to support individuals, families, and
businesses impacted by the virus (e.g. &#x0201c;$1000 a month would go a long way to
helping millions of Americans who will lose their jobs in the coming months from
an economy grinding to a halt.&#x0201d;). Finally, <italic toggle="yes">health-related</italic>
actions were expressed through comments encouraging the adoption of health
measures on the individual or societal levels, such as social distancing, to
slow down the rising number of COVID-19 cases and protect vulnerable groups in
the medical profession (e.g. &#x0201c;social distancing will matter greatly to avoid the
peak happening too quickly.. Let&#x02019;s do all we can to flatten the curve, to care
for the high risk and our medical professionals.).</p><p>All actions were ascribed to either domestic or global actors. On the domestic
level, actions were ascribed to either the <italic toggle="yes">government, collective
society</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">individual</italic> (or
<italic toggle="yes">personal</italic>) actors. Comments ascribing actions and
responsibility to the <italic toggle="yes">government</italic> are requesting actions to be
taken by the state or federal governments in response to the virus. Examples of
actions include, but are not limited to, increasing testing capabilities as one
commenter stated, &#x0201c;Our nation does not have testing kits available for everyone.
We need multiple tests for each person in America.&#x0201d; Another action that was
requested in the comments in the form of a suggestion is to reopen closed
military facilities as hospitals to treat infected individuals, &#x0201c;Beyond
increased testing, what is being done to expand capacity to support the surge in
hospitalizations?. Build new hospitals in 10 days as China did? Reopen closed
military facilities to quarantine infected individuals?&#x0201d;. In addition, some
comments were also demanding further clarification on health strategies to
handle COVID as one commenter puts it, &#x0201c;. . . I don&#x02019;t disagree with the current
strategies, but I would like to hear CDC epidemiologists give modeling updates
frequently and not just tell us what to do, but keep explaining why&#x0201d;.</p><p>Commenters also ascribed actions to collective society by using collective
language and terminology (e.g. &#x0201c;we,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;American public,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;us&#x0201d;) to request and
encourage the public to take precautionary measures in response to the virus.
For example, one commenter encouraged the public to comply with the recommended
aggressive measures of social distancing as stated in their comment: &#x0201c;We all
have to concentrate on social distancing and hand washing&#x0201d;. In another example,
a commenter encouraged others to wear masks in public &#x0201c;Once more vaccines are
approved, things will change for the better. Until then, wear a real mask,
practice social distancing and the virus will have a tough time jumping around&#x0201d;.
Other comments ascribed actions on the <italic toggle="yes">Individual or Personal</italic>
level. This was evident from a group of comments expressing actions that will
and should be taken by commenters on the individual or family levels to minimize
the spread of the virus. After reviewing the models, some commenters, for
example, were &#x0201c;persuaded to lay low and not to visit their elderly parents over
spring break&#x0201d;. Others chose to take extra health precautions by &#x0201c;wearing a mask
and gloves and washing hands for a very long time&#x0201d;.</p><p>On the global level, comments ascribing responsibility to the global or
international community were grouped under the <italic toggle="yes">global community</italic>
actor group category. Comments were encouraging global altruism in vaccination
initiatives to increase vaccination rates around the world (e.g. &#x0201c;. . . The
entire world must help the entire world get vaccinated&#x0201d;). In addition,
commenters were also concerned about the moral implications pertaining to
vaccine inequity as privileged countries produced and purchased more vaccines
than less privileged countries. One commenter writes in that regard, &#x0201c;I am
concerned about rich countries buying up vaccines and smaller, less rich
countries trying to compete for those vaccines. Ignoring the moral implications,
this is not be good for our world.&#x0201d;</p><p>Overall, action-oriented responses can be thought of in terms of a matrix of
actors and actions. In our analysis of users&#x02019; comments, we found the list of
actors to include the government, society, individual/or personal actors, and
the global (or international) community. We also identified political, economic,
and health-related types of actions to be associated with the aforementioned
actors. Despite our findings, we expect the list of actors and actions to expand
depending on the context of future research. In the next section, we shed light
on the remaining group of comments concerning readers&#x02019; evaluations of the
models.</p></sec><sec id="section9-14614448221135632"><title>Evaluative response</title><p>This theme encompasses all the remaining comments consisting of supportive and
critical responses resulting from evaluating the models. Supportive comments
were grouped into three subthemes: <italic toggle="yes">supporting predictive journalism,
model enhancements</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">illustrating modeling
principles</italic>. In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">Critical Comments</italic> were
criticizing the models and the way models were visualized and presented
(<italic toggle="yes">visualizations</italic>). Throughout the thematic analysis, we also
found a few instances of critical comments being directed toward other entities
(e.g. <italic toggle="yes">healthcare system</italic>), and actors (e.g.
<italic toggle="yes">government</italic>, the <italic toggle="yes">public, and
journalists</italic>).</p><p>Supportive comments in the <italic toggle="yes">supporting predictive journalism</italic>
sub-theme were complementing the analyses and models that journalists have put
together. Some readers expressed their appreciation for the ease of
accessibility and understanding of the models, one reader commented: &#x0201c;Thank you
very much for this animated graphic. It really makes the science behind
epidemics much easier for us lay people to understand&#x0201d;. According to another
group of commenters, models seem to have clarified information about the virus,
another commenter wrote: &#x0201c;Great! Curves like these act as a kind of armature
that give a rough idea of the form of the beast we face. Again, great!&#x0201d;. Also,
readers complemented the journalistic efforts sharing models that are
informative of the primary role of interventions in responding to the virus,
&#x0201c;This was the sort of analysis that was needed to explain what and when things
needed to be done. Thank you&#x0201d;. In a few instances, commenters also complimented
the models for giving them an insight into the impact of the virus in other
countries, a reader commented: &#x0201c;This is a great mathematical projection of what
is actually going on in India. The saddest part is so many lives could have been
saved if the authorities had been prepared with proper medical stockpiles&#x0201d;.</p><p>In the <italic toggle="yes">model enhancements</italic> subtheme, comments included several
suggestions to improve the models such as assessing the performance and accuracy
of the models (e.g. &#x0201c;it would be interesting to compare the past predictions of
each model to the actual death count.&#x0201d;). Other suggestions include requests to
account for additional assumptions that were not considered during the model
development process (e.g. &#x0201c;It doesn&#x02019;t seem these models take into account the
potential for new infections in the vast re-opening that is planned in certain
states. They should show that effect estimated&#x0201d;). Commenters also suggested
developing additional models that &#x0201c;takes into account the impacts of mutation of
coronavirus and potential reinfection rates.&#x0201d; A few other comments were relevant
to the user experience of the readers as they read through the results of static
(i.e. noninteractive) models. For example, a commenter suggested for journalists
to give readers the ability to engage with the models: &#x0201c;It&#x02019;d be great if the
designers let the readers use this tool.&#x0201d;</p><p>As for the <italic toggle="yes">illustrating modeling principles</italic> subtheme, in some
instances, comments described how models work (e.g. &#x0201c;Models are not static and
continually get refined with more data. Most models have assumptions. All models
have uncertainty&#x0201d;). In other instances, comments clarified the assumptions made
in the process of making predictions, one commenter elaborates:<disp-quote><p>Models don&#x02019;t know the future outright &#x02013; what people do matters and they
try to adjust to those changes. Think of it this way: the models that
predict deaths are going to decrease assume we will be
sheltering-in-place for longer, while models that predict the number of
deaths will increase assume shelter-in-place will be lifted. Models
extrapolate from trends&#x02014;they don&#x02019;t predict policy decisions.</p></disp-quote></p><p>In addition, commenters shared information on how a model&#x02019;s performance can be
assessed through the quality of its predictions in comparison to observed
outcomes, &#x0201c;There is bound to be an error epsilon between the real deaths and
those predicted by the model.&#x0201d;</p><p>Criticism in the <italic toggle="yes">critical comments</italic> sub-theme was being mainly
directed toward the models with a few other instances of it being directed at
entities and actors. Comments criticized the models for their poor performance
due to the lack of testing data incorporated into the models (e.g. &#x0201c;Garbage in,
garbage out. Until we test enough, we&#x02019;re just guessing.&#x0201d;) or the bias they may
introduce among researchers aiming to understand how the virus is spreading
(e.g. &#x0201c;These models limit a researcher&#x02019;s ability to see how the data develops.
they channel the researcher into seeing if the data fits the model instead of if
the data fits the theory. I know this sounds abstract but it is a genuine
worry&#x0201d;). The over-optimism in some models&#x02019; predictions was also criticized by
commenters as shown in this comment:<disp-quote><p>I looked back at IHME forecast in March. It predicted 1,500 deaths in CA
by end of August. We passed 2000 in April. Even now it predicts we will
be done with deaths by May 19 or so. The model is far too
optimistic.</p></disp-quote></p><p>In addition, a small subset of commenters uniquely focused their criticism on the
way models were presented and visualized. For example, one of the comments
criticized the aesthetics of a graphical plot displaying multiple line charts in
a single chart, the commenter wrote: &#x0201c;I&#x02019;m sorry I don&#x02019;t understand these charts.
I&#x02019;m confused as to where each one starts.&#x0201d; In another example, a commenter also
criticized the visualizations for being too difficult to interpret, the
commenter wrote: &#x0201c;More clarity would be nice, I&#x02019;m a science guy and I struggled
to understand what was being shown.&#x0201d;</p><p>The remaining collection of critical comments were directing criticism to
entities such as the healthcare system that commenters think should have taken
more responsible actions in response to the pandemic. Specifically, in the
context of the lack of accessibility to COVID testing, one physician wrote: &#x0201c;As
a physician, I am appalled at the delivery system for valid coronavirus tests in
comparison to competent medical systems like South Korea who have rapid-result
and drive-through testing.&#x0201d; Other comments focused on the sluggish vaccine
distribution process, one commenter complained: &#x0201c;Most vaccination centers have
little if any vaccine stocks, opening more will not help unless vaccines can be
sent to them by the hundreds of millions.&#x0201d;</p><p>Government entities were also the subject of criticism in the comments. The
executive branch of the government was criticized for its poor leadership and
inaction in response to the virus, a commenter wrote &#x0201c;Yet the schools are still
open. Just the kind of leadership and vision that we&#x02019;ve come to expect.&#x0201d; The
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) was also criticized after it
decides to revoke the masking rules for vaccinated individuals as stated in one
of the comments: &#x0201c;CDC says no masking needed for the vaccinated. what a joke?!
this is what you get when everything is politicalized in US.&#x0201d; Commenters also
criticized a segment of the public for disregarding the dangers of spreading the
virus during travel. One commenter expressed the problem by criticizing &#x0201c;the
people who are infected while traveling are ignoring the fact that they are
spreading the disease by returning home.&#x0201d; Furthermore, some commenters were
critical of people in society dismissing the information presented in the
models, &#x0201c;It makes me nuts reading people dismiss the models as irrelevant simply
because they are imperfect&#x0201d;&#x02014;one commenter wrote.</p><p>In contrast to the comments in the <italic toggle="yes">supporting predictive
journalism</italic> subtheme of <italic toggle="yes">support comments</italic>, there
were a handful of comments in the <italic toggle="yes">critical comments</italic> theme that
focused their criticism on journalists and the models they have developed. For
example, one commenter thinks that journalists <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;</italic>should be out
volunteering instead of complaining and whining [about rising cases due to the
virus].&#x0201d; Another commenter found &#x0201c;a remarkable lack of actual substance&#x0201d; in the
models and therefore decided to &#x0201c;tune them out as distraction.&#x0201d;</p><p>All supportive comments in the <italic toggle="yes">evaluative response</italic> theme were
either complementing the journalistic effort put forth by journalists,
explaining how modeling works, or providing recommendations and suggestions to
enhance the models. Critical comments, however, were predominantly focusing on
criticizing the models with a few instances of comments directing criticism to
other entities as stated earlier.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section10-14614448221135632"><title>Discussion</title><p>In addressing the research question of how the public responded to COVID predictions
in the news media, this research elaborates three main types of public responses
(affective, action-oriented, and evaluative as well as several subthemes of those
types) that we observed in the online news comments to articles of predictive
journalism related to the COVID pandemic. This richly described typology of
responses offers a contribution insofar as it nuances the ways through which
predictive information is processed and could indeed impact cognition or behavior,
suggesting routes through which the misinterpretation of predictions in news media
(<xref rid="bibr15-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Gelman et al.,
2020</xref>; <xref rid="bibr44-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Westwood et al.,
2020</xref>) could be activated. Moreover, the typology offers fertile ground
for researchers to further explore and validate these types of audience responses,
operationalize them for potential quantitative or computational analysis at a larger
scale, and expand and validate them in other contexts such as in political,
economic, or climate forecasts. Studying the range of public response to predictive
journalism is a necessary first step toward understanding how journalistic practice
might also adapt to avoid misinforming the public, biasing its opinion, or
discourage it from civic participation. In the following subsections, we further
discuss implications for research and practice that emerge from our synthesis of the
response types.</p><sec id="section11-14614448221135632"><title>The role of affect in future-oriented cognition</title><p>The intolerance of uncertainty about the future paired with the fear of COVID-19
appears to have an effect on peoples&#x02019; mental well-being (<xref rid="bibr35-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Satici et al., 2022</xref>). The
<italic toggle="yes">affective response</italic> theme surfaced some of the negative
emotions attributed to the pandemic that are in line with recent research (<xref rid="bibr8-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Coelho et al., 2020</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr25-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Mertens et al.,
2020</xref>). Although our findings in this theme reflect readers&#x02019; fear and
anxiety about the future, we suggest that researchers should explore whether
predictive journalism could also have the capacity of eliciting prosocial
emotions, such as empathy, that could motivate cooperation in collective acts,
especially during crises (e.g. motivating the public to wear a mask during the
COVID pandemic as a precautionary measure to protect the elderly). In contrast,
misinterpreting predictive journalism articles could elicit negative emotions,
such as anger, that may divide the public and mobilize it toward hostile
action.</p><p>Our findings also suggest the need to consider the public&#x02019;s affective response to
the models as a feedback system that stimulates retrospective appraisal of
previous actions, and possibly alters future behavior (<xref rid="bibr3-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Baumeister et al., 2007</xref>). For example,
if someone is fearful due to interpreting the model, this emotion can stimulate
the thought of previous actions that should have been taken and possibly inform
future behavior. In light of this, it might be worth exploring whether public
emotionality mediates the possible effect of predictive journalism on informing
readers&#x02019; judgments and decisions or motivating their actions with respect to the
future. Given that affect can drive planning and eventual action (<xref rid="bibr37-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Seligman et al.,
2016</xref>), it seems crucial that future work engage deeply with the affective
response to predictive journalism. This is aligned with the recently termed
&#x0201c;emotional turn&#x0201d; in journalism studies&#x02014;a growing area of research in journalism
in the past decade that recognizes the importance of emotion as a prism to
understand social and political life which suggests an agenda for research on
how emotions and journalism intersect (<xref rid="bibr43-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Wahl-Jorgensen and Pantti, 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="section12-14614448221135632"><title>Responsibility assignment for future actions</title><p>In the <italic toggle="yes">action-oriented response</italic> theme, we identified an
interesting pattern in readers&#x02019; comments that tend to ascribe responsibilities
and actions to different actors. Commenters even outlined actions that can and
must be taken in response to the pandemic by different actors in society,
government, and the international community on the global level. In a sense,
commenters were engaged in a group planning activity where particular actions
and responsibilities are articulated for future action. Summarizing such group
planning, including using other feedback signals on comments such as &#x0201c;likes,&#x0201d;
could be a powerful way to harness the collective future-oriented cognition
(<xref rid="bibr41-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Szpunar et al.,
2014</xref>) of a community to both suggest and evaluate what to do.</p><p>The notion of responsibility assignment also raises the broader question about
the function of predictive journalism in society, especially with respect to
mobilizing the public toward social issues or in crises when there is very
little known about the future. Prior research by <xref rid="bibr45-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Yanovitzky and Weber (2019)</xref> theorized
the effects of news media on policy actors and subsequently on policy making
where they outlined mobilization as one of the core knowledge-brokering
functions of news media. <xref rid="bibr1-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Appelgren and J&#x000f6;nsson (2021)</xref> also found that the merger between
science communication and data journalistic practices coupled with motivational
framing were effective in increasing public engagement with climate change.
Accordingly, it is vital to deeply understand why and how the framing of
forecasts outlined in predictive journalism articles may encourage the public to
conduct a responsibility analysis of who is responsible for what, who needs to
do what, and when. Future work on predictive journalism should consider focusing
on understanding how the design and presentation of predictions could positively
shape and channel collective activities to increase citizen engagement and
willingness to take action on issues related to social and climate justice.</p></sec><sec id="section13-14614448221135632"><title>Harnessing responses for improved communication</title><p>Overall, commenters expressed the significance of predictive journalism by
thanking journalists for their efforts in covering the pandemic and
complementing the models attempting to cast away the uncertainty about the
future. Additional supportive comments came in the form of suggestions such as
enhancing the predictive power of the models (<xref rid="bibr11-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Diakopoulos and Naaman, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr17-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Henrich and Holmes,
2013</xref>). Despite this supportive sentiment, other comments criticized
the models and the way they were visualized. Practitioners may find some of
these comments helpful in developing new communication tools (<xref rid="bibr21-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Kay, 2022</xref>) or shaping
best practices that data journalists could follow to achieve simplicity and
clarity in visualizing forecasts and scientific data.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">critical comments</italic> subtheme in the <italic toggle="yes">evaluative
response</italic> theme further highlights the importance of introducing
novel qualitative and quantitative methods that capture and assess the accuracy
in public understanding of statistical and scientific visualizations in the news
to avoid possible misinterpretations of facts or forecasts on the public level
(<xref rid="bibr36-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Secko et al.,
2011</xref>). Although our findings in the <italic toggle="yes">illustrating modeling
principles</italic> subtheme show examples of commenter-led initiatives to
educate others about basic modeling principles such as model assumptions, model
interpretation, and model performance evaluation, we think that this inclination
could be more explicitly shaped and encouraged through journalistic initiatives
similar to the New York Times &#x0201c;What is Going on in this Graph?&#x0201d;<sup><xref rid="fn6-14614448221135632" ref-type="fn">6</xref></sup> that grants
students and readers the online space to develop their data-literacy skills
through discussing and interpreting visualizations as a group.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section14-14614448221135632"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Predictive journalism offers the public the ability to explore possible future
scenarios on topics that are relevant to society and help them comprehend
uncertainties about the future. In this research, online news comments enabled us to
understand audiences&#x02019; responses to COVID models in the news and more broadly to the
emerging genre of predictive journalism. Specifically, this research is a step
toward examining how this genre of journalism impacts the public&#x02019;s emotions,
behaviors, and future thinking. We elaborate a discussion examining the role of
affect in future-oriented cognition around media, the notion of collective
responsibility assignment which may have implications for how groups plan the future
or think about accountability for failure, and the idea of leveraging comment
responses for improving communication of predictions. Based on our findings, we
propose future research directions around deepening our understanding of the role of
predictive journalism in shaping public opinion especially with respect to future
decisions on policies for a variety of social and political issues. In particular,
survey methods could also be developed to further understand audience responses to
predictive journalism, especially given that not all articles have comments. The
typology presented in this work opens up space for future research to validate it,
operationalize it for quantitative study, and extend it to study it in other
exceeding important domains such as election and climate forecasting.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; Note:</bold> All authors listed in this article confirm that they have agreed to submit this
article to the journal of <italic toggle="yes">New Media &#x00026; Society</italic> and that the
present article is not currently being considered for publication by any other
print or electronic journal.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or
publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iDs:</bold> Mowafak Allaham <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_14614448221135632-img1.jpg"/><ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9211-4598" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9211-4598</ext-link></p><p>Nicholas Diakopoulos <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_14614448221135632-img1.jpg"/><ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5005-6123" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5005-6123</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><bio id="d64e689"><title>Author biographies</title><p><bold>Mowafak Allaham</bold> is a PhD student in Technology &#x00026; Social Behavior
program (a joint PhD in Computer Science and Communication Studies). His research
interests are at the intersection of technology, journalism, and social
behavior.</p><p><bold>Nicholas Diakopoulos</bold> is an associate professor in Communication Studies
and Computer Science (by courtesy) at Northwestern University where he is director
of the Computational Journalism Lab (CJL). He is the author of the book
<italic toggle="yes">Automating the News: How Algorithms are Rewriting the Media</italic>,
published by Harvard University Press in 2019.</p></bio><notes><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-14614448221135632"><label>1.</label><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/03/13/opinion/coronavirus-trump-response.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/03/13/opinion/coronavirus-trump-response.html</ext-link>;
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/22/upshot/coronavirus-models.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/22/upshot/coronavirus-models.html</ext-link>;
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2021/05/25/world/asia/india-covid-death-estimates.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2021/05/25/world/asia/india-covid-death-estimates.html</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-14614448221135632"><label>2.</label><p><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2020/health/coronavirus-how-epidemics-spread-and-end/" ext-link-type="uri">www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2020/health/coronavirus-how-epidemics-spread-and-end/</ext-link>;
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/interactive/2021/vaccination-pace-herd-immunity/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/interactive/2021/vaccination-pace-herd-immunity/</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-14614448221135632"><label>3.</label><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/covid-forecasts/" ext-link-type="uri">https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/covid-forecasts/</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-14614448221135632"><label>4.</label><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/03/13/opinion/coronavirus-trump-response.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/03/13/opinion/coronavirus-trump-response.html</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-14614448221135632"><label>5.</label><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://developer.nytimes.com/apis" ext-link-type="uri">https://developer.nytimes.com/apis</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-14614448221135632"><label>6.</label><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/column/whats-going-on-in-this-graph" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/column/whats-going-on-in-this-graph</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appelgren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f6;nsson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Engaging citizens
for climate change&#x02014;challenges for journalism</article-title>.
<source>Digital Journalism</source><volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>755</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>772</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basch</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kecojevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Coverage of the
COVID-19 pandemic in the online versions of highly circulated U.S. daily
newspapers</article-title>. <source>Journal of Community
Health</source><volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>1089</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1097</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32902813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vohs</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathan DeWall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>)
<article-title>How emotion shapes behavior: feedback, anticipation, and
reflection, rather than direct causation</article-title>.
<source>Personality and Social Psychology
Review</source><volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18453461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Using thematic
analysis in psychology</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Research in
Psychology</source><volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parlapiano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>What 5 Coronavirus models say the next month will look
like</article-title>. <source>The New York Times</source>,
<day>22</day><month>April</month>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/22/upshot/coronavirus-models.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/22/upshot/coronavirus-models.html</ext-link>
(<comment>accessed 2 June 2022</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>TED</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Effects of
exposure to COVID-19 news and information: a meta-analysis of media use and
uncertainty-related responses during the pandemic</article-title>.
<source>Journalism &#x00026; Mass Communication
Quarterly</source><volume>99</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rains</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Online and
uncivil? Patterns and determinants of incivility in newspaper website
comments</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Communication</source><volume>64</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>658</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>679</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Suttiwan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>On the nature of fear and anxiety triggered by
COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Psychology</source>.
Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.581314" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.581314</ext-link>
(<comment>accessed 1 June 2022</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colglazier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Diakopoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Predictive models
in news coverage of the COVID-19 pandemic in the U.S</article-title>. In:
<conf-name>International Communication Association conference</conf-name>,
<conf-loc>Paris, France</conf-loc>, <conf-date>26&#x02013;30 May
2022</conf-date>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diakopoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>) <source>Predictive journalism: on
the role of computational prospection in news media</source>. SSRN Scholarly
Paper 4092033, 22 April. <publisher-loc>Rochester, NY</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Social Science Research Network</publisher-name>. Available
at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=4092033" ext-link-type="uri">https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=4092033</ext-link> (<comment>accessed 1
June 2022</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diakopoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Naaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Towards quality
discourse in online news comments</article-title>. In:
<conf-name>Proceedings of the ACM 2011 conference on computer supported
cooperative work</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Hangzhou, China</conf-loc>,
<conf-date>19&#x02013;23 March 2011</conf-date>, pp.
<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>. <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ACM</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisele</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Litvyak</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000e4;ndle</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2022</year>)
<article-title>An emotional rally: exploring commenters&#x02019; responses to online
news coverage of the COVID-19 crisis in Austria</article-title>.
<source>Digital Journalism</source><volume>10</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>952</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>975</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franck</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Predicting
competitions by combining conditional logistic regression and subjective
Bayes: an academy awards case study</article-title>. <source>The Annals of
Applied Statistics</source><volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>2083</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2100</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friemel</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000f6;tsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <part-title>Online reader
comments as indicator for perceived public opinion</part-title>. In:
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Emmer Mans Strippel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Kommunikationspolitik f&#x000fc;r die digitale
Gesellschaft</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Ifpuk&#x02014;Institute for Media and Communication Studies at Freie
Universit&#x000e4;t Berlin</publisher-name>, pp.
<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hullman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wlezien</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Information, incentives, and goals in election
forecasts</article-title>. <source>Judgment and Decision
Making</source><volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>880</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brazeal</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Playing nice:
modeling civility in online political discussions</article-title>.
<source>Communication Research
Reports</source><volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Web news readers
comments: towards developing a methodology for using on-line comments in
social inquiry</article-title>. <source>Journal of Media and Communication
Studies</source><volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughey</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Racist comments at
online news sites: a methodological dilemma for discourse
analysis</article-title>. <source>Media, Culture &#x00026;
Society</source><volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>332</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>347</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hullman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Diakopoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Momeni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>)
<article-title>Content, context, and critique: commenting on a data
visualization blog</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the 18th
ACM conference on computer supported cooperative work &#x00026; social
computing</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Vancouver, BC, Canada</conf-loc>,
<conf-date>28 February</conf-date>, pp.
<fpage>1170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1175</lpage>. <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ACM</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacmin-Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourdon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Larocque</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Sex-and gender-based analysis of coronavirus crisis
competence</article-title>.
<source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source><volume>119</volume>:
<fpage>104957</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>) <source>ggdist: Visualizations of
Distributions and Uncertainty</source> (R Package Version 3.0.1). Available
at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://mjskay.github.io/ggdist/" ext-link-type="uri">https://mjskay.github.io/ggdist/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>McElroy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Online comments:
the nature of comments on health journalism</article-title>.
<source>Computers in Human Behavior</source><volume>92</volume>:
<fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCombs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Voters&#x02019; need for
orientation and use of mass communication</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper
presented at the annual meeting of the International Communication
Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Montreal, QC, Canada</conf-loc>,
<conf-date>25&#x02013;28 April</conf-date>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maycotte</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Big data triggers
predictive journalism</article-title>. <source>Nieman Lab</source>.
Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.niemanlab.org/2015/12/big-data-triggers-predictive-journalism/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.niemanlab.org/2015/12/big-data-triggers-predictive-journalism/</ext-link>
(<comment>accessed 2 June 2022</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerritsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Duijndam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Fear of the coronavirus (COVID-19): predictors in an online
study conducted in March 2020</article-title>. <source>Journal of Anxiety
Disorders</source><volume>74</volume>:
<fpage>102258</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32569905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neiger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Media oracles: the
cultural significance and political import of news referring to future
events</article-title>.
<source>Journalism</source><volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pakpour</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>The fear of
COVID-19 and its role in preventive behaviors</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Concurrent
Disorders</source><volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <source>Qualitative Research
&#x00026; Evaluation Methods: Integrating Theory and Practice</source>.
<publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pentzold</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fechner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Data journalism&#x02019;s
many futures: diagrammatic displays and prospective probabilities in
data-driven news predictions</article-title>.
<source>Convergence</source><volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>732</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>750</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pentzold</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fechner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Probabilistic
storytelling and temporal exigencies in predictive data
journalism</article-title>. <source>Digital
Journalism</source><volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>736</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pentzold</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fechner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>&#x0201c;Flatten the
Curve&#x0201d;: data-driven projections and the journalistic brokering of knowledge
during the COVID-19 crisis</article-title>. <source>Digital
Journalism</source><volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):
<fpage>1367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1390</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perreault</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Perreault</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Journalists on
COVID-19 journalism: communication ecology of pandemic
reporting</article-title>. <source>American Behavioral
Scientist</source><volume>65</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):
<fpage>976</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>991</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Deliberation 2.0:
comparing the deliberative quality of online news user comments across
platforms</article-title>. <source>Journal of Broadcasting &#x00026; Electronic
Media</source><volume>59</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>555</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Virtuous or
vitriolic: the effect of anonymity on civility in online newspaper reader
comment boards</article-title>. <source>Journalism
Practice</source><volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satici</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Saricali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Satici</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2022</year>)
<article-title>Intolerance of uncertainty and mental wellbeing: serial
mediation by rumination and fear of COVID-19</article-title>.
<source>International Journal of Mental Health and
Addiction</source><volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>2731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2742</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32427165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Secko</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tlalka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>)
<article-title>The unfinished science story: journalist&#x02013;audience
interactions from the globe and mail&#x02019;s online health and science
sections</article-title>.
<source>Journalism</source><volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):
<fpage>814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>831</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seligman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Railton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2016</year>) <source>Homo
Prospectus</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spiegelhalter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Risk and
uncertainty communication</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of
Statistics and Its Application</source><volume>4</volume>:
<fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Basics of Qualitative
Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sukumaran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vezich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>)
<article-title>Normative influences on thoughtful online
participation</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the SIGCHI
conference on human factors in computing systems</conf-name>,
<conf-loc>Vancouver, BC, Canada</conf-loc>, <conf-date>7&#x02013;12 May</conf-date>,
pp. <fpage>3401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3410</lpage>. <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ACM</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szpunar</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Spreng</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schacter</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A taxonomy of
prospection: introducing an organizational framework for future-oriented
cognition</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of
Sciences</source><volume>111</volume>(<issue>52</issue>):
<fpage>18414</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18421</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>The &#x02018;nate silver
effect&#x02019; on political journalism: gatecrashers, gatekeepers, and changing
newsroom practices around coverage of public opinion polls</article-title>.
<source>Journalism</source><volume>20</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):
<fpage>873</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>889</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wahl-Jorgensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Introduction: the
emotional turn in journalism</article-title>.
<source>Journalism</source><volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>1147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1154</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lelkes</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Projecting
confidence: how the probabilistic horse race confuses and demobilizes the
public</article-title>. <source>The Journal of
Politics</source><volume>82</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>1530</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1544</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-14614448221135632"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yanovitzky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>News media as
knowledge brokers in public policymaking processes</article-title>.
<source>Communication Theory</source><volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>212</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>