<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">These three political acts, separately and together, ultimately seek to <italic toggle="yes">promote</italic> market-friendly land policies. While neoliberal land policies are constituted, interpreted and implemented in a highly uneven manner, idealized versions take the defining features of privatized, deregulated and demand-driven land policies aimed at stimulating land sales and rental markets, joint ventures and credit markets. This can be facilitated by ensuring the availability of transparent data and information about private property in land that can in turn allow for informed transactions &#8211; by willing sellers and willing buyers &#8211; which require minimum bureaucracy and are enforceable with minimal transaction costs. The objective is to use land and nature in the most economically efficient manner (Pereira, <xref rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). The notions of appropriate land use and appropriate land users are defined by a mainstream concept of economic efficiency, centred around the maximization of use of scarce land resources for a free market-driven economic growth that could satisfy the profit- and utility-maximizing impulses of individuals (Deininger &amp; Byerlee, <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Formal private land titles can ensure the &#8216;security&#8217; necessary to facilitate dynamic land and rental markets, joint ventures and credit markets. In this context, security means, primarily, security for owners of capital &#8211; from corporate agribusiness to finance capital, from traders to rich farmers (Deininger, <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). It is less about the security for working poor people from being discriminated against, or from being coerced to give up control of land. This is part of the dominant neoliberal narrative where &#8216;investment&#8217; becomes synonymous to &#8216;corporate investments&#8217;, consciously or unconsciously dismissing the two other equally important (if not more important) investments, namely, public investments and investments of working poor people themselves (Kay, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The guiding principle is to ensure that the most economically efficient users (in neoclassical economics/new institutional economics terms) are able to access and use land in the most economically efficient manner &#8211; that is, the greatest profit that can be derived from economic undertaking. This might entail individual or group rights, freehold title or formalizing customary land tenure, or a combination of these; the bottom line is whether it will allow for land sales and rental markets, joint ventures and credit markets, to emerge and flourish, thereby assuring would-be capitalist investors of the security of their investments.</p>