<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">This is captured in the views of Klaus Deininger, author of the 2003 World Bank land policy framework (Deininger, <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>), and co-author of the World Bank&#8217;s 2011 report on the global land grabs (Deininger &amp; Byerlee, <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Deininger stressed the importance of enabling relevant actors to &#8216;register group rights in a way that allows for community management of basic land administration processes (such as allocation of individual rights&#8201;&#8230;); boundaries are recorded and a clear internal governance structure&#8201;&#8230;&#8201;is established to allow interaction with outsiders&#8217;. He explained that this is important &#8216;to allow land users to enter into joint ventures with investors, or to allow groups to gradually individualize land rights if desired&#8217; (Deininger, <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, p. 237). A key neoliberal framework on agriculture and development that is fundamentally anchored on the 2003 World Bank land policy document (see also De Soto, <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) is the <italic toggle="yes">World Development Report (WDR) 2008</italic> (World Bank, <xref rid="CIT0109" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Like its 2003 forerunner, the <italic toggle="yes">WDR 2008</italic> strategy framework synthesizes the past and frames the future in relation to what role agriculture, land and nature will have to play in economic activity. It states: &#8216;Land markets&#8201;&#8230;&#8201;can raise productivity, help households diversify their incomes, and facilitate exit from agriculture&#8217;, and continues: &#8216;land markets are needed to transfer land to the most productive users and to facilitate participation in the rural nonfarm sector and migration out of agriculture&#8217;, before concluding: &#8216;insecure property rights, poor contract enforcement, and stringent legal restrictions limit the performance of land markets, creating large inefficiencies in both land and labor reallocation&#8217; (World Bank, <xref rid="CIT0109" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, p. 9).<xref rid="EN0005" ref-type="fn"><sup>5</sup></xref> The key documents referenced here all point to the question of reallocating land use to more economically efficient users (again, in the definition by neoclassical and new institutional economics) through free market-based mechanisms. The non-efficient and non-viable users have to be assisted in their exit options out of agriculture through a variety of safety net programmes, including cash transfer programmes.</p>