<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The political acts of <italic toggle="yes">rollback</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">containment</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">blocking</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">promoting</italic> have resulted in the current global land politics architecture. As such, the land policy structure is an inherent component of global neoliberal capitalism where it serves at least two major roles: as a strategy to address the capitalist crisis of over-accumulation (Harvey, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) by using land/nature for cheap inputs in production; and, at the same time, as a strategy to address the ecological crisis of capitalist production by expanding the role of land/nature as sink for production waste (Fraser, <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Martinez-Alier, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; O&#8217;Connor, <xref rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). This is not an original political strategy. The <italic toggle="yes">roll back</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">contain</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">block</italic> strategies against redistributive land policies emerging out of socialist or anti-colonial revolutions or electoral victories of left-wing political parties were deployed by conservative political forces worldwide during the Cold War, from the 1950s to the beginning of neoliberalism in the early 1980s. These forces included political coalitions like the 1960s&#8217; US-driven Alliance for Progress, as well as key individuals such as Roy Prosterman and Wolf Ladejinski (Putzel, <xref rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>). During the Cold War, the roll back&#8211;contain&#8211;block strategy fed into the strategy to promote counter and/or pre-emptive land policy reforms. These took the form of formal land titling, land resettlement or internal colonization, limited liberal redistributive land reforms, or a combination of these. This type of intervention was described by Diskin (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>), in the context of El Salvador, as reforms that prevent change. The nature of the contemporary roll back&#8211;contain&#8211;block&#8211;promote political acts is the same as that observed by Diskin decades ago.</p>