<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0015">It is fair to say these different strands of research have increasingly come together in recent years. This is, firstly, due to of the broader conversations that, certainly in the discipline of Geography, have occurred between &#8216;transport&#8217; and &#8216;mobilities&#8217; (<xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr">Shaw and Hesse, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Cidell and Prytherch, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Kwan and Schwanen, 2016</xref>). A second reason is that researchers in different fields and communities have been drawing on the same conceptual resources in attempts to examine questions of transport or mobility justice. Consider, for instance, how <xref rid="bb0300" ref-type="bibr">Sen, 1993</xref>, <xref rid="bb0305" ref-type="bibr">Sen, 1999</xref> work on capabilities is drawn upon across the full spectrum of transport and mobilities research (e.g., <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Kronlid, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Beyazit, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Sheller, 2018b</xref>; <xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr">Schwanen and Nixon, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Vecchio, 2020</xref>). Relatedly, and thirdly, the recent publication of Mimi <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Sheller's (2018b)</xref>
<italic>Mobility Justice: The Politics of Movement in an Age of Extremes</italic> has integrated work on transport and mobility justice by proposing that issues of transport at the spatial scales of individuals and urban areas &#8211; the bread and butter of transport justice &#8211; need to be placed in the broader context of mobility justice, which also encompasses the scales of the nation-state (e.g., the border regimes that shape migration) and the planet (e.g. international tourism, global elite mobilities, and questions of climate justice). The integration works out in the temporal domain as well: she places the daily movements of people and decadal rhythms of changes in transport infrastructure and urban structure within the <italic>longue dur&#233;e</italic> of changes in capitalism, colonialism, and extractivism.</p>