<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0020">Finally, and perhaps most importantly, a host of societal developments have thrown questions of transport and mobility justice into sharp relief. These developments include the historically unparalleled impetus to build &#8216;fast&#8217; transport systems &#8211; elevated highways, flyovers, bus rapid transit, and so forth &#8211; in particular in urban areas in the global South. These systems tend to benefit selected social groups and places (much) more than others. The developments also relate to the uneven consequences of austerity urbanism (<xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">Peck, 2012</xref>) on everyday mobilities and sociotechnical innovations in transport. The question here is not simply who will benefit when and where from the development and expansion of, say, autonomous vehicles and Mobility-as-a-Service (MaaS). It is just as much if and how such innovations will be co-opted by vested interests and elites or rather reshuffle existing socio-spatial stratifications and change discourses about rights, responsibilities, and opportunities with respect to transport and mobility. This brings us to another set of changes: over the last decade transport, from cycling to aviation, has become a quintessential site of contestation and the political &#224; la <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Mouffe (2005)</xref> &#8211; the domain of antagonism where &#8220;questions always involve decisions which require us to make a choice between conflicting alternatives&#8221; (page 10). In some ways, neoliberalisation, planetary urbanisation, the climate emergency, and now the COVID-19 pandemic create the &#8216;perfect storm&#8217; for questions regarding transport and mobility justice to become placed at the heart of broader discussions around fairness and justice. Automobility is increasingly the stuff of culture wars: Should this sociotechnical system be curbed and actively broken down because of detrimental effects on the environment, public health, and social equity? Or is it (still) to be harnessed because it enables upward social mobility and a right to a better life, tends to offer greater protection from infection than many other forms of transport, and can be substantially less polluting after electrification? Consider also how governmental interventions into the out-of-pocket costs of transport can trigger social unrest, from France's <italic>maillots jaunes</italic> to Brazil's attempt to raise public transport fares in 2013 (<xref rid="bb0370" ref-type="bibr">Verlinghieri and Venturini, 2018</xref>). Look finally at how bicycle activism has raised fundamental questions about how road space is allocated, who determines how public space is experienced and governed, and how change in urban transport and the city is enacted (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Blickstein and Hanson, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Furness, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Casta&#241;eda, 2020</xref>).</p>