<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par15">Global socioecological implications and justice implications are central to the EU bioeconomy for several reasons. The first concerns the EU colonial resource accumulation and contemporary vast carbon footprints (Gore and Alstig <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2020</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">b</xref>; UNDP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">2020</xref>). The second, the lack of domestic biocapacity in most EU countries and their reliance on imports (Hoff et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2018</xref>; Fuchs et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2020</xref>; Proskurina <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">2018</xref>; Hickel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2021</xref>). The third and final reason is the transition to bio-based, green, or low-carbon energy and economic systems, which in more than one way, and similarly to non-renewable counterparts, can and do contribute to extraction, extractivism, socioecological conflicts and various kinds of injustices. Building on Lerner&#8217;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2010</xref>) &#8216;sacrifice zones&#8217;, scholars have used the concept &#8216;green sacrifice zones&#8217; (Scott and Smith <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">2017</xref>; Zografos and Robbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>) to conceptualise situations where transition to green and renewable energy and economic systems leads to green grabbing, displacement, dispossession, exploitation and a range of other injustices towards marginalized groups and local indigenous and non-indigenous communities. Such sacrifice zones are reproduced in the process of developing green and renewable infrastructure (e.g. Brock et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2021</xref>; Dunlap and Arce <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2021</xref>; Sovacool et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2021</xref>), as well as in the process of implementing Eurocentric &#8216;green&#8217; policy solutions; the latter tend to favour scientific over local or indigenous knowledge systems, and elite groups over disadvantaged societal groups who are marginalized across various identity lines, from race to gender to class, etc. (Zografos and Robbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>). This leads to various forms of violence and injustices, including epistemic injustice (Harcourt and Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>; Rodr&#237;guez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2020</xref>).</p>