<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par17">Some of the most serious examples of violence and extraction are associated with biomass for production of biofuels (Bastos-Lima and Gupta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2014</xref>; Backhouse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2021</xref>), hydropower (Del Bene et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>) and wind energy (Dunlap and Arce <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2021</xref>), which lead to food insecurity, forced displacement, loss of livelihoods, oppression, dispossession and loss of rights and access to land and resources. Temper et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">2020</xref>) show that globally conflicts associated with biomass and hydropower extraction are comparable to those of extraction of non-renewables. Yet, the political momentum of decarbonization, bioeconomy and transition to green energy have helped reframe energy sources such as biomass and hydropower as &#8216;green&#8217; (Zarfl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">2014</xref>). Wind energy is argued to produce &#8216;infrastructural violence&#8217;, where communities are relocated or otherwise affected by heavy infrastructure (Dunlap and Arce <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2021</xref>). When locals resist the land grabs and dispossession this has led to physical violence, intimidation and in the worse cases death of activists (Butt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>; Menton and Le Billon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2021</xref>). Local resistance movements have nonetheless been effective in slowing down extractive projects worldwide (Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">2020</xref>). While conflicts and violence tend to be more severe in cases where indigenous and politically and socially marginalized groups are involved (Butt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>; Menton and Le Billon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2021</xref>), they occur across different geographies, including in EU countries (Brock et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2021</xref>; Sovacool et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2021</xref>).</p>