<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Nevertheless, research on climate education often focuses primarily or exclusively on students' knowledge of climate change, attending more closely to student understandings and misunderstandings than to other aspects of climate literacy (e.g., Pascua &amp; Chang, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). This narrower, knowledge&#8208;centric approach to climate literacy is one Busch and Rom&#225;n (<xref rid="ece35736-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) discuss in the K&#8208;12 educational context as &#8220;derived&#8221; climate science literacy, which they contrast with &#8220;fundamental&#8221; climate science literacy: an &#8220;ability to read, evaluate, and produce&#8221; climate&#8208;related scientific content, making scientific knowledge intelligible and actionable (Busch &amp; Rom&#225;n, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>, p. 121; see also Norris &amp; Phillips, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Yore, Bisanz, &amp; Hand, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Developing alongside this attention to both derived and fundamental scientific literacies, a growing body of scholarship has identified knowledge of social systems, actors, and practices as important aspects of scientific literacy, generally (e.g., Hand, Lawrence, &amp; Yore, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>; Hurd, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">1998</xref>), and climate science literacy, specifically (e.g., Gonz&#225;lez&#8208;Gaudiano &amp; Meira&#8208;Cartea, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Shwom, Isenhour, Jordan, McCright, &amp; Robinson, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Hurd (<xref rid="ece35736-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">1998</xref>), for instance, has characterized &#8220;[b]ehaviors associated with the production and utilization of science knowledge in human affairs&#8221; as &#8220;represent[ing] the civic basis of scientific literacy&#8221; (p. 413). For their parts, Shwom et al. (<xref rid="ece35736-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) have charged that while faulty models of the climate system impede climate literacy, &#8220;faulty models about social, political, and economic systems are just as damaging to climate literacy, given that they can foster misunderstanding about how those systems contribute to climate change as well as possibilities for mitigation and adaptation&#8221; (p. 377).</p>