<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Within the US, scholars have argued that American adults' perceptions of climate change can be grouped into six categories&#8212;alarmed, concerned, cautious, disengaged, doubtful, and dismissive (Maibach, Roser&#8208;Renouf, &amp; Leiserowitz, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>)&#8212;and, relatedly, that the best approach to communicating climate change with the public will vary with each of these groups (Roser&#8208;Renouf, Stenhouse, Rolfe&#8208;Redding, Maibach, &amp; Leiserowitz, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Similarly, when designing curricula and enacting pedagogy, it is important to remember that students are not merely &#8220;empty &#8216;mind[s]&#8217; passively open to the reception of deposits&#8221; (Freire, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>, p. 75). Instead, students arrive in courses with prior knowledges, beliefs, conceptual frameworks, and misconceptions that influence their engagements with course materials, and affect whether and how they learn course content (see, e.g., Aksit, McNeal, Gold, Libarkin, &amp; Harris, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Chi, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Gilbert &amp; Watts, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">1983</xref>; Rissler, Duncan, &amp; Caruso, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Students' classroom engagements with climate change are no exception to this rule (Dupigny&#8208;Giroux, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Lombardi &amp; Sinatra, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Previous research on college students has found that students generally agree that climate change is happening, but that they also harbor misconceptions regarding climate change (see, e.g., Pfautsch &amp; Gray, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Wachholz, Artz, &amp; Chene, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Fortunately, a study of 17 college students who took a series of sustainability&#8208;related courses found that instruction can improve climate literacy and certainty regarding climate change, while also increasing students' sense of urgency regarding climate change (Burkholder, Devereaux, Grady, Solitro, &amp; Mooney, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>).</p>