<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Even so, increased information related to climate change may, on its own, not cause significant changes in behavior or equip students to successfully combat what Gifford (<xref rid="ece35736-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) calls &#8220;the dragons of inaction&#8221; (see, e.g., Corner et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Gonz&#225;lez&#8208;Gaudiano &amp; Meira&#8208;Cartea, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Wachholz et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Zeidler &amp; Newton, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Apparently, there is a disconnect separating student certainty and concern about climate change from readiness to act in response to that certainty and concern. Exacerbating matters, students may feel fearful, sad, remorseful, despairing, and angry in response to climate change (Pfautsch &amp; Gray, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) and become more worried after instruction (Holthuis, Lotan, Saltzman, Mastrandrea, &amp; Wild, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). This affective impact of climate pedagogy is potentially dangerous, if it means that students leave a course feeling that there is nothing they can do to combat climate change. After all, a constructive sense that one can make a difference can be an important factor in whether students adopt pro&#8208;environmental behavior (Ojala, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) and an absence of self&#8208;efficacy can short&#8208;circuit climate action (Corner et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). In this way, increasing students' sense of urgency about climate change may have negative, unintended consequences, if this sense of urgency is not buoyed by and balanced with a sense of efficacy where climate action across scales is concerned. Instructors might be able to counter this potential negative consequence of instruction if they reimagine the classroom as a place where students not only gain knowledge about climate change and its impacts on different communities, but also gain knowledge about how to use that knowledge and leave feeling empowered to do so.</p>