<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Climate change has become an issue in electoral politics and the politics of planning, which has turned attention to how power relations shape these processes, and the presence of conflicts and trade&#8208;offs. For example, studies of the integration of climate concerns into conventional party politics highlight how issues surrounding risk, political resistance, and economic benefits are balanced and framed by elected politicians (Foss, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0128" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Mullin &amp; Rubado, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0210" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). As Aylett (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0050" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) observed, conflict and protest are both critical elements in the formulation of political priorities. There are no neutral pathways in the pursuit of complex objectives like urban resilience, and trade&#8208;offs are inherent to any prioritization process (Bahadur &amp; Tanner, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0053" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Brown, Dayal, &amp; Rumbaitis Del Rio, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0069" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Chu, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0097" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>; Muller, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0209" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Reed et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0233" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Weinstein, Rumbach, &amp; Sinha, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0290" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Trade&#8208;offs are better tackled through negotiation, shared learning, and deliberative decision&#8208;making processes. However, such inclusive processes rarely overcome underlying tensions, which can only be addressed through deep restructuring of political economies (Chu, Anguelovski, &amp; Roberts, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0094" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Moreover, there is a need to deliver empirical work that recognizes the formidable barriers to climate planning and action posed by vested interests (Francesch&#8208;Huidobro, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0129" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), the impact of perceptions of economic and political gains (Storbj&#246;rk &amp; Hjerpe, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0275" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), the interference of private companies in planning processes (Hrelja, Hjerpe, &amp; Storbj&#246;rk, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0156" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), conflicting interests across government levels and departments (Cousins, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0101" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Jaglin, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0163" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), elite capture (Berquist, Daniere, &amp; Drummond, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0064" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and corruption (Chirisa, Bandauko, Mazhindu, Kwangwama, &amp; Chikowore, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0093" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p>