<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">There is also a scholarly tradition examining the underlying causes behind the uneven distribution of urban emissions (Satterthwaite, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0255" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), the spatial unevenness of local climate change action or inaction (Dierwechter, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0108" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), the integration of justice dimensions into local climate places (Schrock, Bassett, &amp; Green, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0257" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), and the interrelationships between risk and gender (Tibesigwa &amp; Visser, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0277" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) or income and risk (Rasch, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0230" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). This research has led to increasing recognition that the political&#8208;economic structures that produce and reinforce inequalities are the same drivers that create climate vulnerabilities and risk. Efforts to build elite environments simultaneously contribute to informality and marginalization (Rumbach, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0249" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Such underlying causes of vulnerability and risk need to be addressed through strategies that seek transformation of political, social, and economic institutions (Chu et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0094" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Haque et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0140" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Revi et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0236" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Similarly, attention to gentrification in the context of low carbon programs points to risks of displacement as a result of energy efficiency retrofits (Bouzarovski, Frankowski, &amp; Herrero, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0067" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) or beautification projects that may result in land grabbing processes (Anguelovski, Iraz&#225;bal&#8208;Zurita, &amp; Connolly, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). This has led to calls that seek to theorize climate change justice at the local scale, for example, with the distinction between injustice caused through omission or commission (Anguelovski et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), between procedure and outcome (Reckien et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0231" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), or through the development of a rights&#8208;based understanding of climate justice (Ziervogel et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0301" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Ziervogel, Shale, &amp; Du, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0302" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). These initial advances point to a movement from a critical analysis of contemporary neoliberalism as a driver of climate injustice towards propositional theories with practical recommendations to redress such injustices in an urban context.</p>