<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para320">Conservation science is a crisis discipline,<xref rid="bib117" ref-type="bibr"><sup>117</sup></xref> and in its short history has developed methods parallel to crisis management in public health.<xref rid="bib118" ref-type="bibr"><sup>118</sup></xref> Both disciplines are confronted with the need for urgent action, evidence-based policy support, and emergency response, while often facing insufficient resources<xref rid="bib119" ref-type="bibr"><sup>119</sup></xref> (eg, responding to discovery of a pathogen or newly established invasive species for which swift control is imperative).<xref rid="bib120" ref-type="bibr"><sup>120</sup></xref> Similar to its initial wartime application, the regrettable necessity of triaging has also been recognised in conservation,<xref rid="bib118" ref-type="bibr"><sup>118</sup></xref> highlighting the need for careful prioritisation of actions. Decision science in conservation can provide transparent ways of identifying the optimal combination and timing of actions from data acquisition to direct intervention to maximise successful outcomes or minimise likely losses within fixed budgets,<xref rid="bib121" ref-type="bibr"><sup>121</sup></xref> or to optimise return on conservation investment.<xref rid="bib122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>, <xref rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref> The decision science requirement for clear definition of objectives adds to transparent decision-making processes, and methods can incorporate diverse, even divergent, objectives.<xref rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>, <xref rid="bib124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref> Acknowledging and incorporating the probability of programme success or failure<xref rid="bib125" ref-type="bibr"><sup>125</sup></xref> can further affect which management actions are considered optimal, and with the current realisation of dramatic sudden losses in budget, personnel and logistical agility, we foresee that inclusion of these concepts will increase in conservation management planning. As for reducing mortality and economic costs associated with pandemic events, it has been proposed that maintaining intact habitat, by reducing deforestation and regulating wildlife trade, would yield a high return on investment, supporting the adoption of preventive approaches targeting the drivers of emerging infectious diseases.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> The parallels between management of conservation and public health crises can lead to future advances in decision theory relevant to, and essential for, both endeavours.</p>