<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The approach of combining emotions, as <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Rees et al. (2014)</xref> presented, nevertheless seems to be promising. When considering emotions, it is important to note that they rarely occur in isolation, but often as a blend. A current qualitative study (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Marczak et al., 2022</xref>) shows that the emotional landscape concerning climate change is not limited to categories like, e.g., &#8220;anger,&#8221; but rather includes various specific emotions such as exasperation, irritation, frustration, impatience, annoyance, disgust, anger, and rage, as these are related to a perceived lack of commitment to climate action (these are only the emotions in the area of &#8220;anger&#8221;). A quantitative study (<xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Stanley et al., 2021</xref>) confirmed that feeling each of three common climate emotions, fear, anger, and sadness, was a strong predictor of also experiencing the other two and hence the role of emotions under realistic conditions and not just in isolation from other emotions should be investigated. In line with this, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Chapman et al. (2017)</xref> criticized the current research for overemphasizing the role of single emotions and, as a result, more studies investigated emotional profiles instead of single emotions in the context of the environment. <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Fernando et al. (2014)</xref> found, e.g., that sympathy for specific groups of people alone hardly produces intentions to act, but instead requires a (pro-social) emotional profile of sufficient sympathy, shame, and anger at the government and one&#8217;s ingroup, as well as some anger about those affected and some pride. Another example is the study of <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2018)</xref>, who found an emotional profile that was associated with high acceptance of environmental protection measures. This profile consisted of higher values for anger, anxiety, guilt, shame, powerlessness, and desperation (called the self-blame profile). Therefore, addressing emotions as patterns rather than single individual phenomena seems promising to consider in further investigations on pro-environmental behavior and intention.</p>