<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The aim of this study was to investigate the role of justice sensitivity, moral disengagement, and moral emotions on pro-environmental intention and behavior. In Study 1, moral disengagement in high carbon behavior was able to significantly and negatively predict past pro-environmental behavior, while the four justice sensitivities did not. A pro-environmental intention was significantly predicted by moral disengagement in high carbon behavior (negatively) and observer sensitivity (positively). Therefore, Hypotheses 1 and 2 were only partially supported. An attempt to replicate these results in a larger sample (Study 2) with the exact carbon footprint calculator as a proxy for pro-environmental behavior failed. However, the pro-environmental <italic>intention</italic> was significantly predicted in the larger sample by justice sensitivities, moral disengagement, and moral emotions. In the final model, after a backward elimination process, perpetrator sensitivity, guilt, and hubristic pride emerged as significant positive predictors and beneficiary sensitivity and moral disengagement as significant negative predictors. Victim sensitivity, shame, and gratitude were excluded because their explanatory power was too low compared to the other predictors. Consequently, Hypothesis 3 was only partially supported. Based on the results, lower moral disengagement served as the best predictor for (more) pro-environmental intention and behavior in both studies. However, an exploratory analysis in Study 1 showed that past behavior was an even stronger predictor of pro-environmental intention. Whereas beneficiary sensitivity was a significant negative predictor in the final model on pro-environmental intention (Model B), its direct effect on pro-environmental intention in the mediation analysis was positive, as hypothesized. In line with Hypothesis 4, the predictions of perpetrator and beneficiary sensitivity were mediated by guilt, which is the emotion that occurs at high levels in each of these two justice sensitivities.</p>