<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Consistent with Hypothesis 5, victim sensitivity was positively related to moral disengagement, which is a strong negative predictor of pro-environmental behavior and intention in our study. Individuals with high victim sensitivity thus are more prone to morally disengage and justify their actions instead of taking responsibility. As we outlined in the Introduction, pro-environmental behavior requires accepting responsibility. We regard taking responsibility and moral disengagement as opposites, especially in the area of pro-environmental intention and behavior. <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Detert et al. (2008)</xref> found factors that inhibit or facilitate moral disengagement. While empathy, perspective-taking, moral identity, female gender, and an internal locus of control were found to be inhibitors of moral disengagement, trait cynicism and an external locus of control were found to facilitate moral disengagement. According to our findings, victim sensitivity can be added to the list of facilitators. Therefore, people with high victim sensitivity, who rather tend to morally disengage than to take responsibility are the brakemen of socio-ecological transformation, as they are not willing to act for the sake of the common good but only for their own benefit. The twisted part is that these people see themselves as victims. They argue, for example, that something is taken away from them or that they are disadvantaged. This can be observed in various social debates as the following two examples show: First, in Germany, members of the right-wing populist party Alternative f&#252;r Deutschland (AfD) have been portraying themselves as victims of political correctness for years as a political strategy (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Heinze, 2021</xref>). Second, deniers of the COVID-19 pandemic reinforce this perception by wearing a Jewish badge (historic symbol of discrimination, originally used to discriminate Jewish people in Nazi-Germany) with the inscription &#8220;unvaccinated&#8221; (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#246;hlich, 2022</xref>). What is striking here is the general pattern of using self-staging as a victim as a political strategy in radical right-wing movements (<xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Wei&#223;, 2011</xref>), which in turn increasingly attracts victim sensitives. A current study by <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Jahnke et al. (2020)</xref> provides empirical evidence that victim sensitivity predicted stronger right-wing orientations as well as general and right-wing radicalization.</p>