<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Although not all justice sensitivities significantly predicted pro-environmental behavior and pro-environmental intention in all models, most of our hypotheses were supported. The considered constructs performed better at predicting pro-environmental intention than behavior and past behavior. This could be due to the intention-behavior gap, which describes that intended behavior is not always implemented (<xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Sheeran, 2002</xref>). It is conceivable that the constructs used here refer only to intention, but not to implementation. Also, we may have included too many and too similar predictors. Although multicollinearity was absent (except for Model A in Study 1), perpetrator, beneficiary, and observer sensitivity showed high concordance in previous studies (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">M&#252;nscher, 2017</xref>). Therefore, some authors (e.g., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Jahnke et al., 2020</xref>) use only one pro-social justice sensitivity. Another approach could be to aggregate these measures (e.g., by means of factor scores) into an umbrella score for pro-social sensitivities. We further assume that the high predictive power of moral disengagement undermines the prediction of the justice sensitivities, especially the similar effect of victim sensitivity. However, moral disengagement in high carbon behavior and victim sensitivity were correlated but not as high as they would reflect an overarching construct. Although any association with pro-environmental <italic>behavior</italic> was weak in both studies (which also means in the two different scales that were used), we found that victim sensitivity and moral disengagement negatively predicted pro-environmental <italic>intention</italic>, while perpetrator, beneficiary, and observer sensitivity positively predicted pro-environmental intention. This may be explained by different degrees of responsibility taking: Those who perceive injustice from the perspective of the beneficiary, observer, or perpetrator are more likely to feel responsible (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Ehrhardt-Madapathi et al., 2018</xref>). A greater sense of responsibility, in turn, is a promising predictor to engage in pro-environmental behavior (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Kollmuss and Agyeman, 2002</xref>).</p>