<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0175">Global challenges do not have national borders. Some think that climate changes occasionally occur on Earth and have nothing to do with them. Currently, practically, no part of the world is immune to COVID-19, and this is also true of global warming and the prospects for changing climates. COVID-19 has created an opportunity for solidarity among all people that have never been seen before. This is precisely the tool that must be used to deal with climate change. The principle that prevention is better than treatment, a fixed rule in health and medicine, should be adopted to slow global warming and reduce climate change. It will be much easier to challenge the momentum of global warming now, than, it will be to deal with the enormous consequences we face with changing climates. In the post-COVID-19 world, economic redevelopment has become a priority for environmental concerns. The people and governments of the world, by staying at home, forgoing demonstrations, and caring for and protecting each other, have shown that they can unite to prevent disasters and save humanity. The same decisive spirit is needed to deal with climate crises. However, there is a risk that if people abandon public transportation because of the perceived health threat, it poses and returns to their cars, greenhouse gas emissions will be higher than before. Plans should be drawn to encourage people to invest in renewable and low-carbon energy sources. Today's reduced carbon emissions are temporary because there is insufficient infrastructure to migrate to primary reliance on renewable energy; we remain dependent on fossil fuels. We find ourselves (inadvertently) in the world's most massive experiment to reduce, if not halt, the combustion of carbon. However, the oil industry has been the primary engine of technological progress and innovation for decades, and it will be challenging to dispense with it, if not overcome its political power, to achieve clean energy. Clean air and stable climates will only return when we move to make concerted commitments and changes to develop low-carbon economies in the future.</p>