<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par47">Although this study provides important contributions to the literature, there are a number of limitations that should be noted. First, we drew on cross-sectional data and therefore can only describe associations between constructs and not directionality. For example, it is possible that those who are experiencing mental health distress are more vulnerable to the impairing aspects of CCA and have reduced capacity to engage in collective action. Additionally, there were several limitations to the measure used to assess individual climate action, including that some items involved emotional as well as action-related responses and that the measure did not include the full range of individual actions that participants described in their&#160;open-ended responses. Future research is needed to develop more comprehensive measures of individual action to address climate change and to investigate whether a more comprehensive measures may yield difference results. This study also utilized a small, self-selected, non-representative student sample, with those more invested in addressing climate change likely self-selecting into the study. Data were collected in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic and remote learning at most universities, which may have contributed to heightened levels of distress. Future research should examine these constructs in more diverse populations, particularly with respect to race, geography, and education-level, as well as within clinical or treatment-seeking samples. Finally, while the qualitative data included provided a deeper understanding of participants&#8217; experiences than the quantitative data alone, in-depth interviews or focus groups would allow for greater insight into their experiences of CCA. Despite these drawbacks, the current study provides an important step towards understanding CCA among emerging adults and how it relates to clinical measures of MDD and GAD, as well as pointing to the potential of collective action to contribute to the well-being of those experiencing CCA.</p>