<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Epigenet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ Epigenet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Epigenetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2058-5888</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9580270</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36268472</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eep/dvac019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dvac019</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI02302</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COP27 Climate Change Conference: urgent action needed for Africa and the world</article-title><subtitle>Wealthy nations must step up support for Africa and vulnerable countries in addressing past, present and future impacts of climate change</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Atwoli</surname><given-names>Lukoye</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, East African Medical Journal</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Erhabor</surname><given-names>Gregory E</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, West African Journal of Medicine</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gbakima</surname><given-names>Aiah A</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, Sierra Leone Journal of Biomedical Research</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haileamlak</surname><given-names>Abraham</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, Ethiopian Journal of Health Sciences</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ntumba</surname><given-names>Jean-Marie Kayembe</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Chief Editor, Annales Africaines de Medecine</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kigera</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, Annals of African Surgery</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laybourn-Langton</surname><given-names>Laurie</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>University of Exeter</institution>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mash</surname><given-names>Bob</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, African Journal of Primary Health Care &#x00026; Family Medicine</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muhia</surname><given-names>Joy</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>London School of Medicine and Tropical Hygiene</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mulaudzi</surname><given-names>Fhumulani Mavis</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, Curationis</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ofori-Adjei</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, Ghana Medical Journal</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okonofua</surname><given-names>Friday</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, African Journal of Reproductive Health</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rashidian</surname><given-names>Arash</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Executive Editor, Eastern Mediterranean Health Journal</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>El-Adawy</surname><given-names>Maha</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Director of Health Promotion, Eastern Mediterranean Health Journal</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sidib&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Siaka</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Director of Publication, Mali M&#x000e9;dical</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Snouber</surname><given-names>Abdelmadjid</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Managing Editor, Journal de la Facult&#x000e9; de M&#x000e9;decine d&#x02019;Oran</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tumwine</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, African Health Sciences</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yassien</surname><given-names>Mohammad Sahar</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, Evidence-Based Nursing Research</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yonga</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Managing Editor, East African Medical Journal</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zakhama</surname><given-names>Lilia</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Editor-in-Chief, La Tunisie M&#x000e9;dicale</institution>
</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zielinski</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name><!--chris.zielinski@ukhealthalliance.org--><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp"/><aff>
<institution>University of Winchester</institution>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001">*Correspondence address. E-mail: <email xlink:href="chris.zielinski@ukhealthalliance.org">chris.zielinski@ukhealthalliance.org</email></corresp><p>This Editorial is being published simultaneously in multiple journals. For the full list of journals see: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.bmj.com/content/full-list-authors-and-signatories-climate-emergency-editorial-october-2022" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.bmj.com/content/full-list-authors-and-signatories-climate-emergency-editorial-october-2022</ext-link>.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-10-19"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>dvac019</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="dvac019.pdf"/><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000066</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>5K01ES032048</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000066</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>ES017885</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000066</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>ES026697</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000066</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>R35ES031686</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000066</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>T32ES007062</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>The 2022 report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) paints a dark picture of the future of life on earth, characterised by ecosystem collapse, species extinction, and climate hazards such as heatwaves and floods [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. These are all linked to physical and mental health problems, with direct and indirect consequences of increased morbidity and mortality. To avoid these catastrophic health effects across all regions of the globe, there is broad agreement&#x02014;as 231 health journals argued together in 2021&#x02014;that the rise in global temperature must be limited to less than 1.5<sup>o</sup>C compared with pre-industrial levels.</p><p>While the Paris Agreement of 2015 outlines a global action framework that incorporates providing climate finance to developing countries, this support has yet to materialise [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. COP27 is the fifth Conference of the Parties (COP) to be organised in Africa since its inception in 1995. Ahead of this meeting, we&#x02014;as health journal editors from across the continent&#x02014;call for urgent action to ensure it is the COP that finally delivers climate justice for Africa and vulnerable countries. This is essential not just for the health of those countries, but for the health of the whole world.</p><sec id="s2"><title>Africa Has Suffered Disproportionately Although It Has Done Little to Cause the Crisis</title><p>The climate crisis has had an impact on the environmental and social determinants of health across Africa, leading to devastating health effects [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Impacts on health can result directly from environmental shocks and indirectly through socially mediated effects [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Climate change-related risks in Africa include flooding, drought, heatwaves, reduced food production, and reduced labour productivity [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Droughts in sub-Saharan Africa have tripled between 1970-1979 and 2010-2019 [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In 2018, devastating cyclones impacted 2.2 million people in Malawi, Mozambique, and Zimbabwe [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In west and central Africa, severe flooding resulted in mortality and forced migration from loss of shelter, cultivated land, and livestock [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Changes in vector ecology brought about by floods and damage to environmental hygiene have led to increases in diseases across sub-Saharan Africa, with rises in malaria, dengue fever, Lassa fever, Rift Valley fever, Lyme disease, Ebola virus, West Nile virus, and other infections [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Rising sea levels reduce water quality, leading to water-borne diseases, including diarrhoeal diseases, a leading cause of mortality in Africa [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Extreme weather damages water and food supply, increasing food insecurity and malnutrition, which causes 1.7 million deaths annually in Africa [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. According to the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, malnutrition has increased by almost 50% since 2012, owing to the central role agriculture plays in African economies [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Environmental shocks and their knock-on effects also cause severe harm to mental health [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In all, it is estimated that the climate crisis has destroyed a fifth of the gross domestic product (GDP) of the countries most vulnerable to climate shocks [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>The damage to Africa should be of supreme concern to all nations. This is partly for moral reasons. It is highly unjust that the most impacted nations have contributed the least to global cumulative emissions, which are driving the climate crisis and its increasingly severe effects. North America and Europe have contributed 62% of carbon dioxide emissions since the Industrial Revolution, whereas Africa has contributed only 3% [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>The Fight against the Climate Crisis Needs All Hands on Deck</title><p>Yet it is not just for moral reasons that all nations should be concerned for Africa. The acute and chronic impacts of the climate crisis create problems like poverty, infectious disease, forced migration, and conflict that spread through globalised systems [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These knock-on impacts affect all nations. COVID-19 served as a wake-up call to these global dynamics and it is no coincidence that health professionals have been active in identifying and responding to the consequences of growing systemic risks to health. But the lessons of the COVID-19 pandemic should not be limited to pandemic risk [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Instead, it is imperative that the suffering of frontline nations, including those in Africa, be the core consideration at COP27: in an interconnected world, leaving countries to the mercy of environmental shocks creates instability that has severe consequences for all nations.</p><p>The primary focus of climate summits remains to rapidly reduce emissions so that global temperature rises are kept to below 1.5&#x000b0;C. This will limit the harm. But, for Africa and other vulnerable regions, this harm is already severe. Achieving the promised target of providing $100bn of climate finance a year is now globally critical if we are to forestall the systemic risks of leaving societies in crisis. This can be done by ensuring these resources focus on increasing resilience to the existing and inevitable future impacts of the climate crisis, as well as on supporting vulnerable nations to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions: a parity of esteem between adaptation and mitigation. These resources should come through grants not loans, and be urgently scaled up before the current review period of 2025. They must put health system resilience at the forefront, as the compounding crises caused by the climate crisis often manifest in acute health problems Financing adaptation will be more cost effective than relying on disaster relief.</p><p>Some progress has been made on adaptation in Africa and around the world, including early warning systems and infrastructure to defend against extremes. But frontline nations are not compensated for impacts from a crisis they did not cause. This is not only unfair, but also drives the spiral of global destabilisation, as nations pour money into responding to disasters, but can no longer afford to pay for greater resilience or to reduce the root problem through emissions reductions. A financing facility for loss and damage must now be introduced, providing additional resources beyond those given for mitigation and adaptation. This must go beyond the failures of COP26 where the suggestion of such a facility was downgraded to &#x0201c;a dialogue&#x0201d; [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>The climate crisis is a product of global inaction and comes at great cost, not only to disproportionately impacted African countries, but to the whole world. Africa is united with other frontline regions in urging wealthy nations to finally step up, if for no other reason than that the crises in Africa will sooner rather than later spread and engulf all corners of the globe, by which time it may be too late to effectively respond. If so far, they have failed to be persuaded by moral arguments, then hopefully their self-interest will now prevail.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="s4"><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Commissioned; not externally peer reviewed.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>In the interest of transparency the authors wish to declare the following roles and relationships: James Kigera is the Ex-Officio, President and Secretary of the Kenya Orthopedic Association; Paul Yonga been paid to speak or participate at events by Novartis, bioMerieux and Pfizer; Chris Zielinski is a paid consultant for the UK Health Alliance on Climate Change; Joy Muhia is an unpaid board member of the International Working Group for Health systems strengthening; David Ofori-Adjei has a relationship with GLICO Healthcare Ltd. The authors declare no further conflicts of interest beyond those inherent in the editorial roles listed.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>IPCC</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>Climate change 2022: impacts, adaptation and vulnerability</article-title>. <source>Working Group II Contribution to the IPCC Sixth Assessment Report</source>. <publisher-name>IPCC</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>UN</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Paris Agreement: United Nations</article-title>. <publisher-name>UN</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.un.org/en/climatechange/paris-agreement" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.un.org/en/climatechange/paris-agreement</ext-link> (12 September 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kaddu</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gebru</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kibaya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal>
<article-title>Climate change and health in sub-Saharan Africa: the case of Uganda</article-title>. <source>Climate Investment Funds</source>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>WHO</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>Strengthening health resilience to climate change</article-title>. <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>, <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Trisos</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adelekan</surname><given-names>IO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Totin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> Africa. In: <article-title>Climate change 2022: impacts, adaptation, and vulnerability</article-title>. <source>Working Group II Contribution to the IPCC Sixth Assessment Report</source>. <publisher-name>IPCC</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg2/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg2/</ext-link> (26 September 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Bank</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>climate change adaptation and economic transformation in Sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <publisher-name>World Bank</publisher-name>, <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Opoku</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leal Filho</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal>
<article-title>Climate change and health preparedness in Africa: Analysing trends in six African countries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<page-range>4672</page-range>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munslow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Climate change, health, and conflict in Africa&#x02019;s arc of instability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Perspect Public Health</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34787038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Stawicki</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papadimos</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galwankar</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal>
<part-title>Reflections on climate change and public health in Africa in an era of global pandemic</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">Contemporary Developments and Perspectives in International Health Security</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Intechopen</publisher-name>, <year>2021</year>, <page-range>2</page-range>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>African Climate Policy Centre</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>Climate Change and Health in Africa: Issues and Options</article-title>. <year>2013</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://archive.uneca.org/sites/default/files/PublicationFiles/policy_brief_12_climate_change_and_health_in_africa_issues_and_options.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://archive.uneca.org/sites/default/files/PublicationFiles/policy_brief_12_climate_change_and_health_in_africa_issues_and_options.pdf</ext-link> (12 September 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<article-title>Climate Change is an Increasing Threat to Africa</article-title>
<year>2020</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/news/climate-change-is-an-increasing-threat-to-africa" ext-link-type="uri">https://unfccc.int/news/climate-change-is-an-increasing-threat-to-africa</ext-link> (12 September 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Atwoli</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muhia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merali</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mental health and climate change in Africa</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BJPsych Int</italic></source><year>2022</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/bjpsych-international/article/mental-health-and-climate-change-in-africa/65A414598BA1D620F4208A9177EED94B" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/bjpsych-international/article/mental-health-and-climate-change-in-africa/65A414598BA1D620F4208A9177EED94B</ext-link> (26 September 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Vulnerable Twenty Group</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>Climate vulnerable economies loss report</article-title>. <publisher-name>Vulnerable Twenty Group</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ritchie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Who has Contributed Most to Global CO2 Emissions?</article-title><source>Our World in Data</source>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/contributed-most-global-co2" ext-link-type="uri">https://ourworldindata.org/contributed-most-global-co2</ext-link> (12 September 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bilotta</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Botti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Paving the way for greener central banks. Current trends and future developments around the globe</article-title>. <publisher-name>Edizioni Nuova Cultura for Istituto Affari Internazionali (IAI)</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>WHO</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>COP26 special report on climate change and health: the health argument for climate action</article-title>. <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Al-Mandhari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Yousfi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malkawi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal>
<article-title>&#x0201c;Our planet, our health&#x0201d;: saving lives, promoting health and attaining well-being by protecting the planet &#x02013; the Eastern Mediterranean perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">East Mediterr Health J</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26719/2022.28.4.247</pub-id> (26 September 2022, date last accessed).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35545904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabbatiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McSweeney</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal>
<article-title>COP26: Key Outcomes Agreed at the UN Climate Talks in Glasgow</article-title>. <source>Carbon Brief [Internet]</source>. <year>2021</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.carbonbrief.org/cop26-key-outcomes-agreed-at-the-un-climate-talks-in-glasgow/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.carbonbrief.org/cop26-key-outcomes-agreed-at-the-un-climate-talks-in-glasgow/</ext-link> (12 September 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>