<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In WA, we can learn from the oldest continuing living culture developed over tens of thousands of years to live sustainably with this environment in ways that decrease risks associated with &#8216;natural disasters&#8217; like bushfires and adapting to a changing climate. Non&#8208;Aboriginal people have much to learn from Aboriginal cultures. Robertson and Barrow explain that the Nyoongar people in South Western WA have developed a &#8216;value&#8208;based, highly cooperative society&#8217;, which enabled them to use available resources to respond to climate change, including a 10&#8201;000&#8201;year drought.<xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> At the same time, climate change poses multiple threats to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander (henceforth Aboriginal) people's wellbeing, exacerbating pre&#8208;existing disadvantages in health, education, employment, poverty and incarceration.<xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> (We use the term Aboriginal to refer to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander peoples of Australia. We acknowledge that Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander peoples may identify with their local clans or group name and mean no disrespect in using the collective term Aboriginal. We use the term First Nations to refer to the Indigenous peoples of the world.) The WA climate health public inquiry's final report highlighted the long history of Aboriginal stewardship of WA lands and waters and that this is as critical now as it has ever been. The WA health system must engage and co&#8208;design with Aboriginal Elders, peoples, organisations and communities, and respect Aboriginal knowledges and expertise.<xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> For many Aboriginal people, climate change and environmental degradation began with colonisation, which contributes to intergenerational trauma; yet research and solutions rarely focus on this (Box&#160;<xref rid="jpc15649-fea-0001" ref-type="boxed-text">1</xref>).</p>