<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par6">Like the NLRA, most state collective bargaining laws also allowed collection of fees for representation, often denominated as fair share fees, except in those states with right-to-work laws. In 1977, the Supreme Court upheld fair share fees as against constitutional challenge in <italic>Abood v. Detroit Board of Education</italic> (<italic>Abood</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1977</xref>), but in 2018, after decades of effort, the organizations and individuals opposed to unions succeeded in convincing the Supreme Court to reverse <italic>Abood</italic> and hold that fair share fees for government employees violate the First Amendment (<italic>Janus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2018</xref>, 2460). Nothing really changed between <italic>Abood</italic> and <italic>Janus</italic> but the Court. Reconsidering <italic>Abood</italic>, the Court majority concluded that collecting such fees impaired the free speech rights of employees compelled to support the union, even when the fees were used only to support collective bargaining and contract administration (<italic>Janus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2018</xref>, 2460&#8211;61, 2464). Rejecting the distinction that <italic>Abood</italic> made between the union&#8217;s political speech and collective bargaining and contract administration, the Court emphasized that public sector bargaining is &#8220;inherently political&#8221; (<italic>Janus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2018</xref>, 2458). The Court went on to find, contrary to the <italic>Abood</italic> Court, that the interests in labor peace and stability and avoiding free riders (those who benefit from union representation without paying for it) did not justify the infringement on speech rights (<italic>Janus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2018</xref>, 2466, 2469). The decision invalidated thousands of collective bargaining agreements in multiple states, all negotiated in reliance on the Court&#8217;s earlier decision in <italic>Abood</italic> and valid state laws enacted in accord with that decision (<italic>Janus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2018</xref>, 2499).</p>