<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para260">Sustainable investment strategies, such as investment in conservation, can be utilised to mitigate the COVID-19 pandemic's economic effects while simultaneously addressing drivers of zoonotic disease emergence. The economic downturn associated with the COVID-19 pandemic has seen governments globally reacting with a range of fiscal responses to prevent or alleviate national and regional declines in economic activity and stability.<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr"><sup>83</sup></xref> Investment in conservation is crucial for preventing biodiversity declines<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64</sup></xref> and for addressing the key drivers of zoonotic disease. Many conservation practices can be directly linked to managing zoonotic disease risk, such as safeguarding remaining tropical forests<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> and protecting predators and scavengers.<xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr"><sup>96</sup></xref> Directing funding towards conservation actions and promotion of environmental sustainability can be utilised as a recovery mechanism during and following the pandemic, either alongside or as an alternative to other investment strategies, and can be targeted to prevent future zoonotic disease emergence and its potential for substantial global impact. For example, the state government of Western Australia announced in October, 2020, that their COVID-19 recovery plan will include investment of almost AU$67 million over 4 years to increase the state's existing network of protected areas and to fund their Parks and Wildlife Service infrastructure,<xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr"><sup>97</sup></xref> an action which can bolster the state's tourism sector while simultaneously supporting conservation. Similar fiscal policy approaches could reform existing subsidies for forestry, agriculture, mining, and energy production to better support biodiversity conservation and sustainability.<xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr"><sup>92</sup></xref>
</p>