<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para270">Redirecting subsidies that do not promote sustainable socioeconomic recovery, and shifting the policies that they promote to fund conservation-centric activities, such as sustainable agriculture, natural capital projects, and new energy technologies, could safeguard industries and economic stability while promoting practices that address zoonotic disease drivers,<xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr"><sup>92</sup></xref> reducing the risks of future regional and global health crises. For example, global agricultural subsidies alone are estimated at over US$700 billion annually,<xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr"><sup>98</sup></xref> but commonly drive environmental degradation, unsustainable production, provide insufficient social benefits and do not promote, in some cases, environmental and social responsibility initiatives such as the UN Sustainable Development Goals.<xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>, <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref> There are multiple synergies available to explore in the achievement of sustainable development, zoonotic disease risk minimisation, and pandemic recovery, and these should be identified and integrated into national and global policy with urgency.<xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr"><sup>101</sup></xref> For example, new government subsidies aimed at economic recovery during and following the COVID-19 pandemic provide an opportunity to enable a better balance between swift recovery and long-term biodiversity and ecosystem health targets, which will also support the prevention of future pandemics. These subsidies can help promote job creation in areas such as sustainable agriculture, resource recovery and recycling, clean energy, sustainable urban planning, and ecosystem restoration, and replace some subsidies for activities that, while boosting economies, have trade-offs such as promoting deforestation, wildlife trafficking, livestock disease risk, and increased greenhouse emissions.<xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>, <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>
</p>