<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Human mobility to parks can be driven by the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic in different ways. Recent studies pointed out that some places with strict NPI policies or having people with risk&#8208;averse attitudes might result in the overall increase in social confinement which led to reductions in human mobility (Chan et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). However, others have suggested that people have substantially used parks as a substitute for indoor fitness and recreation, leading to an increasing trend of visitations to open spaces and public parks during the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic (Geng et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Volenec et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0047" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Public parks and open spaces serve an important societal function as recreation spaces for diverse communities of people to support community cohesion, city sustainability, and human physical and mental health (Bedimo&#8208;Rung et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Ulrich &amp; Addoms,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>). Under the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic, quarantine/self&#8208;isolation, potential health issues, limited outdoor and social activities, and other pandemic&#8208;driven stressors all yielded negative impacts on human health and wellbeing (Geng et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Accessibility to parks and open green spaces becomes particularly essential since (a) those places often allow people to conduct their recreation behaviors following the social distancing protocols to avoid the risks (Volenec et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0047" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), and (b) recreation behaviors and physical activities can mitigate the pandemic stress and benefit the overall health condition (Xie et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0053" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).</p>