<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Besides the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic, another crisis that complicates people's recreation behavior and mobility to the parks was the massive, severe wildfires and the wildfire&#8208;induced air pollution in the western and central US. Global climate change promotes the conditions on which the potential and severity of the wildfires depend, including the increases in the frequency and intensity of heat waves and drought (Jones et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Xu et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0054" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Until October 2020, over 44,714 wildfires were occurring in the western and central US, associated with over 7.8 million acres of burned areas (Insurance Information Institute,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Uncontrolled wildfires can impact human recreation behaviors and activities, although the available evidence of the impact of wildfires on recreation demand is ambiguous (Nobel et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The wildfire&#8208;induced smoke often consists of highly elevated concentrations of fine particulate matter, carbon monoxide, nitrogen oxides, and volatile organic compounds, which pose major impacts to animal and human health (Tao et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; D. Yang et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0056" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Previous studies demonstrated a significant association between wildfire smoke exposure and risk of respiratory illness in humans (DeFlorio&#8208;Barker et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; H&#228;nninen et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Moore et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). The wildfire&#8208;induced air pollution can even be transported over a long range (e.g., over 1,000&#160;km) and cause the illness and death of humans there (Kollanus et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). However, some other studies also found that wildfires can increase visitations to parks close to wildfires due to people's curiosity of the wildfire events and their impacts (S&#225;nchez et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0041" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Thus, wildfires can drive human mobility in different directions, which might complicate human's recreation behaviors during the pandemic.</p>