<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par30">Applying the theoretical framework outlined above to the EU bioeconomy policy described in &#8220;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">From a policy of green growth to a practice of green sacrifice zones</xref>&#8221;, I first identify the dominant approaches and logics in the EU bioeconomy that act as barriers to socioecological justice and transformations, and then propose alternative ways and logics to support just transformations within the EU bioeconomy in its global context. More attention is given to the alternatives, rather than the better-known barriers and problems. The barriers include:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p id="Par31">Framing the web of life (nature) as a resource and service provider for humans, which is based on and strengthens extractive and &#8216;rent-seeking&#8217; behaviour and relations to nature and at best promotes market-friendly nature-based solutions, such as carbon sequestration and trading. Responding to this framing calls for reimagining the dominant Eurocentric human&#8211;nature relationality and for abandoning human&#8211;nature and other forms of duality (Biermann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020</xref>; Gebara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>; Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>). Relationality concerns the broader way we humans view, live and relate to the world around us. It refers to an idea that humanity is embedded and relationally constituted within it (Gebara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>, p.&#160;238).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="Par32">Dominance of green growth logic and technoscientific policy solutions that promote large-scale economic and industrial activities at the expense of socioecological burdens and small-scale technologies and activities. This approach does not question the current production and consumption levels and prioritizes industrial development that comes at the expense of small-scale, community-based and local economic activities, and the sociocultural and socioecological sustainability (O'Neill <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">2020</xref>; Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p id="Par33">A limited approach to socioecological justice, where only procedural and distributive justice elements are visible, but limited to key stakeholder participation (i.e. European businesses, industry, policymakers and research institutions) and to equitable distribution of job opportunities. Global socioecological injustices, historical, colonial and current exploitation and inequalities related to climate change responsibility and ecological footprints between different societal groups and countries are ignored in the EU bioeconomy.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iv)</label><p id="Par34">EU global leadership and competitiveness in globalized bioeconomic markets as a goal, which motivates relocation of socioecological burdens of EU bioeconomy to its domestic and global peripheries. This furthers reproduction of neo-imperial and neo-colonial relations with the countries in the Global South in the name of European competitiveness, development and carbon-neural economy.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(v)</label><p id="Par35">Hegemonic politico-economic structures and actor coalitions in charge of EU bioeconomy, including international economic organizations, such as OECD, and transnational businesses. These actor coalitions and their policy initiatives and decisions cooperate with state structures, overlooking the legal plurality and indigenous structures as well as state coercion and violence. Recentralization and state-centred initiatives are reproduced in the countries where international policies are implemented, which can lead to further marginalization and violence (Harcourt and Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>; Ramcilovic-Suominen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2021</xref>).</p></list-item></list></p>