<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0300">The pandemic also had direct and indirect effects on bio-based products and the bioenergy sector, clearly linked to the fossil sector and the market disruption generated by COVID-19. For instance, the demand for alcohols and textiles increased rapidly due to the urgent need for disinfectants, facemasks, and sterile medical clothing manufacturing (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Fritsche et al., 2021</xref>). A significant disruption in forest management and forestry sector activities has also been observed in some areas (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Fritsche et al., 2020</xref>). Besides, the need for single-use packaging materials, wrappings, and plastics, which have already started to increase before the pandemic, shows a steady demand highlighting the dynamic for bio-based plastic alternatives in the future (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Fritsche et al., 2021</xref>). Due to the restricted mobility and transport, the respective demand for fuels decreased and, in civil aviation, almost collapsed, though air freight increased. The pandemic's first wave reduced oil price even to negative values, triggered by projections that oil demand would fall by 8.4 mb/d up to the end of 2020 compared to 2019. This trend led to a lack of inland storage availability and led to almost 50 billion &#8364; write-downs during the second trimester of 2020 (<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">IEA, 2020</xref>). US and EU oil majors have so far adopted different strategies. US companies sustain the conventional business (under Trump's Administration), while the European are more active in reducing fossil fuel consumption. Moreover, investments in innovative technologies for the bioenergy sector declined within 2020 due to the lower fossil fuel prices and the challenging economic environment (e.g., lower cash flows, reduced demand, higher debts, and decreased profits) (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Fritsche et al., 2021</xref>).</p>