<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">A search for peer&#8208;reviewed, English language, literature published in the scientific literature since the pandemic emerged in 2020 was developed using the following databases: Cumulative Index for Nursing and Allied Health (CINAHL), Pubmed, and the Cochrane Library. Search terms used were &#8220;climate change,&#8221; &#8220;global warming,&#8221; &#8220;pandemic,&#8221; &#8220;SARS&#8208;CoV&#8208;2,&#8221; and &#8220;COVID&#8208;19.&#8221; Only articles published during 2020 were included since the COVID&#8208;19 epidemic globally emerged in late 2019 with the eruption of the pandemic in January to February 2020. In the initial review process, article titles and abstracts were reviewed for relevance for inclusion. Subsequently full text of the initial review was conducted by two authors to determine relevance based on the inclusion criteria. Exclusion criteria were aimed at limiting any articles that did not address COVID&#8208;19 and its intersection with climate change. The review of articles was conducted with literature published between January 2020 and June 2020. These articles represented the early emerging literature of the intersection of COVID&#8208;19 and climate change. Two reviewers conducted independent full text article reviews and inclusion was determined based on the question: What does the literature indicate regarding the intersection of COVID&#8208;19 and climate change? Each reviewer determined themes independently and subsequently consulted on final emergent themes. The article selection process is presented in the Preferred Reporting Items of Systematic Reviews and Meta&#8208;Analyses (PRISMA) flow diagram (Figure&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and the PRISMA Scoping Review Checklist for Quality Assessment (Figure&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) to support the inclusion of the 22 articles of which 21 were discussion papers or commentaries and only one was a research&#8208;based paper.</p>