<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par30">The authors recognize the complexity and gravity involved with changing an entrenched system, but there are some actions that can be taken to assist those most in need and most at risk. Based on the authors&#8217; research, knowledge, and discussions with FEMA officials and local floodplain managers, the following recommendations could be considered in addressing the increasing impact of climate change on the vulnerable rental population.
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par31">Improve education and outreach to renter communities about risks and insurance.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p id="Par32">Local floodplain managers can work with their tax officials to identify potential rental properties in the floodplains for a targeted flood risk education outreach effort. This could be done in partnership with local NGOs when local government is limited in staffing and funding for such efforts. Working with NGOs and community or cultural leaders can also help to overcome the concerns for immigrants who may not be legally documented or who face language barriers and might otherwise not interact with government officials.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>b.</label><p id="Par33">Communities that participate in the NFIP Community Rating System (CRS) (FEMA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2017</xref>) are considered to be exceeding the federal floodplain management standards. For CRS communities, an outreach effort such as a door-knocking campaign to identify and inform renters about the risks and flood insurance could be awarded in the CRS points system, and would help get the needed information in the hands of those that need it most. A robust outreach effort targeting renters may result in fewer community residents needing assistance following an event as well as potentially lowering flood insurance premiums across the entire community.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>iii.</label><p id="Par34">FEMA and local floodplain officials can improve the ease of access to and availability of easily understandable information. Requiring renters to proactively investigate to understand flood risks and prior flooding at the property through due diligence, data exploration, and the FEMA website is proving insufficient. As one example, the authors learned from a floodplain manager (an individual with sophisticated knowledge of flood impacts and managing recovery funding) that the individual did not personally know without some investigation whether relocation costs or temporary housing for renters is covered by flood insurance.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>2.</label><p id="Par35">Eligible communities not currently in the NFIP CRS should apply and become part of the CRS to reduce flood insurance premiums for residents (both homeowners and renters). Although homeowners may be more directly impacted because owners are more likely to hold the flood insurance policy that receives a CRS program premium discount, renters can benefit in several ways, even if they do not hold flood insurance directly. The CRS rating system incentivizes protection of natural and floodplain barriers, better community education around flood risks, and improved public warning systems. These and other measures impact and benefit the entire community, including renters, and can reduce flood risks for renters and owners alike. There are 19 creditable activities in four categories: public information, mapping and regulations, flood damage reduction, warning, and response (FEMA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2017</xref>).</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>3.</label><p id="Par36">Local or state governments could consider and create a means of enforcement to require landlords to notify tenants of flood risks and prior flooding history of the property. As seen in the Willow River apartment situation in Virginia, many tenants have no idea that they are moving into an at-risk situation. More research is needed, but requiring notifications to tenants in at-risk areas may have the following outcomes:</p></list-item></list><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p id="Par37">Tenants are more risk aware and can make a better-informed decision about the need for rental and/or flood insurance.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par38">A legal requirement of risk notification may in turn incentivize landlords to require tenants to obtain insurance (potential rent reduction could be used in exchange to offset insurance premiums) or to themselves invest in property upgrades to increase resilience.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par39">Notice may&#160;increase knowledge that both&#160;landlord and tenant can use to potentially negotiate lease terms to protect the tenant in the event of a disaster (e.g., should a flood occur, the landlord will use a certain agreed upon amount of FEMA or property insurance recovery to cover the costs of temporary housing for the tenant until repairs can be made).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par40">A notice requirement may de-incentivize property owners from keeping the property after a flood event, knowing the risks and potential loss of income if the risks are disclosed.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>4.</label><p id="Par41">Examine FEMA, NFIP, and State insurance and landlord/tenant laws and regulations for appropriate&#160;areas for modifications that could increase the availability and utilization of renter disaster insurance (i.e., flood or earthquake) for hazards not typically covered by general rental insurance policies. Some potential approaches:</p></list-item></list><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p id="Par42">For renters in floodplains, consider whether lease agreements should require the renter to obtain flood insurance. The national average premium for renter&#8217;s insurance is about $180 per year (Insurance Information Institute <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2020</xref>). Flood insurance can have similar premiums. If such flood insurance is required, there should be appropriate notice provisions and clear understandings regarding who owns the policy, for whose benefit, whether the premium payments are included in the cost of the rent, and what is covered. For example, if the landlord maintains the policy for the benefit of the renter, and the cost is included in the rent, such a policy may not cover the tenant&#8217;s belongings.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>b.</label><p id="Par43">Reflect the property location and risks (e.g., risk of flooding) in the price of renter&#8217;s insurance policy. In this way, the market price of the rent may reflect the increased cost of the insurance policy that the renter must pay in addition to the rent. In short, a landlord may not be able to rent a property for as high a price if it is located in a floodplain and the cost of rental insurance is high.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>iii.</label><p id="Par44">Consider subsidies to offset the costs of flood insurance premiums for renters. For example, subsidies could come from local or state governments, or NGOs and other civic groups that work with low-income residents.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>iv.</label><p id="Par45">Increase knowledge and understanding by local authorities of the opportunities for assistance to renters associated with buy-outs or other federally funded flood mitigation programs, such as assistance with relocation costs.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>5.</label><p id="Par46">Develop FEMA regulations that would incentivize landlords that use home buy-out programs to provide some measure of relief for existing tenants. Buy-out programs typically pay the fair market value of property prior to the disaster event. This does not account for the loss of income for landlords, or the lost home/possessions for the renter. Potential options include:</p></list-item></list><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p id="Par47">1&#8211;2 years of rental income for the landlord (or set the length using a formula that takes account of the frequency of historic flooding to the property, with less payout for more frequent flooding events) based upon current area average rates for similar amenities or rental amount at the time of the disaster. While this would be a large up-front cost to the buy-out program (which is typically predominantly federal dollars), it would reduce future personal assistance (for both the landlord and tenant(s)) and insurance pay outs for the property. As noted by the Pew Charitable Trusts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2016</xref>), approximately 1% of properties account for &#8220;more than a quarter of NFIP claims.&#8221; This would reduce future repetitive loss payouts and potentially save taxpayer dollars over time.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>b.</label><p id="Par48">Create a requirement that a percentage (e.g., 5&#8211;10%) of the buy-out go to the renter(s) to help cover their losses and the burden of being displaced (even if it is temporary). This could be determined based upon valuation of the property and the documented monthly rent (or average rent for the area). This is most important in disaster situations that do not result in a presidentially declared disaster where there may be no coverage or reimbursement for temporary housing. Such a requirement would provide some relief to the tenant (in the absence of NFIP provisions to appropriately provide rental assistance) and also potentially de-incentivize the landlord from continuing to own and operate the property in a high-risk area.</p></list-item></list></p>