<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The context is broadly defined as including all the socioeconomic and political mechanisms facilitating the emission of greenhouse gases (GHG) causing climate change, as well as the creation, configuration and perpetuation of the social stratification and distribution of power and resources within a society [<xref rid="B28-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. This includes, on the one hand, the political tradition and governments, ranging from the local government to the international level, where there are also international bodies that play an important role in halting climate change such as the International Panel on Climate Change (IPCC). On the other hand are the various economic stakeholders, such as the large corporations and social stakeholders such as employers&#8217; associations and non-governmental organizations (NGOs). Together with the culture, values and the sociohistorical legacy of our society, these stakeholders compose the power structures that influences factors important in GHG production, such as: (1) national and international public policies; (2) economic growth and the globalized economy; (3) demographic growth and urbanization; and (4) the overharvesting of natural resources and environmental degradation. Thus, for example, public policies related to the environment, transport, energy, housing, industry, agriculture, and commerce have a huge effect on GHG emissions, as well as on the material and social resources that determine people&#8217;s chances of enjoying good health. The current economic model, based on continuous growth with increasing consumption of natural resources, not only threatens the ecological equilibrium of the planet but has also multiplied social inequalities [<xref rid="B32-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. An example that applies especially to cities with a Mediterranean climate is the growing cruise tourism industry. Cruise ships constitute one of the most energy intense forms of touristic activities [<xref rid="B33-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The Mediterranean is the second largest cruise destination and hosts 10% of the global cruise traffic. Between 1990 and 2020, the annual growth rate of passengers in Mediterranean ports was 6.63%, and the trend is upwards. In 2019, 31 million cruise passenger movements were recorded, with an increase of 11.5% compared to 2018 [<xref rid="B34-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This activity negatively impacts communities through air and water pollution, economic leakage, poor working conditions and wages, tax avoidance, and overtourism [<xref rid="B35-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="B36-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="B37-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], which worsens the density and over-consumption typical of cities. Although cities represent only 2% of the earth&#8217;s surface, they contain 55% of the population, consume 78% of global energy and produce 60% of GHG [<xref rid="B38-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In addition, inequalities in health are usually more marked in urban areas [<xref rid="B25-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Overharvesting of natural resources reduces the ability of ecosystems to halt environmental degradation and provokes forced displacements and socio-environmental conflicts. For example, due to high vulnerabilities and limited adaptive capacities, North African countries face increased probability of climate-conflict linkages though agricultural production and the food&#8211;water&#8211;energy nexus [<xref rid="B39-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Finally, an important role is played by citizen mobilization, which, through social movements and other forms of citizen participation, can act as an agent of change in the dominant system of social, economic, and political organization. Several social movements have already contributed to climate change mitigation through a wide variety of strategies ranging from awareness-raising to changes in regulation, legislation and policy [<xref rid="B40-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. For example, changes in California&#8217;s climate policy limiting permits for new oil wells are the result of social movements towards a low-carbon society [<xref rid="B41-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p>