<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Biological sensing devices are some of the new technological interventions reshaping agricultural systems today, which might be adopted in smart villages. As reported by Antonacci [<xref rid="B6-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], bio-sensors with extremely small structures were found to possess the ability to help in crop maturity evaluation, management of amount of pesticides and fertilizers, as well as detection of humidity levels in soils for effective irrigation. To carry out these functions, bio-sensors rely on the characteristics of nano-materials, such as immobilizing bio-receptors on transducers, integrating and miniaturizing some biological components of plants, transducer systems, and micro-fluids, into very complex plants make-up [<xref rid="B20-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Although the use of harmful pesticides is gradually being phased out in agricultural systems, less harmful pesticides are still very much in use [<xref rid="B22-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In areas known for prior pesticides usage, modern agricultural techniques often aim at detecting pesticide presence, as well as their levels within the soil, before cultivation. To do this, cutting-edge bio-sensors with very high sensitivity (because of their surface-volume ratio), extremely rapid response time, and quick electron-transfer kinetic are utilized. The sensors possess stable strength to map pesticide quantities within soils, and longer lifespan, when compared to the earliest bio-based sensors [<xref rid="B23-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Newly improved bio-sensors with extremely small structures are also able to surpass soil pre-treatment, due to the presence of pesticides, herbicides, and fungicides, without losing their potency [<xref rid="B6-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p>