<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para170">Human life across local, regional, and global scales has been greatly affected by the COVID-19 pandemic. As of Oct 25, 2021, more than 243 million confirmed COVID-19 cases and almost 5 million COVID-19-attributed deaths have been reported globally.<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref> Despite rapid progress of vaccine development and delivery, many countries are still experiencing high transmission rates and repeated resurgences with new SARS-CoV-2 variants arising.<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref> Since early 2020, in an attempt to reduce spread, countries worldwide have enforced varying degrees of travel restrictions, with approximately 75% of nations completely shutting down their borders at some point.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Governments globally have implemented a range of quarantine measures and many have reallocated funding to health-related services and industries.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Lockdowns, curfews, and restrictions of a range of economic activities deemed non-essential have been enacted. Many industries have required employees to work from home.<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref> Simultaneously, governments have been striving to mitigate the inevitable economic, social, and political repercussions of these restrictions, delivering fiscal packages directed toward individuals, as well as public and private sectors.<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref> This suite of COVID-19-related activity has broad direct and indirect effects on biodiversity loss and ecosystem health. Identifying the diverse repercussions of such effects is important for better understanding how they might feed back into the drivers of zoonosis emergence and re-emergence (<xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix pp 11&#8211;21</xref>). Many of these effects could further promote the drivers of zoonotic spillover, hence, reinforcing a feedback loop further contributing to the rising trend of disease emergence.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</p>