<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0395">The IIASA-ISC consultative discussions informed two key overarching areas of emphasis, which we believe should characterize the transformation of food systems as we emerge from the pandemic. First, the recovery process should be harnessed for a fundamental, systemic shift toward greater social resilience and equity. Second, the recovery process should emphasize the integration of human health and planetary health perspectives into the food system architecture. In support of this emphasis, three intervention areas should receive particular attention to catalyze the transition toward greater resilience and sustainability of food systems: i) Advancement of innovation, technology transfer, and scale up of sustainable practices, ii) strengthened mechanisms for cross-sectoral partnerships and multilateral collaboration, and iii) an expanded science-policy interface. <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
presents an overview of suggested areas of emphasis and entry points for action to strengthen the resilience of food systems in the wake of COVID-19. The following sub-sections then describe in further detail the rationale for placing particular attention on the suggested focal areas during the recovery process. It is understood developing pathways toward more resilient, equitable, and sustainable food systems will require that these suggestions to be developed within specific socio-cultural, economic, and environmental contexts, where the synergies and trade-offs between multiple objectives need to be carefully examined.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Resilient food systems &#8211; Overview of suggested areas of emphasis for the recovery process.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="3">Resilient Food Systems<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Transformative Emphasis (section)</th><th>Rationale</th><th>Selected Focal Areas</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Systemic shift toward social resilience (5.1)</td><td>To buffer and secure socio-economic development gains driven by food systems against a changing risk landscape, balancing efficiency concerns with resilience, adaptive and transformative demands.</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="li0005"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0005">Expand the benefits, reach, and duration of social safety nets</p></list-item><list-item id="li0010"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0010">Provide pathways to formal employment</p></list-item><list-item id="li0015"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0015">Promote sustainable farming models, adapted to socio-cultural contexts</p></list-item><list-item id="li0020"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0020">Facilitate just transitions into less vulnerable livelihoods, where necessary</p></list-item><list-item id="li0025"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0025">Reconfigure trade and supply chains, based on their absorptive and adaptive capacity to shocks</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Integration of human and planetary health concerns (5.2)</td><td>To couple social, economic and environmental resilience building efforts for ensuring long-term sustainability.</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0010"><list-item id="li0030"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0030">Adopt ambitious biodiversity and ecosystem conservation targets, coupled with strengthened regulations, monitoring capacities, and enforcement mechanisms</p></list-item><list-item id="li0035"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0035">Accelerate the shift toward healthy and environmentally sustainable diets and associated food production with an emphasis on affordability</p></list-item><list-item id="li0040"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0040">Prioritize investments in water access and sanitation for improved food security and human health</p></list-item><list-item id="li0045"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0045">Account for natural capital in decision-making processes and promote environmental stewardship through integrated planning and appropriate incentive schemes</p></list-item><list-item id="li0050"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0050">Integrate environmental provisions and performance criteria in bi- and multilateral trade agreements</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr><tr><td>Catalytic Intervention Areas (section)</td><td>Rationale</td><td>Selected Focal Areas</td></tr><tr><td>Secure innovation, technology diffusion and upscaling of sustainable practices (5.3)</td><td>To close gaps in innovation and access to sustainable technologies and practices within and across countries, directed toward reducing pressure on the natural resource base, improve risk management practices, improving processes and enabling environments.</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0015"><list-item id="li0055"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0055">Provide clear goals, targets, and regulatory mechanisms to channel private sector engagement</p></list-item><list-item id="li0060"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0060">Strengthen the biological diversity of crops, adapted to diverse environmental conditions, and advance suitable biotechnologies that meet stringent social and ecological safeguards</p></list-item><list-item id="li0065"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0065">Accelerate and scale up technical and financial support for sustainable land and integrated water resource management practices that can readily be adopted</p></list-item><list-item id="li0070"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0070">Strengthen extension services, technical assistance, and funding instruments</p></list-item><list-item id="li0075"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0075">Upscale research on sustainable farm models targeting smallholders</p></list-item><list-item id="li0080"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0080">Facilitate access to digital technology across supply chain, such as precision agriculture, e-commerce, blockchains for tracing foodstuffs</p></list-item><list-item id="li0085"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0085">Provide risk-transfer mechanisms to catalyze investment in innovative technologies and measures</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Strengthen science-policy interface (5.4)</td><td>To strengthen the foundation for fact based decision-making and enabling integrated solutions, which assess impact pathways of policy and measures across the food systems</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0020"><list-item id="li0090"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0090">Advance early warning and near real-time monitoring capacities to rapidly detect potential shocks, risks, and vulnerabilities that undermine the functioning of food systems</p></list-item><list-item id="li0095"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0095">Incentivize collaboration between natural and social sciences to advance an integrated understanding of the biophysical constraints, environmental, economic, and behavioral dynamics shaping food system architecture and levers for transformation</p></list-item><list-item id="li0100"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0100">Expand mechanisms for stakeholder engagement in framing narratives for co-developing resilient and sustainable food systems and support scenario analysis across geographical scales</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Deepen cross-sectoral and multi-lateral collaboration (5.5)</td><td>To improve the capacity to manage multiple hazards and compounding risk factors to food systems and promote transformation pathways that account for sustainability constraints across scales.</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0025"><list-item id="li0105"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0105">Strengthen institutional coordination capacities across scales to manage multiple hazards and risks associated with exponential, non-linear dynamics</p></list-item><list-item id="li0110"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0110">Promote mechanisms for knowledge sharing and collaboration across diverse stakeholder groups and regions</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Source: Authors, informed by IIASA-ISC consultative discussions.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>