<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par40">During the later years of Hu Jintao&#8217;s presidency and under Xi Jinping, Chinese climate policy went from &#8216;neglect to necessity&#8217; (Kwon and Hanlon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>, 1178), with the climate transition increasingly prominent in successive 5-year plans. The shift in <xref rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec">China</xref>&#8217;s economic model to emphasise greener development has been buttressed by innovations in the Communist Party&#8217;s official political doctrine that highlight the importance of a clean environment. The key concept is &#8216;ecological civilisation&#8217;, which evokes the prior slogan of &#8216;spiritual civilisation&#8217;, used by Deng Xiaoping in the 1980s to &#8216;signal that modernisation was not just about getting rich&#8217; (Goron <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2018</xref>, 41). The concept of ecological civilisation was promoted by environmental official Pan Yue in the 2000s. Pan criticised &#8216;black&#8217;, Western industrial civilisation as unsustainable and &#8216;based on the conquest of nature&#8217;. In contrast, ecological civilisation &#8216;conforms to the law of nature and to the policies of sustainable social, economic and cultural development&#8217;. Pan characterised ecological civilisation as distinctively Chinese, referencing the historical legacies of Confucianism, Taoism and Buddhism (Pan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">2006</xref>). Scholars have pointed to the tension between this theory and China&#8217;s actual history (e.g. Hansen, Li and Svarverud <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2018</xref>, 198). Pan also grounded ecological civilisation in socialism (Geall and Ely <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2018</xref>, 1184). Ecological civilization has been inserted into both the Party constitution and the state constitution (Wang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">2018</xref>, 716). The placing of &#8216;ecological civilization&#8217; in the state constitution&#8217;s preamble alongside &#8216;material civilization&#8217; (<italic>inter alia</italic>) signals a change in <xref rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec">China</xref>&#8217;s development model (Zhao <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2021</xref>, 17). The concept, which can be traced back to at least 1986 (Barresi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2017</xref>, 14), was adopted by Hu Jintao in 2007.</p>