<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">For each factor, participants provided ratings on multiple items. Below is an example question for each of the 11 factors and their source. <italic toggle="yes">Affective engagement</italic>: &#8216;When you think about a future impacted by climate change how strongly do you feel the following emotion? Fear&#8230;&#8217;, rated from 1 (none at all) to 7 (very strongly) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Collective efficacy</italic>: &#8216;I feel confident about the capability of our society to address the climate crisis very well&#8217;, rated from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210006C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Perceived behavioural control</italic>: &#8216;How much control do you have over whether you engage in climate activism?&#8217; from 1 (very little control) to 7 (a great deal of control) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Social norm</italic>: &#8216;If I engaged in environmental activism, people who are important to me would&#8217;, from 1 (completely disapprove) to 7 (completely approve) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Faith in institutions</italic>: &#8216;How much do you trust the following group to do what is right in regard to the climate crisis? Governmental groups &#8230;&#8217;, from 1 (never trust) to 7 (completely trust) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Self-efficacy</italic>: &#8216;I, personally, have the skills and resources to address climate change&#8217;, from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Identity</italic>: &#8216;I see myself as a pro-environmentalist&#8217;, from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Attitudes</italic>: &#8216;I think that engaging in climate activism is', from -3 (extremely bad) to +3 (extremely good)&#8217; [<xref rid="RSOS210006C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Intention</italic>: &#8216;I intend to engage in climate activism during the next 6 months', from 1 (extremely unlikely) to 7 (extremely likely) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Openness/Imagination</italic>: &#8216;I would like a job that requires following a routine rather than being creative&#8217;, from 1 (disagree strongly) to 7 (agree strongly) [<xref rid="RSOS210006C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Theory of change</italic>: &#8216;If our society starts changing to help stop the climate crisis, will these changes start from politicians/governments or from people/grassroots movements?&#8217;, from 1 (definitely politicians) to 7 (definitely people). This last factor is an <italic toggle="yes">ad-hoc</italic> measure of participants' belief on how successful change would be implemented: either as a bottom-up process stemming from grassroots action and expanding to the whole society or as a top-down process implemented by governments and authorities. We expected that belief in bottom-up change would more strongly increase the motivation to engage in action.</p>