<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">Hence, an important scholarly debate on decoloniality concerns the questions of what is to be decolonized (i.e. the object of decolonialisation) and whether decoloniality should be used as a means to address a range of socio-political issues (i.e. decoloniality as a means), or an end in itself (i.e. decoloniality as an end) have emerged among decolonial, postcolonial and degrowth scholars (see for example D&#8217;Alisa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>; Deschner and Hust <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2019</xref>; Garcia-Arias and Sch&#246;neberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2021</xref>; Tuck and Yang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2012</xref>). Concerning the object of decoloniality, as noted above, the debate revolves around decoloniality of material (i.e. land and colonial structures of domination), and of immaterial, including mind and imaginary (i.e. knowledges, worldviews, significations). Decoloniality of mind, originally introduced by Fanon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">1965</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144">1967</xref>), has since been used by many decolonial and some postcolonial and degrowth scholars. For example, Latouche (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2015</xref>) frames decoloniality of imaginary as decolonizing of culture, meanings, and significations. Even if he discusses decolonizing imaginary directly in relation to a range of societal, structural and political issues, arguing especially against economic growth, some degrowth scholars criticize Latouche for engaging only slightly with the questions of power and conflicts (Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2019</xref>). Decolonial and post-colonial scholars, in contrast, problematize decoloniality of imaginary as defined by Latouche as an appropriation of the term that takes decoloniality away from its core and intended objectives, which should be repatriation of indigenous land and life (Deschner and Hurst <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Tuck and Yang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2012</xref>). Similarly, some scholars argue for a use of decoloniality strictly in relation to undoing colonial histories and injustices (decoloniality as an end in itself), while others approach it in the context of, and for addressing a range of socio-political issues, including justice and education for example (decoloniality as a means).</p>