<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par38">So, with an approach of cognitive flexibility and frame-bridging across disciplines and policy arenas, we use three levers to raise adaptation framing at a higher strategic plane (Khan and Roberts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2013</xref>). The first lever is &#8220;double exposure&#8221; causing double loss to the PVCs due to their simultaneous exposure to market-led uneven globalization and climate change (Liechenko and O&#8217;Brien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2008</xref>). Today, most of the developing countries suffer from triple distresses: Covid-19, unbearable debt burden, and increased L&amp;D from climate impacts, which are pushing most of the PVCs further down the spiral (HBS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2020</xref>). PVCs number over 100: 43 SIDS, 47 LDCs and a number of other countries including non-LDCs like Zimbabwe, Bolivia, the Philippines, Nicaragua, Pakistan, and India as low-middle income countries. India alone has 18% of the global population. When the PVCs benefit from strengthening their economies and adaptive capacities, other countries also will benefit. Rightly, a number of policy partnerships involving public and private sectors in the 2019 Climate Action Summit have been announced, including Climate Change Resilience Investment, the Africa Adaptation Initiative, a Risk-informed Early Action Programme, a Call for Action (CAS (Climate Action Summit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2019</xref>). The Global Resilience Partnership, the Race for Rural Resilience Initiative under FAO, and many other movements have been initiated as well. Like the Race to Zero, there is the Call for a Race to Resilience: Raising Ambition for Climate Adaptation and Resilience, which has been endorsed by 118 countries and 86 organizations. These are timely steps in globalizing adaptation responsibility, slowly internalizing the new GPG norm as the organizing theme for action.</p>