<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par86">To reduce CO<sub>2</sub> emissions in Australia, the reductive impact of energy intensity should be supported by the two other factors&#8212;namely, carbon intensity and energy structure. Currently, as our research demonstrated, the minor impacts of carbon intensity and energy structure will not help to achieve any sustainability targets in Australia. The country should reduce its overreliance on fossil fuels, especially coal, and invest more in modern renewable energy sources. Because Australia is a developed nation, the investments in modern renewables (e.g., wind and solar) would not hamper the citizens&#8217; welfare. Germany reduced its carbon emissions by rapidly building modern renewable power plants. The performance of Australia regarding renewable energies is relatively poor as compared to other developed nations. In 2017, renewable energy accounted for 9.1% of Australia&#8217;s final energy consumption (IEA, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). However, this value was 15.3% in Germany (the country that is 3.4 times more populous than Australia), 15.6% in Spain, 36.5% in Denmark, and 44.4% in Finland (IEA, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). Australia should follow Germany, Spain, and Denmark in this respect. Furthermore, the public awareness about green infrastructure should also be increased. Educational programs can improve the public support towards urban greening and cultivating climate justice goal could be achieved. The Australian society could also generate wider socioeconomic benefits by reducing the CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. It can reduce the air pollution and related health issues. As a last note, Australia aims to reduce GHGs by around 27% by 2030 compared to the 2005 level. However, if major policy innovations are not implemented, this will be a very challenging target to achieve. Therefore, Australia should reduce its dependence on coal (especially in electricity generation), while increasing its renewable capacity and should particularly focus on the transportation sector, which has the highest level of energy consumption.</p>