<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The FGs included different profiles to evaluate similarities and differences between divergent backgrounds. All groups were gender balanced. Our politically situated approach followed previous exercises of public engagement with emerging technologies conducted by our research centre. Group I was composed of seven environmentalists, belonging to different environmental nongovernmental organizations, social movements or grassroots ecological organizations, and should ideally display strong stances on the climate crisis. Since climate change brings to the fore issues of intergenerational justice, Group II was composed of seven university students studying different subjects at different levels of education (from Bachelor to PhD). Group III gathered five activists &#8211; from feminist and LGBTQIA+<sup>
<xref rid="fn3-09636625221095353" ref-type="fn">3</xref>
</sup> organizations, animal rights collectives, trade unions and student movements &#8211; and it was expected that they would be concerned with socioeconomic and political implications of geoengineering as well as its relationship with other causes. Group IV included seven science communicators from fields related to geoengineering: Earth Sciences, Climate Sciences, Geostatistics and Volcanology. They were expected to display a positive view on scientific and technological progress and to be more aware and knowledgeable of this topic than the others. Group V was only composed of two members (due to unexpected drop-outs) engaged in alternative and holistic therapies and practices. It mirrored the previous one, as these participants were expected to have a sceptical and critical view of modern science and technology. Group VI was heterogeneous, supposed to represent the broader &#8216;Portuguese lay public&#8217;, and included six participants with different professional statuses, ages and genders, and from different cities.</p>