<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par5">This study aims to analyze Australia&#8217;s environmental conditions from a multi-dimensional perspective. Two different approaches, namely, decoupling factor analysis and logarithmic mean Divisia index (LMDI) analysis, are utilized to accomplish this goal. The intended contributions to the literature are as follows:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par6">In the published literature, scholars have mainly investigated the link between CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and real income (Freitas &amp; Kaneko, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2011</xref>). However, in this study, the possible decoupling between CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and other components (such as population) will be also computed. Therefore, a more detailed decoupling factor analysis can be performed to understand the trends in Australia&#8217;s CO<sub>2</sub> emissions over time.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par7">The present study uses the decoupling factor, which was adapted by Zhang (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2000</xref>) and adopted by the OECD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2002</xref>), to examine the link not only between CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and its determinants but also between ecological footprint and its two determinants. Although CO<sub>2</sub> emissions are the primary determinants of ecological footprint, a decoupling factor analysis was also performed to analyze the link between ecological footprint and its two determinants (i.e., real income and population). By conducting this kind of analysis, the researcher aims to determine whether income and population drive the country towards an ecological deficit. Ecological footprint is also used as a proxy variable in this study because it is a more comprehensive environmental variable than CO<sub>2</sub> emissions.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par8">In this study, the temporal changes in Australia&#8217;s CO<sub>2</sub> emissions are elucidated by utilizing the LMDI technique. The LMDI method is based on the Kaya identity and considers the impact of four factors on CO<sub>2</sub> emissions: capita real income, energy intensity, carbon intensity, and population. In the current analysis, however, one more variable is added, namely, the energy structure, to determine the influence of more factors on CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. Hence, the aim is to perform a more detailed decomposition analysis on changes in CO<sub>2</sub> emissions.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par9">R&#252;stemo&#287;lu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2019</xref>) also examined ecological footprint and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions in his paper; however, he evaluated only the per capita ecological balances in Germany by subtracting the per capita ecological footprint from the per capita bio-capacity. The present study aims to build on R&#252;stemo&#287;lu&#8217;s research by conducting decoupling factor analysis not only for CO<sub>2</sub> emissions but also for ecological footprint. CO<sub>2</sub> emissions have the greatest effect on the ecological footprint of Australia, but other factors affect the ecological balances. Thus, a decoupling factor analysis for ecological footprint could be more helpful in identifying the trends in Australia&#8217;s ecological degradation.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par10">By conducting an LMDI decomposition analysis, R&#252;stemo&#287;lu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2019</xref>) demonstrated that Germany is an impressive example for reducing the CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. He conducted a decomposition analysis for Germany, for the time period between 1990 and 2015, focusing on four factors&#8212;namely, per capita income, population, energy intensity, and carbon intensity. In the present study, a similar approach has been followed. However, the impact of a fifth factor on CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (i.e., the energy structure) was also examined. Inspired by R&#252;stemo&#287;lu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2019</xref>), the present study will compare the LMDI results between Australia and Germany in the conclusion section of the present paper.</p></list-item></list></p>