<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Governmental funds have been raised and channelled by, through and for inter-governmental development organizations, bilateral and multilateral agencies, big philanthropic organizations, academic research institutions, and thousands of NGOs worldwide that in turn generated further narratives supporting, directly and indirectly, consciously or unconsciously, this policy shift.<xref rid="EN0010" ref-type="fn"><sup>10</sup></xref> It is part of a broader politics of knowledge around climate change that has been shaped over time. Nightingale et al. (<xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>, p. 347) emphasize &#8216;how the current framing of global climate change and the scientific-policy apparatus built to tackle it limit our imagination and narrow the range of potential responses&#8217;. They elaborate:
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p>Together, they have influenced the expertise that is brought to bear, the questions that can be asked, the people assumed to need assistance, versus those with important knowledge to govern change, and the scales at which responses should be organized. (Nightingale et al. <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>, p. 347)</p></disp-quote>The fixation on what is &#8216;do-able&#8217; has led to petty reforms in land politics. The rise of a global complex of state and non-state actors that have inserted themselves into the political acts of rollback, containment, blocking and promoting of land politics, and the apparent consensus among the dominant socioeconomic classes, together form a historic bloc, the main political force that has transformed what might 40 years ago have been a laughable definition of land tenure security into the current hegemonic narrative that is made authoritative in society by consent and coercion. Thus, petty reforms eventually attain an ideological structure and become &#8216;petty reformism&#8217;: small reforms that are purposively not meant to be ratcheted up into higher and more radical transformation.<xref rid="EN0011" ref-type="fn"><sup>11</sup></xref> It is within this tradition that the concept and practice of &#8216;land tenure security&#8217; have emerged, been sustained, and received a boost from the mainstream idea and practice of climate change mitigation and adaptation.</p>