<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In addition, and especially during the past decade, an old narrative that disparages agrarian societies has been revived and given a new impetus. According to this narrative, some agrarian systems &#8211; such as shifting agriculture and forest foraging, mobile pastoralism and artisanal fishing &#8211; are <italic toggle="yes">ecologically destructive</italic>, and thus are causing or aggravating the climate crisis.<xref rid="EN0007" ref-type="fn"><sup>7</sup></xref> But this narrative can be politically complicated in many societies. For example, while a government may release public statements saying it respects customary land tenure arrangements, it may in practice refuse to register land claims by those practising shifting cultivation, or only register a plot that is a small fraction of the total cultivated land area, and excludes fallow land. The only way for such a small plot to be productively viable is to shift the farming system to a sedentary method. The net effect of this is the cessation of customary production systems and the abrupt shift to sedentary cultivation (in the cases of pastoralism and artisanal fishing, a shift to ranching or aquaculture), which is capital-intensive and dependent on fossil-based inputs. Another implication of this policy action is the freeing up of a large portion of land originally used in mobile production systems. This is immediately captured by the state for reallocation to more socioeconomically and politically powerful capitalist investors. This is what has been unfolding in many borderland ethnic communities in Myanmar during the past decade, for example (Ra et al., <xref rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Springate-Baginski &amp; Kamoon, <xref rid="CIT0095" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) Acknowledging that this process and outcome have been common practice for a long time, Deininger states: &#8216;many countries have considered land and associated natural resources not formally registered as property of the state, which governments could dispose of at will, often without considering the actual status of occupation&#8217; (Deininger, <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, pp. 236&#8211;237). He explains that this widespread practice &#8216;presumes any unclaimed or unregistered land to be &#8220;empty&#8221; and thus available for transfer with few safeguards. This bias can take many forms, including the recognition of rights only to land currently cultivated (i.e. excluding fallow land)&#8217; (Deininger, <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, p. 237).</p>