<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par8">Uttarakhand (<italic>pahar</italic>) state of North India lies in the central Himalayan region. The state is largely rural, agrarian, and Hindu. Most <italic>paharis</italic> (the people of Uttarakhand/literally mountain people) live in villages (and small towns) scattered across a rapidly transforming social-ecological landscape. In many of these villages removed from the bustling marketplace and the clusters of wood/stone/concrete houses next to terraced fields, there is a place reserved for the &#8220;unfortunate&#8221; and the &#8220;cursed.&#8221; These spaces are often filled with widows, people of the lowest caste, and mentally differently abled people. At one such village, in 2016, sitting at the house of one such widow (Ekta), I asked if she had noticed any changes in the rainfall in the past few years. The question was part of a longer list aimed at understanding community perceptions of changes in the climate. In response, she sighed in exasperation and said, &#8220;Why are you so interested in the climate?&#8221; to which after a moment of silence she added, &#8220;&#8230;the climate is not what oppresses us.&#8221; Her adolescent son Sunil who was sitting next to her chimed in, &#8220;The village elite are like vultures. They prey on the vulnerable, pushing us further towards death. I mean you know all about it, it all started when my father died on the border.&#8221; Sunil&#8217;s father Prakash part of the Indo Tibetan Border Police had died under mysterious circumstances somewhere along India&#8217;s contentious Himalayan border with China&#8217;s Tibetan Autonomous Region. In the aftermath of Prakash&#8217;s death, a violent struggle ensued between his surviving brothers to claim his share of the ancestral land. This led to the ostracization of Sunil and Ekta, who lost their privileges to access subsidized grain, share the communal plowshare, and take part in various village institutions. Sunil stated as a matter of fact:</p>