<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par10">Ekta and Sunil&#8217;s story is not unique, and their frustration is echoed by many different households and communities. The impact of climate change on people&#8217;s lives in the mountains is a product of their engagements with the historic processes of power and placemaking. However, their stories of the climate jostle for legitimacy with different expert narratives, which remain rooted in abstract (and data-poor) scientific models, colonial notions of land management, and techno-managerial inclinations of the developmental state (Mathur <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2015</xref>; Satyal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>). During the 2013 monsoons, a multi-day cloudburst over a famous religious tourism spot in Uttarakhand caused a glacier lake to collapse and release its contents. In the subsequent flooding and landslides, over 10000 people died, about 5000 villages were affected, and by some estimates, the total damages incurred by the region were about half a billion US$ (Kala, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>). The causes of this event have since been hotly debated by various scholars, aid agencies, and government bodies. While some have called it a &#8220;natural disaster,&#8221; pointing to the powerful and fairly unprecedented precipitation event, others have described it as a &#8220;man-made disaster&#8221; stating the unmitigated natural resource extraction, industrial infrastructure development (roads, dams) within highly erodible and seismically active mountain lands, and the rapidly growing presence of permanent <italic>pahari</italic> houses in historical flood plains. For <italic>paharis</italic> like Sunil, the event remains both a natural and a man-made one. He thinks of the floods as divine retribution for humanity&#8217;s considerable moral failings. Simultaneously, he sees the event as the latest manifestation of a historical theatre of oppression, orchestrated by the elites against marginalized people and communities. As he eloquently put it, &#8220;Did any politicians, or CEOs, or movie stars die in the floods? Nope. It was just poor sods like me&#8230;the kings of my grandfather&#8217;s days have been replaced by crooked politicians and <italic>thekedars</italic> (government contractors) of today.&#8221;</p>