<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par14">In the end, I decided to stay. My choice (among other factors) was influenced by two important scholarly interventions: the first by Nightingale et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2019</xref>) who state that &#8220;The current techno-scientific apparatus guiding our responses to climate change is deeply disempowering for most people. There is a need to acknowledge the meaning and values of how climate change is made and experienced, and to incorporate this principle into the generation of knowledge through expert organizations such as the IPCC&#8221; (6) and second by Mathur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2015</xref>) who powerfully advocates for <italic>climate translators</italic> whose work would entail grounding &#8220;the Anthropocene within localized politics and ecosystems and can serve to relay the voices, imaginaries, and opinions of the communities, such as the residents of the Indian Himalaya&#8221; (83). Keeping these vital insights in mind, as I look back at the three different interactions presented here, I can situate them within their different subject positions. Ekta and Sunil&#8217;s account represents an assemblage of human and more-than-human entities, material and more-than-material artifacts and processes, historical injustices, and inequities that produce the people and places of the Himalayas. Climate change is rarely voiced directly within this narrative but is often dissociated into different organic elements, many of which appear in conjunction with historically exploitative relationships between the powerful and the marginalized. For Sunil, the sacrifice of his father&#8217;s life at the altar of national security exposes a historically unjust price that Himalayan communities have paid for the fulfillment of geopolitical ambitions (and insecurities) of the nation-state. As he puts it, &#8220;We are like ants, getting crushed under the feet of two angry, fighting elephants.&#8221; Similarly, the burgeoning commercialization of land and various flora and fauna, ruining commons tended over generations and the explosion of infrastructure supporting extractive natural resource management, manufacturing, and energy industries reflect this similar culture of exploitation and abuse. Therefore, in Sunil&#8217;s story, the fates of humans and non-humans in the Himalayas are deeply entangled, foreseeably hurtling towards an unsavory future effectively blurring the lines between nature and society. Climate change emerges in this narrative either as a manifestation of divine retribution aimed at reforming such an immoral world or as one of the many symptoms of human-nature disequilibrium, a symptom of a broken contract. For the scientists working at the confluence of global interest, public finance, and scientific discourse, climate change is their opportunity for legitimacy within the deeply hierarchical culture of global science. But, as techno-managerial representatives of the developmental state, which was an ex-colony and is now pursuing a certain vision of industrial capitalism, they are engaged in maintaining the historically rooted elite control over the reins of knowledge production. Furthermore, their invalidation and dismissal of &#8220;non-scientific&#8221; knowledge hint at the overwhelming acts of allegiance that the scientific worldview demands and the impact of such decisions. Finally, for the scientists working with the IPCC, the need to gather a wide range of scholarship on climate change is seen as a step towards inclusion and possibly democratization of the knowledge production process. However, the disconnect between considerably abstract notions of equity and justice and its potential translations into the empirical, analytical, and representational spheres of knowledge production, is significant. The IPCC still remains fairly biased towards epistemic tools emerging from reductionist, constituent ideologies; recognizes nation-states as the most important spatial units and fails to address the wider stakeholder community of non-state actors; and remains unable to conceptualize climate-society relationships that defy stark human-nature binaries. I believe that the IPCC process fails to address the enduring questions of justice and equity which are critical in the production of Himalayan climate-society relationships.</p>