<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0130">In <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, we describe four broad categories of experiences and risk levels associated with CM and MR. The first category includes populations affected by climate change but are too poor to relocate or migrate, cannot physically move, or may experience other forms of involuntary immobility (<italic>these populations are trapped in place</italic>) (<xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Black et al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0435" ref-type="bibr">Logan et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0520" ref-type="bibr">Nawrotzki and DeWaard, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Ayeb-Karlsson et al., 2018</xref>). There are others who migrate locally, regionally, or internationally but end up trapped in slum settlements, refugee camps, in a cycle of homelessness, or become stateless <italic>(these population are trapped in new place)</italic> (<xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Dowd, 2008</xref>, <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Black and Collyer, 2014</xref>). The trapped populations at both ends of the spectrum potentially face the highest risk associated with climate change and socially-induced vulnerabilities (<xref rid="b0530" ref-type="bibr">O'Neill et al., 2005</xref>, <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Black and Collyer, 2014</xref>). For example, in the case of international CM, evidence suggest, on average, people spend a decade or more in refugee camps (<xref rid="b0510" ref-type="bibr">National Geographic, 2018</xref>). Those in this situation are more likely to be exposed to extreme weather events, diseases, physical and sexual violence, and mental trauma. They also have limited access to health care, education, food, and other basic necessities. Furthermore, the outbreak of the 2020 Coronavirus pandemic revealed people in refugee camps face high exposure to such biological hazards due to their inability to practice social distancing in crowded settlements (<xref rid="b0545" ref-type="bibr">Pollak, 2020</xref>).</p>