<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">This study extends research on climate justice by analyzing social inequities in the spatial distributions of: (1) urban heat exposure, based on the UHRI--an index of physical factors correlated with the urban heat island effect; and (2) proximity to urban greenspace based on the NDVI in the NCT of Delhi. In spatial terms, Delhi has a heterogeneous distribution of the UHRI and NDVI reflecting its complex urban morphology. At its eastern margin, Delhi contains agricultural flood plains and parkland along the Yamuna River characterized by lower heat exposure and higher levels of vegetation. Economically and socially marginalized groups of people are likely to live close to the river due to caste-based occupations [<xref rid="B71-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Parallel to the Yamuna and to its west is the Delhi Ridge, which comprises a series of discontinuous outcrops of the Aravalli Hills. The afforestation of the Ridge was selectively undertaken to benefit governmental elites during British colonial rule, and even as it has been partially deforested since the 1950s, it remains a considerable greenspace within Delhi available as residential and leisure space for affluent residents [<xref rid="B72-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,<xref rid="B73-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Delhi&#8217;s agricultural areas in its north and west also become useful in understanding heterogenous exposure to heat and greenspace. In pre-monsoon May, these areas are in the highest quintile of heat exposure, and the western-most wards remain high in September compared to the rest of Delhi. However, in the post-monsoon period, these northern and western areas show vegetation levels that match or exceed the Yamuna and Ridge areas, possibly due to crop growth. Not only do variations in pre-monsoon and post-monsoon greenspace result in differential heat exposure, these have also sorted the residential population into neighborhoods based on socioeconomic status, the key factor influencing social vulnerability.</p>