<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">There are several limitations to this study that are important to consider, some of which can be addressed in future research. First, the NDVI can be a poor indicator of biomass when there is little groundcover, such as in the semi-arid areas to the west of Delhi, and lose sensitivity when there is dense leaf cover [<xref rid="B74-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="B75-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. This problem can be circumvented by applying image classification and high-resolution aerial imagery [<xref rid="B76-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. However, it should be noted that our study did not completely warrant the application of image classification methods due to the desirability of capturing an image comparable to other data used in calculating UHRI. Second, our analysis was based on ward level data and socio-demographic variables available in the Census of India. The use of additional local information and household-level surveys could help clarify factors influencing statistical relationships reported in this article, and determine the ways in which households residing in specific neighborhoods of Delhi were negatively impacted by heat exposure and greenspace absence. Third, it should be noted that our statistical findings are based on environmental and socio-demographic variables from 2011 which represents the latest year for which population data are currently available in the Census of India. We therefore used remotely sensed imagery from the same year to avoid a temporal mismatch. While more recent data on urban heat and vegetation abundance might indicate higher heat risk and lower greenspace in specific areas, the overall spatial distribution patterns of these indicators are unlikely to have changed significantly over time [<xref rid="B16-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Finally, since our study focuses on a single urban area (i.e., NCT of Delhi) located within India&#8217;s northern agricultural belt, our findings may not be applicable to other cities located in other regions of India. However, the simultaneous consideration of heat exposure, greenspace presence, and social vulnerability factors provides a useful conceptual and analytical framework for examining climate justice within and beyond urban India.</p>