<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">In responding to the modified research question above, it is important to draw important ideas from the definitions of smart- and CSA. Albeit, CSA bears all characteristics of smart agriculture, with a step further in lowering GHG emissions. Consequently, accounts of conceptualizing transformation and change in smart village context might tend towards the adoption of key aspects of climate-smart agriculture (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-20-05977-f001">Figure 1</xref>), which are somewhat multi-disciplinary in nature [<xref rid="B92-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. What this implies is that for smart villages to reach desired level in terms of development through research and policy frameworks, ideas of climate-smartness must be fully embedded across the facets of smart village agenda. According to Katara et al. [<xref rid="B93-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>], continuous adoption of new technologies is the first way to conceptualize transformation of smart villages. Since technology is bound to continually change, it becomes easy to bring evolving and smarter changes to smart village progress. This means that rural population must fully embrace ICT, especially since smart village idea is based on the fact that technology is adopted to hasten the growth of sustainable development [<xref rid="B93-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Secondly, efficiency and productivity are not completely new words in smart village research. Nevertheless, it might be useful for smart village policy analysts to learn from prevention of losses for which CSA is known [<xref rid="B94-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Another important aspect through which transformation of smart villages can be conceptualized is through capacity building of rural dwellers. As in the case of climate-smart agriculture, building capacities would bring about self-sufficiency for persons within these communities, thus reducing urban migration [<xref rid="B15-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B19-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. This is part of the current efforts within the different smart village initiatives. Of all the initiatives that smart village research can draw from climate-smart agricultural practices, the idea of seeking and promoting &#8220;new knowledge&#8221; [<xref rid="B95-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>] might be technically referred to as the most significant. Given that the world has now embraced a knowledge-based economy for which smart village development has to be a part. </p>