<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par3">Globally, many studies have reported on decreasing lake levels, both natural and man-made. For instance, Fathian et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2016</xref>) reported on a persisting trend in the levels of Lake Urmia in Iran between 1966 and 2012, propagated by both natural forces (i.e., climate change) and human forces (i.e., diversion of surface water for upstream use, construction of dams, drought, and mismanagement). The human-made factors alone in Lake Urmia basin have been found to account for the loss of over 70% of the lake area (Garousi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2013</xref>). Similarly, Okonkwo et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2014</xref>) found decreasing levels of Lake Chad, which were negatively associated with key climate forcing such as rainfall and inflowing river discharge and were closely associated with the El Nino Southern Oscillation (ENSO), low-frequency large-scale climate variability forcing. In addition, Yang and Lu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2014</xref>) noted on the complete disappearance of more than 350 lakes of greater than 1 km<sup>2</sup> in size across China, largely due to man-made influence such as water over-exploitation, land reclamation, and urbanization. The result by Yang and Lu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2014</xref>) is in contrast with that of Han et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2016</xref>) in their study in Lake Dongting who found increasing patterns in the maximum lake water level, annual mean lake water level, and annual minimum lake water level from 1961 to 2014 that were largely driven by the change of precipitation and the operation of reservoirs. Other studies that have reported on changes in lake levels (i.e., either decreases or increases) in various regions include the following: &#218;beda et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2013</xref>) in the Ibera wetland of Argentina; Stefanidis et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2016</xref>) in their study of two Mediterranean karstic lakes, namely Vegoritis and Petron in northern Greece; and Song et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2014</xref>) in the Tibetan Plateau. Awange et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2008</xref>) reported of recessions of Lake Victoria in east Africa between 1977 and 2001. These studies have associated such changes to either climate, man-made, or both, with non-uniform and non-region-specific associations on the lake levels across globally (&#352;raj et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2016</xref>).</p>