<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par5">Lake Malawi is a critical transboundary water resource between Malawi, Mozambique, and Tanzania at the southern end of the Great East Africa Rift Valley system (Drayton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1984</xref>). According to Jury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2014</xref>), Lake Malawi&#8217;s levels are quite sensitive to variations in the balance between mean annual rainfall over the lake (about 1.3 m), mean annual inflows from 4 main rivers (about 0.9 m), mean annual lake or open water evaporation (1.8 m), and mean annual outflow to the only outlet, the Shire River (0.4 m). The lake is the second largest and deepest among the Great East Africa Rift Valley lakes, after Lake Tanganyika (Neuland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1984</xref>). A long-term history of the lake levels from various data sources (proxy, in situ, and modeling) by Owen et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">1990</xref>) and Nicholson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1998</xref>) suggests a complex variation pattern mainly attributed to climatic controls. The lakeshore areas are also prone to the extreme lake level variations at both low and high frequency, which affects both infrastructure and socio-economic livelihoods of the riparian communities. Since the peak of 1979, the lake levels have been undergoing a considerable recession (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Makwinja et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>) developed a stochastic model for forecasting lake levels based on historical levels. Calder et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1994</xref>) attributed lake level changes from 1896 to 1967 to rainfall alone, but assumed constant evaporative demand and forest cover. To our knowledge based on available literature, a frequency analysis of the lake levels both under stationary and non-stationary conditions has not been undertaken. With various proposed infrastructural and major water abstraction projects (e.g., Salima-Lilongwe Water Project), there is a critical need for understanding the nature of lake levels in terms of their magnitudes, return periods, and the role various forcing (e.g., low-frequency climate variability like El Nino Southern Oscillation (ENSO) on the design extreme lake levels). This aspect has motivated our present study<bold>.</bold> Therefore, this study is aimed at examining the nature of extreme lake levels under stationary and non-stationary conditions, using the case of Lake Malawi in East-Southern Africa. Specifically, this was achieved through the following: (1) temporal analysis of the lake levels for evidence of non-stationarity; and (2) developing models for frequency analysis of the lake levels under stationary and non-stationary conditions. The results are very critical in flood zoning especially with various planned infrastructural and related developments around the lakeshore. To our knowledge, there are no many studies (e.g., Drayton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1984</xref>, Neuland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1984</xref>, Calder et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1994</xref>, Kumambala and Ervine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">b</xref>) that have been attempted to account for changes in the levels of Lake Malawi. In addition, there is no documented study on SFA or NFA of levels of Lake Malawi.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The extent of Lake Malawi recession showing the exposed lake bed in February, 2017. The boats&#8217; docking area used to be close to the exposed house terrace on the right</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10661_2020_8519_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>