<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0100">The abject is neither an object nor a subject, but an entity that is radically different by our symbolic order of meaning to allow for an intersubjective community to persist (<xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">Kristeva, 1982</xref>). It is &#8220;what disturbs identity, sense, and order. What does not respect borders, positions, or rules and highlights the fragility of the law and the eruption of the &#8216;real&#8217; into our lives&#8221; (<xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">Kristeva, 1982, p.6</xref>). We are simultaneously attracted and repelled by the abject because of the images of trauma, sympathy, and suffering they conjure (<xref rid="b0570" ref-type="bibr">Schinina, 2017</xref>). Our sense of sympathy and othering is aroused in response to their suffering, even as they are not seen as humans or sub-humans, but as a social category to which we must apply spatial rules and etiquette of social distancing. This abjectification of people brings to bear the under-theorized and politicized ways in which CM is often discussed at the international level as a response of desperate people fleeing a location at risk with no livelihood, no prospects of return, and therefore must be &#8220;othered&#8221; or kept out until society can determine who or what they are. By implication, this creates a double victimization, or &#8216;second disaster&#8217; for those already battling the impacts of climate change. This can be seen in the case of Alaskan Natives and the Biloxi-Chitimacha-Choctaw Tribe of Isle de Jean Charles (IDJC), Louisiana, who were labelled America&#8217;s <italic>&#8216;first climate refugees&#8217;</italic> despite not crossing internationally recognized borders (<xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Davenport and Robertson, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr">Herrmann, 2017</xref>). Yet, these resettlements are better understood as examples of MR.</p>