<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Soc Anthropol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Soc Anthropol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1469-8676</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SOCA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Social Anthropology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0964-0282</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-8676</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8251067</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1469-8676.13000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SOCA13000</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Forum</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Forum</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A pandemic can do what a movement cannot</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">A PANDEMIC CAN DO WHAT A MOVEMENT CANNOT</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">ALF HORNBORG</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="soca13000-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hornborg</surname><given-names>Alf</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2102-5875</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="soca13000-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>alf.hornborg@hek.lu.se</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="soca13000-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Human Ecology Division</named-content>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Human Geography</named-content>
<institution>Lund University</institution>
<named-content content-type="street">S&#x000f6;lvegatan 12</named-content>
<city>Lund</city>
<postal-code>223 62</postal-code>
<country country="SE">Sweden</country>
</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/soca.v29.1</issue-id><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright">&#x000a9; 2021 European Association of Social Anthropologists<copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2021 European Association of Social Anthropologists</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is being made freely available through PubMed Central as part of the COVID-19 public health emergency response. It can be used for unrestricted research re-use and analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source, for the duration of the public health emergency.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:SOCA-29-210.pdf"/><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1137"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>February 2021</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.0.4 mode:remove_FC converted:02.07.2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body id="soca13000-body-0001"><p>Over the past two centuries, more and more of humankind has taken progress for granted. Growing numbers of people have assumed that problems of various kinds will eventually be solved. Some problems have been alleviated &#x02013; in privileged parts of the world &#x02013; by economic and technological development, such as the drudgery of heavy labour that has been relegated to machines. Other issues have required legislation and political activism, such as the abolition of slavery, universal suffrage and agreements on human rights. After more than two centuries of such progress, there is a widespread expectation that social movements are a proper vehicle of change.</p><p>Given a responsive, democratic establishment, the underlying assumption is that popular demands are met if voiced strongly enough. This is the common foundation of a wide spectrum of movements demanding better conditions for specific categories of people or championing abstract causes such as democracy, disarmament or sustainability. The expectations propelling these movements are at the core of modernity: they are based on the faith that society can &#x02013; and will &#x02013; be improved through the agency of political activism.</p><p>Over the past 50 years, however, the trust in activism has been undermined by various circumstances, most conspicuously in the Euro&#x02010;American &#x02018;West&#x02019; or &#x02018;North&#x02019; where it emerged. The postmodern deposition of the master narrative reflected the observation that power structures had proven more resilient than anticipated: the Euro&#x02010;American victories in terms of social welfare, democracy and human rights generally did not extend to the low&#x02010;wage nations to which capital increasingly migrated. Moreover, several central concerns of social movements pertained to issues &#x02013; such as global justice and sustainability &#x02013; that appeared to transcend the reach of political decision&#x02010;making. It became evident that problems of economic polarisation and ecological degradation were intrinsic to the logic of globalised capital.</p><p>Against this background, the recent eruptions of climate justice activism demand our attention not only for the urgency of their message but also for illustrating the impasse of social movements confronting global societal processes that unfold beyond the potential control of politics. This impasse became even more troubling as the world economy reacted to the Covid&#x02010;19 pandemic.</p><p>The pandemic has taught us that politicians and affluent consumers are not at all as unlikely to curb neoliberal capitalism as decades of failed negotiations on greenhouse gas emissions have led us to believe. The main obstacle to behavioural change and political decisions that would lower emissions is that the threat of disastrous climate change is less tangible than the threat of a global health emergency. In contrast to climate change, the pandemic poses an immediate threat to individuals, rather than a long&#x02010;term threat to society. An optimistic conclusion is that greenhouse gas emissions <italic>can</italic> be swiftly reduced without entailing debilitating sacrifices,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="soca13000-note-1001">1</xref> while a pessimistic one is that, for most people, the threat of climate change is too abstract to be taken seriously.</p><p>Paradoxically, just as we have begun to give up on the prospects of politically averting climate crisis, we have seen that it is practically possible. What lessons can the climate movement draw from this? Having raised public awareness of climate change but found the practical responses from politicians disappointing, influential climate activists like Greta Thunberg and Extinction Rebellion may now need to lower their aspirations to inspire political decisions and instead focus on how to understand and contravene the driving forces that generate growing emissions. While protesting climate change has certainly raised awareness, it has accomplished remarkably little in practical terms, as Thunberg herself is the first to observe. The abundant media coverage and striking dramaturgy notwithstanding, the demands of the climate movement have remained too general and intangible to prompt significant policy decisions.</p><p>To demand that fossil fuels be abandoned without simultaneously demanding substantial economic degrowth is to assume that the fossil energy currently sustaining modern civilisation can be replaced with other energy sources. Although this assumption is widely promoted, it is highly dubious.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="soca13000-note-1002">2</xref> Given the modest progress of capitalist and socialist nations alike in struggling to decarbonise, and given the unlikelihood of a <italic>global</italic> hegemony of the fossil fuels lobby, we must infer structural constraints operating through the financial or spatial requirements of alternative energy technologies (Hornborg et al. <xref rid="soca13000-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). To the extent that it does not acknowledge these constraints, for instance by explicitly advocating degrowth, the climate movement risks posing demands that are simply dismissed by mainstream politicians as incompatible with the energy requirements of modern civilisation. Many people will wonder what the implications of its demands would be for their lifestyles. While the curtailing of personal mobility is obvious, it is legitimate to ask how the globalised trade in foodstuffs and other commodities can be upheld in the absence of fossil fuels. The climate activists will need to explain how they would reorganise the production and transport of food and other necessities. The climate movement has excelled in <italic>communicating</italic> our growing anxiety about climate change but needs to elaborate its programme for dismantling our fossil infrastructure.</p><p>As the climate movement is increasingly disillusioned by the inertia of our global fossil metabolism, some militant activists will advocate violent sabotage (cf. Malm <xref rid="soca13000-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2021</xref>). While the frustration and despair are understandable, attacks against fossil infrastructure effective enough to cripple our dependence on fossil fuels are unlikely to be able to discriminate between the luxury consumption of the super&#x02010;rich and the subsistence needs of the economically least resilient. Such sabotage is thus morally incompatible with the struggle for climate <italic>justice</italic>. Nor is the call for eco&#x02010;sabotage likely to enhance the legitimacy of the climate movement.</p><p>Climate activism has contributed to a research&#x02010;based majority consensus on the reality of anthropogenic climate change, but it has not convinced me that the climate apocalypse can be averted politically. On the other hand, the new Corona virus has taught us that anything that seriously impairs the operation of the global economy &#x02013; whether a pandemic, financial collapse or a natural disaster &#x02013; <italic>could</italic> effectively avert climate apocalypse. While climate activists and proponents of degrowth affirm that the current global response to the pandemic is <italic>not</italic> a welcome development from their perspectives, they seriously need to consider the possibility that these may be the only kind of conditions that might make their visions materialise. Although at this point the prospects for a post&#x02010;carbon future seem remote, we have not yet seen the end of what a pandemic might accomplish.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn id="soca13000-note-1001"><label><sup>1</sup></label><p>Of course, we still don&#x02019;t know what the long&#x02010;term consequences of lockdowns and massive fiscal debts will be for the viability of modern civilisation.</p></fn><fn id="soca13000-note-1002"><label><sup>2</sup></label><p>Energy expert Vaclav Smil has recently estimated that global dependence on fossil energy is around 90% and <italic>growing</italic> (Voosen <xref rid="soca13000-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="soca13000-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="soca13000-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="soca13000-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Hornborg</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Cederl&#x000f6;f</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Roos</surname>
</string-name>
<year>2019</year>. &#x02018;<article-title>Has Cuba exposed the myth of &#x0201c;free&#x0201d; solar power? Energy, space, and justice</article-title>&#x02019;, <source xml:lang="en">Environment and Planning E: Nature and Space</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>989</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1008</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13000-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13000-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Malm</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2021</year>. <source xml:lang="en">How to blow up a pipeline</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13000-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="soca13000-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Voosen</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2018</year>. &#x02018;<article-title>Meet Vaclav Smil, the man who has quietly shaped how the world thinks about energy</article-title>&#x02019;, <source xml:lang="en">Science</source> 21 March.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>