<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="news" dtd-version="1.3"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Development (Rome)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Development (Rome)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Development (Society for International Development)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-6370</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1461-7072</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8514803</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34664005</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">309</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1057/s41301-021-00309-w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Who's Who</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Who's Who</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>64</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Society for International Development 2021</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Society for International Development 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1"><bold>Barbara Adams</bold> is Chair of the Board of Global Policy Forum. She was trained as an economist in the UK, worked as Executive Director of the Manitoba Council for International Affairs in Canada and has undertaken development programming in Uruguay. She worked for the United Nations for 20&#x000a0;years and her experiences have also included being a member of the President of UN General Assembly CSO taskforce for MDG 2010 Summit, the Coordinating Committee of Social Watch and the Civil Society Reflection Group on Global Development Perspectives, which released its report, No future without justice, in the Development Dialogue series. Barbara has authored and co-authored many articles, reports and books on the UN and multilateral issues, including &#x02018;Accounting for Africa at the United Nations&#x02019;; &#x02018;Putting Gender on the Agenda: A Guide to Participating in UN World Conferences&#x02019;; &#x02018;Climate Justice in a Changing World&#x02019;; &#x02018;Reclaiming Multilateralism for People, Rights and Sustainable Development, and Fit for Whose Purpose?&#x02019;, co-authored with Jens Martens.</p><p id="Par2">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par3"><italic>Email</italic>: barbaraadams@globalpolicy.org</p><p id="Par4"><bold>Roberto Bissio</bold>, from Uruguay, coordinates the Secretariat of Social Watch, a network of citizen organizations that monitor how their governments implement their international commitments.</p><p id="Par5">He is co-editor of Global Policy Watch and a member of the Civil society Reflection Group on Sustainable Development. He was a member of the civil society advisory group to the UNDP administrator and regularly writes on development issues as a columnist.</p><p id="Par6">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par7"><italic>Email</italic>: rbissio@item.org.uy</p><p id="Par8"><bold>Juan Pablo Bohoslavsky</bold> is currently coordinator of the postgraduate course on &#x02018;Human rights and public policies in Covid-19 times&#x02019;, Universidad Nacional de R&#x000ed;o Negro, Argentina. He is also consultant on finance and human rights to the OHCHR. He was the Independent Expert on Debt and Human Rights at the United Nations between 2014 and 2020; he worked for UNCTAD, ECLAC and the Argentine State in international arbitrations. He has a Ph.D. in Law, and he is author of books and articles on public debt, investments, and human rights.</p><p id="Par9">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par10"><italic>Email</italic>: juanpablobohos@gmail.com</p><p id="Par11"><bold>Nandini Chami</bold> is Deputy Director at IT for Change. Her work largely focuses on research and policy engagement in the domains of Big Tech regulation, platform workers&#x02019; rights, and development justice and gender equality in the digital economy.</p><p id="Par12">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par13"><italic>Email</italic>: Nandini@itforchange.net</p><p id="Par14"><bold>Anis Chowdhury</bold> has concurrent adjunct professorial positions at the School of Social Sciences and Psychology, Western Sydney University and the School of Business, University of New South Wales (ADFA, Canberra). He is also co-editor of the Journal of the Asia&#x02013;Pacific Economy and on the Editorial Board of the Economic and Labour Relations Review. He was Director of the UN-ESCAP Macroeconomic Policy &#x00026; Development Division and Statistics Division (July 2012&#x02013;May 2015). He was Chief of the UN-DESA (Financing for Development Office, Multi-Stakeholder Engagement &#x00026; Outreach; June 2015&#x02013;Jan. 2016). Prior to joining the United Nations, he was a Professor of Economics, University of Western Sydney (Australia) between 2001 and 2008. He has published extensively on macroeconomic and development issues.</p><p id="Par15">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par16"><italic>Email</italic>: anis.z.chowdhury@gmail.com</p><p id="Par17"><bold>Debora Irene Christine</bold> is Research Assistant at the United Nations University Institute in Macau. Her research interests are on the nexus of development, media, ICTs, inequality and social exclusion, and the construction of knowledge.</p><p id="Par18">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par19"><italic>Email</italic>: debora@unu.edu</p><p id="Par20"><bold>Nicoletta Dentico</bold> is a journalist and a human rights advocate, with a long experience in disarmament issues, international cooperation and global health. In 1993, she started the Coalition to Ban Landmines in Italy and coordinated it until early 2000, when she took over as Director-General of M&#x000e9;decins Sans Fronti&#x000e8;res (MSF). In 2004 she joined the MSF Access to Essential Medicines Campaign and then Drugs for Neglected Diseases Initiative (DNDi) in Geneva. She worked as WHO consultant in Geneva and at EMRO in Cairo. From 2011 to 2014 she coordinated the Democratizing Global Health Coalition on the WHO Reform (DGH). She has published extensively on issues related to access to medicines and the right to health. From 2013 to 2019 she served as board member in the Italian Ethical Bank (Banca Popolare Etica). She currently directs the global health programme at Society for International Development (SID).</p><p id="Par21">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par22"><italic>Email</italic>: ndentico@sidint.org</p><p id="Par23"><bold>Marina Durano</bold> is Senior Program Officer at the Women&#x02019;s Rights Program of the Open Society Foundations and Board Member at Global Policy Forum.</p><p id="Par24">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par25"><italic>Email</italic>: marina.durano@opensocietyfoundations.org</p><p id="Par26"><bold>Ibrahim Farah</bold>, a Somali academic and former lecturer at the University of Nairobi, is the founder and head of the research unit of the Mogadishu-based Justice &#x00026; Peace Network (aka&#x000a0;<italic>Maandeeq&#x02014;JPN</italic>), a global Somali political movement.&#x000a0;Dr. Farah has some 30&#x000a0;years' experience in academic teaching and research, humanitarian aid and development cooperation as well as in socio-political and security analysis. He is also an expert in strategic peacebuilding and state-building processes.</p><p id="Par27">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par28"><italic>Email</italic>: farahiq2002@yahoo.com</p><p id="Par29"><bold>Levi Gahman</bold>&#x02019;s focus areas include anti-racist and anti-colonial praxis, environmental defence, gender justice and engaged movement research. Drawing from the work of Fanon, he is currently exploring how collective action and mutual aid animate pathways out of structural violence and alienation.</p><p id="Par30">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par31"><italic>Email</italic>: levi.gahman@liv.ac.uk</p><p id="Par32"><bold>Adaeze Greenidge</bold> is a community outreach volunteer from the Caribbean working on issues of environmental awareness, gender justice and mental health. Drawing on critical development studies, emancipatory praxis, and postcolonial feminisms, her research focuses on social movements, resistance, cultural change, and well-being.</p><p id="Par33">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par34"><italic>Email</italic>: adaeze.greenidge@my.uwi.edu</p><p id="Par35"><bold>Anita Gurumurthy</bold> is a founding member and Executive Director of IT for Change, where she leads research collaborations and projects in relation to the network society, with a focus on governance, democracy and gender justice. Her work reflects a keen interest in southern frameworks and the political economy of Internet governance and data and surveillance.</p><p id="Par36">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par37"><italic>Email</italic>: anita@itforchange.net</p><p id="Par38"><bold>Nora McKeon</bold> studied history and political science before joining the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) of the United Nations where she directed the organization&#x02019;s relations with civil society. She now engages in research, teaching and advocacy around food systems and movements and closely follows evolutions in global food governance. She is technical adviser to the Network of Peasant and Agricultural Producers Organizations of West Africa (ROPPA). She teaches at Roma Tre University and the International University College of Turin. Her publications include: <italic>The United Nations and Civil Society: Legitimating Global Governance?</italic> (Zed 2009), <italic>The New Alliance for Food Security and Nutrition: a coup for corporate capital?</italic> (Terra Nuova/Transnational Institute 2014), <italic>Food Security Governance: empowering communities, regulating corporations</italic> (Routledge 2015). &#x02018;Are Equity and Sustainability a Likely Outcome When Foxes and Chickens Share the Same Coop? Critiquing the Concept of Multistakeholder Governance of Food Security&#x02019; (<italic>Globalizations</italic> Vol 14 2017 issue 3), <italic>Global food governance</italic>. <italic>Between Corporate Control and Shaky Democracy</italic> (Development and Peace Foundation 2018)<bold>,</bold> &#x02018;Reclaiming democracy from below: from the contemporary state capitalist system to peoples&#x02019; sovereignty&#x02019; (<italic>Globalizations</italic> Vol 17 2020 issue 7).</p><p id="Par39">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par40"><italic>Email</italic>: nora.mckeon@fastwebnet.it</p><p id="Par41"><bold>Kinda Mohamadieh</bold> is legal advisor and senior researcher with the Third World Network office in Geneva. Her work covers WTO processes and negotiations, international investment governance and business and human rights. Previously, she served as senior researcher for seven years with the South Centre. She also worked with the Arab NGO Network for Development. Kinda holds an LL.M. in International Economic Law from the University of Lausanne, a master&#x02019;s degree in Public Affairs from the University of California &#x02013; Los Angeles (UCLA), and an undergraduate degree in economics. She is currently PhD candidate at the international law department of the Graduate Institute in Geneva.</p><p id="Par42">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par43"><italic>Email</italic>: kindam@twnetwork.org</p><p id="Par44"><bold>Sof&#x000ed;a Monsalve Su&#x000e1;rez</bold> is the Secretary General of FIAN International, an international human rights organization working for the right to food and nutrition. Before turning Secretary General in 2016, she coordinated FIAN&#x02019;s program on land and natural resources for more than 15&#x000a0;years. This work included field research visits and fact-finding missions to twenty five countries; close collaboration with peasants, family farmers, landless people, fisher folks, indigenous peoples and rural workers; conceptual work and research on the intersection between human rights, land and natural resource governance in collaboration with various academic institutions; and extensive advocacy work in the UN human rights system including contributing to the development of human rights standard setting. Likewise, she has extensive experience collaborating with the UN agencies working on food and agriculture, inter alia, coordinating the civil society participation to various process of the UN Committee on World Food Security (CFS).</p><p id="Par45">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par46"><italic>Email</italic>: monsalve@fian.org</p><p id="Par47"><bold>Manuel F. Montes</bold> is Senior Advisor of the Society for International Development. Montes was Permanent Observer to the UN and Senior Advisor on Finance and Development at the South Centre; Chief, Development Strategies branch at the United Nations&#x02019; Department of Economic and Social Affairs (UNDESA); UNDP Regional Programme Coordinator, Asia Pacific Trade and Investment Initiative in Colombo, Sri Lanka; Program Officer for International Economic Policy at the Ford Foundation in New York; Coordinator for Economics Studies at the East&#x02013;West Centre in Honolulu; and Associate Professor of Economics at the University of The Philippines, aside from visiting research fellowships in Tokyo (IDE), Helsinki (UNU/WIDER) and Singapore (ISEAS). Montes has an AB in Economics from the Ateneo de Manila University and PhD in Economics from Stanford University.</p><p id="Par48">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par49"><italic>Email</italic>: montesmf0@gmail.com</p><p id="Par50"><bold>Mariana Rulli</bold> is a political scientist (UBA), with a PhD in Social Sciences from FLACSO, a master&#x02019;s degree in Social Policies from the Latin American Faculty of Social Sciences (FLACSO) and a master&#x02019;s degree in Gender and Family Diversity from the University of Barcelona. She has worked as a teacher at the UBA and is currently a professor and researcher in the area of political science, CIEDIS-National University of R&#x000ed;o Negro (UNRN). Her main research topics are gender, social security, business, and human rights on which he has made numerous publications in Latin America and Europe.</p><p id="Par51">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par52"><italic>Email</italic>: mrulli@unrn.edu.ar</p><p id="Par53"><bold>Jackie Smith</bold> is professor of sociology and activist-scholar at the University of Pittsburgh. She has authored or co-authored numerous works on global and local social movements, including <italic>Social Movements and World-System Transformation</italic> (2017, co-edited with Michael Goodhart, Patrick Manning, and John Markoff), <italic>Social Movements in the World-System: The Politics of Crisis and Transformation</italic> (with Dawn Wiest) and <italic>Social Movements for Global Democracy</italic>. From 2012 to 2020 she served as editor of the open access <italic>Journal of World-Systems Research</italic>. Smith is co-coordinator of Pittsburgh&#x02019;s Human Rights City Alliance and serves on the national steering committee of the U.S. Human Rights Cities Alliance.</p><p id="Par54">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par55"><italic>Email</italic>: jgsmith@pitt.edu</p><p id="Par56"><bold>Mamello Thinyane</bold> is Principal Research Fellow at the United Nations University Institute in Macau. He is passionate about technology innovation and about seeing individuals and communities empowered to lead &#x02018;their happy&#x02019; lives. His research investigates the role of locally relevant, citizen-generated data to empower individuals and community-level actors towards the Sustainable Development Goals targets, as well as the role of this data within the larger social indicators data ecosystem.</p><p id="Par57">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par58"><italic>Email</italic>: mamello@unu.edu</p><p id="Par59"><bold>Gabrielle Thongs</bold> specializes in disaster planning and spatial modelling. Her work measures risk perception and assesses hazards throughout the Caribbean using open-source GIS. She is currently examining regional risk reduction and mitigation strategies as well as the social and political factors that reduce disaster resilience.</p><p id="Par60">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par61"><italic>Email</italic>: gabrielle.thongs@sta.uwi.edu</p><p id="Par62"><bold>Antonia Wulff</bold> is the Director of Research, Policy and Advocacy at Education International (EI), the global federation of teacher unions. EI represents 32,5 million teachers and education support personnel in 178 countries.</p><p id="Par63">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par64"><italic>Email:</italic> Antonia.Wulff@ei-ie.org</p><p id="Par65"><bold>Robert Zuber</bold> is director of UN-based Global Action to Prevent War and Armed Conflict where he directs a small team of policy advocates and interns monitoring the UN's work on security, gender, sustainable development and human rights policy. He also serves as consultant, adviser or board member to a variety of non-profit and educational organizations, including Green Map System, Global Connections Television, FIACAT (human rights) the Peace Angels Project, and Women in International Security (NY and CA). Based in Harlem, New York and with graduate degrees from Yale and Columbia Universities, he has written and spoken extensively on peacekeeping, Security Council reform, the global arms trade, and related human security and global governance concerns. He has co-organized events in over 30 countries on topics from the impact of trafficked weapons on sustainable development to the role of civil society and women advocates in policy development and peace processes.</p><p id="Par66">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par67"><italic>Email:</italic> zuber@globalactionpw.org</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>