<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par36">The deal between the EU and Mercosur was announced on 28 June 2019 at the G20 Osaka summit. Although Angela Merkel and Emmanuel Macron had both made public warnings against Bolsonaro because of his recent setbacks in environmental policy, the negotiations were not affected. A common understanding of the economic and commercial opportunities was at the roots of this agreement (Friedrich-Ebert-Stiftung <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2020</xref>). The EU&#8217;s interests were based on the access to Brazil&#8217;s primary goods and domestic market for the EU&#8217;s industrial goods (Saraiva and Gavi&#227;o <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2020</xref>). In terms of climate negotiations, the inter-regional agreement does not incorporate procedures and instruments for monitoring, evaluating and accountability. In a Gramscian perspective, such absences illustrate that the climate agenda&#8217;s historical materialism, since the beginning, has stressed the creation of a specialized space that hardly relates to the regimes that govern other global issues, such as security, trade and human rights. Moreover, through this agreement with Mercosur, the EU is challenged by the paradox of addressing climate solutions in another region and, at the same time, handling the negative environmental effects of its trade and investment portfolios. Transnational social forces of resistance to Bolsonaro&#8217;s strategies have generated an unfavourable environment for the implementation of the Mercosur-EU strategic partnership: 2&#160;years after the 2019 announcement, the agreement has not yet been ratified by the countries that compose the European bloc, and there is no unanimity among its members. Principles of climate justice claimed by the EU, such as impartiality, may become empirically controversial. In addition, climate change norms may become less statutory and more dependent on political variables that engage the EU in a much-needed conversation on policy coherence across sectors.</p>