<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par39">Illegal fires, land grabbing activities and illegal extraction of wood and minerals in protected areas are all associated with this scenario. &#8216;Land appropriation&#8217; is yet another practice that has increased in recent times: under the logic of &#8216;non-occupied&#8217; lands, the process of nature financialization has further increased interest in Brazilian biomes. The value of the land business is reproduced in astronomical numbers and, consequently, opens up an even larger scale for the use of natural resources, acquisition or development of infrastructure projects and agricultural production for the global market (Borras et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2012</xref>, Human Rights Watch et al. <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>, IPAM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2017</xref>). The &#8216;milestones thesis&#8217; for the demarcation of indigenous lands (Apib <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2021</xref>) is currently one of the most relevant topics on the Brazilian justice, and it&#8217;s on the core of those processes. Investments in land in Brazil by international pension funds with the participation of European nations, such as Germany, Sweden and the Netherlands, have been operating in the Matopiba<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn6">6</xref> region, and have contributed to multiple social and environmental impacts (Buzato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2018</xref>; FIAN International et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2018</xref>). The production of iron and the exploration of coal to steel production in the Amazon is also a serious situation that, as Veras and Casara (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2004</xref>) point out, is one of the economic sectors most closely related to highly polluting emissions, slave labour and deforestation in Brazil. According to Russau (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>), Brazilian iron and steel are consumed by several multinational companies, including the former ThyssenKrupp (currently Ternium Brasil). Inconsistencies between a claimed pro-climate leadership and trade and investment relations leading to violations of native and traditional peoples&#8217; rights cannot be more evident.</p>