<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11076558</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38714717</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">61140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-61140-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Universal and cultural factors shape body part vocabularies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tjuka</surname><given-names>Annika</given-names></name><address><email>annika_tjuka@eva.mpg.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Forkel</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>Johann-Mattis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02a33b393</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419518.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2159 1813</institution-id><institution>Department of Linguistic and Cultural Evolution, </institution><institution>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology, </institution></institution-wrap>04103 Leipzig, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05ydjnb78</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11046.32</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0656 5756</institution-id><institution>Chair for Multilingual Computational Linguistics, </institution><institution>University of Passau, </institution></institution-wrap>94032 Passau, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>10486</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Every human has a body. Yet, languages differ in how they divide the body into parts to name them. While universal naming strategies exist, there is also variation in the vocabularies of body parts across languages. In this study, we investigate the similarities and differences in naming two separate body parts with&#x000a0;one word, i.e., colexifications. We use a computational approach to create networks of body part vocabularies across languages. The analyses focus on body part networks in large language families, on perceptual features that lead to colexifications of body parts, and on a comparison of network structures in different semantic domains. Our results show that adjacent body parts are colexified frequently. However, preferences for perceptual features such as shape and function lead to variations in body part vocabularies. In addition, body part colexification networks are less varied across language families than networks in the semantic domains of emotion and colour. The study presents the first large-scale comparison of body part vocabularies in 1,028 language varieties and provides important insights into the variability of a universal human domain.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Semantics</kwd><kwd>Body parts</kwd><kwd>Cross-linguistic comparison</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Language</kwd><kwd>Psychology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>International Max Planck Research School for the Science of Human History</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000781</institution-id><institution>European Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>101044282</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>Johann-Mattis</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology (2)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The languages of the world have different strategies for naming human body parts. English speakers have two words <italic>foot</italic> and <italic>leg</italic>, whereas Belhare speakers use one word, <italic>la&#x0014b;</italic>, to express the concepts <sc>foot</sc> and <sc>leg</sc>. Exploring the variation of body part vocabularies across languages has attracted the attention of researchers in linguistics, anthropology, and psychology over many years. Similar to the principles developed for the semantic domains of colour<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, universal tendencies were established and contrasted with culturally specific variations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The emergence of new methods in network analysis made it possible to conduct large-scale comparisons of vocabulary in specific semantic domains to examine universal and cultural structures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Variation in vocabularies is influenced by internal and external linguistic factors. Early comparative studies on the hierarchical structures of body part vocabularies across languages showed that they had generally five levels and never more than six<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. In addition, general principles were established: (1) body parts such as <sc>head</sc> and <sc>arm</sc> are named in all languages, (2) <sc>leg</sc> and <sc>arm</sc> always receive distinct names, and (3) if a separate word exists for <sc>foot</sc>, then there will also be one for <sc>hand</sc><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. These cross-linguistic studies showed that visual discontinuity plays a role in the emergence of frequent patterns, for example, using the same word for the concepts <sc>hand</sc> and <sc>arm</sc> or for <sc>foot</sc> and <sc>leg</sc><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The similarities in body part vocabularies were also used to decipher language relatedness since genealogically related languages overlap in strategies for naming body parts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. However, anthropological studies on body part vocabularies of diverse languages challenged the claims that the body part domain conforms to the same hierarchical principles across languages and that universal concepts such as <sc>body</sc> exist<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. When considering linguistic diversity, the challenge is to identify the constraints that lead to the same outcome in different languages. Apart from visual features such as shape and contiguity, functional features, for example, that walking is performed by the foot and leg, are more important in some languages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. One possible explanation for why some languages colexify <sc>foot</sc> and <sc>leg</sc> or <sc>hand</sc> and <sc>arm</sc> is that their body part lexicon is based on the motor system used to perform actions, rather than the visual system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. The use of the same word for two body parts appears to be based on perception in general and the cultural significance of certain visual discontinuities in particular.</p><p id="Par4">In this study, we investigate the structure of body part vocabularies across 1028 diverse languages. The overarching research question of the study is: What factors influence the variation of body part vocabularies across languages? The analyses are based on a large sample of lexical data and a computational approach to language comparison. We examine associations between body parts by analysing concepts that are expressed by the same word, i.e., colexifications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. We compute network comparisons across language families and examine body part colexifications in terms of their frequency and distribution. To investigate the internal structure of body part colexification networks, we compare network variation in the domain of body parts, colour, and emotion. Our study offers insights into the interplay between cognition and culture while demonstrating methodological advances in the computational analysis of cross-linguistic lexical data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><p id="Par5">We conducted three different analyses to examine the structure of body part vocabularies across language varieties and language families. In total, 110 body part colexifications across 1028 language varieties were found. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> includes the ten most frequent body part colexifications. The results reveal that concepts related to the limbs, i.e., parts of the arm and leg, are frequently colexified across different language families. In addition, body parts associated with the head are commonly referred to with the same word which is reflected in colexifications such as <sc>chin&#x02013;jaw</sc>, <sc>mouth&#x02013;lip</sc>, and <sc>eyebrow&#x02013;eyelash</sc>. Part-of relations are expressed in colexifications such as <sc>breast&#x02013;nipple</sc> and <sc>face&#x02013;forehead</sc>.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The 10 most frequent body part colexifications.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Concept A</th><th align="left">Concept B</th><th align="left">Families</th><th align="left">Language varieties</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><sc>foot</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>leg</sc></td><td align="left">57</td><td align="left">322</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>hand</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>arm</sc></td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">255</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>chin</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>jaw</sc></td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">48</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>breast</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>nipple</sc></td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">45</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>finger</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>toe</sc></td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">104</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>breast</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>chest</sc></td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>mouth</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>lip</sc></td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">78</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>eyebrow</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>eyelash</sc></td><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">45</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>finger</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>hand</sc></td><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><sc>face</sc></td><td align="left"><sc>forehead</sc></td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">14</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par6">The comparison of cross-linguistic patterns reveals that universal tendencies described in previous studies exist<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. There is only one exception to the principle that if <sc>hand</sc> and <sc>foot</sc> are labelled, they are named by different words: Washo colexifies <sc>hand&#x02013;foot</sc>. The general principle that a separate word for <sc>leg</sc> implies a separate word for <sc>arm</sc><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> is generally supported although there is one Nakh-Daghestanian language variety, Budukh, which colexifies <sc>leg&#x02013;arm</sc>. The tendency of adjacent body parts to share the same name<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> is supported by multiple body part colexifications and leads to cross-linguistically frequent patterns. While these overarching patterns reveal uniformity across the structure of body part vocabularies in diverse language varieties, many language family-specific patterns arise.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Language family network comparison</title><p id="Par7">Most colexifications between body part concepts occur in one or two language families. This shows that numerous body part colexifications are specific to a particular language family. Thus, we created language family networks for the eight language families with the highest number of language varieties in our sample to compare differences. The comparison of the language family networks shows striking variation in terms of the frequency and distribution of body part colexifications. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the number of body part colexifications in each language family. The comparison of the colexification frequencies demonstrates that a higher number of language varieties in a given language family does not lead to an increase in the number of body part colexifications. To compare the frequency and distribution of body part colexifications across the body, Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> illustrate the colexification networks for the eight language families. The colour of the nodes shows the membership to a community, with communities representing groups of nodes that have more connections among themselves than to other nodes in a network<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Number of body part colexifications across language families.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Family</th><th align="left">Colexifications</th><th align="left">Language varieties</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Sino-Tibetan</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">151</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Atlantic-Congo</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">117</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indo-European</td><td align="left">38</td><td align="left">57</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Afro-Asiatic</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pama-Nyungan</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tupian</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nakh-Daghestanian</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tai-Kadai</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">28</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par8">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Language family colexification networks (1/2). The graph represents a weighted network in which the thickness of the edges indicates the frequency of a colexification across language varieties in a language family. The colour of the nodes shows the membership to the overall community.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61140_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Language family colexification networks (2/2). The graph represents a weighted network in which the thickness of the edges indicates the frequency of a colexification across language varieties in a language family. The colour of the nodes shows the membership to the overall community.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61140_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par9">The comparison of the network structures across eight language families reveals linguistic variation. While Sino-Tibetan and Indo-European language varieties have colexifications between different parts of the arm, only Indo-European language varieties show different colexifications of parts of the leg. In Atlantic-Congo language varieties, the colexification <sc>elbow&#x02013;heel</sc> is frequent and it is specific to this language family. Afro-Asiatic, Pama-Nyungan, Tupian, and Tai-Kadai language varieties have primarily colexifications between adjacent body parts whereas Nakh-Dagestanian language varieties have multiple colexifications between non-adjacent body parts. Tupian is the only family in which no language variety shows a colexification between <sc>hand&#x02013;arm</sc> and <sc>foot&#x02013;leg</sc>.</p><p id="Par10">The results of the descriptive comparison demonstrate that the structure of body part vocabularies varies across language families. Each language family has several body part colexifications that occur in 1-2 language varieties and many language family-specific body part colexifications exist. Often body part colexifications are confined to one area of the body and some language families tend to colexify different parts of a particular area of the body. While our approach provides an overview of the different patterns, studies on language subgroups<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, genealogically related languages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, or individual languages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> offer a detailed comparison of systematic preferences within language families.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Contiguity, function, and shape</title><p id="Par11">Each of the 110 body part colexifications was coded for three perceptual features: contiguity, function, and shape. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows the networks with the body part colexifications associated with a particular perceptual feature across 20 language families. The network based on body part colexifications associated with contiguity is the densest compared to the other two networks. This demonstrates that most cross-linguistic colexifications between body parts are based on a contiguous relation. While the networks of contiguity and function include cross-linguistically frequent body part colexifications, the majority of colexifications based on shape are language family-specific. For example,&#x000a0;Manep, a language of the&#x000a0;Nuclear Trans New Guinea&#x000a0;family, colexifies <sc>head</sc> and <sc>knee</sc>&#x000a0;with the word <italic>kumu</italic>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Colexification networks illustrating contiguity, function, and shape. The networks show colexifications based on contiguity (upper left), function (upper right), and shape (bottom left). The colours indicate the major parts of the body: head (blue), upper limb (orange), trunk (pink), and lower limb (green).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61140_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">Based on the coding for contiguity, function, and shape, we determined the proportions of the categories for the 20 language families. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> illustrates the proportion of the three perceptual features across language families. The pie charts show the total number of colexifications associated with each perceptual feature in a given language family. The language families vary in their total number of colexifications which is illustrated by the size of the pie chart. For example, Indo-European has a total of 38 body part colexifications, whereas Uto-Aztecan only has four. The map shows the geographical origin of the language families to illustrate their spread across the globe.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of the three perceptual features across language families. The perceptual features are contiguity, function, and shape. The size of the pie charts corresponds to the number of cross-linguistic colexifications present in the languages. The map illustrates the geo-coordinates for the origin of languages belonging to the same language family.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61140_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">The main result is that contiguity is prevalent in all language families. While Austronesian, Turkic, Chocoan, and Tucanoan languages have fewer body part colexifications associated with contiguity than all other language families, contiguity has still the highest proportion. There are slight cross-linguistic differences in the proportions of the body part colexifications associated with certain perceptual features. For example, Indo-European languages have an almost even number of body part colexifications associated with function and shape. Similar patterns are found in Atlantic-Congo and Tupian. In Arawakan and Tungusic languages, half of the body part colexifications are based on contiguity and the other half is split between shape and function. In contrast, there are no language families in which shape outweighs function. Most of the language families such as Uralic, Austroasiatic, Pama-Nyungan, or Tucanoan have more body part colexifications related to function over shape. Uto-Aztecan is the only language family that has no body part colexifications based on shape.</p><p id="Par14">The geographical distribution of perceptual features shows interesting patterns. Contiguity is a cross-linguistically stable dimension that indicates universality. In contrast, the perceptual features of shape and function are culturally varied and languages employ different systems to structure their body part vocabularies. Multiple factors may lead to different preferences. In some regions, it is more likely to find languages that colexify body parts based on their function. These languages could be more likely to highlight actions systematically in their grammar by having a word order that places the verb at the beginning or by using a different system of verb agreement for transitive versus intransitive verbs. The perceptual feature of shape is&#x000a0;frequent in only&#x000a0;a few languages. However, some languages use this feature systematically for colexifications between body parts. One reason for this could be that these languages use shape markers to describe objects or have classifier systems based on shape features. The cultural variation and the interplay between lexicon and grammar could be further analysed with information about the grammatical structures of languages from the Grambank database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Variation in body part, emotion, and colour networks</title><p id="Par15">For comparing the variation in colexifications across three different semantic domains, we selected 20 language families with the highest number of languages in which colexifications of at least two out of three domains occurred. The comparison is a replication of the study by Jackson and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> which examined variation in colexifications in the domain of emotion and colour. We extended the list of concepts and created a new list with 21 colour concepts and 62 emotion concepts. To compare the differences in network structures, we derived adjusted rand index (ARI) and adjusted mutual information (AMI) values, illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. The ARI values provide information on how similar the network clusters are compared to each other and give a measure for comparing whether two nodes remain in the same cluster, i.e., the rand index<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. The AMI values also provide information on the similarities of clusters but they are more suited for networks with small clusters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. The resulting index lies between 0 and 1 corresponding to <italic>completely random</italic> and <italic>completely identical</italic>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Distribution of pairwise language family ARI and AMI values for body, emotion, and colour networks with a 5-step random walk. The density plots show the distributions of ARI values for the domains of body part (green), emotion (orange), and colour (blue), and the distributions of AMI values for body part (dark green), emotion (dark orange), and colour (dark blue).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61140_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par16">We performed an analysis with a 5-step random walk in line with the approach by Jackson et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> The analysis shows that the networks in the body part domain had a mean ARI of 0.3 (<italic>sd</italic> = 0.17). In comparison, the mean ARI of the emotion networks was 0.16 (<italic>sd</italic> = 0.29) and for colour <italic>m</italic> = 0.14 (<italic>sd</italic> = 0.26). The mean values of the AMI comparison across the three domains yielded similar results: body part <italic>m</italic> = 0.37 (<italic>sd</italic> = 0.16), emotion <italic>m</italic> = 0.18 (<italic>sd</italic> = 0.3), and colour <italic>m</italic> = 0.16 (<italic>sd</italic> = 0.28).</p><p id="Par17">To test whether the variance in network clustering differed across domains, we performed Welch two sample <italic>t</italic>-tests with the mean ARI values. The results show that the body part networks vary significantly from the emotion networks with a higher variance in the emotion networks (<italic>t</italic> = 5.58, <italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c; 0.001). The comparison with colour networks also shows a significant difference (<italic>t</italic> = 5.9, <italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c; 0.001). The variance of clusters in the emotion and colour networks do not show a significant difference (<italic>t</italic> = 0.76, <italic>p</italic> = 0.45). The findings demonstrate that body part networks are more uniformly structured than emotion and colour networks. However, the finding that emotion networks varied significantly from colour networks was not replicated. The reason for the discrepancy could be the additional emotion and colour concepts that were added in the present analysis. They may have added more variation in the colour clusters.</p><p id="Par18">Due to the low number of edges in the networks, we performed a third analysis to test the degree of edges in each language family. We ran 1000 trials selecting <italic>n</italic> nodes randomly in each trial, with <italic>n</italic> being the size of the selected nodes in the body, colour, and emotion networks. From these random selections, weighted degrees for selected nodes in the network per language family for each semantic domain were computed. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> illustrates the distribution of the language family weighted degrees in proportion to the number of language varieties for the domains of body part, emotion, and colour.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Distribution of language family weighted degrees for body, emotion, and colour networks. The density plot shows the frequency for the domains of body part (green), emotion (orange), and colour (blue).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61140_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">The plot shows that the distribution of the weighted degrees differs slightly across the three domains. The mean weighted degree in the body part domain was 2.87 (<italic>sd</italic> = 2.3). In the emotion domain, the mean was 2.6 (<italic>sd</italic> = 2.75) and in the colour domain, the mean was 3.21 (<italic>sd</italic> = 3.69). This result demonstrates that across&#x000a0;the 20 language families&#x000a0;in our sample, colour colexifications have the highest degree of edge connections, followed by body part and emotion. The comparison of the weighted degrees based on a Welch two sample <italic>t</italic>-test across domains showed no significant difference between the three domains. The findings indicate that the degree of edge connections in body part, emotion, and colour colexification networks is similar.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par20">Body part vocabularies vary across languages. However, within the diversity, general tendencies arise. Body parts that are adjacent to one another are more frequently colexified. At the same time, linguistic diversity arises due to preferences for colexifications based on a perception of shape or function. Our study provided a first analysis of colexifications in body part vocabularies across 1028 languages. The results showed that uniform structures arise across language families indicating that body part vocabularies are not random. In addition, we demonstrated that body part colexification networks differ significantly from the domains of emotion and colour in that body part colexification networks are less varied across language families.</p><p id="Par21">Apart from theoretical implications, the study demonstrates three important methodological improvements to the study of colexification networks. The first improvement is the use of Lexibank<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> as the basis for the data in combination with the workflows in CLICS<sup>3</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> which makes our approach more flexible for future applications to other semantic domains. We included datasets with large coverage and from different geographical areas. In a subsequent study, the data need to be optimised to reach a genealogical and geographically balanced sample. We did not restrict our sample in the present study because it is the first large-scale study on body part colexifications so we aimed to get a broad perspective on the emerging patterns. The second methodological improvement is the inclusion of a cognate detection method to account for language relatedness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Although preliminary tests did not detect noteworthy differences in the resulting colexification networks when different thresholds of cognates were considered, the method needs further testing and will become important in studies on individual language families. The third methodological improvement is the replication of the comparison of semantic domains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. By implementing the analysis in Python code, the underlying analysis is now more transparent and parts can be conveniently adapted. In addition, we compared weighted degrees across language families to examine the structure of colexification networks. This method is particularly important given the sparseness of the connections found in the three semantic domains and it allows us to bridge gaps in the data.</p><p id="Par22">Future studies can use our workflows to add more language varieties or compare other semantic domains. Our approach was exploratory to some extent and a more balanced sample is required for further research. Although we included as many concepts as possible, the coverage of concepts is skewed across the world&#x02019;s languages and further data collection is necessary. Our study provides the first large-scale analysis of body part vocabularies and offers insights into the structure of body part vocabularies in diverse languages which can lead to more robust interpretations of colexifications in different semantic domains.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Language sample</title><p id="Par23">The study is based on a sample of 1028 language varieties from different geographic regions and 20 language families, see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents the 20 language families with the number of language varieties in the sample. The largest language families are Sino-Tibetan (151 language varieties), Atlantic-Congo (117 language varieties), and Pama-Nyungan (61 language varieties). We incorporated language families with a large number of language varieties to have sufficient coverage of body part, emotion, and colour concepts.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Distribution of language varieties in the sample. The colour indicates membership to a language family. The classification and coordinates are taken from Glottolog Version 4.7<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://glottolog.org">https://glottolog.org</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_61140_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Number of language varieties across language families.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Rank</th><th align="left">Family</th><th align="left">Language varieties</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Sino-Tibetan</td><td align="left">151</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Atlantic-Congo</td><td align="left">117</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">Pama-Nyungan</td><td align="left">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">Afro-Asiatic</td><td align="left">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">Indo-European</td><td align="left">57</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Tupian</td><td align="left">42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">Nakh-Daghestanian</td><td align="left">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">Tai-Kadai</td><td align="left">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">Uralic</td><td align="left">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">Hmong-Mien</td><td align="left">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">Austroasiatic</td><td align="left">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">Tucanoan</td><td align="left">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">Arawakan</td><td align="left">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">Tungusic</td><td align="left">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">Turkic</td><td align="left">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">Uto-Aztecan</td><td align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">Austronesian</td><td align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">Pano-Tacanan</td><td align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">Cariban</td><td align="left">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">Chocoan</td><td align="left">6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Concept selection</title><p id="Par24">The body part concepts for the study were selected from the semantic field &#x02018;The body&#x02019; in Concepticon Version 2.5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. A description of the selection process and the list are provided in blog posts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. We excluded body part concepts for which no corresponding word was available in the datasets and less than five words in at least ten language families were elicited. This process led to a selection of 36 body part concepts (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The lexical data were taken from 51 datasets consisting of word lists with at least 250 concepts curated in Lexibank<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The datasets are listed in the Supplementary Information.
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Body part concepts.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">ID</th><th align="left">Concept</th><th align="left"/><th align="left">ID (cont.)</th><th align="left">Concept (cont.)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1402</td><td align="left"><sc>breast</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1303</td><td align="left"><sc>finger</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">834</td><td align="left"><sc>buttocks</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">123</td><td align="left"><sc>forehead</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1173</td><td align="left"><sc>eyebrow</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1277</td><td align="left"><sc>hand</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1301</td><td align="left"><sc>foot</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1256</td><td align="left"><sc>head</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">980</td><td align="left"><sc>heel</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1745</td><td align="left"><sc>hip</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1371</td><td align="left"><sc>knee</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">798</td><td align="left"><sc>jaw</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">803</td><td align="left"><sc>ankle</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1297</td><td align="left"><sc>leg</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1673</td><td align="left"><sc>arm</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">478</td><td align="left"><sc>lip</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1291</td><td align="left"><sc>back</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">674</td><td align="left"><sc>mouth</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1251</td><td align="left"><sc>belly</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1838</td><td align="left"><sc>navel</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1730</td><td align="left"><sc>cheek</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1333</td><td align="left"><sc>neck</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1592</td><td align="left"><sc>chest</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">796</td><td align="left"><sc>nipple</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1510</td><td align="left"><sc>chin</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1221</td><td align="left"><sc>nose</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1247</td><td align="left"><sc>ear</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1482</td><td align="left"><sc>shoulder</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">981</td><td align="left"><sc>elbow</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1389</td><td align="left"><sc>toe</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1248</td><td align="left"><sc>eye</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1205</td><td align="left"><sc>tongue</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1540</td><td align="left"><sc>eyelash</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1380</td><td align="left"><sc>tooth</sc></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1560</td><td align="left"><sc>face</sc></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">799</td><td align="left"><sc>wrist</sc></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The concepts are based on Concepticon Version 2.5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>
</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par25">The study includes an additional comparison with concepts from other semantic domains, i.e., emotion and colour. Thus, we collected the emotion and colour concepts used by Jackson and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> and extended the list with concepts available in Concepticon Version 2.5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. The final list included 22 colour concepts and 62 emotion concepts (see Supplementary Information).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Workflows</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Colexification networks</title><p id="Par26">The workflow of identifying colexification networks is based on the workflows that are the foundation for creating the network in CLICS<sup>3</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Apart from computing the frequencies of cross-linguistic colexifications of a given set of concepts, the computer-assisted approach using the CLICS algorithm creates a weighted network of colexifications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. The graphs were produced with the Python package NetworkX<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. To identify communities within these networks, we employed the Infomap algorithm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> integrated into the Python package igraph<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The Supplementary Information provides additional details on the methods.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Cognate detection</title><p id="Par27">To account for language relatedness in the emergence of colexifications, we established a new method that detects cognates in genealogically related languages to identify whether a colexification was transmitted from a shared ancestor language. We employed an automated approach to generating phonetic transcriptions based on the cross-linguistic transcription systems (CLTS) reference catalogue<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clts.clld.org">https://clts.clld.org</ext-link>. These phonetic transcriptions are now incorporated in Lexibank<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> and allow a comparison of sounds rather than symbols<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>.The method computes all colexifications inside the same family and then automatically clusters all word forms that colexify the same concepts across different language varieties into cognate sets. We used state-of-the-art methods for automated cognate detection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, as implemented in LingPy Version 2.6.13<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://lingpy.org">https://lingpy.org</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par28">While previous approaches list all language varieties for which a colexification inside a given family could be detected<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, our revised approach counts only the number of distinct cognate sets. As a result, we capture cases where a colexification evolved only once in the past and was then transmitted to all neighbouring languages in a sample. For example, in the Austronesian language family, most language varieties use the word forms <italic>lima</italic> or <italic>nima</italic> for the colexification <sc>hand</sc>-<sc>five</sc>. Since the cognate detection method detects that <italic>lima</italic> and <italic>nima</italic> are cognate, it assigns both words to the same cluster and thus guarantees that we count the colexification only once, instead of counting it multiple times. Preliminary tests show no striking differences in colexification networks of body part concepts with different thresholds for cognate detection, but the method needs further examination in subsequent studies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Language family origin detection</title><p id="Par29">The origins of language families, i.e., homelands, were computed using an algorithm implemented in the homelands module provided by the Python package pyglottolog (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pypi.org/project/pyglottolog/3.11.0">https://pypi.org/project/pyglottolog/3.11.0</ext-link>). Geographic point locations for Glottolog subgroups (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://glottolog.org">https://glottolog.org</ext-link>) are determined recursively as the nearest point on land to the intersection centroid of the coordinate set of immediate daughter languages or subgroups (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pyglottolog.readthedocs.io/en/latest/homelands.html#module-pyglottolog.homelands">https://pyglottolog.readthedocs.io/en/latest/homelands.html#module-pyglottolog.homelands</ext-link>). This method is used for visualisation purposes only, i.e., to illustrate language families on a map, not as the basis for quantitative analysis of the origins of language families.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Perceptual features</title><p id="Par30">The perceptual features <italic>contiguity</italic>, <italic>shape</italic>, and <italic>function</italic> offer important insights into the structure of body vocabularies across languages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. We, therefore, coded each body part colexification for <italic>presence</italic>/<italic>absence</italic> (1/0) of a perceptual feature. Since some of the body part colexifications can be interpreted in terms of different features, we allowed for multiple coding of presence. The colexification <sc>hand</sc>-<sc>arm</sc>, for instance, was coded as follows: contiguity 1, shape 0, and function 1. In comparison, the colexification <sc>head</sc>-<sc>knee</sc> was coded as contiguity 0, shape 1, and function 0. The full list of coding is given in the Supplementary Information.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec15"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2024_61140_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-024-61140-0.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dami&#x000e1;n E. Blasi for his insights and suggestions in the initial phase of the project. A.T. was supported by a stipend from the International Max Planck Research School (IMPRS) at the Max Planck Institute for the Science of Human History and the Friedrich-Schiller-Universit&#x000e4;t Jena. J.-M.L. was funded by&#x000a0;the&#x000a0;ERC Consolidator Grant 101044282 &#x0201c;Productive Signs&#x0201d; (10.3030/101044282).&#x000a0;Views and opinions expressed are however those of the author(s) only and do not necessarily reflect those of the European Union or the European Research Council Executive Agency (nor any other funding agencies involved). Neither the European Union nor the granting authority can be held responsible for them.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>A.T. wrote the first draft, conducted the analyses, created the figures, and implemented the revisions. R.F. provided the method for the language family origin detection and revised the code&#x000a0;for data curation and analysis. J.-M.L.&#x000a0;wrote the initial Python code for data curation and analysis and established the cognate detection method for cross-linguistic colexifications. All authors reviewed the manuscript and agreed with the final version.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The Supplementary Information provides an overview of the datasets, concepts, and coding. The data and scripts for the analysis of this study are accessible on GitHub (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/clics/clicsbp/releases/tag/v1.0">https://github.com/clics/clicsbp/releases/tag/v1.0</ext-link>) and stored on Zenodo (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10955934">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10955934</ext-link>).</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par31">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Basic Color Terms: Their Universality and Evolution</source><year>1969</year><publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>General principles of human anatomical partonomy and speculations on the growth of partonomic nomenclature</article-title><source>Am. Ethnol.</source><year>1976</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/ae.1976.3.3.02a00020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Enfield</surname><given-names>N J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Staden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parts of the body: Cross-linguistic categorisation (Special Issue)</article-title><source>Lang. Sci.</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0388-0001(06)00005-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wierzbicka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bodies and their parts: An NSM approach to semantic typology</article-title><source>Lang. Sci.</source><year>2007</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.langsci.2006.07.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>On the universal structure of human lexical semantics</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. Biol. Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>1766</fpage><lpage>1771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1520752113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emotion semantics show both cultural variation and universal structure</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2019</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1517</fpage><lpage>1522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaw8160</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31857485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31857485</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lexical universals of body-part terminology</article-title><source>Universals of Human Language: Word Structure</source><year>1978</year><publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>368</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Malt</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Words for parts of the body</article-title><source>Words and the Mind: How Words Capture Human Experience</source><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>71</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matisoff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Variational Semantics in Tibeto-Burman: The &#x0201c;Organic&#x0201d; Approach to Linguistic Comparison</source><year>1978</year><publisher-name>Institute for the Study of Human Issues</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Durie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural tendencies of semantic change and the search for cognates</article-title><source>The Comparative Method Reviewed: Regularity and Irregularity in Language Change</source><year>1996</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>304</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Semantic systems in closely related languages</article-title><source>Lang. Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.langsci.2014.11.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tversky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parts, partonomies, and taxonomies</article-title><source>Dev. Psychol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0012-1649.25.6.983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tversky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bodies and their parts</article-title><source>Mem. Cogn.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BF03195336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Staden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can nomenclature for the body be explained by embodiment theories?</article-title><source>Top. Cogn. Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tops.12159</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26466949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26466949</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ois</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vanhove</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Semantic maps and the typology of colexification: Intertwining polysemous networks across languages</article-title><source>From Polysemy to Semantic Change: Towards a Typology of Lexical Semantic Associations</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>215</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modularity and community structure in networks</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>8577</fpage><lpage>8582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0601602103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16723398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16723398</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-anatomy: The structure of the domain</article-title><source>Anthropol. Linguist.</source><year>1975</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>JLA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hout</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of semantic variation differ across body parts: Evidence from the Japonic languages</article-title><source>Cogn. Linguist.</source><year>2021</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/cog-2020-0079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The lexical structure of Quechua body parts</article-title><source>Anthropol. Linguist.</source><year>1969</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicodemus</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coeur d&#x02019;Alene exceptions to proposed universals of anatomical nomenclature</article-title><source>Am. Ethnol.</source><year>1985</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/ae.1985.12.2.02a00090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skirg&#x000e5;rd</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Grambank reveals the importance of genealogical constraints on linguistic diversity and highlights the impact of language loss</article-title><source>Sci. Adv.</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.adg6175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Networks: An Introduction</source><year>2018</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinh</surname><given-names>NX</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Verspoor</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adjusting for chance clustering comparison measures</article-title><source>J. Mach. Learn. Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lexibank, a public repository of standardized wordlists with computed phonological and lexical features</article-title><source>Sci. Data</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>316</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-022-01432-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rzymski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The database of cross-linguistic colexifications, reproducible analysis of cross-linguistic polysemies</article-title><source>Sci. Data</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-019-0341-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31896794</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenhill</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential of automatic word comparison for historical linguistics</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0170046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammarstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Forkel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haspelmath</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bank</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Glottolog (Version 4.7)</source><year>2022</year><publisher-name>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Concepticon. A Resource for the Linking of Concept Lists (Version 2.5.0)</source><year>2021</year><publisher-name>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tjuka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A list of 171 body part concepts</article-title><source>Comput. Assist. Lang. Comp. Pract.</source><year>2020</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tjuka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A list of color, emotion, and human body part concepts</article-title><source>Comput. Assist. Lang. Comp. Pract.</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tjuka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extending the list of color, emotion, and human body part concepts</article-title><source>Comput. Assist. Lang. Comp. Pract.</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mayer, T., List, J.-M., Terhalle, A. &#x00026; Urban, M. An interactive visualization of crosslinguistic colexification patterns. In <italic>Proceedings of the LREC Workshop &#x02019;VisLR: Visualization as Added Value in the Development, Use and Evaluation of Language Resources&#x02019;</italic> (eds Hautli-Janisz, A. <italic>et al.</italic>) 1&#x02013;8 (European Language Resources Association, Reykjavik, Iceland, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">List, J.-M. Towards a History of Concept List Compilation in Historical Linguistics. <italic>History and Philosophy of the Language Sciences</italic> (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hagberg, A. A., Schult, D. A. &#x00026; Swart, P. J. Exploring Network Structure, Dynamics, and Function Using NetworkX. In Varoquaux, G., Vaught, T. &#x00026; Millman, J. (eds.) <italic>Proceedings of the 7th Python in Science Conference (SciPy2008)</italic>, 11&#x02013;15 (Pasadena, United States, 2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosvall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maps of random walks on complex networks reveal community structure</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1118</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0706851105</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18216267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216267</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cs&#x000e1;rdi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nepusz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The igraph software package for complex network research</article-title><source>Inter J. Complex Syst.</source><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.3630268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tresoldi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Forkel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cross-Linguistic Transcription Systems (Version 2.2.0)</source><year>2021</year><publisher-name>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inference of partial colexifications from multilingual wordlists</article-title><source>Front. Psychol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1156540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Forkel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>LingPy. A Python Library for Quantitative Tasks in Historical Linguistics [Software Library, Version 2.6.13]</source><year>2023</year><publisher-name>MCL Chair at the University of Passau</publisher-name></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>