<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0415"><xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents a collection of bioeconomy solutions to support green recovery and enhance system resilience in the post-COVID-19 world derived from Fritsche et al. and the authors' further work (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Fritsche et al., 2021</xref>). Food systems' resilience and mitigation strategies that allow adapting rapidly to inevitable crises should become a priority, ensuring that future shocks and extreme events will minimally affect food chains and vulnerable people. It is also vital to increase circularity and integration of biochemical and thermochemical processes for waste's valorization targeting, the production of bio-based products and biofuels. The integration can be achieved using biorefinery processes to extract critical raw materials, e.g., as identified and listed by the EC. In a more general view, it is time and an excellent opportunity to develop a transformative, circular, inclusive, and sustainable bioeconomy that includes all citizens, fosters innovation and provides at least partial economic recovery solutions post-COVID-19 world. It is vital to swift the well-known slogan of &#8220;no one left behind&#8221; to &#8220;leaving no one out.&#8221; This change could be achieved in practice by promoting short- and long-term strategies and actual measures supporting communities, stakeholders, and operators to preserve and diversify economic activities, keep jobs, and ultimately build the required resilience to overcome the crisis. These actions should be combined with sustainable production and decarbonization and stimulate private investments in this direction and monitor the resulting impact of mitigation measures.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Bioeconomy solutions to support green recovery and enhance system resilience in the post-COVID-19 world.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sector</th><th>Solutions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Agriculture</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0045"><list-item id="li0165"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0165">Digitize agriculture-related activities and administration</p></list-item><list-item id="li0170"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0170">Support creation of open big data platforms and Agricultural and Rural Knowledge and Innovation Systems (ARKIS) focused on data-driven farming</p></list-item><list-item id="li0175"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0175">Promote and deploy the potential of carbon farming and agroecology</p></list-item><list-item id="li0180"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0180">Develop sustainable livestock and fisheries, and organic nutrient recovery</p></list-item><list-item id="li0185"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0185">Learn from success policies implemented in different countries</p></list-item><list-item id="li0190"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0190">Develop crisis management plans that predict potential threats, and prevention and emergency response tools</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Food</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0050"><list-item id="li0195"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0195">Promote community marketing channels for local commodities to ensure their distribution at primary and secondary markets</p></list-item><list-item id="li0200"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0200">Intensify efforts on reducing and valorizing food waste via integrated biorefineries</p></list-item><list-item id="li0205"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0205">Support the establishment of food councils at municipal or provincial levels</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Energy</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0055"><list-item id="li0210"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0210">Stimulate local supply chains and securing investments in renewable fuels by stable policies and dedicated financial instruments</p></list-item><list-item id="li0215"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0215">Improve energy resilience through balancing the grid, developing smart infrastructures, and enhancing digital capacities to recalculate potential bioenergy role in the post-COVID-19 era</p></list-item><list-item id="li0220"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0220">Account for changes in urban environments (e.g., teleworking, consumer behavior) to re-adjust planning and market uptake of bioenergy carriers within the circular bioeconomy</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Forestry</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0060"><list-item id="li0225"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0225">Develop tools and support forest practitioners to implement the principles of climate smart forestry</p></list-item><list-item id="li0230"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0230">Demonstrate relevant forest areas adapting these principles</p></list-item><list-item id="li0235"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0235">Cooperate the mobilization of wood resources, while maintaining forest carbon stocks and carbon sequestration</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Finance</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0065"><list-item id="li0240"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0240">Increase funding for circular bioeconomy by mobilizing private investments</p></list-item><list-item id="li0245"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0245">Stimulate biobased products and services through tax rebates and other subsidies promoting their usage</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Cross-cutting</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="l0070"><list-item id="li0250"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0250">Promote the &#8220;BioWEconomy&#8221; and the industrial symbiosis concepts</p></list-item><list-item id="li0255"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0255">Support innovations and technological disruptions</p></list-item><list-item id="li0260"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0260">Promote decentralized biorefineries Establish sustainability criteria for production</p></list-item><list-item id="li0265"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0265">Support the optimal utilization of biomass</p></list-item><list-item id="li0270"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0270">Ameliorate negative impacts on carbon stocks and sequestration in agricultural and forest systems</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>