<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">On the one hand, the cruise ship represents the values of a&#160;powerful industry and the dreams of many travelers. On the other, it symbolizes the concerns and anger of activists and local residents. Through knowledge circulation and direct action, the <italic>Comitato No Grandi Navi </italic>has established the cruise ship as a&#160;symbol of the profound and long-standing impact of the maritime economy on the shore. In addition, it has helped connect different discourses (Link <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1986</xref>: 6) in a&#160;transnational manner. While current debates over social challenges revolve around concepts like growth, de-growth, and post-growth, the cruise ship reflects the increase of growth through its very dimensions. Hence, it has become a&#160;projection screen for different actors and is perceived at the same time as both desirable and destructive. A&#160;particularly important issue represented by the symbol of the cruise ship concerns the effects that the dominance of the tourism industry has on Venice&#8217;s natural and urban infrastructures as well as its everyday life. The <italic>Comitato No Grandi Navi</italic> frequently refers to the dominance of external interests and the heteronomy this creates. The power of industries like the shipping sector stands in contrast with a&#160;city that is shrinking as well as residents who feel that their opportunities are decreasing. While trade once brought wealth to Venice, experts argue that due to an increasingly externalized supply chain, cruise tourism &#8220;brings scant benefit to the port territory&#8221; (Fabbri &amp; Tattara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2014</xref>: 18). Only a&#160;small part of the local population is involved in the sector and benefits from it economically. Meanwhile, many suffer from its consequences: &#8220;Cruise tourism at Venice has been presented by the local administration, the Port Authority, Venice Terminal Passeggeri and the trade unions as an opportunity wellnigh free of cost, to swell the income of the city and its jobs. This is far from being the case. The earnings stemming from increased tourist demand need to be downsized since they entail large external diseconomies (&#8230;)&#8221; (Fabbri &amp; Tattara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2014</xref>: 32f.). The ship stands for the excesses of the industry and for urban economic policies that are contrary to the interests of many citizens. As Donatella della Porta and Sidney Tarrow put it, one can observe &#8220;a&#160;shift in the locus of institutional power&#8221; from politics to the market, resulting in &#8220;the development of a&#160;system of &#8216;complex internationalism,&#8217; which provides both threats and opportunities to ordinary people, to organized nonstate actors&#8221; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2005</xref>: 2). This &#8220;complex internationalism&#8221; is reflected in the cruise industry: it is a&#160;symbol of abundance, social injustice, waste of resources, and displacement. In the passage quoted at the beginning, Silvio Testa grapples with this lack of sustainability, and with the profit maximization of an industry that&#8212;at least until the outbreak of Covid-19&#8212;seemed to represent infinite growth.</p>