<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="news" dtd-version="1.3"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Development (Rome)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Development (Rome)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Development (Society for International Development)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-6370</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1461-7072</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7677425</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33235409</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1057/s41301-020-00278-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>WHO's WHO</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Who's Who</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>63</volume><issue>2-4</issue><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Society for International Development 2020</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Society for International Development 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1"><bold>Salma M. Abdalla</bold> is a physician by training and currently pursuing a doctoral degree in public health at Boston University School of Public Health. She is a research fellow and the lead Project Director of the Rockefeller-Boston University 3-D Commission on Determinants of Health, Data science, and Decision Making. Dr Abdalla&#x02019;s research focuses on applying a systems-thinking approach to the social, political, and commercial determinants of health. She is also interested in studying the effects of mass trauma on the mental health of populations.</p><p id="Par2">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par3"><italic>Email</italic>: abdallas@bu.edu</p><p id="Par4"><bold>Marine Al Dahdah</bold> is a sociologist and a CNRS fellow at Center for the Study of Social Movements. Her research focuses on digital policies in Asia and Africa and more particularly of digital health in India, Ghana and Kenya. She recently published &#x02018;From Evidence-Based to Market-Based Health: Itinerary of a Mobile (for) Development Project&#x02019;<italic>, Science, Technology, &#x00026; Human Values</italic>, 21 January 2019.</p><p id="Par5">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par6"><italic>Email</italic>: marine.aldahdah@gmail.com</p><p id="Par7"><bold>Baba Aye</bold> is the health and social sector officer of Public Services International (PSI). He used to be Deputy General Secretary of the Medical and Health Workers Union of Nigeria (MHWUN) and Coordinating Secretary of the West African Heath Sector Unions (WAHSUN). Baba Aye has a rich history in social movements and was equally Deputy National Secretary of the Labour Party while working in Nigeria. He holds a Master in Labour Policy and Globalization from the Global Labour University.</p><p id="Par8">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par9"><italic>Email</italic>: baba.aye@world-psi.org</p><p id="Par10"><bold>Bhavya Chitranshi</bold> is currently a PhD fellow at the Institute for Culture and Society at the University of Western Sydney. She is co-founder of an indigenous (Kondh) single women's collective, Eka Nari Sanghathan, in India. In close collaboration with the collective, she has been working on issues of gender, sustainable agriculture and post-capitalism, particularly referring to the Kondh context.</p><p id="Par11">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par12"><italic>Email</italic>: b.chitranshi@westernsydney.edu.au</p><p id="Par13"><bold>Anis (Anisuzzaman) Chowdhury</bold> has concurrent adjunct professorial positions at the School of Social Sciences and Psychology, Western Sydney University and the School of Business, University of New South Wales (ADFA, Canberra). He is also co-editor of the Journal of the Asia&#x02013;Pacific Economy and on the Editorial Board of the Economic and Labour Relations Review. He was Director of the UN-ESCAP Macroeconomic Policy &#x00026; Development Division and Statistics Division (July 2012&#x02013;May 2015). He was Chief of the UN-DESA (Financing for Development Office, Multi-Stakeholder Engagement &#x00026; Outreach; June 2015&#x02013;January 2016). Prior to joining the United Nations, he was a Professor of Economics, University of Western Sydney (Australia) between 2001 and 2008. He has published extensively on macroeconomic and development issues.</p><p id="Par14">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par15"><italic>Email</italic>: anis.z.chowdhury@gmail.com</p><p id="Par16"><bold>Isabel Craveiro</bold> is a sociologist from the Coimbra University and has a PHD in Global Health from the Universidade Nova in Lisbon. Since 2018 she has worked as researcher and assistant Professor at the Institute of Hygiene and Tropical Medicines in the Universidade Nova in Lisbon (IHMT NOVA). She coordinates WHO Collaborating Center on Health Workforce Policy and Planning. She works on health informed policies, comparisons of health workforce interventions, social determinants of health and she leads the academic program on Methods and Qualitative Investigation in Health, Health Education and Promotion at Nova University. She also coordinates the Euro-Latin American network on SDG5 on gender equality.</p><p id="Par17">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par18"><italic>Email</italic>: isabelc@ihmt.unl.pt</p><p id="Par19"><bold>Nicoletta Dentico</bold> is a journalist and a human rights advocate, with a long experience in disarmament issues, international cooperation and global health. In 1993 she started the Coalition to Ban Landmines in Italy and coordinated it until early 2000, when she took over as Director-General of M&#x000e9;decins Sans Fronti&#x000e8;res (MSF). In 2004 she joined the MSF Access to Essential Medicines Campaign and then Drugs for Neglected Diseases Initiative (DNDi) in Geneva. She worked as WHO consultant in Geneva and at EMRO in Cairo. From 2011 to 2014 she coordinated the Democratizing Global Health Coalition on the WHO Reform (DGH<italic>)</italic>. She has published extensively on issues related to access to medicines and the right to health. From 2013 to 2019 she served as board member in the Italian Ethical Bank (Banca Popolare Etica). She currently directs the global health programme at Society for International Development (SID).</p><p id="Par20">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par21"><italic>Email</italic>: ndentico@sidint.org</p><p id="Par22"><bold>Gradon Diprose</bold> is a geographer and works as a researcher in environmental social science at Manaaki Whenua&#x02014;Landcare Research in Wellington, New Zealand. His research is informed by feminist and community development approaches to understanding social and environmental change. He is currently working on a range of projects relating to urban wellbeing and food systems, climate change adaptation, and citizen science for biodiversity and landscape restoration. He is a member of the Community Economies Collective.</p><p id="Par23">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par24"><italic>Email:</italic> diproseg@landcareresearch.co.nz</p><p id="Par25"><bold>Mohammed El Said</bold> is a legal consultant and Professor in International Trade and Intellectual Property Law at the School of Justice, the University of Central Lancashire (UK). He worked as a resource person extensively with international organizations including the UNDP, WIPO, UNITAID and WHO in the field of IP policy, IP and development, public health and access to medicines. El Said has several books and publications in the area of intellectual property, public health and access to medicines. He is the author of WHO's policy guide entitled <italic>Public Health Related TRIPS-Plus Provisions in Bilateral Trade Agreements: A Policy Guide for Negotiations and Implementers in the Eastern Mediterranean Region</italic>, WHO-ICTSD, 2010.</p><p id="Par26">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par27"><italic>Email</italic>: MEl-said@uclan.ac.uk</p><p id="Par28"><bold>Teppo Eskelinen</bold> is senior lecturer in development studies at the University of Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;, Finland. His main research interests are alternative and community economies, heterodox economics, critical development theory and social movements. His recent publications include the co-edited book <italic>Enacting community economies within a welfare state</italic> (Mayflybooks, 2020), and articles in journals such as International journal of sociology and social policy, European countryside, and Nordic journal of social research.</p><p id="Par29">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par30"><italic>Email:</italic> teppo.h.i.eskelinen@jyu.fi</p><p id="Par31"><bold>Catherine K. Ettman</bold> is Chief of Staff and Director of Strategic Initiatives for the Dean&#x02019;s Office at Boston University School of Public Health. She is pursuing a PhD in Health Services Research at Brown University School of Public Health. Her research focuses include the social, physical, and economic factors that shape population mental health. She has previously worked in campaign politics in Washington, D.C., and Texas. She is the co-editor of Urban Health (Oxford University Press, 2019).</p><p id="Par32">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par33"><italic>Email:</italic> cettman@bu.edu</p><p id="Par34"><bold>Sandro Galea</bold>, a physician, epidemiologist, and author, is dean and Robert A. Knox Professor at Boston University School of Public Health. He is chair of the board of the Association of Schools and Programs of Public Health and past president of the Society for Epidemiologic Research and of the Interdisciplinary Association for Population Health Science. His work is about the social causes of health, mental health, and the consequences of trauma. He has been listed as one of the most widely cited scholars in the social sciences. He is an elected member of the National Academy of Medicine.</p><p id="Par35">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par36"><italic>Email</italic>: sgalea@bu.edu</p><p id="Par37"><bold>Luzia Gon&#x000e7;alves</bold> is PhD in Experimental Statistics and Data Analysis, Works on Bayesian statistics applied in medical fields; urban planning and health, impact of the financial crisis on physicians, among other. She is assistant professor at the Institute of Hygiene and Tropical Medicines in the Universidade Nova in Lisbon (IHMT NOVA).</p><p id="Par38"><italic>Contact </italic>details</p><p id="Par39"><italic>Email:</italic> LuziaG@ihmt.unl.pt</p><p id="Par40"><bold>Stephen Healy</bold> is a geographer and a Senior Research Fellow at the institute for Culture and Society, University of Western Sydney. His research is informed by Marxian, feminist and psychoanalytic theorizations of social transformation. He is co-author of <italic>Take Back the Economy: An Ethical Guide for Transforming our Communities</italic> with J.K. Gibson-Graham and Jenny Cameron. His works have appeared in Geoforum, Antipode, Emotion Space and Society, Environment and Planning D, and the Annals of the American Association of Geographers. He is a founding member of the Community Economies Collective, and an editorial board member or the <italic>Rethinking Marxism Journal.</italic></p><p id="Par41">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par42"><italic>Email</italic>: Stephen.Healy@westernsydney.edu.au</p><p id="Par43"><bold>Paula Johns</bold> was born and grew up in Brazil. She has a Master of Arts Degree in English and International Development Studies from the Roskilde University Center, in Denmark. She is the co-founder and director of the ACT Health Promotion, a Brazilian coalition of over a thousand members created in 2003 to support the ratification and implementation process of the WHO-Framework Convention on Tobacco Control (FCTC) in Brazil. Since 2013, ACT has expanded its scope of work to include the NCDs agenda. ACT is also one of the leading organizations of the Brazilian Alliance for Healthy and Adequate Food formed in 2016 to support food policy issues. Thanks to her strong advocacy and civil society mobilization profile, Johns has made many presentations on tobacco control and other risk factors for NCDs at national and international conferences and events. She also served as chair of the Board of Directors of the Framework Convention Alliance (FCA), as Board Member of the NCD Alliance and Board Member of Global Alcohol Policy Alliance (GAPA). Johns is also an Ashoka Fellow.</p><p id="Par44">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par45"><italic>Email</italic>: paula.johns@actbr.org.br</p><p id="Par46"><bold>Richard Kozul-Wright</bold> is Director of the Globalization and Development Strategies Division in the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD). He has worked at the United Nations in both New York and Geneva. He is currently Director of the Division on Globalization and Development Strategies and is responsible for the UNCTAD flagship publication The Trade and Development Report. He holds a Ph.D. in economics from the University of Cambridge UK and has published widely on economic issues in academic journals, books and newspapers.</p><p id="Par47">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par48"><italic>Email</italic>: richard.kozul-wright@unctad.org</p><p id="Par49"><bold>Jomo Kwame Sundaram</bold> was Professor at the University of Malaya (1986&#x02013;2004), Founder-Chair of International Development Economics Associates (IDEAs), UN Assistant Secretary General for Economic Development (2005&#x02013;2012) and Assistant Director General for Economic and Social Development, Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) of the United Nations (2012&#x02013;2015). He has received several honours and awards for his work including the 2007 Wassily Leontief Prize for Advancing the Frontiers of Economic Thought.</p><p id="Par50">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par51"><italic>Email</italic>: jomoks@yahoo.com</p><p id="Par52"><bold>Kin Chi Lau</bold> is Adjunct Associate Professor in Cultural Studies and Research Coordinator of the Programme on Cultures of Sustainability, Centre for Cultural Research and Development, Lingnan University, Hong Kong, China. She is member of the International Board of Peace Women Across the Globe, and a Founding Member of Global University for Sustainability.</p><p id="Par53">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par54"><italic>Email</italic>: Laukc@Ln.edu.hk</p><p id="Par55"><bold>Nason Maani</bold> is a biomedical scientist, public health researcher and 2019&#x02013;2020 Harkness Fellow in Healthcare Policy and Practice at Boston University School of Public Health. He is an Assistant Professor in the Faculty of Public Health and Policy at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, an Advisor to the Rockefeller-Boston University 3-D Commission on Determinants of health, Data science, and Decision making. He is a Fellow of the Royal Society of the Arts. His research interests center on the commercial and structural determinants of health and their broader impacts on knowledge generation, discourse, and equity.</p><p id="Par56"><italic>Contact </italic>details</p><p id="Par57"><italic>Email</italic>: Nason.Maani-Hessari@lshtm.ac.uk</p><p id="Par58"><bold>Alejandro Macchia</bold> is specialized in internal medicine and cardiology, and he has been working in the field of public health and epidemiology for more than 20&#x000a0;years in Argentina. The focus of his research is the study of inequities in access to healthcare provision. He is currently researcher at the GESICA Foundation, an independent clinical research group based in Buenos Aires, and consultant to the Ministry of Health of the City of Buenos Aires. In the past, he has worked as research fellow at the Mario Negri Institute in Italy. He has more than 50 indexed publications.</p><p id="Par59">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par60"><italic>Email</italic>: alejandromacchia100@gmail.com</p><p id="Par61"><bold>Anisah Madden</bold> is a PhD Candidate at the Institute for Culture and Society, Western Sydney University, Australia. Her PhD participant-research investigates how transnational food sovereignty movements are reshaping the idea of global food and agriculture governance as &#x02018;caring for the planetary commons&#x02019;. Anisah also supports the participation of youth from grassroots food sovereignty movements in the UN Committee on World Food Security (CFS), through an autonomous Civil Society and Indigenous People&#x02019;s Mechanism (CSM). Previously, she lived and worked in rural communities in Canada for 15&#x000a0;years as a practical herbalist, agroecological gardener, and in a range of small co-operative food enterprises.</p><p id="Par62">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par63"><italic>Email</italic>: a.madden@westernsydney.edu.au</p><p id="Par64"><bold>Francine Mestrum</bold> has a PhD in social sciences and worked at the European institutions and several Belgian universities. Her research concerns the social dimension of globalization, poverty, inequality, social protection, public services and gender. She is an active member of the International Council of the World Social Forum and co-coordinates the social justice cluster in the Asia Europe People&#x02019;s Forum. She is the author of several books (in Dutch, French and English) on development, poverty, inequality and social commons. She is the founder of the global network of Global Social Justice and currently works on a project for social commons. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socialcommons.eu">www.socialcommons.eu</ext-link></p><p id="Par65">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par66"><italic>Email</italic>: mestrum@skynet.be</p><p id="Par67"><bold>Marcela Mulholland</bold> is Deputy Director for Climate at Data for Progress. She represents Data for Progress&#x02019;s work on the Green New Deal and progressive climate policy to the media, policymakers and key partners in the environmental justice and labor movements. Previously, she worked as a Policy Entrepreneur at Next100 developing policy related to the Green New Deal and public housing. Prior to this, Marcela interned with the NAACP&#x02019;s Environmental and Climate Justice Program and served as an organizer and national spokesperson for Sunrise Movement. At Sunrise, Marcela supported climate champions in her home state of Florida and expanded the influence of the Green New Deal among journalists and activists. She has been featured in <italic>The Guardian, The Intercept, New York Daily News,</italic> and <italic>South Florida Sun Sentinel.</italic> Marcela is a South Florida native and holds a B.A. in Political Science and Sustainability Studies from the University of Florida.</p><p id="Par68">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par69">Email: marcelamulholland@gmail.com</p><p id="Par70"><bold>Mathieu Quet</bold> is a research fellow in sociology at CEPED (IRD) in France. His research analyses technological markets and South to South circulations, focussing on pharmaceutical and digital products. He is author of <italic>Impostures pharmaceutiques. M&#x000e9;dicaments illicites et luttes pour l&#x02019;acc&#x000e8;s &#x000e0; la sant&#x000e9;</italic> (Paris, La D&#x000e9;couverte, 2018).</p><p id="Par71">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par72">Email: mathieu.quet@gmail.com</p><p id="Par73"><bold>Carla Ramos Cort&#x000e9;s</bold> is a researcher at Navdanya International. Her work focuses on studying the worldviews that gave way to our current world system crises and the imperatives of agroecological food systems to pave a new path forward. She is an anthropologist, geographer and she holds a Master in International Development, with her specialization in topics of agroecology and traditional farming methods, the decolonization of worldviews and food systems politics.</p><p id="Par74">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par75"><italic>Email</italic>: carla.ramos@navdanyainternational.org</p><p id="Par76"><bold>Emilia Reyes</bold> holds Masters and Bachelor&#x02019;s Degrees in International Relations, from the <italic>Universidad Nacional Aut&#x000f3;noma de M&#x000e9;xico</italic> (National Autonomous University of Mexico). She specialized in gender responsive public policies and budgets and development issues, including comprehensive disaster risk management and climate change. In those fields she trained governmental officers from the Legislative, Judiciary and Executive Branch, as well as officers from UN agencies at national and regional level. She has been a consultant of international organizations, such as the United Nations Entity for Gender Equality and the Empowerment of Women (UN Women), United Nations Development Program (UNDP), United Nations Population Fund (UNFPA). Currently she is the Programme Director of Policies and Budgets for Equality and Sustainable Development, at Equidad de G&#x000e9;nero: Ciudadan&#x000ed;a, Trabajo y Familia (Gender Equity: Citizenship, Work and Family), a non-governmental organization that seeks to mainstream a gender perspective in public policies and budgets at different government levels (state and local), as well as in public institutions. From 2014 to 2019, Emilia Reyes was one of the eight Organizing Partners (OP) of the Women&#x02019;s Major Group for the 2030 Agenda, aiming to promote the active participation of women&#x02019;s and feminists&#x02019; organizations in the 2030 Agenda. From 2017 to 2019 she was a Co-Chair of the High-Level Political Forum Major Groups and other Stakeholders Coordination Mechanism. Since 2017, she is a Co-Convener of the Women&#x02019;s Working Group on Financing for Development.</p><p id="Par77">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par78"><italic>Email</italic>: emilia@equidad.org.mx</p><p id="Par79"><bold>Hernando Salcedo Fidalgo</bold> is a Medical Doctor from the National University of Colombia. He holds a Master in Sociology from the Higher Social Studies School of Paris (EHESS), and was a researcher at the Pragmatic and Reflexive Sociology Group (GSPR) at the EHESS. He currently coordinates the Nutrition Branch in FIAN Colombia.</p><p id="Par80">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par81"><italic>Email</italic>: investigacion1@fiancolombia.org</p><p id="Par82"><bold>Inka Santala</bold> is an urban geographer and a PhD Candidate at the School of Geography and Sustainable Communities, University of Wollongong. Her research explores the perceptions of agency and the dynamics of social change in cities. Drawing from the thinking of transformative social innovation and diverse economies, her current project seeks to understand the citizen subjectivities and collective capacities embedded in community-based sharing. She is a member of the Community Economies Research Network.</p><p id="Par83">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par84"><italic>Email</italic>: ias998@uowmail.edu.au</p><p id="Par85"><bold>Susan K. Sell</bold> is professor at the School of Regulation and Global Governance, Australian National University, and emeritus professor of political science and international affairs at George Washington University. She has published widely on intellectual property, trade and global governance.</p><p id="Par86">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par87"><italic>Email</italic>: susan.sell@anu.edu.au</p><p id="Par88"><bold>Ruchi Shroff</bold>, Director of Navdanya International, is based in Rome (Italy), where she coordinates the international programs and campaigns related to seed freedom, food sovereignty as well as resistance to GMOs, free trade agreements, seed monopolies and biopiracy. One of her main interests lies in investigating the true costs of the industrial food system paradigm and its impacts on agro-biodiversity, socio-economic and ecological sustainability. Trained in physics, economics and management, she has worked for over a decade with social movements struggling for the protection of the environment as well as democratic rights of minorities and indigenous communities.</p><p id="Par89">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par90"><italic>Email</italic>: ruchi@navdanya.net</p><p id="Par91"><bold>Gianni Tognoni</bold> is a medical doctor by profession, and the Secretary General of the Rome-based Permanent Peoples Tribunal since its establishment in 1979. Over the last 35&#x000a0;years, Tognoni has been deeply involved in the promotion of human and people&#x02019;s rights, beginning with his participation in the Russell Tribunal 2 on Latin American Dictatorships (1973&#x02013;1976) and in the preparation of the Universal Declaration of Peoples Rights. In his professional field of medicine, he was involved in the WHO technical group set up for the formulation of essential drugs policies (1977). Tognoni has been instrumental in activating research groups in community epidemiology in most of the countries of Central and Latin America, and in Africa. As research director at the Mario Negri Institute in Milan over the last 30+ years, Dr Tognoni has led scientific projects in the fields of cardiology, intensive care, neurology and psychiatry. The findings have been published in some of the world's leading professional journals.</p><p id="Par92">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par93"><italic>Email</italic>: gianni.tognoni@marionegri.it</p><p id="Par94"><bold>Els Torreele</bold> is a medical innovation &#x00026; access researcher and advocate. Bioengineer and PhD in Applied Biological Sciences from the Free University Brussels (VUB), she became involved in medicines and science policy with M&#x000e9;decins Sans Fronti&#x000e8;res (MSF), including the foundation in 2003 of the Drugs for Neglected Diseases <italic>initiative</italic> (DNDi), where she led R&#x00026;D projects. From 2009&#x02013;2016, she was the director of Access to Medicines at Open Society Foundations (OSF) in New York, after which she re-joined MSF to lead their Access Campaign from 2017-mid 2020. She&#x02019;s a Science Fellow at the VUB and Visiting Fellow at IIPP-University College London.</p><p id="Par95">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par96"><italic>Email</italic>: Els.Torreele@protonmail.com</p><p id="Par97"><bold>Tsui Sit</bold> is Associate Professor at the Institute of Rural Reconstruction of China, Southwest University, Chongqing, China. She is board member of Asian Regional Exchanges for New Alternatives (ARENA-HK), and a Founding Member of Global University for Sustainability.</p><p id="Par98">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par99"><italic>Email</italic>: sittsui@gmail.com</p><p id="Par100"><bold>Jorge Varanda,</bold> Ph.D., is Assistant Professor of Social and Cultural Anthropology in the Department of Life Sciences, University of Coimbra and member of the Direction of the&#x000a0;Centre for Research in Anthropology (CRIA). His research focuses on global health, biomedical care and epidemiology, ethics, urbanization and climate change in Portuguese speaking countries. He was principal investigator (PI) and national PI in several research projects, and as consultant for Ebola (2014&#x02013;2016) and Yellow Fever outbreak research. His recent publications include &#x02018;Putting Anthropology in Global Health&#x02019; in <italic>Anthropology in Action</italic> (2019). Varanda is co-author of the 2018 report &#x02018;Data Sharing in Public Health Emergencies: Anthropological and Historical Perspectives on Data Sharing during the 2014&#x02013;2016 Ebola Epidemic and the 2016 Yellow Fever Epidemic&#x02019; for DFID-Wellcome.</p><p id="Par101">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par102"><italic>Email</italic>: jorge.varanda@uc.pt</p><p id="Par103"><bold>Katharina Weingartner</bold> is a filmmaker, writer and radio-producer, who lives in Vienna. She spent 15&#x000a0;years in New York City. She creates film documentaries, TV-and radio programmes. She writes books and exhibitions about politics, popular/urban culture and consumerism. Her first film &#x02018;Too soon for sorry&#x02019; is a documentary about African-American and Latin youth trapped in the US prison industry. This was followed by &#x02018;Knock Off. Revenge On the Logo&#x02019;, &#x02018;Sneaker Stories&#x02019;, &#x02018;The Gruen Effect&#x02019;. Her latest work is the much acclaimed &#x02018;The Fever&#x02019; in 2019.</p><p id="Par104">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par105"><italic>Email</italic>: wgt@pooldoks.com</p><p id="Par106"><bold>Miriam Williams</bold> is a Lecturer in Geography and Planning at the Macquarie School of Social Sciences, Macquarie University, Sydney, where she is the course director of the Bachelor of Planning. Her research focuses on care, justice, sustainability and commons in the city. Her current work explores the politics and practices of care through an empirical focus on diverse community food initiatives, high-rise living and sustainable household practice. Miriam&#x02019;s work has been published in Antipode, Urban Studies, Area, Cities and Geography Compass. Miriam is a member of the Community Economies Institute and Community Economies Research Network.</p><p id="Par107">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par108"><italic>Email</italic>: miriam.williams@mq.edu.au</p><p id="Par109"><bold>Owain Williams</bold> is an expert on access to medicines, the pharmaceutical and generic sectors and the global legal and institutional regimes governing R&#x00026;D, drug production and pricing. His work has also focused on the politics and political economy of contemporary global health, including work on partnerships and philanthropic foundations in health, Universal Health Coverage (UHC), and capitalism and health. More recently, he has conducted a series of studies on community-based testing programmes for blood borne viruses involving novel point of care diagnostic technologies; a series of studies on tiered pricing for access to drugs in Africa; and an edited a special issue on the political economy of global health and health security. He presently convenes the Pacific Health Governance Research Network (with the SPC) and edits and maintains a website of international social sciences analysis of COVID-19 and is authoring a book on neoliberalism and pandemics for Cambridge University Press.</p><p id="Par110">
<italic>Contact details:</italic>
</p><p id="Par111"><italic>Email</italic>: O.D.Williams@leeds.ac.uk</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>