<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0075">Ethnography in courtroom settings requires engagement over time with diverse temporal, political, legal, ethical and relational concerns (<xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Walenta, 2020</xref>). With courts around the world playing diverse roles as theatres of power, notions of courtroom ethnography and critical socio-legal analysis might give rise to any number of points of emphasis in navigating tensions around capitalist interests, environmental justice, Indigenous rights and climate concerns (<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Setzer &amp; Vanhala, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Williams, 2012</xref>). In certain contexts, research on climate justice is focusing attention to emerging forms of litigation and related optimism (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Klaudt, 2018</xref>). As moves to criminalise peaceful oil pipeline protests (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Horn, 2019</xref>) reached new levels of intensity in 2019 and early 2020, arguments supporting civil disobedience are also receiving increasing attention (<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Rausch, 2019</xref>). Internationally, some judges have both agreed to hear &#8220;necessity defences&#8221; and upheld these defences when acts of conscience were deemed justifiable.<xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref>
Yet, a flurry of new evidence would indicate that industry lobbying to increasingly penalise protest has further weaponized judicial statutes against resistance (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Johnson, 2019</xref>). Concerns have grown that anti-protest legislation is threatening people and the planet, beckoning critical rethinking of why governments are not using resources to prosecute fossil fuel companies instead of &#8216;protestors&#8217; (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Brown, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Ellinger-Locke, 2019</xref>). The tendency of liberalism has long been to locate violence outside of the law so that &#8220;violence and law appear antithetical&#8221; (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Blomley, 2003</xref>), obscuring specificities of injustice (see <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Barnett, 2018</xref>). In an age of rampant fossil fuel violence<xref rid="fn3" ref-type="fn">3</xref>
with legal apparatuses aggressively propping up short-term wealth maximization based on unsustainable resource exploitation (<xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Christie, 2013</xref>), there is increasing impetus to theorize violence at play in &#8216;justice&#8217; systems and re-situate arguments and actions with regard to the necessity of land, water and earth defence.</p>