<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0095">Courthouse moods &#8211; and ethnographies they generate &#8211; are thus invariably shaped by events both near and far. Importantly, two weeks after the above 17-year old boy's sentencing was rendered (and amid many other pending injunction cases in that same court), a different legal drama unfolded, far from this court. Tsleil-Waututh Nation - an Indigenous Nation especially affected by the oil terminal in the Burrard Inlet - earlier had mobilised resources to legally challenge the pipeline approval. On August 30th, 2018, coincidentally the same day as Canada's Federal Government offer to purchase the pipeline was accepted by Kinder Morgan shareholders in Texas, the Federal Court of Appeals ruled that the expansion project's approval was &#8220;impermissibly flawed&#8221;, with unacceptable omissions in the EIA review process and fatally lacking &#8220;meaningful&#8221; consultation with Indigenous people or consideration of the impact on an endangered whale population.<xref rid="fn6" ref-type="fn">6</xref>
While notably not addressing all the problems of concern (still omitting global climate threats and Indigenous health issues), the Federal Court required the project construction to be halted. Yet, the Prime Minister within hours, asserted that the project &#8220;will&#8221; go forward &#8211; seemingly regardless of what any new EIA review and Indigenous consultation processes might reveal. Crown prosecutors thereafter began to be seen in BC Supreme Court hearings for the arrested pipeline injunction defendants, clarifying that prosecutions would continue despite the court decision to halt construction. Far from acknowledging that the land and water defenders were in any way vindicated by this ruling, the aforementioned judge began to <italic>increas</italic>e penalties for those he deemed to have breached his injunction. More trials began, and more prison sentences were issued, with more than 230 people charged by this time.</p>