<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.3"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Soc Work J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Soc Work J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical Social Work Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-1674</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-3343</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9045018</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35502323</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">846</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10615-022-00846-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The 15 Year Relay</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tosone</surname><given-names>Carol</given-names></name><address><email>ct2@nyu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.137628.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8753</institution-id><institution>New York University Silver School of Social Work, </institution></institution-wrap>New York, USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>50</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2022</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2022</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2022</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1"><italic>Activism isn&#x02019;t a sprint, nor is it a marathon. It is a relay race, and it is my time to pass the baton.</italic> While this sage&#x000a0;observation has been made about transgender advocacy by Emily Gorcenski and climate justice by Jane Fonda, it can be equally applied to clinical social work activism through my editorship of the <italic>Clinical Social Work Journal (CSWJ).</italic> Much has changed within social work and the larger mental health profession since I assumed the Editor-in-Chief position in March 2007.</p><p id="Par2">Fifteen plus year ago I began my editorial marathon in earnest, with the primary goals of: (1) ensuring that clinical social work scholarship garners the respect it so richly deserves in the academy; (2) inculcating social work students into the robust theoretical and evidence-based world of clinical social work in an effort to debunk the myth that clinical social work only pertains and caters to wealthy clients in private practice; and, (3) having the <italic>CSWJ</italic> continue to serve as a vital resource for clinicians in agency-based and private practice settings. Toward these ends, I instituted a number of changes to build upon the fine works of my predecessor, the late Dr. Carolyn Saari. Specifically, I expanded the editorial board and consulting reviewer pool to include international social work luminaries, thereby establishing the <italic>CSWJ</italic> as a global entity, one more responsive to the needs of a cross-cultural readership. As part of that expansion, I continually sought reviewers with expertise in different evidence-based practice modalities, problem areas, theoretical perspectives, and vulnerable client populations to better tailor the review process to meet the didactic needs of the writers, some of whom were first time authors. To further enhance the quality and standing of the <italic>CSWJ</italic>, I employed a double-blind review process, increased the number of reviewers from two to three, and reduced the turnaround time from submission to decision.</p><p id="Par3">Perhaps the most influential change to the <italic>CSWJ</italic> was the inclusion of special issues to supplement the general ones. Drawing upon the expertise of noted clinical social work scholars in their respective areas, I enlisted guest editors for a wide range of au courant topics: agency-based practice with vulnerable populations, the art and science of social work, case-based research, child and adolescent therapy, clinical practice with older adults, cybertechnology, DSM-5, evidence-informed and evidence-based practice models, family and couples treatment, group therapy, integrative treatment, LGBTQ clinical work, medical social work, mindfulness, psychoanalysis and clinical social work, a retrospective of social work practice in celebration of Flexner, secondary trauma and compassion fatigue, simulation in field education, supervision in field work and agency settings, and most recently, the impact of COVID-19 on the educational and therapeutic processes. In all, half of the 62 issues during my tenure have been special issues guest edited by prominent scholars and academics, many of whom serve on the editorial board, including Editor-in-Chief Elect, Dr. Melissa Grady.</p><p id="Par4">Many of these special issues spawned the inspiration for <italic>The Essential Clinical Social Work</italic> Series, a collection of (to date) 13 MSW student textbooks that I edit; the purpose of the series is to translate key, timely topics from the <italic>CSWJ</italic> special issues to nascent social workers seeking to&#x000a0;hone their skills and find&#x000a0;their niches in our ever-expanding field. Along my marathon route and in keeping with the language of millennials and Gen Z, social media became a mainstay of communication and a viable means to disseminate news about the journal publications and calls for papers; the <italic>CSWJ</italic> Twitter and Facebook accounts have proven indispensable vehicles for interacting with the readership and responding to their needs and interests through the journal content. I am indebted to Geoffrey Golia, LCSW, the founding Social Media Manager, for his foresight in establishing these accounts. Under his leadership and that of his successor, Jack Osea, MPA, the <italic>CSWJ</italic> Twitter and Facebook accounts have grown substantially (Twitter:&#x02009;~&#x02009;7300 followers; Facebook&#x02009;~&#x02009;4700 followers) and increased the reach of clinical social work.</p><p id="Par5">In addition to Geoffrey and Jack, there have been&#x000a0;numerous contributors to the success of the <italic>CSWJ</italic>, all of whom provided sustenance and cheer along the route, whether by reviewing, guest editing, providing editorial assistance, serving on the editorial board, or most significantly, by reading and disseminating the knowledge contained in the volumes. I am particularly grateful to Dr. Carol Ganzer, Managing Editor of the <italic>CSWJ</italic>, who accompanied me for the duration of this race and who provided the quality assurance that the journal&#x02019;s content had clinical relevance. Carol would often query &#x0201c;What are the clinical implications of the research for practicing clinicians?&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;How will this paper specifically help a clinician with their client?&#x0201d;, two crucial questions that kept the <italic>CSWJ</italic> on course to deliver the promised objectives. The Springer editorial staff, both in the United States and in India, have been stellar throughout the years; Carol Bischoff, Jennifer Hadley, and Teresa Krauss, the Springer Editors and liaisons to the <italic>CSWJ</italic>, consistently provided advice and guidance that furthered the aims of the journal. My editorial assistants during this run ensured the integrity of the double-blind review process and kept the process on pace: Sarah Miller, Ruth Karasik, and Jennifer Bauwens. The editorial board members, guest editors, reviewers, and authors lent their good names to this endeavor, and have been instrumental to the success of the <italic>CSWJ.</italic></p><p id="Par6">At the completion of my race, the <italic>CSWJ</italic> enjoys a respectable impact factor of 1.787 (5-year: 1.825) and is ranked in the middle of journals in the social work field. When I began my editorship, the CSWJ&#x000a0;had an&#x000a0;impact factor of 0.2 and was&#x000a0;the next to last social work-ranked journal.</p><p id="Par7">Of course, the greatest contribution to the success of the journal and the clinical social work field is by you, the reader. To the extent that you have written, interacted with the content, applied the theoretical insights and research findings to your clients, and enhanced your identity as a clinical social worker, you can be proud of these achievements to date.</p><p id="Par8">In choosing the next Editor-in-Chief, I am delighted to pass the baton to a fellow marathoner (literally), Dr. Melissa Grady, Professor of Social Work at The Catholic University of America. Melissa is an eminent and prolific scholar-researcher-practitioner who maintains an abiding belief in the efficacy of clinical social work. As my leg of the race concludes, I am excited for the next chapter of the <italic>CSWJ</italic>, and confident that Melissa will be dedicated to the task at hand. I am also confident that Melissa can count on you to support her vision for the <italic>CSWJ.</italic></p><p id="Par9">With deepest respect and appreciation to all who have contributed to the success of the <italic>Clinical Social Work Journal,</italic></p><p id="Par10">Carol Tosone, PhD</p><p id="Par11">Editor-in-Chief</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>