<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">There is also a statistically significant relationship between the degree of segregation and its effect on SUHI intensity in the inter-city analysis. For every standard deviation increase (0.11) in the <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> index there is on average a corresponding 0.42 K increase in SUHI intensity. The intercept implies that areas with zero degrees of segregation&#8212;complete integration&#8212;would have a SUHI intensity of 0.59 K and as segregation measures increases so does the heat island temperature intensity. This model similarly contains random effect specifications accounting for influences that are geographically and temporally variable. Observations support Mitchell and Chakraborty where higher measures of the <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> index were shown to indicate increases in urban heat risk for Black and Hispanic communities [<xref rid="B6-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Residential segregation tends to compact racial and ethnic groups into densely populated smaller communities, evidenced by the varying number of prevalent census tracts in the study for each group (27,338 White, 6597 Black, 7917 Hispanic, and 2624 Asian prevalent tracts). However, simply integrating these areas within a city, or lowering the level of segregation would not precipitate a lowering of the heat island intensity. There are far too many detrimental environmental impacts of segregation which are difficult to amend and such locations tend to have higher proportions of impervious surface land cover and less tree canopy [<xref rid="B55-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B56-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Simply lowering the level of segregation does not increase tree cover or lower the amount of impervious surface without emphasis placed on urban greening. However, such gentrification initiatives have been shown to continue to relegate historically marginalized groups [<xref rid="B57-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Numerous studies have identified &#8220;Redlining&#8221; or the Home Owners&#8217; Loan Corporation practice beginning in the 1930s of grading neighborhoods for home loans as being a significant driver in the persistence of the observed spatially variable disparities in thermal exposure and components of the physical and social environment that lead to them [<xref rid="B56-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="B58-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="B59-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="B60-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="B61-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Significant interventions within the urban environment, that include input from historically marginalized urban populations, will be necessary to lower these observed disparities in SUHI exposure in impactful ways.</p>