<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par2">Increasing evidence indicates that climate change will have far-reaching impacts on human health, including mental health (Doherty &amp; Clayton, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2011</xref>; Hayes et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2018</xref>). A large body of literature has investigated the mental health consequences of one marker of climate change, weather-related disasters, showing elevated rates of common psychiatric conditions like Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) (Goldmann &amp; Galea, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2014</xref>; Hrabok et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>), and a growing number of studies also suggest that rising temperatures can impair mental health and increase risk for suicidal behavior (Burke et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2018</xref>; Cianconi et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2020</xref>; Heo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2021</xref>). However, a focus on weather-related disasters and temperature misses the full range of climate change exposures, including its subtler indicators, and their mental health consequences. Recent research indicates that even the existential threat of climate change may be associated with adverse mental health outcomes, particularly among younger populations, and recent studies have documented the existence of climate change anxiety (CCA). CCA is defined as negative responses associated with concerns about climate change (Clayton, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2020</xref>; Wullenkord et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>). It may include cognitive, emotional, and behavioral responses, for example, persistent worries, psychological distress, or sleep difficulties related to long-term consequences of climate change, and can result in functional impairment, such as when concerns about climate change interfere with an individual&#8217;s ability to engage fully in work, school, or relationships (Clayton &amp; Karazsia, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2020</xref>). This constellation of responses does not itself qualify as a psychiatric disorder, such as MDD or GAD, but indicates a source of stress that can have a negative impact on mental health (Clayton, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2020</xref>).</p>