<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0020">For instance, with consumers enjoying access to a multiplicity of energy-efficient yet easier and openly accessible services, living potentially outside environmental limits, energy use may instead grow <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. This has been the case over the last quarter century, with energy consumption increasing far quicker than population growth, despite the uneven distribution of benefits from increased energy access <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> and energy efficiency being considered a top priority in some regions. More recently, increasing Google services users tripled respective energy consumption during the past eight years. The annual carbon footprint of cryptocurrency mining networks is now comparable to national economies <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The majority of global bandwidth is consumed for video streaming. And so on <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. And, although free access to emerging digital services is socially beneficial and contributes to sustainability in various manners (for instance, by reducing inequalities), it may not be in keeping with the traditional climate policy model and required sustainability efforts <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, when referring to highly energy-consuming lifestyles. Nevertheless, to date, only limited attention has been paid to the demand side of energy transition. Recent, yet scarce, examples of research in the demand side include the multiple dimensions of structural changes <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>; the role and readiness of individuals and households <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>; psychological barriers at the household level <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, the importance of social innovation and systemic forms of social change <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>; challenges of energy sufficiency <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and living within planetary boundaries; social justice <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> and gender aspects <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>.</p>