<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0025">These observations and knowledge gaps have been evident in the coronavirus health emergency as well. The policy and market responses to the pandemic, including imposition of social lockdowns <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> and disruptions to global supply chains <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, have led to unprecedented short-term reductions of GHG emissions that are expectedly comparable to the Paris-compliant, year-on-year decrease rates necessary in the coming decades <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Fuelled by confinement rather than freewill, however, most of the changes contributing to the environmental silver lining of COVID-19 are likely to be temporary as they do not reflect the desired structural changes in the economic, transport and energy systems <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Moreover, a socio-economic rebound of COVID-related consequences has already shifted burdens, reallocating the care work and diverting electricity costs over to households and individuals, opening further discussion on gender roles, energy poverty and justice <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. While discussions focus on the governments&#8217; eagerness to recover, make up for lost economic ground and even push towards a rebound with even higher emission pathways compared to pre-pandemic trajectories, with implications for progress on climate change <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> and sustainable energy infrastructure <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, there appear to be little targeted planning and communication strategies for a recovery based on more sustainable practices and lifestyles. In this scientific &#8216;opportunity&#8217; to ground a new research agenda <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, behavioural science is critical <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> to explore and model the ways, in which such extreme situations could alter future trajectories <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>: should the coronavirus-related massive and rapid behavioural responses of the general citizenry <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref> be taken for granted, or are citizens to be considered eager to return to the previous norm, with the expected exception of some social distancing measures <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> and voluntary working-from-home habits <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>? Again, the question on &#8216;who benefits&#8217; from these arrangements is highly relevant, given that not everyone has the same opportunity to socially distance or work from home.</p>