<contrib-group xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/"><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0889-1023</contrib-id><name><surname>Lipper</surname><given-names>Leslie</given-names></name><address><email>leslie.lipper@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><bio><sec id="FPar1"><title>Leslie Lipper</title><p id="Par1">is a natural resource economist who has worked for over 30 years in the field of sustainable agricultural development. She holds a doctorate in Agricultural and Resource Economics from the University of California at Berkeley. She was the Executive Director of the Independent Science and Partnership Council of the CGIAR from 2016 to 2019 and the Senior Environmental Economist at the Food and Agriculture Organization for over 10 years. At present she holds a visiting fellow position at Cornell University, and she is a technical advisor to the Ceres 2030 project and senior advisor to IFAD on the 2021 Rural Development Report on Food Systems Transformation.<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="12571_2021_1210_Figa_HTML" id="MO1"/></p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cavatassi</surname><given-names>Romina</given-names></name><address><email>r.cavatassi@ifad.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><bio><sec id="FPar2"><title>Romina Cavatassi</title><p id="Par2">is the lead natural resource economist in the Research and Impact Assessment Division of IFAD where she is in charge of leading the Impact Assessment and research cluster in addition to leading the preparation of the Rural Development Report on Inclusive Food System Transformation. Prior to this role she was the lead technical Specialist for Environment and Climate in the Environment and Climate division of IFAD. Her expertise ranges from Impact assessment to evidence based analysis for decision and policy making particularly in the field of climate change, natural resource economics, poverty alleviation, survey design, training, data collection, data base management, data analysis, management. Prior to joining IFAD, Romina worked for FAO, where she focused on development and natural resource economics. She holds a PhD in natural resources and development economics from Wageningen University and Research Centre in the Netherlands, an MSc in environmental assessment and evaluation from the London School of Economics in the UK and a master&#8217;s-level degree in economics from the University of Bologna, Italy.<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="12571_2021_1210_Figb_HTML" id="MO2"/></p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Symons</surname><given-names>Ricci</given-names></name><address><email>r.symons@ifad.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><bio><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ricci Symons</title><p id="Par3">is a technical Specialist on Environment and Climate Change with the Environment Climate Gender and Social Inclusion division of IFAD. Ricci backstops and provide guidance to ensure quality implementation of the ASAP1 and contributed to its reporting, he also contributes to the design of the Rural Resilience Programme, resource mobilisation, providing technical inputs to projects, engagement with corporate events such as replenishment committees and executive boards, and deals with ad hoc senior management requests. Prior to IFAD, he worked at JP Morgan in both due diligence and compliance roles. He holds a BSc in Chemistry from the University of Cardiff (UK)<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="12571_2021_1210_Figd_HTML" id="MO3"/></p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gordes</surname><given-names>Alashiya</given-names></name><address><email>a.gordes@ifad.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><bio><sec id="FPar4"><title>Ms. Alashiya Gordes</title><p id="Par4">is a Technical Specialist with the Environment Climate Gender and social Inclusion and with the Operational Policy and Results divisions of IFAD. She works on IFAD&#8217;s climate results reporting and supporting the implementation of the IFAD11 mainstreaming commitments.</p><p id="Par5">Prior to joining IFAD in 2019, Alashiya worked as a Natural Resources Officer in the Climate and Environment Division of the UN Food and Agriculture Organization, supporting countries to integrate agriculture in their National Adaptation Plans and promoting Climate-Smart Agriculture approaches. She has also worked with the Global Donor Platform for Rural Development in Bonn, Germany and the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change in Warsaw, Poland (at COP19).</p><p id="Par6">Alashiya holds an MSc in Environmental Policy from the University of Oxford, UK. She is a national of Cyprus and Germany and speaks English, German, French, Italian and Greek.<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="12571_2021_1210_Figc_HTML" id="MO4"/></p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>Oliver</given-names></name><address><email>o.page@ifad.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><bio><sec id="FPar5"><title>Oliver Page</title><p id="Par7">is the Lead Climate and Environment Specialist for the Latin America and the Caribbean Region (LAC) at IFAD. He has over 15 years&#8217; experience working in the climate and environment field with specialization in mobilizing climate finance. Currently he is responsible for ensuring that IFAD&#8217;s LAC portfolio meets all climate, environment and social inclusion commitments, and that all projects adequately develop and apply IFAD environmental and social standards. He also leads LAC&#8217;s efforts in mobilizing external climate finance and has secured GCF financing for two IFAD/GCF projects in Belize and Brazil. Oliver has triple Argentinian/Uruguayan/British citizenship. He holds a Master&#8217;s degree in Environmental Policy from Columbia&#8217;s School of International and Public Affairs, and a Bachelor&#8217;s degree in Environmental Engineering from Cornell University.<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="12571_2021_1210_Fige_HTML" id="MO5"/></p></sec></bio></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5386.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000041936877X</institution-id><institution>Department of Global Development, </institution><institution>Cornell University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ithaca, NY 14850 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466871.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1956 6627</institution-id><institution>Research and Impact Assessment Division, International Fund for Agricultural Development, </institution></institution-wrap>Roma, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466871.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1956 6627</institution-id><institution>Environment and Climate Change, Environment Climate Gender and Social Inclusion Division, International Fund for Agricultural Development, </institution></institution-wrap>Roma, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466871.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1956 6627</institution-id><institution>Latin America and Caribbean Region, International Fund for Agricultural Development, </institution></institution-wrap>Roma, Italy </aff></contrib-group>