<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par28">If we assume that a CA supplemented with ceilings is reasonable, how much is one permitted or required to restrict agents&#8217; capabilities when they have reached the threshold and others are below it? If the capability ceiling is equivalent to the threshold, then a restriction applies to an agent just after it has reached the threshold. While Holland concedes that the threshold and ceiling overlapping may seem reasonable, she also writes that &#8216;the capability to control one&#8217;s material environment might allow for a ceiling that is set far above the threshold&#8217; (Holland, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2008</xref>: 419). For instance, a property owner may extract groundwater from their property above a level required for subsistence, for a variety of other reasons, but only up to the point at which further extraction &#8216;starts to undermine other central capabilities&#8217; (Holland, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2008</xref>: 419). Consequently, we may specify <italic>the threshold&#8211;ceiling relation</italic> in the following manner:<disp-quote><p id="Par29">The threshold and the ceiling are <italic>equivalent</italic> if passing the threshold results in others not reaching up to the threshold. The threshold and the ceiling are <italic>not equivalent</italic> if passing the threshold is consistent with others reaching up to the threshold.</p></disp-quote>Restricting capabilities of those that have reached high levels above the threshold is required within the CA when supplemented with ceilings. The requirement of such ceilings is motivated when they are necessary for allowing others to reach the threshold. Giving the capabilities of those under the minimal threshold levels absolute priority is consistent with setting the ceiling equivalent to the threshold, <italic>if</italic> that is required. When capabilities require consumption of finite resources, it may very well be the case that the threshold and ceiling are equivalent suggesting that no one is entitled to consume <italic>more</italic> than is necessary for that capability, as doing so would mean blocking others from reaching their capability thresholds. This is what the example of the groundwater illustrates. What such a requirement results in may differ regarding the means necessary to fulfill specific capabilities and the capabilities that one is considering.</p>