<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Kabeer&#8217;s analytical framework (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>) is helpful to explore our findings further. She points out that the concept of agency has positive and negative meanings in relation to power. The negative sense of &#8220;power over&#8221; refers to the capacity of people (and organisations) to override the agency of others. To an extent, our data supports the enactment of this form of power through the RDRS (and its funders). Its targeting criteria, which are both &#8220;hard&#8221; (area of land farmed) and &#8220;soft&#8221; (the trainee should be known to us) exclude low-income women and men and thus disallow them the chance to express and build their agency. This may have the long-term effect of deepening their marginalisation. In the positive sense of &#8220;power to&#8221;, agency describes people&#8217;s capacity to define their own life choices and to pursue their own goals (Kabeer <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). Our data supports this reading of agency as well. Some Santal and ethnic Bengali women are starting to define their own life choices and pursue their own goals &#8211; facilitated by the women&#8217;s organisation. A third form of agency, described as &#8220;power with&#8221;, refers to the capacity to augment power through collective action. There is evidence of this form of power being operationalised in the study community. Successful women innovators receive support from male family members and their extended family. Santal and Muslim women are working together through the Kalipara Union Federation to cooperate in securing access to wheat&#8211;maize innovations. Finally, power can also exist in the absence of any apparent agency. Norms and rules governing social behaviour can ensure that certain outcomes, such as identity-based marginalisation, are reproduced without obvious exercise of agency (Kabeer <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>).</p>