<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0035">Air travel represents a growing challenge to the global carbon budget as it is expected to increase by 300% by 2050 (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Higham et al., 2019</xref>; ICAO, 2016). In addition, tourism demands are expected to contribute to 40% of global CO2 emission by 2050 (<xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Dubois &amp; Ceron, 2006</xref>), of which aviation adds the largest share (<xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Higham, Cohen, &amp; Cavaliere, 2013</xref>). While transportation is responsible for 23% of annual greenhouse gas emissions, emissions specific to aviation are about 4&#8211;5% (<xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Larsson et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Higham et al., 2014</xref>). There are about 4.23 billion total airline passengers per year (<xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">ICAO, 2018</xref>). However, only about 6% of the global human population travel by air in any given year and about 20% of people have flown in their lives (<xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Negroni, 2016</xref>). This would make roughly 455.640.000 people responsible for the 1660 Mt of annual CO2 emissions from air travel (4% of 41,500 Mt<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
Global C02 Emissions in 2018; <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Le Qu&#233;r&#233; et al., 2018</xref>). This results in a per person annual impact of 3.64&#160;t<xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref>
when divided evenly. Therefore, this behavior alone places this 6% as one of the highest emitting populations globally, well above the yearly per capita average of many nations (<xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">World Bank, 2015</xref>). Concerning Covid-19, many of these air travel projections will need reassessment to account for the travel slump during the pandemic. Nonetheless, air travel is likely to recover and the passengers who fly in the interim will have inflated footprints if their flights are not full. To contextualize the impact of air travel relative to national averages, a single round-trip flight is compared to the average per capita emissions of the developing countries where <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Kashwan (2017)</xref> documents conservation conflict with community forestry enterprises (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The percent of average yearly per capita emissions of roundtrip flights compared to annual national per capita averages. The calculations use the effective climate impact of flying at 0.189&#160;kg/pkm<xref rid="fn3" ref-type="fn">a</xref> from <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Larsson et al. (2018)</xref> for international flights. Great circle distances were taken from Google Earth. Average annual per capita emissions were taken from the <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">World Bank (2015)</xref>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Country</th><th>Average annual per capita emissions t/person</th><th>One round-trip flight t/person</th><th>Percent of the average annual per capita emissions of the round-trip flight</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Global Average</td><td align="char">4.98</td><td>2.10 (New York to London)</td><td>42%</td></tr><tr><td>United States</td><td align="char">16.50</td><td>2.10 (New York to London)</td><td>13%</td></tr><tr><td>Mexico</td><td align="char">4.00</td><td>3.37 (Mexico City to London)</td><td>84%</td></tr><tr><td>India</td><td align="char">1.70</td><td>2.54 (New Delhi to London)</td><td>149%</td></tr><tr><td>Tanzania</td><td align="char">0.20</td><td>2.75 (Dodoma to London)</td><td>1373%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>