<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">A reasonably consistent finding across messaging studies is that negatively framed messages tend to be more effective than positively framed ones for influencing attitudes and behaviors (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_003" ref-type="bibr">Amatulli et&#160;al. 2019</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_014" ref-type="bibr">Davis 1995</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_019" ref-type="bibr">Ganzach and Karsahi 1995</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_043" ref-type="bibr">Levin et&#160;al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_052" ref-type="bibr">Meyerowitz and Chaiken 1987</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_061" ref-type="bibr">Olsen et&#160;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_093" ref-type="bibr">White et&#160;al. 2011</xref>). That is to say, messages that emphasize the benefits of engaging in pro-environmental behavior are typically less persuasive than those that emphasize the risks or potential losses associated with not engaging in that behavior, e.g. the benefits of purchasing a &#8216;green&#8217; product versus the disadvantages associated with not purchasing it, or positively framed product claims such as &#8220;biodegradable&#8221; and &#8220;recyclable&#8221; versus negatively framed ones such as &#8220;no pesticides&#8221; and &#8220;no phosphates&#8221; (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_061" ref-type="bibr">Olsen et&#160;al. 2014</xref>). <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_003" ref-type="bibr">Amatulli et&#160;al. (2019)</xref> argue that this effect can be attributed specifically to the activation of the emotion of shame, or &#8220;anticipated shame&#8221;, while <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_093" ref-type="bibr">White et&#160;al. (2011)</xref> propose that it is due in part to fluency, i.e. ease of cognitive processing. <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_093" ref-type="bibr">White et&#160;al. (2011)</xref> contest, however, that negative frames are always more effective: they find that negative, or loss-framed, messages are more persuasive in contexts of low-level or concrete actions (e.g. the act of reusing or returning packaging), while positive, or gain-framed, messages are potentially more appropriate for high-level or abstract purposes (e.g. fostering beliefs about why reusing and returning packaging is important). These are also the findings of <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_048" ref-type="bibr">Lord (1994)</xref>, whose study on recycling concludes that the most effective motivator of recycling behaviors is a negatively framed message conveyed by a personal acquaintance, while positively framed messages are more effective at promoting a favourable attitude towards recycling generally.</p>