<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Policy Plan</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Policy Plan</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">heapol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Health Policy and Planning</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0268-1080</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2237</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7996636</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33347561</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/heapol/czaa165</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">czaa165</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentaries</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Climate change: an urgent priority for health policy and systems research</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marten</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="czaa165-cor1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="czaa165-aff1">1</xref><!--<email>martenr@who.int</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yangchen</surname><given-names>Sonam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="czaa165-aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell-Lendrum</surname><given-names>Diarmid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="czaa165-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prats</surname><given-names>Elena Villalobos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="czaa165-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Neira</surname><given-names>Maria Purificacion</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="czaa165-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghaffar</surname><given-names>Abdul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="czaa165-aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="czaa165-aff1"><label>1</label>
<institution>Alliance for Health Policy and Systems Research, World Health Organization</institution>, Avenue Appia 20, 1211 Geneva, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="czaa165-aff2"><label>2</label>
<institution>Environment, Climate Change and Health Department, World Health Organization</institution>, Avenue Appia 20, 1211 Geneva, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="czaa165-cor1">Corresponding author. Alliance for Health Policy and Systems Research, World Health Organization, Avenue Appia 20, 1211 Geneva, Switzerland. E-mail: <email>martenr@who.int</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2020-12-21"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>36</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020. Published by Oxford University Press in association with The London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc-nd" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="czaa165.pdf"/><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Climate change is the defining global public health threat of the twenty-first century (<xref rid="czaa165-B22" ref-type="bibr">Whitmee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="czaa165-B24" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="czaa165-B21" ref-type="bibr">Watts <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) and has profound implications for nearly every aspect of health. The ongoing COVID-19 crisis is causing unprecedented disruptions to health systems, but climate change will have even greater&#x02014;much greater&#x02014;consequences. Yet health policy and systems researchers largely continue to ignore and overlook climate change. This is a critical oversight. Countries with the greatest vulnerability to climate change have the least developed health systems (<xref rid="czaa165-B19" ref-type="bibr">Salas and Jha, 2019</xref>), and climate change will further compound and exacerbate existing inequalities (<xref rid="czaa165-B3" ref-type="bibr">Costello <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Health policy and systems research (HPSR) is well positioned to accelerate the needed response and transformation (<xref rid="czaa165-B14" ref-type="bibr">Peters, 2018</xref>). HPSR could make countless contributions to address the climate challenge. We highlight three interlinked reasons, which should motivate the HPSR community to prioritize a focus on climate change.</p><p>First, HPSR is crucial to understanding the impact and implications of climate change. HPSR seeks to analyse how different actors interact in policy and implementation processes to improve health outcomes. It draws on a blend of public health, economics, sociology, anthropology, political science and epidemiology and can serve as a multidisciplinary bridge to these various fields. HPSR seeks to analyse how health systems respond and adapt to health policies, and how health policies can shape and be shaped by health systems and broader determinants of health like climate change (<xref rid="czaa165-B1" ref-type="bibr">AHPSR, 2007</xref>). The interdisciplinary nature of HPSR makes it well positioned to tackle the complexity of climate change and can improve the analysis of linkages between health and climate. Until now, the climate change and health literature have focused on infectious diseases (<xref rid="czaa165-B7" ref-type="bibr">Hosking and Campbell-Lendrum, 2012</xref>), along with deaths and injuries from extreme weather events, the adverse health effects of extreme heat (<xref rid="czaa165-B7" ref-type="bibr">Hosking and Campbell-Lendrum, 2012</xref>), and risks of under-nutrition due to declines in food yields (<xref rid="czaa165-B4" ref-type="bibr">Friel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="czaa165-B7" ref-type="bibr">Hosking and Campbell-Lendrum, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="czaa165-B27" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). These studies show how climate change affects health outcomes; HPSR could augment ongoing efforts and widen this understanding by applying a systems approach. There is an urgent need to take a broader health systems and health policies perspective; this is the role of the HPSR community. Researchers can help policymakers appreciate, anticipate and work to prevent the effects of climate change on human health and well-being. For example, most efforts to achieve primary health care (PHC) do not sufficiently consider the implications of the climate crisis (<xref rid="czaa165-B10" ref-type="bibr">Kadandale <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). There is a need to revise the discourse, policy and practice on efforts to achieve PHC, but also universal health coverage to include explicit consideration of climate change and its health effects.</p><p>Second, HPSR is essential to developing and designing both climate change mitigation and adaptation policies within the health sector. It can also help policymakers appreciate how to implement these policies. The emergent literature on health systems and climate change considers adaptation (<xref rid="czaa165-B12" ref-type="bibr">Mayhew and Hanefeld, 2014</xref>), but there is comparatively limited work on mitigation, though these will vary by context, with mitigation policies needed urgently in high-income, high-emitting countries and adaptation policies needed in countries with relatively fewer emissions, both approaches are crucial. A 2019 World Health Organization (WHO) survey found that knowledge of the health implications of climate change is shaping policymaking, however, additional financial or human resources are not being allocated to meet the challenge (<xref rid="czaa165-B25" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2019</xref>). Adequate financial resources, including from climate change funding sources, have not shifted to health budgets. For example, the same survey identified financing as one the main barriers with only 9% of National Adaptation Plans for Health (H-NAP) being fully resourced (<xref rid="czaa165-B25" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2019</xref>).</p><p>Addressing this requires strengthening health policymakers&#x02019;, health workers&#x02019; and health institutions&#x02019; capacities to adapt to and address climate-induced health risks, but also to study and assess how the health sector can mitigate climate change by moving away from fossil-fuels and decarbonizing. For example, implementation research, a core approach in HPSR, could help improve and accelerate the development and roll-out of these policies (<xref rid="czaa165-B15" ref-type="bibr">Peters <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). It could also help codify, document and share lessons applicable for other countries. This could also help address climate justice (<xref rid="czaa165-B16" ref-type="bibr">Pratt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Linking health justice, social justice and climate justice is an integral part to addressing the climate crisis and is another place where HPSR could help foster deeper understanding of the needed policy changes (<xref rid="czaa165-B18" ref-type="bibr">Rouf and Wainwright, 2020</xref>). In doing so, the HPSR community can play a catalytic role empowering researchers and communities to make informed decisions and influence political action (<xref rid="czaa165-B20" ref-type="bibr">Theobald <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p><p>Third, by helping transform the health sector in response to climate change, the HPSR community can demonstrate leadership and develop linkages both within and beyond the health sector to respond to climate change and create healthier populations (<xref rid="czaa165-B6" ref-type="bibr">Healthier Societies for Healthy Populations Group, 2020</xref>). As the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic highlights, this is critical for a wider transformation towards a greater focus on sustainability. HPSR can deepen understandings of how to overcome policy obstacles both within and beyond the health sector, and how different actors are able to successfully (or unsuccessfully) pursue reforms. For example, an assessment found that efficiency gains from coherent multisectoral policies addressing energy use, health, climate change and air quality could save 40% of the total costs (<xref rid="czaa165-B9" ref-type="bibr">International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, 2012</xref>).</p><p>Researchers and policymakers are also beginning to recognize the connection between climate change, pollution, environmental risks and non-communicable diseases (NCDs) (<xref rid="czaa165-B11" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="czaa165-B2" ref-type="bibr">Campbell-Lendrum and Pr&#x000fc;ss-Ust&#x000fc;n, 2019</xref>); HPSR could help expand these understandings. Equipping health sector actors to become strong advocates on climate change is critical given the many linkages across determinants of health&#x02014;clean air, safe drinking water, enough food and secure shelter (<xref rid="czaa165-B21" ref-type="bibr">Watts <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). Until recently health has not featured prominently within the international climate change agenda (<xref rid="czaa165-B23" ref-type="bibr">Workman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="czaa165-B13" ref-type="bibr">Ossebaard and Lachman, 2020</xref>). HPSR can help the health sector contribute to improved governance developing coherent and sensitively designed, cross-sectoral policies and programmes, which could produce major co-benefits for people and planet (<xref rid="czaa165-B27" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). For example, multisectoral collaboration and action for health are critical, but capacities for multisectoral action for health are underdeveloped and limited (<xref rid="czaa165-B17" ref-type="bibr">Rasanathan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>); this is especially the case for climate change.</p><p>The HPSR community must urgently consider and engage with climate change. As countries and policymakers continue to address the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic, the focus will be on &#x02018;building back better&#x02019;. As part of this, WHO&#x02019;s manifesto for a healthy recovery from COVID-19 details six prescriptions to create a healthier society, more resilient to future outbreaks and epidemics (<xref rid="czaa165-B26" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020</xref>). One of these is the need to focus on investing in essential health services. To make this happen, HPSR is critical. But more broadly as the HPSR community rethinks and reconsiders HPSR in the post-COVID era (<xref rid="czaa165-B5" ref-type="bibr">Gilson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>), thinking beyond the &#x02018;six health systems building blocks&#x02019; and addressing climate change must be an integral part of the post-COVID-19 agenda.</p><p>
<italic>Conflict of interest statement.</italic> None declared.</p><p>
<italic>Ethical approval.</italic> No ethical approval was required for this study.</p></body><back><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References </title><ref id="czaa165-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alliance for Health Policy and Systems Research (AHPSR). <year>2007</year>. <italic>What Is Health Policy and Systems Research and Why Does It Matter?</italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/alliance-hpsr/resources/Alliance%20HPSR%20-%20Briefing%20Note%201.pdf?ua=1">https://www.who.int/alliance-hpsr/resources/Alliance%20HPSR%20-%20Briefing%20Note%201.pdf?ua=1</ext-link>, accessed 18 July 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Campbell-Lendrum</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pr&#x000fc;ss-Ust&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2019</year>. 
<article-title>Climate change, air pollution and noncommunicable diseases</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30728622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Costello</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2009</year>. 
<article-title>Managing the health effects of climate change</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source><volume>373</volume>: <fpage>1693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>733</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Friel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell-Lendrum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>. 
<article-title>Climate change, noncommunicable diseases, and development: the relationships and common policy opportunities</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Public Health</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Gilson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayepong</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>What role can health policy and systems research play in supporting responses to COVID-19 that strengthen socially just health systems?</article-title><source>Health Policy and Planning</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33020815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Healthier Societies for Healthy Populations Group. <year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>Healthier societies for healthy populations</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source><volume>395</volume>: <fpage>1747</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Hosking</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell-Lendrum</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>. 
<article-title>How well does climate change and human health research match the demands of policymakers? A scoping review</article-title>. <source>Environmental Health Perspectives</source><volume>120</volume>: <fpage>1076</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22504669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis. <year>2012</year>. <italic>The Global Energy Assessment</italic>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://iiasa.ac.at/web/home/research/Flagship-Projects/Global-Energy-Assessment/Home-GEA.en.html">https://iiasa.ac.at/web/home/research/Flagship-Projects/Global-Energy-Assessment/Home-GEA.en.html</ext-link>, accessed 25 July 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Kadandale</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marten</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dalglish</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>Primary health care and the climate crisis</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</source><volume>98</volume>: <fpage>818</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33177781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell-Lendrum</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. 
<article-title>Climate change and health in Pacific island states</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</source><volume>93</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26668431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Mayhew</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanefeld</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. 
<article-title>Planning adaptive health systems: the climate challenge</article-title>. <source>The Lancet Global Health</source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e625</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.PMID: 25442681.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25442681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Ossebaard</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lachman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>Climate change, environmental sustainability and health care quality</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Quality in Health Care</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>mzaa036</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>DH.</given-names>
</string-name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>. 
<article-title>Health policy and systems research: the future of the field</article-title>. <source>Health Research Policy and Systems</source><volume>16</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30134979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alonge</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>. 
<article-title>Implementation research: what it is and how to do it</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><volume>347</volume>: <fpage>f6753</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24259324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Pratt</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barasa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>Justice: a key consideration in health policy and systems research ethics</article-title>. <source>BMJ Global Health</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e001942</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Rasanathan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>. 
<article-title>Governing multisectoral action for health in low- and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>PLoS Medicine</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>e1002285</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28441387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Rouf</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wainwright</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>Linking health justice, social justice, and climate justice</article-title>. <source>The Lancet Planetary Health</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32353288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Salas</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>AK.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2019</year>. 
<article-title>Climate change threatens the achievement of effective universal healthcare</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><fpage>366</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>:4378.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Theobald</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brandes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gyapong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>. 
<article-title>Implementation research: new imperatives and opportunities in global health</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source><volume>392</volume>: <fpage>2214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Watts</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arnell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2019</year>. 
<article-title>The 2019 report of the Lancet Countdown on health and climate change: ensuring that the health of a child born today is not defined by a changing climate</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source><volume>394</volume>: <fpage>1836</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Whitmee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beyrer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>. 
<article-title>Safeguarding human health in the Anthropocene epoch: report of the Rockefeller Foundation&#x02013;Lancet Commission on planetary health</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source><volume>386</volume>: <fpage>1973</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2028</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Workman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blashki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>. 
<article-title>The political economy of health co-benefits: embedding health in the climate change agenda</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>674</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization (WHO). <year>2018</year>. <italic>Climate Change and Health</italic>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/climate-change-and-health">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/climate-change-and-health</ext-link>, accessed 20 August 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization (WHO). <year>2019</year>. <italic>WHO Health and Climate Change Survey</italic>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/329972/WHO-CED-PHE-EPE-19.11-eng.pdf?ua=1,">https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/329972/WHO-CED-PHE-EPE-19.11-eng.pdf?ua=1,</ext-link> accessed 20 August 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization (WHO). <year>2020</year>. <italic>WHO Manifesto for a Healthy Recovery from COVID-19</italic>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/feature-stories/detail/who-manifesto-for-a-healthy-recovery-from-covid-19">https://www.who.int/news-room/feature-stories/detail/who-manifesto-for-a-healthy-recovery-from-covid-19</ext-link>, accessed 20 August 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="czaa165-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>E. D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abelsohn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>. 
<article-title>Challenges and opportunities in planetary health for primary care providers</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planetary Health 2 (5):</source><fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>