<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The escalation of youth climate activism in WA and internationally responds to the very real threat of climate change and inaction.<xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref> Some strong examples in WA:<list list-type="order" id="jpc15649-list-0001"><list-item id="jpc15649-li-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">School Strike 4 Climate</italic> is a climate justice movement led by school students. Students regularly organise strikes from school for peers and adult allies to demand political action to end new fossil fuel projects, enable a just transition to 100% renewable energy and fund jobs for impacted workers and communities.</p></list-item><list-item id="jpc15649-li-0002"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Millennium Kids Inc</italic> is a youth&#8208;led environmental organisation that empowers young people to have their say and initiate action projects to address environmental and sustainability issues. Young people explore ways to solve problems through education, education for behaviour change, advocacy, innovation and design, community action and rules and regulations.</p></list-item><list-item id="jpc15649-li-0003"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Climate Justice Union WA</italic> is growing a movement of people of all ages taking community&#8208;based action for a fair and just transition to net zero emissions, while also supporting communities to prepare for and adapt to climate change impacts. Climate justice involves a transition process of decolonisation, caring for people and place and tackling inequality.</p></list-item><list-item id="jpc15649-li-0004"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Sharma v Minister for Environment</italic>: Eight Australian high school students (including a WA student and co&#8208;author) launched a legal challenge against the federal Minister for Environment. They successfully argued that the Minister has a duty to protect young people from the devastating impacts of climate change.</p></list-item></list>
</p>