<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0065">Third, an ecomodernist approach emphasizes the need to tap into the &#8220;power of human ingenuity and creativity&#8221; for managing planetary problems such as climate change (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nisbet, 2014</xref>). According to ecomodernists, social change can be catalyzed by government investment in specific policies and technologies recommended by experts in science and economics. Ecomodernists reject neo-Malthusian warnings against population growth and recognize that much of the world's population suffers from &#8220;local environmental health risks,&#8221; such as indoor and outdoor air pollution and many preventable diseases (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Asafu-Adjaye et&#160;al., 2015</xref>). However, their main solutions to such problems lie in the deployment of modern technologies&#8212;for example, nuclear energy, carbon capture, genetically modified organisms, or geoengineering (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Keith and Irvine, 2016</xref>). Geoengineering, some ecomodernists argue, should even be seen as an act of climate justice, given that climate change affects the poor and marginalized the most (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Preston, 2016</xref>; critically here: <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Biermann and M&#246;ller, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Flegal and Gupta, 2018</xref>). Most writing in ecomodernism, however, hardly reflects poor people's lived realities, their struggles to cope with the devastating consequences of global change, and their desire to have their voices heard. The widely cited &#8220;Ecomodernist Manifesto&#8221; barely acknowledges the problems of overconsumption (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Asafu-Adjaye et&#160;al., 2015</xref>). Ecomodernism also remains the only type of environmentalism that rejects the argument that social protest could contribute significantly to global environmental progress (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nisbet, 2014</xref>). In short, while ecomodernism hopes to include the global poor in their vision of a &#8220;good Anthropocene,&#8221; it is doubtful whether global technocracy can improve the lot of the global poor&#8212;or not rather increase the systematic risks and widespread disempowerment that they face. Simply put, justice&#8212;at international and local levels&#8212;is not a core consideration for ecomodernists.</p>