<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0225">When this double movement of <italic>recognition</italic> and <italic>taking responsibility</italic> is coupled with <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Davidson's (2020)</xref> understanding of mobility as a material-semiotic process of energetic transformation, it can help to reframe mobility justice as an emergent process of participatory reflection, decision-making and action. Recognition then becomes a process of unravelling in the situated and multi-scalar way that <xref rid="bb0320" ref-type="bibr">Sheller, 2018a</xref>, <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Sheller, 2018b</xref> proposes and <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Henderson (2020)</xref> adopts for electric vehicles (EVs) the assumptions on which current mobility systems are based, the ways they operate, and how they bind together specific socio-technical, politico-economic, and energetic configurations. This means, firstly, asking, for each movement enacted, how much violence and (human and non-human) suffering goes or has gone into making that specific form of mobility possible, thereby fully charting the implications of the socio-technical and energetic configuration enabling movement for other humans and living forms. It also, and secondly, means making room for individuals' histories and mobility needs and, as the papers in this VSI have done, amplifying those voices that have so far not been heard by conventional approaches to transport and urban planning. As part of this process of making room, researchers should investigate the causes for people's inability to fulfil their needs. Is this due to missing capabilities and/or transport supply? Or does it rather reflect patterns of socio-spatial segregation and urban (re)development that are made possible by the same socio-technical, politico-economic and energetic configurations that enable and shape the movements of other people (as well as goods and information)?</p>