<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">It is important to note that those who are vulnerable, marginalized, from communities of color and those living with chronic illnesses are among those individuals, families, communities, and populations who are most susceptible to infectious diseases such as COVID&#8208;19 and climate health consequences. Our integrative review on COVID&#8208;19 and climate change yielded no specific literature to date that explicitly focused on the issues of the most vulnerable. This finding is complex and unanticipated since recent literature suggests that systemic and structural racism are embedded in the health consequences of COVID&#8208;19 and climate change. Azar and colleagues found that &#8220;compared with non&#8208;Hispanic white patients, African Americans had 2.7 times the odds of hospitalization, after adjusting for age, sex, comorbidities, and income&#8221; (Azar et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>, p. 1,253). In April 2020, the CDC explicitly linked risk factors for COVID&#8208;19 to include race/ethnicity, age, gender, certain medical conditions, medication use, poverty/crowding, certain occupations, and pregnancy (CDC, April 4, 2020). While in July 2020, the journal <italic toggle="yes">Health Affairs</italic> published a paper calling for racism and racial health inequities to be explicitly identified in matters of public health (Boyd et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>), which certainly includes the public health problems of COVID&#8208;19 and climate&#8208;related health consequences. Further they noted that: &#8220;In short, racism kills. Whether through force, deprivation, or discrimination, it is a fundamental cause of disease and the strange and familiar root of racial health inequities.&#8221; Waite et&#160;al.&#160;(<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) discussed structural racism and its disenfranchisement of black/brown race groups, suggesting that key steps to address racism for health equity are critical for health and public health. They offered a call to action for governing bodies of the nursing profession and key leadership organizations in public health and global organizations to engage in policy and advocacy efforts to address social justice in public health practice. Waite et&#160;al.&#160;(<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) further suggested that &#8220;social justice accounts for human dignity, respect, and recognition of longstanding oppressions such as racism that have impacted current health systems and outcomes&#8221; (p. 127). Lemery, Williams, and Farmer (2014) noted that there are complex disparities and social inequalities related to health challenges for those who least contribute to greenhouse gas emissions, yet are disproportionately affected by the negative health outcomes in our climate&#8208;changing world.</p>