<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">What can educators do if they want students to leave their courses with an increased understanding of the science of climate change <italic>and</italic> with a sense of purpose and empowerment? As a place to start, we recommend educators ask themselves questions like the following, as they (re)plan and (re)design their courses:
<list list-type="order" id="ece35736-list-0001"><list-item><p>
<italic>&#8220;What do my students already know or think about climate change as they enter my course?&#8221;</italic> Because no student enters her introductory science course a blank slate, it is important for instructors to get a sense for student conceptions of climate change&#8212;both to aid in addressing misconceptions (see Monroe, Plate, Oxarart, Bowers, &amp; Chaves, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Pascua &amp; Chang, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) and to ensure that valuable class time can be devoted to extending what students know, rather than attempting to convince them of things they come to us already accepting. Diagnostically or formatively assessing students' understandings of climate change&#8212;whether through surveying or testing them in some manner, as we did (see surveys in Appendices <xref rid="ece35736-sup-0006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> and <xref rid="ece35736-sup-0007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>) and as others have done (e.g., Pascua &amp; Chang, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Versprille et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>); or by engaging in additional activities, like concept mapping (Rebich &amp; Gautier, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>) and other in&#8208;class writing tasks (see, e.g., Hand et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>)&#8212;can provide a powerful basis for tailoring instruction to meet students where they are at, and to meet their intellectual and affective needs in ways that promote writerly climate literacy.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic>&#8220;What things are being done locally (by individuals or communities) that are effectively combating climate change?&#8221;</italic> Important as it may be to support students in understanding global climate systems, there is a need to complement this knowledge with a nuanced understanding of how effective climate action can be, and is being, taken at local scales. Focusing only on the problem of climate change can be, in more senses than one, a problematic approach to promoting climate literacy. To use the &#8220;bright spot&#8221; framing (Heath &amp; Heath, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), instructors can ask themselves and their students: <italic>What seems to be working in our local context, and how can we replicate, expand, or intensify this bright spot?</italic> By focusing on local bright spots, instructors can help students reframe a large, very difficult problem so that it seems less distant and more actionable, perhaps increasing students' perceived self&#8208;efficacy&#8212;the absence of which can be a significant barrier to climate intervention and behavioral change (see, e.g., Corner et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Gifford, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic>&#8220;What can we gain by fighting climate change?&#8221;</italic> Relatedly, focusing on potential gains from tackling climate change&#8212;rather than fixating exclusively on what we lose if we do not&#8212;may position students to feel more positively toward taking action to address climate change (Corner et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Gifford &amp; Comeau, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). As Ojala (<xref rid="ece35736-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) contends, a &#8220;constructive&#8221; sense of hope can be a powerful source for climate engagement. This shift in framing can take the form of how we present information in our courses or in the work we ask students to complete. Asking students to internalize information about impending climate catastrophe, and testing them on this knowledge, may send a different, more disempowering message than the one communicated by asking them to think through what the world might look like&#8212;5, 10, or 50&#160;years hence&#8212;if particular actions are taken to slow or reverse climate change. Meaningfully answering this latter kind of question requires students to understand the severity of climate change's projected impacts, but it does not take knowledge of climate catastrophe as its foregone conclusion. Instead, it invites students to imagine what it might look like to compose an alternative future.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic>&#8220;How can course activities and assignments support students in thinking through their role(s) in climate change solutions (across spatial and temporal scales)?&#8221;</italic> Because this last question intersects with and integrates insights from the preceding three, we discuss it at greater length. A 2017 systematic review of climate change education research found that pedagogically successful strategies often took the form of &#8220;activities that allow learners to actively engage with concepts, discuss their understanding, practice actions, and engage with relevant, local examples of climate change impacts&#8221; (Monroe et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>, p. 15). Classroom activities and assignments can support students in revising, deepening, or extending their prior understandings in a writerly, socially conscious manner. By providing concrete opportunities for students to explore how human actions shape climate outcomes, our courses can help them develop a critical repertoire for appraising how individual and collective practices participate in climate change&#8212;and how action can be taken to slow and adapt to it.</p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="simple" id="ece35736-list-0002"><list-item><p>For example, an assignment might ask students to focus on identifying solutions for real world scenarios, such as by leading the World Climate Simulation, which has been shown to leave participants with greater feelings of urgency and hope and a greater desire to act in response to climate change (Rooney&#8208;Varga et al., <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Instructors might engage students in analyzing and writing responses to local or national climate&#8208;related news coverage, or else follow the example Hand et al. (<xref rid="ece35736-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>) set by tasking students to compose their own mock newspaper articles (pp. 1030&#8211;1031). Relatedly, another project could be to have students consider the potential benefits, limitations, and implications of the various interventions listed by Project Drawdown (Hawken, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Project Drawdown, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">n.d.</xref>), and to brainstorm ways to publicize their conclusions for one or more specific audiences (e.g., climate&#8208;skeptical relatives, local community members, state or national policy makers). In any of these examples, students could be asked to think through how the findings from these activities could be used to guide effective social and/or scientific intervention&#8212;positioning students to imagine what they learn in the classroom as a prelude to potential action in the world beyond it.</p></list-item><list-item><p>As part of this pedagogical process, it is important to bear in mind that climate change is a complexly anthropogenic problem&#8212;driven, experienced, and responded to by humans. For this reason, robust climate literacy requires attention to global climate justice and injustice: asking how structural injustices (e.g., classism, racism, colonialism, sexism) relate to&#8212;<xref rid="ece35736-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Lotz&#8208;Sisitka, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Schlosberg &amp; Collins, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Shue, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Zeidler &amp; Newton, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). One direct way for courses to draw in and draw on some of these themes is to discuss (and develop activities around) how demographic groups and geographic regions are asymmetrically implicated in and impacted by climate change, helping students to understand that &#8220;those countries&#8221;&#8212;and populations&#8212;&#8220;most at risk from the consequences of climate change are ironically and paradoxically also the ones that have contributed least to climate change&#8221; (Lotz&#8208;Sisitka, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>, p. 72; see also Cuomo, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Whyte, <xref rid="ece35736-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). In this vein, increased classroom attention to climate justice promises not only to foreground the ethical stakes and implications of climate change, but also to shift the curricular focus of introductory courses toward a more writerly climate literacy, attentive to the need and potential for intervention.</p></list-item></list>
</p>