<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Scherr et al. [<xref rid="B78-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] reported that CSA offers to rebrand villages by providing them with embrace &#8216;climate-smart landscapes&#8217;. This means that integrated landscape management principles that adopts the pillars of climate change must be in place prior to agricultural land allocation. The development of CSA objectives also requires strong institutional mechanism. When such systems are in place, its effects transcends to other parts of the village. Steenwerth [<xref rid="B74-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] noted that while smart village residents might consider migrating to big cities, climate-smart agriculture could cause a rethink, as it gives room for entrepreneurial development in the agricultural sector, as seen in the case of youth training embarked upon in rural areas across Europe. Additionally, CSA also caters for increased demand for food due to the world&#8217;s growing population. This is achieved through methods that do not jeopardize environmental health [<xref rid="B74-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. With respect to animal husbandry, some zoonotic diseases can be detected early, so that treatment plans are set underway to prevent the farmer from infection. CSA also motivates the achievement of sustainable development goals through agricultural practices that use techniques that can drive food security, improve resilience, and effectively manage emissions [<xref rid="B70-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. CSA practices are also able to curb environmental challenges related to water pollution through the use of agrochemicals [<xref rid="B91-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. A notable aspect where smart agriculture surpasses expectations is the possibility of using it as a tool for enterprise resource planning, through which the safety of agricultural products/foods can be monitored [<xref rid="B46-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</p>