<table xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name and location</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Convenors</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Learners</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aims</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedagogic approach</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Diplomado Territorio y H&#225;bitat &#8211;</italic> Diploma on
Territory and Habitat; Mexico City</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Universidad Aut&#243;noma de la Ciudad de M&#233;xico, Movimiento Urbano
Popular, Centro Operacional de Vivienda y Poblamiento, AC
(COPEVI)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Members of collective and neighbourhood organizations,
Indigenous inhabitants of the city and university students</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To develop critical, reflexive and propositional thinking; based
on popular urban movements&#8217; perspective on <italic toggle="yes">buen
vivir</italic>, participatory democracy and territory and
habitat rights.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focusing on dialogic methods, inter-learning and the
co-production of knowledge among participants, the Diploma is
structured across 4 online modules over a period of almost 8
months. Before the pandemic, the course also included field
visits.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cooperativism and women-led housing construction and habitat
processes; Potrerillos and La Palma, San Salvador</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fundaci&#243;n Salvadore&#241;a de Desarrollo y Vivienda M&#237;nima
(FUNDASAL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Female) community and cooperative members.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To strengthen women&#8217;s knowledge and capacities to claim and
enact their habitat rights.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">From self-recognizing one&#8217;s rights to constructing them
collectively through women-led housing, FUNDASAL&#8217;s pedagogy
works through a mix of workshops aimed at developing a new
consciousness and hands-on sessions on self-construction
techniques.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Medell&#237;n Ciudad Accesible</italic> &#8211; Medell&#237;n Accessible
City; Medell&#237;n, Colombia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corporaci&#243;n Regi&#243;n + Fuerza Incluyente</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neighbourhood organizations, collectives of disabled people, and
advocacy target audiences (such as taxi drivers, local
government officials and the general public).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To strengthen participants&#8217; consciousness and capacities to
advocate an intersectional perspective in building mobility as
part of the Right to the City.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Largely experiential pedagogies, which engage with and through
the realities of differently-abled people, for example, through
discussions, events in public squares, shared walks and transits
through the city.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cooperativism schools, with a particular focus on
intergenerational and gendered learning and relationships with
the state; across Uruguay</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Federaci&#243;n Uruguaya de Cooperativas de Vivienda por Ayuda
Mutua<break/>(FUCVAM)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current and future members of cooperatives, with some learning
processes particularly focused on youth and women.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To nurture, sustain and mobilize the housing cooperative
movement as a key strategy to reclaim the social function of
housing and land.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capacity-building is integral to the working of cooperatives and
operates through different modes of learning, including
learning-by-living/doing, decentralized workshops, and peer
learning across cooperatives.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feminism schools &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">Voces de Mujeres Diversas por
Ciudades Seguras, Inclusivas y Sostenibles</italic> &#8211; Voices
of Diverse Women for Safe, Inclusive and Sustainable Cities;
C&#243;rdoba, Argentina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CISCSA Ciudades Feministas</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community leaders and members of women and feminist
organizations, as well as women working in urbanism and urban
planning.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To strengthen debates on the rights of women and diversities to
the city; to build social force around the experiences and
demands of those identifying as women, trans and lesbians; to
develop concrete proposals that advocate for a feminist
city.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capacity-building and participatory workshops developed through
feminist methodologies, such as
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;cuerpo-territorio&#8221;</italic>, visioning exercises,
manifestos, public manifestations and celebrations.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Diplomado Iberoamericano Dise&#241;o Participativo
Sustentable del Habitat &#8211;</italic> Ibero-American Diploma in
Participatory Sustainable Habitat Design; LA Regional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Universidad Nacional Aut&#243;noma de M&#233;xico in collaboration with
HIC-AL and Taller 36 of the National University of Cordoba</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anyone interested in the social production of habitat, including
leaders of grassroots organizations, university students and
professionals of different disciplines.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To learn and apply concepts, methodologies and tools for the
social production and management of habitat, which are not
taught in regular design courses.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inter-learning spaces as well as group and individual work
across 210 hours, 2 x 2 hours of live sessions per week
(workshops) and 8 hours of independent learning.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escola da Cidadania</italic> &#8211; Citizenship School, with
a cycle of 16 different thematic courses (such as culture and
cities, climate justice and urban infrastructures, etc); S&#227;o
Paulo, with online participants across Brazil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instituto P&#243;lis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400&#8211;500 online learners with diverse identities and backgrounds
(in terms of professional experience, gender, age, geography and
others). Core target groups are social movements and public
officials.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To be a space for reflection and formation of critical thinking
in the different dimensions of constructing citizenship: human
rights, right to the city, activism and public policies.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polis Institute applies creative pedagogic practices, such as
the collective development of thematic playlists, and the use of
social media as a means to extend the learning beyond the
boundaries of the school.<break/>Practically, each thematic
course consists of six online 2-hour weekly sessions, with
voluntary discussion groups in between sessions.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Programa de Formaci&#243;n en Derechos para Referentes
Barriales</italic> &#8211; Formative Programme in Rights for
Community Leaders; Buenos Aires 2019, now online and with reach
across Argentina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asociaci&#243;n Civil por la Igualdad y la Justicia (ACIJ)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In 2019 ACIJ&#8217;s school brought together 60 community leaders,
including representatives of social and political organisations
in informal settlements, and independent leaders, who seek to
incorporate or reinforce within their repertoire of public
actions, the use of legal tools and the language of rights as a
way to strengthen their interaction with public
authorities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To promote communities&#8217; understanding of their rights as
guaranteed by the legal system.<break/>To strengthen grassroots
organizations&#8217; capacities to claim their right to the city and
to claim parity of political participation in their
neighbourhood improvement and redevelopment processes.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACIJ&#8217;s approach is learner-centred and works through horizontal
exchanges that valorize the knowledges and practices of
community leaders as pedagogues. The curriculum is therefore
open and flexible to respond to specific needs, contexts and
challenges and typically works through 13 sessions/4 modules/40
hours of classes over three months.<break/>Sessions are
facilitated as interactive workshops &#8211; with space for debates
and role plays.</td></tr></tbody></table>