<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par51">Remote service and supervision arrangements in place for these specialist in-house clinical placements are as follows:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par52">The Anti-Death Penalty Clinic (with the Capital Punishment Justice Project [CPJP]<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn51">51</xref>) involves students working on death penalty cases, related projects, and the development of advocacy briefs for clients in a range of countries. Students work on cases and projects that highlight the profound impacts of capital punishment on the families and communities of people facing the death penalty. The clinic has established partnerships with a number of non-government organisations (NGOs) and lawyers across Asia and was central to Monash and the CPJP developing a broader Capital Punishment Impact Initiative, now launched as Eleos Justice, with support from the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn52">52</xref></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par53">The Australian Law Reform Commission (ALRC) Clinic involves students working on current inquiries being conducted by the ALRC with input from a range of commission staff as well as their Monash supervisor. Students have been acknowledged for their contributions to a range of ALRC inquiries, including its reviews of the Family Law System,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn53">53</xref> the Framework of Religious Exemptions in Anti-discrimination Legislation,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn54">54</xref> Australia&#8217;s Corporate Criminal Responsibility Regime,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn55">55</xref> and the Future of Law Reform.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn56">56</xref> The subject matter of these inquiries provides extensive opportunities for students to develop their &#8216;social justice radar&#8217; when considering the need for law reform in major public policy areas.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par54">The Climate Justice Clinic<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn57">57</xref> involves students advising climate activists, climate-focused NGOs, and concerned citizens who wish to use legal tools and legal advocacy in their work&#160;for climate justice. This clinic highlights the human rights and social justice issues raised by displacement due to climate change. A secondment arrangement, whereby Russell Kennedy Lawyers contribute the time of a senior lawyer, has expanded the reach of this clinic.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par55">Human Rights Clinic (with the Castan Centre for Human Rights Law<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn58">58</xref>): Students work with external clients (such as domestic and&#160;international human rights organisations) on policy or advocacy projects as well as drafting submissions to parliamentary inquiries and preparing shadow reports to United Nations treaty bodies. The framework that underpins the work of this clinic emphasises the importance of social justice concerns in framing and advancing human rights.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par56">International Economic Law Clinic (with TradeLab<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn59">59</xref>): Students work in small project teams on specific legal questions related to World Trade Organization issues for clients (characterised as &#8216;beneficiaries&#8217;) such as international organisations, governments, small-medium enterprises, and NGOs. The focus of the clinic is to contribute to building lasting legal capacity for organisations in developing countries, making global economic regulation work more effectively for marginalised people. Close supervision from an academic is augmented by invited experts (&#8216;mentors&#8217;) who also provide substantive background to the respective topics through introductory seminars.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn60">60</xref></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par57">Modern Slavery Clinic:<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn61">61</xref> Working with partners across Asia (including the Global Pro Bono Bar Association), students assist people caught up in modern slavery, engaging with the ethical, moral, and political dimensions of this complex area. Students engage in research and advocacy tasks, contributing to legal interventions to assist people who might not otherwise have access to resources and expertise. Students develop their sense of the challenges and injustices that pervade modern slavery issues as they work in project teams with close supervision from their academic supervisor and invited experts on specific legal and social questions.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par58">National Justice Project Clinic:<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn62">62</xref> Students work on projects involving active cases and complaints being handled by in-house lawyers of the Sydney-based National Justice Project. These areas include cases relating to the offshore detention of people seeking asylum, coronial inquests where people have died while detained in custody, as well as a submission to an inquiry into overincarceration of Indigenous Australians. Student supervision is structured to reveal the social justice implications of these cases and projects.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par59">Start-Up &amp; Innovation Clinic:<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn63">63</xref> Students address specific legal questions relating to a range of issues for clients looking to start up new businesses and develop innovative ideas. This clinic involves a partnership with a leading start-up hub (the Eastern Innovation Business Centre) and Monash University colleagues (Monash Innovation and the Generator).</p></list-item></list></p>