<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par29">Fourth, funding for adaptation brings in both direct and indirect global benefits through many different pathways (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), such as, bio-physical (shifts in eco-systems/species range, transboundary river basins), trade disruptions, financial instability, and human displacements (Sundin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2014</xref>). Better monitoring and prediction of climate change, better understanding of impacts on human and ecosystem health, etc. are examples of global benefits. Also, adaptation measures may prevent potentially huge climate-induced displacement, regarded as an indirect global benefit (Pickering and Rubbelke <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2014</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Key types of adaptation benefits</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Local private benefits</th><th>Local public benefits</th><th>Direct global benefits</th><th>Indirect global benefits</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Value of saved crops for individual farmers, improved water storage for households, and strong and resilient housing</td><td>Flood-proofed infrastructure, afforestation preventing mudslides, coastal afforestation as wind and flood breaks, and local water storage facilities</td><td><p>Control of climate-sensitive infectious disease, protection of climate-sensitive biodiversity,</p><p>agricultural research on flood- and saline-resistant crops, and improved modeling of climate impacts</p></td><td>Continuation of statehoods by many SIDS, avoided international migration, lower price volatility on climate-sensitive agricultural products, and enhanced purchasing power among the vulnerable communities and countries</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Source: Adapted from Persson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2011</xref>) and expanded by the authors.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>