<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par21">The irony is that the effects of undersupply of mitigation as increased disasters are not regarded as a GPB. Even if it is, adaptation to those effects is not considered a GPG. The Netherlands Environmental Assessment Agency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2011</xref>) rightly argues that GPBs should be countered by GPGs. Though some scholars theorize the normative or equity aspects of adaptation, none but Gardiner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2006</xref>) attempts to conceptualize climate impacts as a result of failed mitigation. Another exception is Vanderheiden&#8217;s expansive idea of adaptation tending to plug the conceptual gap a little: &#8220;Adaptation intervenes in the causal chain between climate change and human harm, allowing the former but preventing the latter, but when this is not possible, a third category of <italic>compensation</italic> costs must be assigned in order to remedy failed mitigation &#8230;so adaptation shall be understood to include prevention of harm as well as <italic>ex post</italic> compensation to it&#8221; (Vanderheiden <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2011</xref>: 65). So the no-harm rule and <italic>ex post</italic> compensation should be considered as obligatory, as in the EU (Khan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2015</xref>). Birdsall and de Nevers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2012</xref>:1) rightly argue that adaptation finance &#8220;is better thought of as a financial transfer based on the &#8216;causal responsibility&#8217; of richer to poorer countries for the disproportionate costs to the poor ...&#8221; These costs are the result of &#8220;imported&#8221; impacts from beyond their borders (Persson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2019</xref>). Benzie and Persson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2019</xref>) demonstrate how borderless climate risks, both direct and indirect, challenge the territorial framing of adaptation. So they argue for globalizing adaptation governance, while appreciating the notion of adaptation as a GPG.</p>