<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par7">In July 2021, smallholders from across Asia and the Pacific came together as part of the Peoples&#8217; Autonomous Response to the UN Food Systems Summit to discuss <italic>our</italic> proposals for a radical transformation of the food system. Our solutions focused on the following:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par8">The importance of agency and autonomy of Indigenous Peoples, peasants, and fisherfolk in solving the problems we face on the ground is fundamental&#8212;embedded in place and determined democratically.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par9">We must continue to form stronger alliances across countries and the region to fight corporate control of the food system.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par10">We must continue building producer-owned cooperatives for production, processing, and distribution.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par11">We need secure land tenure and access to natural resources, and we resolved to strengthen the struggle against land grabbing.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par12">We need a radical paradigm shift away from Blue Economy to Blue Justice in fisheries, which is crucial for climate justice, encompassing economic, social, and environmental justice.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par13">We must promote and scale out agroecology as a science, a set of practices, and a social movement, as agroecology is central to the genuinely radical transformation of the food system we need (M&#233;ndez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2013</xref>).</p></list-item></list>
We will now share initiatives and hopeful signs of progress in our region that demonstrate the difference between the corporate and neoliberal discourses of &#8216;aid&#8217; and &#8216;food security&#8217; intrinsic to the UNFSS so-called dialogues and solutions, and our grassroots, social movements&#8217; discourses of &#8216;agency&#8217; and &#8216;food sovereignty&#8217; in action.</p>