<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0055">We would expect the repercussions of an economic crisis to affect WNV transmission in several ways, at the individual level (bottom-up) and government level (top-down). Previous studies have shown that socio-economic factors tend to influence the distribution and intensity of mosquito-borne diseases both pre-infection and post-infection <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Poorer communities are less likely to have air-conditioned homes, tap water and adequate drainage, and therefore may be more exposed to biting mosquitoes. Several studies have demonstrated the link between WNV infections and a range of local-level socio-economic and demographic factors such as income, sanitation, and population density <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. In general, we would expect to see a drop in living standards in regions experiencing an economic shock followed by sluggish economic growth. Those people most affected would find it more difficult to prevent mosquito infections through direct measures i.e. sprays and repellents and less likely to pay for things that indirectly influence WNV transmission, like the upkeep of homes and use of air conditioning. Factors associated with higher economic status can also bring humans into closer contact with mosquitoes, for example, home owners with gardens and potted plants, swimming pools and ponds or having good access to recreational space where mosquitoes can breed <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. However, neglect of such things through economic decline can have further unintended effects, even in wealthy neighborhoods <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>.</p>