<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0070">Western governments have specifically rejected the idea of climate-induced migration (<xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Bourke, 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0560" ref-type="bibr">Rieffel, 2020</xref>) and some have weaponized it as a rationale for border walls and other forms of protectionism. For example, the U.S. has refused to acknowledge the climate-migrants from its southern border by detaining people in concentration camps and subjecting them to poor living conditions while enforcing strict rules on family separation to deter such migration (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Blitzer, 2019</xref>; The <xref rid="b0600" ref-type="bibr">Guardian, 2020</xref>). Similarly, individuals from Kiribati who applied for climate refugee status based on SLR were rejected by Australia and New Zealand (<xref rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr">Koerth, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">Law Library of Congress, 2015</xref>). European nations have also refused to grant asylum to people migrating due to climate change impacts (<xref rid="b0615" ref-type="bibr">Tidey, 2020</xref>). Germany, for example, has expressed disagreement with a United Nations Human Rights Committee&#8217;s ruling which states &#8220;<italic>countries may not deport individuals who face climate change-induced conditions that violate the right to life</italic>&#8221; (<xref rid="b0525" ref-type="bibr">OHCHR, 2020 p.5</xref>). Other countries have tightened their borders, increased bureaucratic rules for migration, or otherwise made themselves inhospitable. These increasing protectionist measures are not unconnected to the rise of right-wing nationalism, anti-immigrant rhetoric, and the securitization of migration promoted by scholars and the media (<xref rid="b0430" ref-type="bibr">Levy, 1995</xref>, <xref rid="b0500" ref-type="bibr">Myers, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Corporation, 2007</xref>, <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Boas, 2015</xref>). These problems narrow the space for thoughtful considerations of how CM might be framed as part of broader developmental, humanitarian, and climate justice goals (<xref rid="b0555" ref-type="bibr">Ransan-Cooper et al., 2015</xref>).</p>