<p>Though academics have been relatively quiet concerning social justice issues, it appears that awareness of inequity in companion animal sheltering has been increasing (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B97" ref-type="bibr">Marceau 2019</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B57" ref-type="bibr">Guenther 2020</xref>). The discussion has come mainly from activists in other fields (e.g., sociology, civil rights law) and from animal welfare nonprofit organizations (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B66" ref-type="bibr">HASS 2021</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B114" ref-type="bibr">PFL 2021</xref>), rather than researchers working in companion animal science. However, there is ample opportunity for scientists to incorporate climate justice studies into their existing work. For example, researchers who focus on shelter operations and adoption programs can include data on whether new or existing programs differentially affect vulnerable populations. Restrictive application processes involved in pet adoption&#8212;which often require potential adopters to live in a single-family house, have a backyard, allow a home visit to determine if the family is a &#8220;good fit,&#8221; or bring the entire family for a meet-and-greet&#8212;likely disproportionately affect Black, Indigenous, and People of Color. The subjective nature of home visits opens the door to racial and economic discrimination. Additional criteria such as excluding persons with a criminal history, persons who have previously relinquished a pet, or persons who do not have an established relationship with a veterinarian are even more opportunities for racial and socio-economic discrimination. Basic operating procedures, such as business hours and location, may also cater to particular racial, socio-economic, able-bodied, and age-specific demographics (<xref rid="icab025-B20" ref-type="bibr">Buley 2017</xref>). These are all understudied topics that could be incorporated into companion animal science research. Doing so would not only generate knowledge, but the data could be used to scientifically back policy change and create adaptation strategies for a more equitable future.</p>