<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?subarticle pone.0304835.r001?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11178169</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-23-32614</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Linguistics</subject><subj-group><subject>Semantics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Computer and Information Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Information Theory</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Geometry</subject><subj-group><subject>Ellipses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics</subject><subj-group><subject>Similarity Measures</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Computer and Information Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Software Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Programming Languages</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Engineering and Technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Software Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Programming Languages</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Database and Informatics Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Information Retrieval</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Probability Theory</subject><subj-group><subject>Random Variables</subject><subj-group><subject>Discrete Random Variables</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">CEKGRL</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Haolin</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Ran</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Su</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal analysis</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Likuan</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Baoyan</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/">Funding acquisition</role><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Wanting</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5966-335X</contrib-id><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Junlu</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<addr-line>School of Information, Liaoning University, Shenyang, Liaoning, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>Asadullah</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref rid="edit1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Najran University College of Computer Science and Information Systems, SAUDI ARABIA</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>bysong@lnu.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0304835</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 Zhang et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang et al</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0304835.pdf"/><abstract><p>Blockchain-based applications are becoming more and more widespread in business operations. In view of the shortcomings of existing enterprise blockchain evaluation methods, this paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality evaluation model for enterprise business activities, so as to achieve efficient evaluation of business activity information consistency, credibility and value. This paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment method for enterprise business activities, aiming at the problems that most of the data in enterprise business activities come from different data sources, information representation is inconsistent, information ambiguity between the same block chain is serious, and it is difficult to evaluate the consistency, credibility and value of information. The method firstly proposes an entity information representation method based on the Representation learning for fusing entity category information (CEKGRL) model, which introduces the triad structure of related entities in blockchain, then associates them with enterprise business activity categories, and carries out similarity calculation through contextual information to achieve blockchain information consistency assessment. After that, a trustworthiness characterization method is proposed based on information sources, information comments, and information contents, to obtain the trustworthiness assessment of the business. Finally, based on the information trustworthiness characterization, a value assessment method is introduced to assess the total value of business activity information in the blockchain, and a blockchain quality assessment model is constructed. The experimental results show that the proposed model has great advantages over existing methods in assessing inter-block consistency, intra-block activity information trustworthiness and the value of blockchain.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award001"><funding-source>
<institution>the General Program of University Basic Scientific Research of Education Department of Liaoning Province (Science and Engineering) (Initiating Flagship Service for Local Projects)</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>JYTMS20230761</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5966-335X</contrib-id>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Junlu</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award002"><funding-source>
<institution>the Applied Basic Research Program of Liaoning Province</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>2022JH2/101300250</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Baoyan</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award003"><funding-source>
<institution>the Ministry of Education University-Industry Collaborative Education Program</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>230701160261310</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Su</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award004"><funding-source>
<institution>the Nature Science Foundation Program Doctoral Startup Project of Liaoning Province</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>2023-BS-085</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Wanting</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the General Program of University Basic Scientific Research of Education Department of Liaoning Province (Science and Engineering) (Initiating Flagship Service for Local Projects) (No. JYTMS20230761); the Applied Basic Research Program of Liaoning Province (No.2022JH2/101300250); the Ministry of Education University-Industry Collaborative Education Program (No. 230701160261310); the Nature Science Foundation Program Doctoral Startup Project of Liaoning Province (No. 2023-BS-085).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="22"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The datasets are available from <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.25143503.v1" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.25143503.v1</ext-link>.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The datasets are available from <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.25143503.v1" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.25143503.v1</ext-link>.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>1 Introduction</title><p>Blockchain [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] is a new distributed technology [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] for generating [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], storing, manipulating and verifying data through block-chain structure, consensus algorithm [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and smart contract [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. It can achieve value communication between trustless [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] nodes without relying on third-party trusted institutions [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. These characteristics make blockchain widely used in enterprise business activities, such as upstream and downstream supply chains, digital assets, business event monitoring, enterprise credit investigation, etc. Many IT companies around the world, such as IBM, Baidu and Alibaba, have established their own enterprise federated blockchain systems.</p><p>Blockchain is divided into public chain, private chain, and consortium chain based on its degree of decentralization. Public chain is completely open and transparent, not controlled by any organization, and everyone can participate; The write permission of private chains only belongs to individuals or a certain organization, with a high degree of centralization; The alliance chain, on the other hand, falls between the two and is only open to specific group organizations [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Participants can conduct transactions or access information, but only nodes in the alliance have the right to perform transaction verification, publish contracts, and other functions.</p><p>The quality of the information in existing enterprise blockchain systems varies. The information on business activities mostly originates from different fields and institutions, and the way of information representation is ambiguous. Moreover, it is difficult to ensure the credibility and value of the information in the block due to the constraints of the enterprise&#x02019;s own credibility and other conditions. Therefore, in the process of block establishment, there are problems of inconsistent information between blocks and inconsistent indicators such as credibility and value of content.</p><p>Moreover, traditional evaluation methods do not make full use of the features of blockchain. Blockchain features include leaving traces throughout the process, being non-temper able, and traceable. Evaluation efficiency and accuracy are low with traditional methods. This results in the inability of enterprise users and relevant regulatory authorities to quickly screen out suitable blockchains. Establishing a unified analysis model becomes challenging [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In the enterprise blockchain data layer, each distributed node encapsulates the business activity information received over a period of time into a data block and links it to the longest blockchain in the current blockchain network, forming a new block [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. At the same time, with the increasing channels for obtaining information on enterprise business activities in blockchain, the amount of data is increasing. This information may originate from different institutions and fields, and there may be certain differences in the representation of information. Its credibility and information value cannot be measured, making it difficult to determine the overall quality of blockchain. Therefore, effective evaluation of enterprise blockchains is a hot spot and difficult area of research in the blockchain field.</p><p>To address these issues, this paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities to achieve an efficient assessment of the consistency, credibility and value of business activity information. The main contributions of this paper are as follows:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>To address the problem of inconsistent and poor accuracy of enterprise business activity information in the blockchain, a semantic similarity calculation method between blocks based on contextual information is proposed to construct a triadic representation of enterprise activity information based on the CEKQRL model, introduce an attention mechanism [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] to realize the association between activity categories and activity information, increase the weight of key concern information, and construct a structural graph model through information context to improve the efficiency of similarity calculation, and then realize the information consistency assessment of the blockchain.</p></list-item><list-item><p>In response to the challenge of assessing the credibility of business information on the blockchain, we introduce a novel method for characterizing information trustworthiness that integrates the source, evaluative features, and content features. This method not only verifies the credibility of the information source through an assessment of the trustworthiness of the publishing platform, page, and publisher but also generates a comment-based credibility representation by analyzing comment tendencies based on lexicon types [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Furthermore, it achieves a content-based credibility representation by examining the content characteristics of business activities. This holistic approach provides a comprehensive solution for information evaluation within the blockchain ecosystem.</p></list-item><list-item><p>To address the problem of value assessment of activity information in the blockchain, an information value assessment method is proposed to express the uncertainty of information through the magnitude of information, and then measure the amount of value of business operation activities in the block. Finally, a multivariate heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities is derived by integrating semantic similarity between blocks, blockchain content assessment and value assessment.</p></list-item></list><p>The rest of the paper is ordered as follows. A literature review section is provided in the Related Studies. In the Methods section, we introduce the calculation of the consistency, accuracy and value of blockchain information, and then conclude the quality assessment model. In the Experiments and Results section, we test the proposed model and discuss the experimental results. Finally, the Conclusion section is a summary of this paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>2 Related studies</title><p>At present, many scholars have conducted in-depth research on data quality assessment methods and have achieved certain research results.</p><p>In blockchain information consistency evaluation, literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] proposed a structured gradient tree boosting (SGTB) algorithm for entity disambiguation method, which has better performance in cross-domain evaluation, but it ignores the role of contextual information of entities on the computation process; literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] proposed a factor graph-based inconsistent record pair computation method, which parses entities but does not correlate entity representation with the category it belongs to; literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] proposes a neural network with multi-view focus so as to capture more information features and improve disambiguation performance, but the method does not focus on entity contextual information and requires a large number of comparisons, which is less efficient.</p><p>In terms of blockchain information credibility assessment, literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] proposes a comprehensive credibility calculation method that effectively integrates multidimensional evaluation data, but focuses only on the relevant evaluation without paying attention to the information source as an influencing factor; literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] proposes a data credibility assessment method based on multi-source heterogeneous information fusion, which shows better results in improving the convergence of credibility calculation, but ignores the information content itself credibility; literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] proposes a supervised machine learning method for user-generated content credibility assessment, but the method only focuses on relevant comment information, ignoring the attention to information content and its sources.</p><p>In terms of blockchain information value assessment, literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] proposes a confidence-based reliability assessment method, which can accurately obtain the distribution to which the data belongs, but ignores where the value of the data itself lies; literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] combines variable weight theory and cloud model theory to construct a VW&#x00026;ICM computational model for risk assessment, which weakens the influence of subjective factors on the assessment results, but the model focuses more on the weight assignment factors and ignores the information of the overall value of the data; literature [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] developed a new linguistic operation model to determine the overall weight and evaluation criteria from both subjective and objective aspects, which overcomes the limitation of a single model but is only applicable to the case of large information uncertainty.</p><p>This paper introduces a novel approach: a multi-source, heterogeneous blockchain quality assessment model tailored for enterprise business activities. It addresses the limitations of current methods by prioritizing consistency, credibility, and data value [<xref rid="pone.0304835.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. This model enhances blockchain consistency assessment efficiency while also factoring in content credibility, yielding promising results even in scenarios with high information uncertainty.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec003"><title>3 Methods</title><p>As the information of business activities in blockchain mostly comes from different data sources, which leads to inconsistent information representation, such as data record format, entity and activity name designation methods. Moreover, the same enterprise entity will have different designations in different activities, and the same entity designation can refer to different entities in different contexts, resulting in the ambiguity of the business activity information stored in the blockchain and low data quality. To address this problem, this paper evaluates the consistency of blockchain data by comparing the semantic similarity between entities. The <xref rid="pone.0304835.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref> is the technical flowchart of this section.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0304835.g001"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>The logic flowchart of showcase assessment model technical roadmap.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.g001" position="float"/></fig><sec id="sec004"><title>3.1 Block entity representation based on CEKGRL model</title><p>The data related to enterprise entities are stored in the enterprise business activity blockchain, and in order to ensure the computational efficiency while effectively representing the information of this entity category, this paper proposes a block entity representation based on the CEKGRL model. Entity triad representation is introduced, and while learning triad knowledge, inconsistency detection of entity information is performed through accurate knowledge representation, and then potential correlations between entity categories and triad relationships are captured through attention mechanism, and entity similarity comparison is performed by combining the importance of different entity categories for a particular relationship and entity category information.</p><sec id="sec005"><title>3.1.1 Ternary information structure</title><p>The triple evaluation structure is a data model widely used for representing information, consisting of three components: subject, predicate, and object. It is extensively applied in fields such as knowledge graphs and the semantic web. The triple evaluation structure is highly flexible and can be employed to represent various types of information. Different combinations of subjects, predicates, and objects can capture rich semantic relationships, making it suitable for diverse knowledge representation. In summary, the advantages of the triple evaluation structure lie in its flexibility, clear semantic representation, scalability, and effective expression of relationships, making it a key technology in the fields of knowledge representation and the semantic web.</p><p>Based on the CEKGRL model, business activity information is defined as <italic toggle="yes">G</italic> = (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>), where <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> is the set of enterprise entities; <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> is the set of enterprise relationships; <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> &#x02286; <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> &#x000d7; <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> &#x000d7; <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> denotes the set of triples, and the set of triples is represented by (<italic toggle="yes">h</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">h</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> represents the head entity (enterprise name), relationship (activity information direction) and tail entity (business activity information), respectively. In addition, this paper uses c to denote the activity categories and defines structure-based and category-based entity representations, representing the entity representation learned from the triad and the entity representation obtained by introducing the category representation, respectively. The overall architecture of the CEKGRL model is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0304835.g002"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Overall architecture of the CEKGRL model.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.g002" position="float"/></fig><p>Among them, the ellipse composed of diagonal circles represents the structure-based vector representation, the ellipse composed of lattice-like circles represents the category-based vector representation, the ellipse composed of solid circles represents the vector representation of relationships, and the ellipse composed of hollow circles represents the vector representation of entity categories, a represents the attention fraction, and in order to integrate the two representation types, the energy function is defined in this paper as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e001" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (1)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e001">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e001.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e001g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(1)</label>
</disp-formula><p><italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ss</italic></sub> = &#x02225;<italic toggle="yes">h</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">s</italic></sub> + <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">s</italic></sub>&#x02225; is the energy functions obtained by using structure-based entity representations for head and tail entities; <italic toggle="yes">h</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">s</italic></sub> and <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">s</italic></sub> are the structure-based representations for head and tail entities, respectively; and the hyperparameters &#x003b2; is used to adjust the importance of the category-based representations in the CEKGRL model. <italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">cc</italic></sub> = &#x02225;<italic toggle="yes">h</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sub> + <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sub>&#x02225; is the energy functions obtained by using category-based entity representations for head and tail entities. It should be noted that both the structure-based and category-based representations of entities use a unified relational representation r during the training process, ensuring that the vector representation space of both types can be unified by the same relational representation.</p><p>In the training process, the correlation between the entity category representation and the triadic relationship, i.e., the attention score, is first obtained through the attention mechanism, and then this attention score is used to weight and sum the category representation and use it as the category-based entity representation.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>3.1.2 Associated information categories and activity representation</title><p>Different categories of enterprise entities can portray entities from multiple perspectives, and the same entity will focus on its different categories of information under different relationships, which is manifested by the different semantic relevance between different categories of the same entity and different relationships. In order to effectively utilize the potential correlation between the relationship and entity categories in the triad, this paper calculates and obtains the similarity between them by the following attention mechanism.</p><p>The essence of the attention mechanism lies in the ability to learn to ignore irrelevant information and focus on the key information when comparing similarities. In this paper, we first construct a scaled dot product attention model, combining the CEKGRL model with relationships <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> as <italic toggle="yes">query</italic> vectors and categories <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> as both vectors <italic toggle="yes">key</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">value</italic> vectors. In the implementation process, in order to speed up the processing efficiency, the attention is calculated in the form of a matrix, and the representation vectors of multiple inter-enterprise relationships and their corresponding activity category representation vectors are stitched into a relationship matrix <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> and a category matrix <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, respectively. Then, the weight matrices <italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">Q</italic></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">K</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sup> to be trained are introduced, and the matrix multiplication operations are performed on the weight matrix, the relationship matrix and the category matrix to obtain the matrices <italic toggle="yes">query</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">key</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">value</italic> corresponding to <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">K</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> and the attention scores as shown in Eqs <xref rid="pone.0304835.e002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0304835.e003" ref-type="disp-formula">(3)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e002">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e002.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e002g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(2)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e003">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e003.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e003g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M3" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(3)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> is the vector dimension of entities and relationships, and <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></sub> is the weight matrix dimension. The higher the attention score obtained by the above attention calculation model, the stronger the relevance of the category <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> to the relationship <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>, when the category is assigned a higher weight.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>3.2 Similarity calculation based on contextual information</title><p>In traditional blockchain enterprise business activities information, there may be a situation where one entity has similarity with multiple different entities, which is called a "one to many" mapping problem. By introducing contextual information, a contextual information association graph model can be established to more accurately capture the relationships between entities. This model considers the ternary relationship between entities and their related entities, which helps to solve the ambiguity problem in similarity calculation and better reflect the true relationship between entities. In this paper, we introduce enterprise contextual information and build a context structure graph model to calculate the ambiguity of entity name designation. In the inter-block similarity measure, assuming that the total number of blocks in the blockchain is <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, this paper takes the first block in the blockchain as the block to be compared and the other blocks as the candidate comparison blocks, and uses the average value of the similarity between the block to be compared and the other blocks as the consistency measure of this blockchain, i.e., the average similarity measure.</p><sec id="sec008"><title>3.2.1 Contrasting entity generation</title><p>In this paper, the entity ambiguity calculation is carried out for the example of business entity names and business transaction activities. Based on Stanford NER for named entity identification, the set of entity designations of the candidate comparison blocks is obtained and denoted as <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = {<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">1</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">2</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">3</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">&#x02026;</italic>}. When performing entity ambiguity calculation, contextual activity information plays an important role as evidence for entity designation. Therefore, the Stanford NER tool is used to extract the activity context information <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> from the activity information of the removed entity designation set <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>, which constitutes the context set of the activity context information <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, denoted as <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> = {<italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">1</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">2</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">3</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">&#x02026;</italic>}.</p><p>The named entity designations in the set <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> are passed through other blocks to obtain the candidate comparison entity set, and the information extraction and formatting of the prepared candidate entity set are sorted out and filtered to generate the final candidate comparison entity set <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> = {<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i1</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i2</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i3</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">&#x02026;</italic>}.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>3.2.2 Contextual information association graph model construction</title><p>In this paper, the contextual structure in an enterprise entity is represented as an entity-related graph model <italic toggle="yes">G</italic> = (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>), where <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> denotes the vertex set and <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> denotes the edge set. The construction of the entity-related graph is divided into two steps: vertex set construction and edge set construction.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">(1) Vertex set construction</italic>. Vertex set <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>: the set <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> of entity contextual activities that appear with a given enterprise activity, where <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> denotes the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>th contextual information corresponding to this activity, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> = {<italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> |&#x02200;<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> &#x02208; <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>}.</p><p>Each vertex in the graph is assigned a Confidence Measure (<italic toggle="yes">CM</italic>), which indicates the importance of the node without considering other contextual information, and is calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e004" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (4)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e004">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e004.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e004g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M4" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Re</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Re</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(4)</label>
</disp-formula>
Where <italic toggle="yes">ResultScore</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>) is the matching score obtained based on Google Knowledge Graph, and the higher the matching score, the more accurate the contextual information represents.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">(2) Side set construction</italic>. The edges of the graph model in this paper consist of the path correlations of the contextual information corresponding to this enterprise activity.</p><p>In this paper, we propose a new method to determine the path association degree between two messages, i.e., the two-way shortest path determination method, considering the hyperlink structure between messages as a directed graph, remembering that the path from message <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> link to message <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> is the forward shortest path, and the path from entity <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> link to entity <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> is the backward shortest path, and the shortest path between two nodes is calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (5)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e005">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e005.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e005g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M5" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(5)</label>
</disp-formula>
Where <italic toggle="yes">FShortPath</italic> denotes the forward shortest path length and <italic toggle="yes">BShortPath</italic> denotes the backward shortest path length. In order to better describe the path correlation between two nodes, the route length is converted into path correlation and calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e006" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (6)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e006">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e006.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e006g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M6" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(6)</label>
</disp-formula><p>From this formula, the smaller the path length between two nodes, the greater the path association between the two nodes. According to the theory of "six degrees of separation", when exploring the shortest path length of two nodes, the upper limit of the shortest path length is set to six, that is, if the path length between two nodes exceeds six, the two nodes are considered to have no path association.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>3.2.3 Inter-block similarity calculation</title><p>In this paper, the semantic similarity is calculated using the name of the business entity and the specific content of the business transaction activities, using <italic toggle="yes">SimText</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) to denote the semantic similarity of the blocks represented by block <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and block <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>, respectively, and vectorizing the semantic description information represented by block <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and block <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> as <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> = {<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">11</italic></sub>,<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">12</italic></sub>,<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">13</italic></sub>,<italic toggle="yes">&#x02026;</italic>} and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> = {<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">21</italic></sub>,<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">22</italic></sub>,<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">23</italic></sub>,<italic toggle="yes">&#x02026;</italic>}, respectively, using cosine similarity calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e007" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (7)</xref>:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e007">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e007.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e007g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M7" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cos</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="&#x02016;" open="&#x02016;"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close="&#x02016;" open="&#x02016;"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(7)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>The normalization process is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e008" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (8)</xref>:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e008">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e008.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e008g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M8" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cos</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(8)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>Finally, the total consistency of the blockchain is calculated using the average measure of the similarity of these blocks, and the average similarity is calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e009" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (9)</xref>:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e009">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e009.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e009g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M9" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(9)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> is the total number of blocks to be compared, <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> is the blocks other than the blocks to be compared, and <italic toggle="yes">SimText</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>) is the similarity measure between the blocks to be compared and the other blocks.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>3.3 Blockchain quality assessment model construction</title><p>In this paper, based on the characteristic attributes of credibility, the credibility of information sources, evaluations and contents of business activities are used to independently characterize the credibility of information, and the results of the characterization are fused.</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Source-based information trustworthiness characterization. It includes three parts: the trustworthiness of the publishing platform is characterized by the trustworthiness of the information source; the trustworthiness of the page is based on the trustworthiness transfer theory, and the trustworthiness of the current page is characterized by the relevant link evaluation; the trustworthiness of the publisher is taken as the average trustworthiness of the publisher through continuous knowledge accumulation.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Comment-based information credibility characterization. Firstly, the comments are classified explicitly and implicitly, then the comment tendency analysis is performed using the lexicon approach, and finally the results of comment-based information credibility characterization are obtained.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Content-based credibility characterization. Using the information credibility results derived from using the dictionary of business activity characteristics as the main condition, the information is ranked in terms of credibility and given corresponding weights to smooth out the differences between various types of information, and finally the results of the information credibility characterization based on content characteristics are obtained.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>3.4 Blockchain content evaluation based on trustworthiness theory</title><p>The source or carrier of enterprise activity information directly reflects the degree of information credibility, and this paper characterizes the information credibility by assessing the activity information source.</p><sec id="sec013"><title>3.4.1 Source-based information trustworthiness characterization</title><p><italic toggle="yes">(1) Credibility of information sources</italic>. In this paper, we assume that the higher the click-through rate of information sources, the higher the credibility. The click through rate is considered an important basis for measuring the credibility of information sources. Firstly, the click through rate reflects the level of interest and recognition of users towards the content of the information source. Users are more likely to click on information they consider useful, authentic, and trustworthy. Therefore, information sources with high click through rates often imply user trust in the source, thus becoming one of the indicators for evaluating credibility. Secondly, click through rate is a direct feedback of user behavior. The behavior of users clicking on a certain information source indicates that they are interested in the content of that source and believe that the content is valuable to them. This positive user behavior feedback is seen as an affirmation of the credibility of the information source. Due to the limitations of certain information sources (e.g., forums, blogs) for access restrictions and their own audience limitations, their click-through rates as a whole will be lower than those of official information sources (e.g., news sites, official websites), so the adverse effects of the above should be smoothed out. The information source credibility model is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e010" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (10)</xref>:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e010">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e010.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e010g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M10" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(10)</label>
</disp-formula>
Where, <italic toggle="yes">Site_R</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>) is the credibility of a certain information source, <italic toggle="yes">hits</italic> denotes the click rate, <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> denotes the columns related to business activities in the information source, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> denotes the number of all columns in the information source, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> is the number of a certain type of information source. The model soothes out the heat by calculating the ratio of column clicks to the whole information source, reducing the rise in clicks on the business activity column due to interest in other information in a source.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">(2) Credibility of information pages</italic>. To a certain extent, the web page where the information is located also characterizes the credibility of the information. In this paper, we propose a method to characterize the trustworthiness of a page based on the information of the relevant links on the page, i.e., the accessibility of the links in the page and the availability of the reached page to judge the trustworthiness of an information source. The specific model is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (11)</xref>:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e011">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e011.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e011g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M11" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0222a;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(11)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">Page</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">i</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></sub>) denotes the credibility of the information page, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> denotes the set of reachable links among the relevant links, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> denotes the set of unreachable links among the relevant links, and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> denotes the set of unavailable pages among the pages reached by the links. Reachability means that the link can link and open the specified page normally, and availability means that the new page linked to has sufficient information and relevance.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">(3) Credibility of the information publisher</italic>. The credibility of the information publisher is mainly focused on the credibility judgment of the publisher, only for the credibility of the person to judge whether the information is credible, and then gradually converted to credible information users and untrustworthy information users after a certain knowledge reserve with the deepening of people&#x02019;s understanding of information and the acquisition of knowledge.</p><p>In this paper, we consider the network users who can receive information as a whole, and the total number of users is denoted as <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>. Initially, the users who receive data are considered as unknowns <italic toggle="yes">ignorant</italic>; as the information spreads on the network, these users can be further divided into two categories: those who consider the information credible <italic toggle="yes">believed</italic> and those who consider the information untrustworthy <italic toggle="yes">unbelieved</italic>. Based on this, this paper defines a benchmark for measuring the credibility of the information itself, which is used to discern the probability that the publisher of the information releases the information, the probability of determining the truthfulness of the information when it is published.</p><p>Therefore, based on the above considerations, the user states in the network can be divided into three categories:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Ignorant</italic>. This state refers to the state in the network when a piece of information has not yet been disseminated; or, when the information is published, users who do not know the truth or falsity of the information and have not yet made a judgment.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Believed</italic>. After having a certain knowledge base, when seeing the information, make a judgment that the information released by the publisher is credible.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Unbelieved</italic>. After having a certain knowledge base, when seeing the information, make a judgment that the information released by the publisher is not credible.</p></list-item></list><p>The schematic diagram of state transition between network nodes during information dissemination is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0304835.g003"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Inter-node state transition.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.g003" position="float"/></fig><p>Suppose a publisher publishes a message publicly, then the user who sees the message for the first time is regarded as an unknowing person, and the probability that the message is seen by other users in the unit time starting from moment <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> is &#x003b1;; in contrast, the probability that the user thinks the message is untrustworthy is &#x003b2;.</p><p>With the passage of time and the accumulation of their own learned knowledge and awareness, the users&#x02019; cognitive state of information will change. Therefore, assuming that the probability that a trusted user thinks the information is untrustworthy is &#x003b3; per unit time starting from moment <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, then it is shown that the trusted information user converts to an untrustworthy information user; at the same time, the probability that an untrustworthy information user thinks the information is trustworthy is &#x003b4;, then the untrustworthy information user converts to a trusted information user. Therefore, based on the above information content-based interaction rules, a system of equations is established as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e012" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (12)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e012">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e012.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e012g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M12" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="" open="{"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(12)</label>
</disp-formula>
Where: <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) denote the proportion of the total number of users at the time of the unknowns, trusted information users, and untrusted information users, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">0</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">0</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">0</italic>) denote the value of the number of users in each state in the initial state, and all are non-negative numbers.</p><p>In the above interaction rule, assume that the user&#x02019;s trustworthiness of the message publisher is <italic toggle="yes">Publish_R</italic>. When other users see the message, they can directly judge whether the message is trustworthy or not by their intuitive impression of the publisher of the message, then the average trustworthiness probability of the publisher is calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e013" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (13)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e013">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e013.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e013g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M13" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(13)</label>
</disp-formula><p>The probability of implausibility is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e014" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (14)</xref>:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e014">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e014.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e014g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M14" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(14)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p><italic toggle="yes">(4) The fusion of credibility characterization results of the source</italic>. The source-based credibility is calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e015" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (15)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e015">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e015.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e015g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M15" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(15)</label>
</disp-formula></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>3.4.2 Information trustworthiness characterization based on evaluation features</title><p>Information credibility is assessed by calculating the extrinsic representations of the comments, which are first defined as follows.</p><p>Invalid comments: Comments that do not contain emotional words or are not related to the credibility of the content of the message.</p><p>Explicit comments: Comments that contain words that can clearly characterize the tendency of credibility.</p><p>Implicit comments: Comments that contain emotional words but do not have the tendency to explicitly characterize credibility words.</p><p>Explicit and implicit comments have different contributions to the evaluation of information credibility based on comments. These two types of comments reveal different attitudes and perspectives of users when facing information. By comprehensively analyzing them, the credibility of information can be more comprehensively evaluated. Explicit comments usually contain clear attitudes, opinions, or feedback from users. This direct expression helps to understand the user&#x02019;s true view of the information, thereby providing direct clues about the credibility of the information. And Explicit comments often contain more facts, data, or specific information. This clear statement makes it easier to evaluate the accuracy of information and helps confirm whether the information is based on verifiable content. Implicit comments may involve emotional vocabulary, emotional color, or suggestive language, revealing the user&#x02019;s emotional feedback. This is of great significance for evaluating the user experience and impact of information. Implicit comments can provide additional context or information for explicit comments. Sometimes users may not express themselves clearly in their words, but through the tone and emotions in implicit comments, they can gain a deeper understanding of their views. These implicit viewpoints help to gain a more comprehensive understanding of the user&#x02019;s overall perception of information, providing more dimensions for credibility assessment.</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Dispositional analysis of explicit commentary representations</italic>. In this paper, the sentiment intensity is adjusted by the modifier window strategy to control the representational value. If the current analyzed word is a sentiment word, the word is placed in the corresponding calculator based on the specific sentiment tendency, and the degree to which the current sentiment word is modified by the modifier words in the sliding window is taken out to obtain the value of the word&#x02019;s contribution to the sentiment of the sentence. If the sliding window contains a negative word when the current sentiment word is analyzed, the sentiment tendency is reversed and the sliding window range is used to control the range of action of the negative word. Finally, the sentiment tendency is calculated for the whole comment tendency, which is calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e016" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (16)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e016">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e016.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e016g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M16" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(16)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">R_review_dominant</italic> denotes the value of a user&#x02019;s comment on the credibility of the message, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> denotes the number of sentences in the total comment, <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> denotes the score of credible representations in a sentence, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> denotes the score of suspicious representations in a sentence, and <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> denotes the length of a sentence. When the single-sentence sentiment score lies in the (- 0.1, + 0.1) interval, the comment has a weak tendency to be characterized and is not considered.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Implicit commentary representation propensity analysis</italic>. The analysis of representational tendency for implicit comments is performed in two steps: first, the relevance of the comments to the message is calculated; second, the representational tendency value is calculated for the relevant implicit comments.
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Relevance of comments to information</italic>. In this paper, a probabilistic retrieval model is used to calculate the relevance of information and comments, i.e., comments and information are considered as retrieval problems. The set of information constitutes the set of documents when the comment <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> is assumed to be a query string and the information <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> is treated as a document. On the basis of the classical probabilistic retrieval model, it is smoothed as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e017" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (17)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e017">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e017.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e017g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M17" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close="" open="|"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0220f;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close="" open="|"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0220f;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0220f;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close="" open="|"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close="" open="|"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(17)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> is the message, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> is an entry in the set of comments of <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">w</italic> is a word in <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">C|I</italic>) is the probability of <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> generating <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">w|I</italic>) is the probability of <italic toggle="yes">w</italic> appearing in <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> is the set of topics of message <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> is a topic in <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub>, &#x003bb; is a parameter, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">w|t</italic>) is the probability of word <italic toggle="yes">w</italic> appearing in topic <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t|I</italic>) is the probability of topic <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> appearing in message <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">C|I</italic>) is calculated for all comments in message <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>. If the probability value is greater than a certain threshold, the relevant comment is determined to be relevant to the message.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Related implicit commentary on representational tendencies</italic>. In addition to explicit emotion words, some implicit words also have attitudinal characteristics, and for implicit evaluation representation tendency values are calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e018" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (18)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e018">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e018.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e018g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M18" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mtext>min</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(18)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> denotes a paragraph, sentence or word, and <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> corresponds to a whole comment, paragraph or sentence, the sentiment score of <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> is denoted as <italic toggle="yes">w(R)</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">p(a</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub><italic toggle="yes">)</italic> denotes the position of the sentiment unit <italic toggle="yes">a</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> in <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">count</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">a|R</italic>) denotes the total number of <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> containing <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>.</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Comment-based fusion of credibility characterization results</italic>. The process of fusion is divided into two steps: first, the objects of the comments are obtained and classified; second, the results of the classified comments are fused in the way shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e019" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (19)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e019">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e019.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e019g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M19" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(19)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">R_review</italic> is the trustworthiness of the message based on the comment, <italic toggle="yes">Tar</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>) is the characterization of the trustworthiness of the message by the object <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> being commented on, <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> is the characterization of the trustworthiness of a comment <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> on <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></sub> is the characterization of the trustworthiness of a direct comment on the message.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>3.4.3 Information trustworthiness characterization based on content features</title><p>Existing methods of content credibility calculation assess the content of a certain type of activity information with the help of external information and lack a direct and reliable evaluation algorithm for information from multiple sources. This paper proposes a method for characterizing information trustworthiness using data content features based on a study of enterprise activity information characteristics, which is based on two assumptions:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Feature words determine the professionalism of information, i.e. the more words characterizing enterprise activities in the information content, the more professional the information is.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The professionalism of the information determines the credibility of the information, i.e. the more professional the information is, the more credible it is.</p></list-item></list><p>Considering the uneven distribution of corporate activity information features in information from multiple sources, this paper uses a corporate activity feature dictionary to count the frequency of corporate activity feature words in various types of information. The credibility of the content is calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e020" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (20)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e020">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e020.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e020g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M20" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(20)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">word_f</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">word_s</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">word_t</italic> denote the number of common, characteristic and specialized words occurring in the message, respectively, &#x003b1;, &#x003b2; and &#x003bb; denote the associated weights, and &#x003bc; is the information type characteristic coefficient.</p><p>Finally, information trustworthiness in the blockchain is a combined measure of source-based trustworthiness, comment-based trustworthiness and content-based trustworthiness, as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e021" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (21)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e021">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e021.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e021g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M21" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(21)</label>
</disp-formula><p>Among them <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic> &#x0003c; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic> &#x0003c; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic>, since the information source is the key factor to measure the credibility of information, such as official information is 100% credible, the credibility of the information source has the largest weight, the content credibility is the second, and the comment-based credibility has the smallest weight since the comment depends on the subjectivity of the commenter. Some situation may affect the method like different fields may have different professional standards and vocabulary usage habits. Some fields may place more emphasis on the use of professional terminology, while others may place more emphasis on common language. Therefore, the relationship between the number of feature words and professionalism may vary between different fields. Sometimes, the number of feature words does not always reflect the depth and detail level of information. Some content may require more professional terminology and detailed explanations, which may not necessarily lead to an increase in the number of feature words. Therefore, quantity cannot fully represent the professionalism and credibility of the text. But in most cases, these issues will not have a significant impact on the conclusions of the model output, so no additional discussion is needed.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>3.5 Blockchain value assessment based on the amount of information</title><p>To measure the validity of information on business activities in the blockchain, this paper adopts the method of calculating the amount of information, which is measured by the amount of information on business activities in the block. The method realizes the value assessment of the blockchain through the amount of information contained in the blockchain, determines the indeterminacy of the information representation source based on the determination of the indeterminacy of the information selection of the source, and transforms the study of the indeterminacy of a random event into the study of the totality of the probability corresponding to that random event. Its relevant definitions and properties are as follows:</p><p><bold>Definition</bold> Self-informative amount. The self-information of an arbitrary random event is defined as the negative of the logarithm of the probability of occurrence of the event. Let the probability of the event <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> be <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>). Then its self-information is defined as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e022" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (22)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e022">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e022.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e022g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M22" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(22)</label>
</disp-formula><p><bold>Property 1</bold> There is no negative value for the amount of information, and the smaller the value means the smaller the amount of information carried, and the larger the value, the greater the amount of information.</p><p><bold>Property 2</bold> The amount of information is additive in nature. According to this property, the amount of information in a blockchain node can be considered as the sum of the amount of information of each active message in the block.</p><p>Information amount can quantitatively describe exactly how much information about business activities is contained in each block in the blockchain. In the process of blockchain information amount calculation, information amount represents the amount of information contained in a block, and is a measure of the validity of activity information. Each block can be regarded as a discrete source, and if it is a discrete random variable (a certain chain), the set of values of the random variable and its probability measure are as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e023" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (23)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e023">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e023.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e023g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M23" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>&#x02026;</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(23)</label>
</disp-formula><p>The probability space of the discrete random variable <italic toggle="yes">X</italic> is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e024" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (24)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e024">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e024.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e024g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M24" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(24)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> is the probability of occurrence of active information in block <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>. The amount of information is calculated as shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e025" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (25)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e025">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e025.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e025g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M25" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(25)</label>
</disp-formula><p>Here, <italic toggle="yes">X</italic> is a random variable, <italic toggle="yes">Validity</italic> is the amount of information contained in the block, and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>) is the probability distribution function of the variable <italic toggle="yes">X</italic>.</p><p>In practical applications, the use of this method is more practical for unknown unordered structures. The degree of information uncertainty is expressed by a non-negative value, and the magnitude of the information quantity value directly determines the amount of information. For a certain blockchain, the amount of information can be measured by this value, and the larger the value, the more information the blockchain contains, and thus the greater the value of the blockchain.</p></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>3.6 Quality assessment model</title><p>Multi-source heterogeneous blockchain quality assessment is used to assess the consistency, trustworthiness, and value of the information on business activities stored in the blockchain. In this paper, we propose a weighted approach to construct a blockchain quality assessment model, which uses the similarity of block representations, source-based block trustworthiness representations, and the weighted average of the values contained in the blocks to measure the comprehensive quality of the blockchain. The final evaluation model is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.e026" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (26)</xref>.
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e026">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e026.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e026g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M26" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(26)</label>
</disp-formula>
where &#x003b1;, &#x003b2; and &#x003b3; represent the weights of three assessment metrics, respectively. Since blockchain value is an important indicator of blockchain quality, the greater the value contained in the blockchain, the greater the application value of that blockchain, followed by information trustworthiness, hence the weight <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic> &#x0003e; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic> &#x0003e; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>3.7 Case analysis of enterprise alliance chain evaluation</title><p>This section mainly evaluates the quality of our existing enterprise blockchain business activities, and obtains the final blockchain data quality evaluation result through comprehensive consistency, accuracy, and value calculation results. We will use effective data obtained from local enterprises to apply in this section.</p><p>Firstly, based on the credibility of the information source, it is mainly measured comprehensively by the credibility of the information source, information page, and publisher. For the credibility of the information source, its click through rate is calculated as click through rate = click through rate/exposure rate (as used in the example in this article); For the credibility of information pages, it is mainly measured by the accessibility of the page where the information is located and whether it is available after accessibility, while the credibility of publishers is judged by users through certain knowledge accumulation. Based on the calculation results of the above three factors, the credibility of the information source can be calculated as follows:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e027">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e027.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e027g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M27" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>source</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mn>0.6</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>20</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.75</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>40</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.9</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(27)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>Secondly, calculate the credibility of the information evaluation. When the evaluation of the activity event is none, the evaluation characterizes the credibility of the information as 0; When the evaluation of an activity event is an explicit evaluation, its credibility representation value is directly calculated; When the evaluation of an activity event is calculated as an implicit evaluation, the first step is to determine whether the evaluation is related to the information, and then calculate the tendency value of the relevant representation. The above blockchain calculates the credibility representation values based on evaluation information as follows:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e028">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e028.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e028g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M28" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mtext>review</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(28)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>The representation of information credibility based on content features is mainly measured by the number of common words, feature words, and professional words in the information content. By conducting relevant statistics on the frequency of various features in enterprise business activity information and calculating them:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e029">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e029.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e029g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M29" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>content</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>38</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.3</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>14</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.3</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>64</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>64</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>500</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01598</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(29)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>The credibility of information sources is determined by a combination of source based, evaluation based, and content-based credibility. The calculated credibility of information sources is as follows:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e030">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e030.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e030g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M30" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Accu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>3.9</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.3</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>0.01598</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.005</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(30)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>Finally, calculate the value information of blockchain:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e031">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e031.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e031g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M31" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>Validity</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.782</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(31)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>The final quality evaluation result of blockchain is weighted by three factors:
<disp-formula id="pone.0304835.e032">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.e032.jpg" id="pone.0304835.e032g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M32" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>0.72</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>2.005</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mi>*</mml:mi><mml:mn>2.782</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.4204</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(32)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>The above process can prove that the final quality evaluation model of blockchain in this article has good operability and feasibility.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>4 Experiments and results</title><sec id="sec020"><title>4.1 Experiments setting</title><p>The experimental hardware and software environment is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0304835.t001"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Experimental platform sets.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.t001" id="pone.0304835.t001g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hardware</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bytes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPU</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intel Core i5-7400</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPU running</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3GHz</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Memory</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8GB</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operation system</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Windows11</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Programming environment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PyCharm 2020.3.3</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Programming language</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Python</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Programming language version</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7.3</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The experimental dataset consists of two parts, which are official data searched and crawled on the search engine with the subject term of business activities and real data of enterprises, totaling about 210,000 items, and then simple data cleaning is performed by filling in missing values, smoothing or removing outlier points and other operations to get about 200,000 items of data, and the details of the dataset are listed in <xref rid="pone.0304835.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The datasets are available from <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.25143503.v1" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.25143503.v1</ext-link>. In this paper, simulation experiments are conducted in terms of model parameter taking and model evaluation efficiency respectively, and the model built in this paper (DQAM) is used to compare with other models, and the comparison models are AHP, DSMM, etc.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0304835.t002"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Experimental data sets.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.t002" id="pone.0304835.t002g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entity Name</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bytes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16bytes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 bytes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">activityOntology</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable length bytes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">comment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable length bytes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">informationSource</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 bytes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Code</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 bytes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">registrationDay</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 bytes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">capital</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 bytes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">address</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 bytes</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>4.2 Model parameter setting</title><p>The experiments in this section focus on verifying the parameter settings of the proposed evaluation model, through which it can be seen that the blockchain value takes the largest weight, followed by the information credibility, i.e., weight <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic> &#x0003e; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic> &#x0003e; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>. The values of the three can affect the model evaluation effect. Therefore, the experiments in this section verify three different parameter settings and then select the optimal weight setting. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>, the better relative running efficiency of the vertical axis indicates the better setting of this parameter, and the horizontal axis indicates the number of data sets run, in units of ten thousand, and the effect of different &#x003b3;: &#x003b2;: &#x003b1; ratio runs is as follows.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0304835.g004"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Model parameter settings.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.g004" position="float"/></fig><p>As can be seen from <xref rid="pone.0304835.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>, when the model parameters are set to &#x003b3;: &#x003b2;: &#x003b1; = 7: 2: 1, the model runs more efficiently, optimizing 5% to 10% over the other ratios.</p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>4.3 Consistency assessment efficiency comparison</title><p>In this section, the inconsistency detection efficiency of entity information is evaluated on the dataset in <xref rid="pone.0304835.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, where the horizontal axis represents the number of data entries, in units of ten thousand, and the vertical axis represents the consistency assessment efficiency, and the efficiency is compared by the structured gradient tree boosting (SGTB) algorithm, disambiguation of inconsistent record pairs based on factor graphs (DIBFM), neural network disambiguation with multi-view concerns (NDMP) method and the semantic similarity calculation method between blocks based on contextual information (SCBCI) proposed in this paper, and the experimental results are shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0304835.g005"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Consistency assessment efficiency comparison.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.g005" position="float"/></fig><p>As can be seen from <xref rid="pone.0304835.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>, with the increase of data amount, the evaluation efficiency of the consistency assessment method proposed in this paper is gradually improved compared with the existing methods, and the efficiency is not reduced due to the large amount of data.</p></sec><sec id="sec023"><title>4.4 Accuracy assessment efficiency comparison</title><p>This section validates the efficiency of the trustworthiness theory-based blockchain content evaluation (CEBT) method. The vertical axis is the operational efficiency, and the horizontal axis represents the number of data entries, in units of ten thousand, and the specific operational efficiency comparison of each method on different data sets is shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>. As can be seen from the figure, the average evaluation efficiency of the CEBT method is higher than that of the other methods. The comparison methods are the sensor data trustworthiness assessment (MHIF) method based on multi-source heterogeneous information fusion and the supervised machine learning (SML) method for user-generated content trustworthiness assessment.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0304835.g006"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Accuracy assessment efficiency comparison.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.g006" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec024"><title>4.5 Comparison of value assessment efficiency</title><p>The experiments were conducted by simulating the comparison of the value assessment efficiency using the amount of information approach (VIS) with the value assessment approach based on data distribution (VADD) and the VW&#x00026;ICM calculation model, with the horizontal coordinate indicating the amount of data, in units of ten thousand, and the vertical coordinate indicating the assessment efficiency, and the experimental results are shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0304835.g007"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title>Valuation efficiency comparison.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.g007" position="float"/></fig><p>From the experimental results, it can be found that the information amount-based assessment method proposed in this paper is more efficient. The main reason for this is that the information-amount-based data value assessment focuses on the data value itself rather than its secondary factors such as distribution and regularity, so the method is intuitive, clear and more efficient.</p></sec><sec id="sec025"><title>4.6 Total evaluation efficiency comparison</title><p>This section compares the running efficiency of each model, the horizontal coordinate represents the entity data set in the blockchain, in units of ten thousand, the vertical coordinate indicates the time required to run each model, and the experimental results are shown in <xref rid="pone.0304835.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0304835.g008"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.g008</object-id><label>Fig 8</label><caption><title>Model efficiency comparison.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0304835.g008" position="float"/></fig><p>From the results, it can be seen that the average running time of AHP and DSMM methods is around 10~15ms, and the evaluation time of DQAM model proposed in this paper is around 5ms, and the evaluation time of DQAM model basically fluctuates little with the increase of data amount, and the average time is the shortest compared with other methods, which is more suitable for users to conduct blockchain quality evaluation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec026"><title>5 Conclusion</title><p>This paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities. Initially, leveraging pertinent enterprise entity data within the blockchain, we introduce a triadic representation of enterprise entities utilizing the CEKGRL model, intricately linked with relevant activity categories. This integration enables the construction of an association graph model for entity context information, thus enhancing the efficiency of similarity computations between blocks. Subsequently, through an examination of blockchain content, we ascertain the credibility of blockchain information via a credibility characterization method. This method is grounded in information source analysis, information commentary evaluation, and the content of business activity information, amalgamating all characterization outcomes to provide a comprehensive credibility assessment. Finally, the value assessment method is used to evaluate the value amount contained in the content of the blockchain, and the above information is combined to obtain the blockchain quality assessment model.</p><p>This paper has conducted in-depth research on the blockchain data quality evaluation model, proposed corresponding solutions for the shortcomings of current evaluation methods, and achieved some meaningful research results. However, the application of blockchain technology involves other fields besides the financial field. For its different application scenarios, the following issues related to this study need further exploration and research:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The blockchain data quality evaluation model in this paper is aimed at the business activities data information of enterprises in the financial field, while other fields are also producing a lot of data information at all times. Therefore, applying the evaluation model proposed in this paper to data in other fields is the next research direction.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The model proposed in this paper is based on the established blockchain, but in reality, the information in the blockchain is sometimes stored dynamically, and may be linked at any time. Therefore, when new block information is generated in the blockchain, how to evaluate its quality in real time is worth studying.</p></list-item></list></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank the reviewers for their constructive comments in improving the quality of this paper.</p><sec id="sec027"><title>Preprint version statement</title><p>A preprint version of the paper has been published in Research Square, Zhang Haolin, Su Li, and Likuan Du making revisions to the second edition, so the order of authors has been adjusted and two new authors have been added.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0304835.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <source>Smart Grid Nontechnical Loss Detection Based on Power Gateway Consortium Blockchain</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>A Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Recognition method of Abnormal Transaction Behavior of Blockchain digital Currency based on Motivation Analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computers</source>, <volume>44</volume>(<issue>01</issue>): <fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>208</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Research on Sharding Model for Enabling Cross Heterogeneous Blockchain Transactions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Digital Convergence</source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Ethereum Coin Voting Protocol Based on Smart Contract</article-title>. <source>Journal of software</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>3486</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3502</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Formal verification of smart Contract for MSVL</article-title>. <source>Journal of software</source>, <volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1849</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1866</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guitton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>A blockchain-based trust system for decentralized applications: When trustless needs trust</article-title>. <source>Future Generation Computer Systems</source>, <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>G M</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>A blockchain-based trust system for decentralized applications: When trustless needs trust</article-title>. <source>Future Generation Computer Systems: the international journal of grid computing: theory, methods and applications</source>
<volume>124</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zheng Peilin, Xu Quangqing, ZHENG Zibin, et al. (2021) Meepo: Sharded consortium blockchain. 2021 IEEE 37th International Conference on Data Engineering, Chania, Greece, 1847&#x02013;1852.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Colomo-Palacios</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez&#x02010;Gord&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arias-Aranda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>A critical review on blockchain assessment initiatives: A technology evolution viewpoint. Journal of Software</article-title>: <source>Evolution and Process</source>
<volume>32</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>e2272</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farooque</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Blockchain-based life cycle assessment: An implementation framework and system architecture</article-title>. <source>Resources, Conservation and Recycling</source>
<volume>152</volume>: <fpage>104512</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Prediction of information Heat based on social circle and attention mechanism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computers</source>
<volume>44</volume>(<issue>05</issue>): <fpage>921</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>936</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yi Yang, Ozan Irsoy, and Kazi Shefaet Rahman. (2018) Collective Entity Disambiguation with Structured Gradient Tree Boosting. In Proceedings of the 2018 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies, Volume 1, New Orleans, Louisiana. Association for Computational Linguistics, 777&#x02013;786.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang Y, Irsoy O, Rahman K S (2018) Collective entity disambiguation with structured gradient tree boosting. arXiv preprint arXiv:1802.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>Jiang</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kai</surname><given-names>Wang</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yueqiang</surname><given-names>Xu</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Optimal Caching Strategy of Operators Based on Consortium Blockchain</article-title> [J]. <source>Journal of Electronics &#x00026; Information Technology</source>, <volume>44</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>3043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3050</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Entity disambiguation leveraging multi-perspective attention</article-title>. <source>IEEE Access</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>113963</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113974</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>A Multi-dimensional credibility Calculation Method based on feedback credibility in MAS Environment</article-title>. <source>Journal of software</source>
<volume>31</volume>(<issue>02</issue>): <fpage>374</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>394</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Credibility Assessment Method of Sensor Data Based on Multi-Source Heterogeneous Information Fusion</article-title>. <source>Sensors</source>
<volume>21</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>2542</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2542</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s21072542</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 33916389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33916389</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>P K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pamula</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>S. A</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Supervised Machine Learning Approach for the Credibility Assessment of User-Generated Content</article-title>. <source>Wireless Personal Communications</source>
<volume>118</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>2469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2485</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaul</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gorsich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>) <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Confidence-based reliability assessment considering limited numbers of both input and output test data</article-title>. <source>Structural and Multidisciplinary Optimization</source>
<volume>57</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>2027</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2043</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>A new quantitative method for risk assessment of water inrush in karst tunnels based on variable weight function and improved cloud model</article-title>. <source>Tunnelling and Underground Space Technology</source>
<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>103136</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Improved assessment model for candidate design schemes with an interval rough integrated cloud model under uncertain group environment</article-title>. <source>Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>104352</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0304835.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2022</year>). <source>Research on quality assessment method of blockchain multi-source heterogeneous business data</source>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0304835.r001" specific-use="decision-letter"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.r001</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>Asadullah</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 Asadullah Shaikh</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Asadullah Shaikh</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0304835" id="rel-obj001" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">2 Jan 2024</named-content>
</p><p><!-- <div> -->PONE-D-23-32614<!-- </div> --><!-- <div> -->Multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities<!-- </div> --></p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>Dear Dr. Wang,</p><p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#x02019;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p><p>Please submit your revised manuscript by Feb 16 2024 11:59PM. If you will need more time than this to complete your revisions, please reply to this message or contact the journal office at&#x000a0;<email>plosone@plos.org</email>. When you're ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p><p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). You should upload this letter as a separate file labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list><!-- <div> -->If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter. Guidelines for resubmitting your figure files are available below the reviewer comments at the end of this letter.</p><p>If applicable, we recommend that you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io to enhance the reproducibility of your results. Protocols.io assigns your protocol its own identifier (DOI) so that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link>. Additionally, PLOS ONE offers an option for publishing peer-reviewed Lab Protocol articles, which describe protocols hosted on protocols.io. Read more information on sharing protocols at <ext-link xlink:href="https://plos.org/protocols?utm_medium=editorial-email&#x00026;utm_source=authorletters&#x00026;utm_campaign=protocols" ext-link-type="uri">https://plos.org/protocols?utm_medium=editorial-email&#x00026;utm_source=authorletters&#x00026;utm_campaign=protocols</ext-link>.</p><p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p><p>Kind regards,</p><p>Asadullah Shaikh, Ph.D.</p><p>Academic Editor</p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>Journal requirements:</p><p>When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p><p>1. Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and</p><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link>
</p><p>2. In your Methods section, please include additional information about your dataset and ensure that you have included a statement specifying whether the collection and analysis method complied with the terms and conditions for the source of the data.</p><p>3. Please note that PLOS ONE has specific guidelines on code sharing for submissions in which author-generated code underpins the findings in the manuscript. In these cases, all author-generated code must be made available without restrictions upon publication of the work. Please review our guidelines at <ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/materials-and-software-sharing#loc-sharing-code" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/materials-and-software-sharing#loc-sharing-code</ext-link> and ensure that your code is shared in a way that follows best practice and facilitates reproducibility and reuse.</p><p>4. Thank you for stating the following financial disclosure:</p><p>&#x0201c;This study was supported by the Applied Basic Research Program of Liaoning Province(No.2022JH2/101300250); the Digital Liao-ning Smart Building Strong Province (Direction of Digital Economy)(No.13031307053000568); the National Key R&#x00026;D Program of China(No.2021YFF0901004); the Central Government Guides Local Science and Technology Development Foundation Project of Liaoning Province (No.2022JH6/100100032); the Natural Science Foundation of Liaoning Province (No.2022-KF-13-06).&#x0201d;</p><p>Please state what role the funders took in the study.&#x000a0; If the funders had no role, please state: "The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript."</p><p>If this statement is not correct you must amend it as needed.</p><p>Please include this amended Role of Funder statement in your cover letter; we will change the online submission form on your behalf.</p><p>5. In this instance it seems there may be acceptable restrictions in place that prevent the public sharing of your minimal data. However, in line with our goal of ensuring long-term data availability to all interested researchers, PLOS&#x02019; Data Policy states that authors cannot be the sole named individuals responsible for ensuring data access (<ext-link xlink:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/data-availability#loc-acceptable-data-sharing-methods" ext-link-type="uri">http://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/data-availability#loc-acceptable-data-sharing-methods</ext-link>).</p><p>Data requests to a non-author institutional point of contact, such as a data access or ethics committee, helps guarantee long term stability and availability of data. Providing interested researchers with a durable point of contact ensures data will be accessible even if an author changes email addresses, institutions, or becomes unavailable to answer requests.</p><p>Before we proceed with your manuscript, please also provide non-author contact information (phone/email/hyperlink) for a data access committee, ethics committee, or other institutional body to which data requests may be sent. If no institutional body is available to respond to requests for your minimal data, please consider if there any institutional representatives who did not collaborate in the study, and are not listed as authors on the manuscript, who would be able to hold the data and respond to external requests for data access? If so, please provide their contact information (i.e., email address). Please also provide details on how you will ensure persistent or long-term data storage and availability.</p><p>6. PLOS requires an ORCID iD for the corresponding author in Editorial Manager on papers submitted after December 6th, 2016. Please ensure that you have an ORCID iD and that it is validated in Editorial Manager. To do this, go to &#x02018;Update my Information&#x02019; (in the upper left-hand corner of the main menu), and click on the Fetch/Validate link next to the ORCID field. This will take you to the ORCID site and allow you to create a new iD or authenticate a pre-existing iD in Editorial Manager. Please see the following video for instructions on linking an ORCID iD to your Editorial Manager account: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_xcclfuvtxQ" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_xcclfuvtxQ</ext-link>.</p><p>7. Please review your reference list to ensure that it is complete and correct. If you have cited papers that have been retracted, please include the rationale for doing so in the manuscript text, or remove these references and replace them with relevant current references. Any changes to the reference list should be mentioned in the rebuttal letter that accompanies your revised manuscript. If you need to cite a retracted article, indicate the article&#x02019;s retracted status in the References list and also include a citation and full reference for the retraction notice.</p><p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p><p>Reviewers' comments:</p><p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p><p>
<!-- <font color="black"> -->
<bold>Comments to the Author</bold>
</p><p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p><p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. <!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********&#x000a0;</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? <!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********&#x000a0;</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p><p>The <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ext-link-type="uri">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#x02014;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#x02014;those must be specified.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********&#x000a0;</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p><p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********&#x000a0;</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->5. Review Comments to the Author</p><p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Dear Author,</p><p>I have carefully reviewed the manuscript titled "Multi-Source Heterogeneous Blockchain Data Quality Assessment for Enterprise Business Activities." While the paper proposes an intriguing approach to address the challenges in evaluating the consistency, credibility, and value of information in enterprise business activities stored in blockchain, there are several aspects that need clarification and improvement:</p><p>Experimental Details and Data:</p><p>The manuscript lacks specific details on experimental setups, controls, replications, and sample sizes. To ensure the technical soundness of your research, it is essential to provide comprehensive information about the experiments conducted, including the datasets used, methodology for control, and the size of the samples involved.</p><p>Clarity in Methodology:</p><p>The methodology section, especially in Section 3.1 regarding the CEKGRL model, is intricate and could benefit from additional clarity. A more detailed explanation of the entity triad representation, attention mechanism, and how the model addresses inconsistencies in entity information would enhance the reader's understanding.</p><p>Contextual Information and Ambiguity:</p><p>While the introduction of contextual information for similarity calculation is interesting, further details are needed to understand how this addresses the "one-to-many" mapping problem and ambiguity in entity name designation. A clearer explanation of how the contextual information association graph model contributes to resolving these issues would be beneficial.</p><p>Source Credibility Model:</p><p>The credibility characterization of information sources in Section 3.4 requires more explanation, particularly regarding the calculation of the click-through rate and how it directly correlates with credibility. Please provide more insights into how this model aligns with established credibility standards.</p><p>Comment-Based Information Credibility:</p><p>The methodology for comment-based information credibility characterization (Section 3.4) could be further detailed. Consider providing examples or case studies to illustrate how explicit and implicit comments are classified and contribute to the overall credibility assessment.</p><p>Content-Based Credibility Characterization:</p><p>The content-based credibility characterization assumes a direct relationship between the number of feature words and professionalism/credibility. It is important to discuss potential limitations of this assumption and consider other factors that may influence credibility.</p><p>Conclusion and Implications:</p><p>The conclusion should summarize the key findings and their implications. Discuss the potential limitations of the proposed method and suggest avenues for future research to strengthen the manuscript's overall impact.</p><p>I appreciate the effort invested in this research and believe that addressing these concerns will significantly enhance the manuscript's quality and contribution to the field.</p><p>Best regards,</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;Start by summarizing the paper's objectives, which focus on assessing the quality of data in multi-source heterogeneous blockchain environments, particularly in the context of enterprise business activities. Highlight the importance of this topic in the rapidly evolving blockchain landscape and its relevance to businesses relying on blockchain technology.</p><p>1. The abstract needs refinement. Clearly articulate the role of the proposed study and highlight the actual contributions. This will provide readers with a better understanding of the paper's significance.</p><p>2. Expand the introduction to provide more context and background information. A more detailed introduction will better set the stage for the problem you are addressing, helping readers grasp the significance of your research.</p><p>3. Include a section that compares your work with previous studies and techniques. This comparison can provide additional support for the validity and novelty of your research. Highlight similarities, differences, and advancements over prior work</p><p>4. Suggest a more in-depth analysis of security and privacy concerns associated with multi-source blockchain data.</p><p>Encourage the inclusion of case studies or practical examples to demonstrate the model's application in real business scenarios and also Propose collaborations with blockchain enterprises for real-world testing and validation of the model.</p><p>**********&#x000a0;</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ext-link-type="uri">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p><p>If you choose &#x0201c;no&#x0201d;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p><p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ext-link-type="uri">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;No</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;<bold>Yes:&#x000a0;</bold>Tahir Alyas</p><p>**********</p><p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files.]</p><p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool,&#x000a0;<ext-link xlink:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email PLOS at&#x000a0;<email>figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0304835.r002"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.r002</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title></title-group><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0304835" id="rel-obj002" related-article-type="editor-report"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">15 Feb 2024</named-content>
</p><p>Dear Editor and Reviewers,</p><p>Thanks for your comments concerning our manuscript entitled &#x0201c;multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities". The comments are very valuable and helpful for revising and improving our manuscript. We have carefully revised the manuscript and responded all comments below. The changes will not affect the content and framework of the paper. The revised sentences are highlighted in yellow in the manuscript.</p><p>Best regards,</p><p>Baoyan Song</p><p>Reviewer 1:</p><p> Experimental Details and Data. The manuscript lacks specific details on experimental setups, controls, replications, and sample sizes. To ensure the technical soundness of your research, it is essential to provide comprehensive information about the experiments conducted, including the datasets used, methodology for control, and the size of the samples involved.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a separate subsection to the experimental section that describes the experimental setting and experimental dataset of this paper, as well as other models that were tested in comparison with the model proposed in this paper. The details are as follows.</p><p>Experiments setting</p><p>The experimental hardware and software environment is shown in Table 1.</p><p>Table 1 Experimental platform sets</p><p>Hardware Bytes</p><p>CPU Intel Core i5-7400</p><p>CPU running 3GHz</p><p>Memory 8GB</p><p>Operation system Windows11</p><p>Programming environment PyCharm 2020.3.3</p><p>Programming language Python</p><p>Programming language version 3.7.3</p><p>The experimental dataset is searched on search engines with the subject term of business activities and crawled official data, about 110,000 items, and then simple data cleaning is performed by filling in missing values, smoothing or removing outlier points and other operations to get about 100,000 items of data, and the details of the dataset are listed in Table 2. In this paper, simulation experiments are conducted in terms of model parameter taking and model evaluation efficiency respectively, and the model built in this paper (DQAM) is used to compare with other models, and the comparison models are AHP, DSMM, etc.</p><p>Table 2 Experimental data sets</p><p>Entity Name Bytes</p><p>name 16bytes</p><p>type 8 bytes</p><p>activityOntology Variable length bytes</p><p>comment Variable length bytes</p><p>informationSource 16 bytes</p><p>code 4 bytes</p><p>registrationDay 4 bytes</p><p>capital 16 bytes</p><p>address 32 bytes</p><p> Clarity in Methodology. The methodology section, especially in Section 3.1 regarding the CEKGRL model, is intricate and could benefit from additional clarity. A more detailed explanation of the entity triad representation, attention mechanism, and how the model addresses inconsistencies in entity information would enhance the reader's understanding.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have reorganized the logic of Section 3.1 and added additional explanations related to the entity triad representation, the attention mechanism, and how the model resolves inconsistencies in entity information. The details are as follows.</p><p>The triple structure is a data model widely used for representing information, consisting of three components: subject, predicate, and object. It is extensively applied in fields such as knowledge graphs and the semantic web. The triple structure is highly flexible and can be employed to represent various types of information. Different combinations of subjects, predicates, and objects can capture rich semantic relationships, making it suitable for diverse knowledge representation. In summary, the advantages of the triple structure lie in its flexibility, clear semantic representation, scalability, and effective expression of relationships, making it a key technology in the fields of knowledge representation and the semantic web.</p><p> Contextual Information and Ambiguity. While the introduction of contextual information for similarity calculation is interesting, further details are needed to understand how this addresses the "one-to-many" mapping problem and ambiguity in entity name designation. A clearer explanation of how the contextual information association graph model contributes to resolving these issues would be beneficial.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a description of contextual information and ambiguity in Section 3.2. We explain specifically how contextual information solves the "one-to-many" mapping problem and the ambiguity of entity name designation.</p><p>In traditional blockchain enterprise business activities information, there may be a situation where one entity has similarity with multiple different entities, which is called a "one to many" mapping problem. By introducing contextual information, a contextual information association graph model can be established to more accurately capture the relationships between entities.</p><p> Source Credibility Model. The credibility characterization of information sources in Section 3.4 requires more explanation, particularly regarding the calculation of the click-through rate and how it directly correlates with credibility. Please provide more insights into how this model aligns with established credibility standards.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a description related to the information source credibility model in section 3.4, explaining the process of calculating the click-through rate and how it relates to credibility. We also explain the way in which the model is aligned with existing credibility standards. The details are presented below.</p><p>The click through rate is considered an important basis for measuring the credibility of information sources. Firstly, the click through rate reflects the level of interest and recognition of users towards the content of the information source. Users are more likely to click on information they consider useful, authentic, and trustworthy. Therefore, information sources with high click through rates often imply user trust in the source, thus becoming one of the indicators for evaluating credibility. Secondly, click through rate is a direct feedback of user behavior. The behavior of users clicking on a certain information source indicates that they are interested in the content of that source and believe that the content is valuable to them. This positive user behavior feedback is seen as an affirmation of the credibility of the information source.</p><p> Comment-Based Information Credibility. The methodology for comment-based information credibility characterization (Section 3.4) could be further detailed. Consider providing examples or case studies to illustrate how explicit and implicit comments are classified and contribute to the overall credibility assessment.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a related description of comment-based information credibility in Section 3.4, with example explanations that illustrate how explicit and implicit comments can be categorized and how they can contribute to the overall credibility assessment. The details are as follows.</p><p>Explicit and implicit comments have different contributions to the evaluation of information credibility based on comments. These two types of comments reveal different attitudes and perspectives of users when facing information. By comprehensively analyzing them, the credibility of information can be more comprehensively evaluated. Explicit comments usually contain clear attitudes, opinions, or feedback from users. This direct expression helps to understand the user's true view of the information, thereby providing direct clues about the credibility of the information. And Explicit comments often contain more facts, data, or specific in-formation. This clear statement makes it easier to evaluate the accuracy of information and helps confirm whether the information is based on verifiable content. Implicit comments may involve emotional vocabulary, emotional color, or suggestive language, revealing the user's emotional feedback. This is of great significance for evaluating the user experience and impact of information. Implicit comments can provide additional con-text or information for explicit comments. Sometimes users may not express themselves clearly in their words, but through the tone and emotions in implicit comments, they can gain a deeper understanding of their views. These implicit viewpoints help to gain a more comprehensive understanding of the user's overall perception of information, providing more dimensions for credibility assessment.</p><p> Content-Based Credibility Characterization. The content-based credibility characterization assumes a direct relationship between the number of feature words and professionalism/credibility. It is important to discuss potential limitations of this assumption and consider other factors that may influence credibility.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a relevant description of the content credibility characteristics in the last paragraph of Section 3.4. The details are as follows.</p><p>Some situation may affect the method like different fields may have different professional standards and vocabulary usage habits. Some fields may place more emphasis on the use of professional terminology, while others may place more emphasis on common language. Therefore, the relationship between the number of feature words and professionalism may vary between different fields. Sometimes, the number of feature words does not always reflect the depth and detail level of information. Some content may require more professional terminology and detailed explanations, which may not necessarily lead to an increase in the number of feature words. Therefore, quantity cannot fully represent the professionalism and credibility of the text. But in most cases, these issues will not have a significant impact on the conclusions of the model output, so no additional discussion is needed.</p><p> Conclusion and Implications. The conclusion should summarize the key findings and their implications. Discuss the potential limitations of the proposed method and suggest avenues for future research to strengthen the manuscript's overall impact.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have reorganized the conclusion section and added a description related to the limitations of the paper's methodology and future perspectives as follows.</p><p>This paper has conducted in-depth research on the blockchain data quality evaluation model, proposed corresponding solutions for the shortcomings of current evaluation methods, and achieved some meaningful research results. However, the application of blockchain technology involves other fields besides the financial field. For its different application scenarios, the following issues related to this study need further exploration and research:</p><p>(1) The blockchain data quality evaluation model in this paper is aimed at the business activities data in-formation of enterprises in the financial field, while other fields are also producing a lot of data information at all times. Therefore, applying the evaluation model proposed in this paper to data in other fields is the next research direction.</p><p>(2) The model proposed in this paper is based on the established blockchain, but in reality, the information in the blockchain is sometimes stored dynamically, and may be linked at any time. Therefore, when new block information is generated in the blockchain, how to evaluate its quality in real time is worth studying.</p><p>Reviewer 2: </p><p> The abstract needs refinement. Clearly articulate the role of the proposed study and highlight the actual contributions. This will provide readers with a better understanding of the paper's significance.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have refined the abstract by adding a relevant description of the problem and significance of the paper to be studied as follows.</p><p>Blockchain-based applications are becoming more and more widespread in business operations. In view of the shortcomings of existing enterprise blockchain evaluation methods, this paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality evaluation model for enterprise business activities, so as to achieve efficient evaluation of business activity information consistency, credibility and value. This paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment method for enterprise business activities, aiming at the problems that most of the data in enterprise business activities come from different data sources, information representation is inconsistent, information ambiguity between the same block chain is serious, and it is difficult to evaluate the consistency, credibility and value of information. The method firstly proposes an entity information representation method based on the Representation learning for fusing entity category information (CEKGRL) model, which introduces the triad structure of related entities in blockchain, then associates them with enterprise business activity categories, and carries out similarity calculation through contextual information to achieve blockchain information consistency assessment. After that, a trustworthiness characterization method is proposed based on information sources, information comments, and information contents, to obtain the trustworthiness assessment of the business. Finally, based on the information trustworthiness characterization, a value assessment method is introduced to assess the total value of business activity information in the blockchain, and a blockchain quality assessment model is constructed. The experimental results show that the proposed model has great advantages over existing methods in assessing inter-block consistency, intra-block activity information trustworthiness and the value of blockchain.</p><p> Expand the introduction to provide more context and background information. A more detailed introduction will better set the stage for the problem you are addressing, helping readers grasp the significance of your research.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a description in the third paragraph of the introduction of the Section 1 to illustrate some of the problems of traditional enterprise blockchain, to better introduce the background information of the problem to be researched in this paper, and to highlight the significance of the research in this paper. The details are as follows.</p><p>In the enterprise blockchain data layer, each distributed node encapsulates the business activity information received over a period of time into a data block and links it to the longest blockchain in the current blockchain network, forming a new block. At the same time, with the increasing channels for obtaining information on enterprise business activities in blockchain, the amount of data is increasing. This information may originate from different institutions and fields, and there may be certain differences in the representation of information. Its credibility and information value cannot be measured, making it difficult to determine the overall quality of blockchain.</p><p> Include a section that compares your work with previous studies and techniques. This comparison can provide additional support for the validity and novelty of your research. Highlight similarities, differences, and advancements over prior work.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a description in the last paragraph of Section 2 explaining the results achieved by building the new model as follows.</p><p>In summary, this paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain quality assessment model for enterprise business activities by addressing the shortcomings of existing blockchain enterprise business activity information assessment methods and considering the consistency, credibility and value of data [21] and improve the efficiency of blockchain consistency assessment and considered the credibility of content, while achieving good results in situations with low information uncertainty.</p><p> Suggest a more in-depth analysis of security and privacy concerns associated with multi-source blockchain data. Encourage the inclusion of case studies or practical examples to demonstrate the model's application in real business scenarios and also Propose collaborations with blockchain enterprises for real-world testing and validation of the model.</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. </p><supplementary-material id="pone.0304835.s001" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Attachment</label><caption><p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Response to Reviewers.docx</named-content></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0304835.s001.docx"/></supplementary-material></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0304835.r003" specific-use="decision-letter"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.r003</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>Asadullah</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 Asadullah Shaikh</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Asadullah Shaikh</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0304835" id="rel-obj003" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">4 Apr 2024</named-content>
</p><p><!-- <div> -->PONE-D-23-32614R1<!-- </div> --><!-- <div> -->Multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities<!-- </div> --><!-- <div> -->PLOS ONE</p><p>Dear Dr. Wang,</p><p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#x02019;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p><p>Please submit your revised manuscript by May 19 2024 11:59PM. If you will need more time than this to complete your revisions, please reply to this message or contact the journal office at&#x000a0;<email>plosone@plos.org</email>. When you're ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p><p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:<!-- </div> --><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). You should upload this letter as a separate file labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list></p><p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter. Guidelines for resubmitting your figure files are available below the reviewer comments at the end of this letter.</p><p>If applicable, we recommend that you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io to enhance the reproducibility of your results. Protocols.io assigns your protocol its own identifier (DOI) so that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link>. Additionally, PLOS ONE offers an option for publishing peer-reviewed Lab Protocol articles, which describe protocols hosted on protocols.io. Read more information on sharing protocols at <ext-link xlink:href="https://plos.org/protocols?utm_medium=editorial-email&#x00026;utm_source=authorletters&#x00026;utm_campaign=protocols" ext-link-type="uri">https://plos.org/protocols?utm_medium=editorial-email&#x00026;utm_source=authorletters&#x00026;utm_campaign=protocols</ext-link>.</p><p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p><p>Kind regards,</p><p>Asadullah Shaikh, Ph.D.</p><p>Academic Editor</p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p><p>Reviewers' comments:</p><p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p><p>
<!-- <font color="black"> -->
<bold>Comments to the Author</bold>
</p><p>1. If the authors have adequately addressed your comments raised in a previous round of review and you feel that this manuscript is now acceptable for publication, you may indicate that here to bypass the &#x0201c;Comments to the Author&#x0201d; section, enter your conflict of interest statement in the &#x0201c;Confidential to Editor&#x0201d; section, and submit your "Accept" recommendation.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;All comments have been addressed</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;(No Response)</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;(No Response)</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->2. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p><p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. <!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;Partly</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->3. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? <!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;I Don't Know</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;(No Response)</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->4. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p><p>The <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ext-link-type="uri">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#x02014;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#x02014;those must be specified.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;No</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;(No Response)</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->5. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p><p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;No</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->6. Review Comments to the Author</p><p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Dear</p><p>I wanted to inform you that the work you presented is commendable and well-crafted. The previous errors have been addressed effectively, and I find that it has added more clarity and completeness to the research. I look forward to seeing further development in this work.</p><p>Thank you very much for your efforts.</p><p>Best regards,</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;The following comments are regarding the version that is called Revision 1.</p><p>1. Language is poor, enhance the language and check the miss typos. For example, many words are separated into 2 parts, i.e. (s hortcomings) where &#x0201c;s&#x0201d; separated from &#x0201c;hortcomings&#x0201d;, and so on.</p><p>2. The introduction needs to be restructured and be more informative to guide the reader, starting with the basic concepts and fundamental definitions and then gradually going through the more related problems and terms. The basic definitions and important clarifications in the introduction should have references. Also, there is redundancy even inside the introduction.</p><p>3. While the research tends more toward the enterprise blockchain data layer rather than traditional) blockchain data layers, it is necessary to includes in the introduction an explanation about this distinction ((with references)).</p><p>4. Many sentences are long and take place over three or more lines. It is preferable to shorten the length of sentences, for example, by breaking them into 2 or more sentences.</p><p>5. The author, in introduction wrote &#x0201c;Large domestic and foreign enterprise units ..&#x0201d;, such sentence is not clear!, at first which of the mentioned example are domestic ? and domestic relating for whom?, and what is the meaning of &#x0201c;units&#x0201d; in such contexts?.</p><p>6. In the introduction the author mention that &#x0201c; &#x02026; Google, Baidu and Alibaba, have established their own enterprise federated blockchain systems&#x0201d;. But they do not provide reference for such examples! For instance, it is well known that Google's offers Blockchain-as-a-Service (BaaS) which is primarily support public blockchains, but the Authors need to provide references supports their examples about federated blockchains.</p><p>7. As a continuation of the previous note, the authors already mention (federated blockchains) without explanation, and why it is related to their work. So, the authors also prefer to insert brief definitions of Public, private, and Federated Blockchains in the introduction, making clear the differences between them.</p><p>8. In the related works, the author listed some references under works that is specifically (In blockchain information consistency evaluation), but it not!!! For example, (and not limited to), the reference number (14) is related for natural language processing and the author of (14) dose not mentions any explicitly relationship with Blockchain!!!. Without a clear connection or application area identified within the blockchain, the direct applicability is limited. ((((The authors should reanalyze all the related works again and focus on the similarities within the area of challenges to determine the feasibility of such an application)))). The author should recheck all the related works!. All of them should have direct relationship with the proposed work.</p><p>9. I could not find some cited papers in any resource in the internet !!! for example (Disambiguation method of inconsistent records based on factor graph)!!!???? Please provide the correct link, and explain this. I miss something here?!!!!.</p><p>10. In the related works, the authors cited the preprint version of a paper (the reference number 12) while this work have official published version: <ext-link xlink:href="https://aclanthology.org/N18-1071/" ext-link-type="uri">https://aclanthology.org/N18-1071/</ext-link> . The authors need to focuses on the officially published version and analysis it again.</p><p>11. Any fundamental used terms, for example (and not limited to) the triple structure, better to be well defined in the introduction or in the related works with citations</p><p>12. The third section needs to reconsider the structure of its sections. The logical connection between its sub-sections must be clearer. Perhaps there is a need for a workflow in the form of an illustration (new figure) or something similar.</p><p>13. Let sub-section 3.7 have more informative title.</p><p>14. It is necessary to provide an explanation of each data set used in the experiment, along with a reference or link to these data sets.</p><p>15. It is important to provide a clear explanation regarding the comparison with reference to the related works, , include citations.</p><p>16. In fact, I cannot agree with what is stated in the conclusion, because there is a major weakness in the study of related works.</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Comment # 1: The second contribution indicated in the introduction should be looked at and rewritten well. it's confusing which basis that statement is based on.</p><p>Comment #2 The summary of the introduction should be rewritten because it is too long and makes it difficult to get what you are communicating. some more sentences are long making reading them difficult, and they should be looked at.</p><p>Comment # 3: The literature survey must be comprehensive. Add more existing literature</p><p>comment# 4: it will be appreciated if the experimental dataset is made available on a publicly accessible repository with a correct or accessible doi. the one provided here can not be assessed.</p><p>Comment # 5: In the references section, all references must be of the same style and must be complete eg. Check reference # 21</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->7. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ext-link-type="uri">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p><p>If you choose &#x0201c;no&#x0201d;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p><p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ext-link-type="uri">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;<bold>Yes:&#x000a0;</bold>Atheer Alrammahi</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;No</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;No</p><p>**********</p><p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files.]</p><p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool,&#x000a0;<ext-link xlink:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email PLOS at&#x000a0;<email>figures@plos.org</email>. Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0304835.r004"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.r004</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 1</article-title></title-group><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0304835" id="rel-obj004" related-article-type="editor-report"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>2</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">6 May 2024</named-content>
</p><p>Responses to Reviewers&#x02019; Comments</p><p>Dear Editor and Reviewers,</p><p>Thanks for your comments concerning our manuscript entitled &#x0201c;multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities". The comments are very valuable and helpful for revising and improving our manuscript. We have carefully revised the manuscript and responded all comments below. The changes will not affect the content and framework of the paper. The revised sentences are highlighted in yellow in the manuscript.</p><p>Best regards,</p><p>Baoyan Song</p><p>Reviewer 1:</p><p>I wanted to inform you that the work you presented is commendable and well-crafted. The previous errors have been addressed effectively, and I find that it has added more clarity and completeness to the research. I look forward to seeing further development in this work.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>First of all, please allow me to express my sincerest gratitude to you. Thank you for taking the time out of your busy schedule to carefully review and evaluate my paper. </p><p>Once again, thank you for your attention and support for my paper. Your professional spirit and rigorous attitude have left a deep impression on me, and they also inspire me to continue striving for excellence in my future academic pursuits. I hope to have the opportunity to engage in more academic exchanges with you and jointly promote the development of related fields.</p><p>Finally, please continue to follow the progress of my paper. If there are any questions or further modifications needed, please feel free to let me know. I will make the necessary adjustments as soon as possible to ensure the quality and accuracy of the paper.</p><p>Thank you once again for your careful guidance and valuable opinions! Wishing you a smooth work and good health!</p><p>Reviewer 3: </p><p>1. Language is poor, enhance the language and check the miss typos. For example, many words are separated into 2 parts, i.e. (s hortcomings) where &#x0201c;s&#x0201d; separated from &#x0201c;hortcomings&#x0201d;, and so on.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have made revisions to the entire text and improved the language expression. The specific modifications are listed below.</p><p>Blockchain-based applications are becoming more and more widespread in business operations. In view of the shortcomings of existing enterprise blockchain evaluation methods, this paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality evaluation model for enterprise business activities, so as to achieve efficient evaluation of business activity information consistency, credibility and value. This paper proposes a multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment method for enterprise business activities, aiming at the problems that most of the data in enterprise business activities come from different data sources, information representation is inconsistent, information ambiguity between the same block chain is serious, and it is difficult to evaluate the consistency, credibility and value of information. The method firstly proposes an entity information representation method based on the Representation learning for fusing entity category information (CEKGRL) model, which introduces the triad structure of related entities in blockchain, then associates them with enterprise business activity categories, and carries out similarity calculation through contextual information to achieve blockchain information consistency assessment. After that, a trustworthiness characterization method is proposed based on information sources, information comments, and information contents, to obtain the trustworthiness assessment of the business. Finally, based on the information trustworthiness characterization, a value assessment method is introduced to assess the total value of business activity information in the blockchain, and a blockchain quality assessment model is constructed. The experimental results show that the proposed model has great advantages over existing methods in assessing inter-block consistency, intra-block activity information trustworthiness and the value of blockchain.</p><p>2. The introduction needs to be restructured and be more informative to guide the reader, starting with the basic concepts and fundamental definitions and then gradually going through the more related problems and terms. The basic definitions and important clarifications in the introduction should have references. Also, there is redundancy even inside the introduction.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have reorganized and revised the contents of the Introduction to make it specifically better logical and readable.</p><p>Blockchain is divided into public chain, private chain, and consortium chain based on its degree of decentralization. Public chain is completely open and transparent, not controlled by any organization, and everyone can participate; The write permission of private chains only belongs to individuals or a certain organization, with a high degree of centralization; The alliance chain, on the other hand, falls between the two and is only open to specific group organizations [8]. Participants can conduct transactions or access information, but only nodes in the alliance have the right to perform transaction verification, publish contracts, and other functions.</p><p>3. While the research tends more toward the enterprise blockchain data layer rather than traditional) blockchain data layers, it is necessary to includes in the introduction an explanation about this distinction ((with references)).</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a description in the introduction and add a reference 8. The specific modifications are listed below.</p><p>Blockchain is divided into public chain, private chain, and consortium chain based on its degree of decentralization. Public chain is completely open and transparent, not controlled by any organization, and everyone can participate; The write permission of private chains only belongs to individuals or a certain organization, with a high degree of centralization; The alliance chain, on the other hand, falls between the two and is only open to specific group organizations [8]. Participants can conduct transactions or access information, but only nodes in the alliance have the right to perform transaction verification, publish contracts, and other functions.</p><p>4. Many sentences are long and take place over three or more lines. It is preferable to shorten the length of sentences, for example, by breaking them into 2 or more sentences.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have revised the full text description by breaking down long sentences into short ones, making the paper more readable. The specific modifications are listed below.</p><p>Moreover, traditional evaluation methods do not make full use of the features of blockchain. Blockchain features include leaving traces throughout the process, being non-temper able, and traceable. Evaluation efficiency and accuracy are low with traditional methods. This results in the inability of enterprise users and relevant regulatory authorities to quickly screen out suitable blockchains. Establishing a unified analysis model becomes challenging [9].</p><p>5. The author, in introduction wrote &#x0201c;Large domestic and foreign enterprise units ..&#x0201d;, such sentence is not clear!, at first which of the mentioned example are domestic ? and domestic relating for whom?, and what is the meaning of &#x0201c;units&#x0201d; in such contexts?.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We change the description in the introduction. The specific modifications are listed below.</p><p>Many IT companies around the world, such as IBM, Baidu and Alibaba, have established their own enterprise federated blockchain systems. </p><p>6. In the introduction the author mention that &#x0201c; &#x02026; Google, Baidu and Alibaba, have established their own enterprise federated blockchain systems&#x0201d;. But they do not provide reference for such examples! For instance, it is well known that Google's offers Blockchain-as-a-Service (BaaS) which is primarily support public blockchains, but the Authors need to provide references supports their examples about federated blockchains.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have changed the description. The specific modifications are listed below.</p><p>Many IT companies around the world, such as IBM, Baidu and Alibaba, have established their own enterprise federated blockchain systems.</p><p>7. As a continuation of the previous note, the authors already mention (federated blockchains) without explanation, and why it is related to their work. So, the authors also prefer to insert brief definitions of Public, private, and Federated Blockchains in the introduction, making clear the differences between them.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have added a description in the introduction. The specific description is listed below.</p><p>Blockchain is divided into public chain, private chain, and consortium chain based on its degree of decentralization. Public chain is completely open and transparent, not controlled by any organization, and everyone can participate; The write permission of private chains only belongs to individuals or a certain organization, with a high degree of centralization; The alliance chain, on the other hand, falls between the two and is only open to specific group organizations [8]. Participants can conduct transactions or access information, but only nodes in the alliance have the right to perform transaction verification, publish contracts, and other functions.</p><p>8. In the related works, the author listed some references under works that is specifically (In blockchain information consistency evaluation), but it not!!! For example, (and not limited to), the reference number (14) is related for natural language processing and the author of (14) dose not mentions any explicitly relationship with Blockchain!!!. Without a clear connection or application area identified within the blockchain, the direct applicability is limited. ((((The authors should reanalyze all the related works again and focus on the similarities within the area of challenges to determine the feasibility of such an application)))). The author should recheck all the related works!. All of them should have direct relationship with the proposed work.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have reanalyzed all the related works again. The specific modifications are listed below.</p><p>This paper introduces a novel approach: a multi-source, heterogeneous blockchain quality assessment model tailored for enterprise business activities. It addresses the limitations of current methods by prioritizing consistency, credibility, and data value [22]. This model enhances blockchain consistency assessment efficiency while also factoring in content credibility, yielding promising results even in scenarios with high information uncertainty.</p><p>9. I could not find some cited papers in any resource in the internet !!! for example (Disambiguation method of inconsistent records based on factor graph)!!!???? Please provide the correct link, and explain this. I miss something here?!!!!.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have corrected the incorrectly cited papers. The specific modifications are listed below.</p><p>[8] Zheng Peilin, Xu Quangqing, ZHENG Zibin, et al. (2021) Meepo: Sharded consortium blockchain. 2021 IEEE 37th International Conference on Data Engineering, Chania, Greece, 1847&#x02013;1852</p><p> [12] Yi Yang, Ozan Irsoy, and Kazi Shefaet Rahman. (2018) Collective Entity Disambiguation with Structured Gradient Tree Boosting. In Proceedings of the 2018 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies, Volume 1, New Orleans, Louisiana. Association for Computational Linguistics, 777&#x02013;786.</p><p>[14] Jiang Jing, Wang Kai, Xu Yueqiang, et al. (2022) Optimal Caching Strategy of Operators Based on Consortium Blockchain [J]. Journal of Electronics &#x00026; Information Technology, 44 (9): 3043-3050.</p><p>10. In the related works, the authors cited the preprint version of a paper (the reference number 12) while this work have official published version: <ext-link xlink:href="https://aclanthology.org/N18-1071/" ext-link-type="uri">https://aclanthology.org/N18-1071/</ext-link> . The authors need to focuses on the officially published version and analysis it again.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have reanalyzed and cited reference 12.</p><p>[12] Yi Yang, Ozan Irsoy, and Kazi Shefaet Rahman. (2018) Collective Entity Disambiguation with Structured Gradient Tree Boosting. In Proceedings of the 2018 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies, Volume 1, New Orleans, Louisiana. Association for Computational Linguistics, 777&#x02013;786.</p><p>11. Any fundamental used terms, for example (and not limited to) the triple structure, better to be well defined in the introduction or in the related works with citations.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. The concept of triple structure is proposed in this article. In order to distinguish from the existing definition, this article is modified to "Triple Evaluation Structure".</p><p>The triple evaluation structure is a data model widely used for representing information, consisting of three components: subject, predicate, and object. It is extensively applied in fields such as knowledge graphs and the semantic web. The triple evaluation structure is highly flexible and can be employed to represent various types of information. Different combinations of subjects, predicates, and objects can capture rich semantic relationships, making it suitable for diverse knowledge representation. In summary, the advantages of the triple evaluation structure lie in its flexibility, clear semantic representation, scalability, and effective expression of relationships, making it a key technology in the fields of knowledge representation and the semantic web.</p><p>12. The third section needs to reconsider the structure of its sections. The logical connection between its sub-sections must be clearer. Perhaps there is a need for a workflow in the form of an illustration (new figure) or something similar.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We add a logic flowchart to show our technical roadmap.</p><p>Fig 1. The Logic flowchart of Showcase Assessment Model technical roadmap</p><p>13. Let sub-section 3.7 have more informative title.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We change the title as &#x0201c;Case analysis of enterprise alliance chain evaluation&#x0201d;.</p><p>14. It is necessary to provide an explanation of each data set used in the experiment, along with a reference or link to these data sets.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have uploaded the dataset of this paper to the figshare database and added the generated doi to the content of the experimental setup. The specific modifications are as follows.</p><p>The experimental dataset consists of two parts, which are official data searched and crawled on the search engine with the subject term of business activities and real data of enterprises, totaling about 210,000 items, and then simple data cleaning is performed by filling in missing values, smoothing or removing outlier points and other operations to get about 200,000 items of data, and the details of the dataset are listed in Table 2. The datasets are available from <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.25143503.v1" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.25143503.v1</ext-link>.</p><p>15. It is important to provide a clear explanation regarding the comparison with reference to the related works, include citations.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have improved the literature and analysis of the relevant work, supplemented the latest technologies and methods, analyzed the advantages and disadvantages, added citations throughout the text, and compared them with the methods proposed in this paper in experiments.</p><p>This section compares the running efficiency of each model, the horizontal coordinate represents the entity data set in the blockchain, in units of ten thousand, the vertical coordinate indicates the time required to run each model, and the experimental results are shown in Fig 8.</p><p>16. In fact, I cannot agree with what is stated in the conclusion, because there is a major weakness in the study of related works.</p><p>Response&#x0ff1a;</p><p>Thanks for the reviewer 's advice. We have improved the literature an</p><supplementary-material id="pone.0304835.s002" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Attachment</label><caption><p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Response to Reviewers-v3.docx</named-content></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0304835.s002.docx"/></supplementary-material></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0304835.r005" specific-use="decision-letter"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.r005</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 2</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>Asadullah</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 Asadullah Shaikh</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Asadullah Shaikh</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0304835" id="rel-obj005" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>2</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">21 May 2024</named-content>
</p><p>Multi-source heterogeneous blockchain data quality assessment model for enterprise business activities</p><p>PONE-D-23-32614R2</p><p>Dear Dr. Wang,</p><p>We&#x02019;re pleased to inform you that your manuscript has been judged scientifically suitable for publication and will be formally accepted for publication once it meets all outstanding technical requirements.</p><p>Within one week, you&#x02019;ll receive an e-mail detailing the required amendments. When these have been addressed, you&#x02019;ll receive a formal acceptance letter and your manuscript will be scheduled for publication.</p><p>An invoice will be generated when your article is formally accepted. Please note, if your institution has a publishing partnership with PLOS and your article meets the relevant criteria, all or part of your publication costs will be covered. Please make sure your user information is up-to-date by logging into Editorial Manager at <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ext-link-type="uri">Editorial Manager&#x000ae;</ext-link>&#x000a0;and clicking the &#x02018;Update My Information' link at the top of the page. If you have any questions relating to publication charges, please contact our Author Billing department directly at <email>authorbilling@plos.org</email>.</p><p>If your institution or institutions have a press office, please notify them about your upcoming paper to help maximize its impact. If they&#x02019;ll be preparing press materials, please inform our press team as soon as possible -- no later than 48 hours after receiving the formal acceptance. Your manuscript will remain under strict press embargo until 2 pm Eastern Time on the date of publication. For more information, please contact <email>onepress@plos.org</email>.</p><p>Kind regards,</p><p>Asadullah Shaikh, Ph.D.</p><p>Academic Editor</p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>Additional Editor Comments (optional):</p><p>Reviewers' comments:</p><p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p><p>
<!-- <font color="black"> -->
<bold>Comments to the Author</bold>
</p><p>1. If the authors have adequately addressed your comments raised in a previous round of review and you feel that this manuscript is now acceptable for publication, you may indicate that here to bypass the &#x0201c;Comments to the Author&#x0201d; section, enter your conflict of interest statement in the &#x0201c;Confidential to Editor&#x0201d; section, and submit your "Accept" recommendation.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;All comments have been addressed</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;All comments have been addressed</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->2. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p><p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. <!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->3. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? <!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->4. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p><p>The <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ext-link-type="uri">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#x02014;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#x02014;those must be specified.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->5. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p><p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->6. Review Comments to the Author</p><p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;(No Response)</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;This manuscript is a better revision of the previously mentioned comments. It has clarity now and awaiting future improvements in this work</p><p>**********</p><p><!-- <font color="black"> -->7. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ext-link-type="uri">what does this mean?</ext-link>). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p><p>If you choose &#x0201c;no&#x0201d;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p><p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ext-link-type="uri">Privacy Policy</ext-link>.<!-- </font> --></p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;No</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;No</p><p>**********</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="pone.0304835.r006" specific-use="acceptance-letter"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304835.r006</article-id><title-group><article-title>Acceptance letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>Asadullah</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 Asadullah Shaikh</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Asadullah Shaikh</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0304835" id="rel-obj006" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">23 May 2024</named-content>
</p><p>PONE-D-23-32614R2 </p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>Dear Dr. Wang, </p><p>I'm pleased to inform you that your manuscript has been deemed suitable for publication in PLOS ONE. Congratulations! Your manuscript is now being handed over to our production team.</p><p>At this stage, our production department will prepare your paper for publication. This includes ensuring the following:</p><p>* All references, tables, and figures are properly cited</p><p>* All relevant supporting information is included in the manuscript submission,</p><p>* There are no issues that prevent the paper from being properly typeset</p><p>If revisions are needed, the production department will contact you directly to resolve them. If no revisions are needed, you will receive an email when the publication date has been set. At this time, we do not offer pre-publication proofs to authors during production of the accepted work. Please keep in mind that we are working through a large volume of accepted articles, so please give us a few weeks to review your paper and let you know the next and final steps. </p><p>Lastly, if your institution or institutions have a press office, please let them know about your upcoming paper now to help maximize its impact. If they'll be preparing press materials, please inform our press team within the next 48 hours. Your manuscript will remain under strict press embargo until 2 pm Eastern Time on the date of publication. For more information, please contact <email>onepress@plos.org</email>.</p><p>If we can help with anything else, please email us at <email>customercare@plos.org</email>.</p><p>Thank you for submitting your work to PLOS ONE and supporting open access. </p><p>Kind regards, </p><p>PLOS ONE Editorial Office Staff</p><p>on behalf of</p><p>Prof. Asadullah Shaikh </p><p>Academic Editor</p><p>PLOS ONE</p></body></sub-article></article>