<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par5">Although the number of tools to support CRA has rapidly increased in the last few years, these tools have been found to suffer from major limitations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. CRA requires not only knowledge of the climate change hazards across multiple space and timescales (e.g., likelihood of changes to extreme rain over North America over the next decade), knowledge of the exposures (e.g., location of assets and value chains), and knowledge of the vulnerabilities (e.g., response of communities to drought or response of supply chain to changes in carbon taxes). Crucially, appropriate CRA also requires the ability to integrate all these heterogeneous sources of information&#8212;and their associated and unavoidable uncertainties&#8212;to evaluate the effectiveness of possible interventions, helping to communicate risk and prioritise investments. From this perspective of integration, we have identified three key constraints on the effectiveness of the current CRAs:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par6"><bold><italic>Scope</italic></bold> &#8211; today&#8217;s CRAs evaluate risks in isolation and do not fully consider compounding or systemic risks.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par7"><bold><italic>Data</italic></bold> &#8211; today&#8217;s CRAs typically use either top&#8211;down data that provide global coverage but are not locally robust, or bottom-up data that provide detailed local information but cannot be scaled globally.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par8"><bold><italic>Transparency</italic></bold> &#8211; today&#8217;s lack of commonly accepted methods and principles and the extensive use of &#8216;black-box&#8217; approaches to CRA limits trust and the ability to improve, compare and combine the results of different assessments.</p></list-item></list></p>