<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par64">We have to be very careful when asking what exactly follows for the Moral Equivalence Thesis. The capability approach to justice can be designed in many different forms, which will have implications for whether Pearl would have to share her own individual greenhouse gas emissions budget with a possible third child (perhaps even with her second child). A capability theory of the fair allocation of individuals&#8217; emissions budgets could defend the view that everyone should be given an individual emissions budget that is needed to meet the basic capabilities; if the total of those individual emissions budgets is smaller than the aggregate emissions budget, the remaining budget could be divided up into a so-called luxury budget per capita. At that point, procreative decisions would be regarded as equivalent to decisions about overconsumption. This would be justified, since the valuable capability to engage in procreative parenting would be met up to a sufficiency level. However, depending on the remaining aggregate global emissions budget, it could also be the case that there won&#8217;t be any per capita luxury emissions budget to be divided up. In that case, each person would be allowed an emissions budget to meet their basic consumption needs and an emissions budget for one or two children per couple. There are climate change scenarios conceivable in which even the second child per couple would be violating principles of ecological sustainability and intergenerational justice. Under those scenarios, fair divisions may not give us more than the emissions budgets for meeting our basic consumption needs and at most for those of one child per couple, which would also require us to rethink social institutions of child-rearing in such a way that all adults can enjoy the goods of parenting and the needs of children are met.</p>