<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par7">Attributing loss and damage to climate change, that is, being able to state the extent to which human induced climate change increases the probability of an event or outcome, is a relatively new and evolving literature. Allen<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> was one of the first articles to explore the extent to which it is possible to attribute outcomes to climate change through its impact on weather. Since then, the number of attribution studies that quantify links between climate change and health has grown, driven in the main by climatologists, who use established formal detection and attribution methods to determine the extent to which climate change is affecting health<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. These &#8220;D and A&#8221; methods are based on statistical and process-based approaches to determining a causal link between a hazard linked to climate, and a negative health outcome. For example<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, focus on the links between heat extremes and mortality. They take temperature data for Stockholm, Sweden, defining extreme heat and cold event thresholds, and calculate the number of such extreme events in 1900-1929 and 1980-2009. Then, combining the long-term temperature data set with recent health data, the authors are able to attribute recent deaths from extremes of temperature to observed climate change, controlling for various confounders such as age and urbanisation. More recently, Vicedo and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> use mortality and weather data from 732 locations in 43 countries during 1991&#8211;2018 to attribute 37% of warm-season heat-related deaths to anthropogenic climate change. Mitchell and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> focus on the heatwave of 2003 and estimate that anthropogenic climate change increased the risk of heat-related mortality in Central Paris by 70% and by 20% in London.</p>