<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0060">Climate change experts consider climatic or natural disasters as a direct push-factor for MR (<xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Dun, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Alexander et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed and McEvoy, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Bowman and Henquinet, 2015</xref>). However, migration scholars argue that climatic events such as floods, rainfall variability, droughts, or other hazards are not the cause of migration; rather, it is their immediate and midterm effects that trigger mobility, mostly, crop loss, rising unemployment, food price hikes, and poverty (<xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Afifi, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">Gray and Mueller, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Black et al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0460" ref-type="bibr">Martin, 2013</xref>). <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Black et al. (2011)</xref> find that structural conditions and individual characteristics dynamically interact to influence CM decisions. For example, non-farming poor families might not be as sensitive to rainfall variability as farmers, but they may migrate due to food insecurity, especially when their coping strategies are stretched thin and official interventions for in situ adaptation are unavailable (<xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">de Brauw et al., 2014</xref>). Furthermore, <xref rid="b0475" ref-type="bibr">McLeman et al. (2016)</xref> find that migration associated with hazards such as flooding or crop failure are mostly seasonal or temporary, occur over short distances, and focus on reducing vulnerability, with residents returning to the flood-affected zones after the event. In contrast, MR is an anticipatory or reactionary response to a specific or combination of hazards (e.g. flood, wildfire or SLR). It is can be applied at a range of spatial and temporal scales (<xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">Hanna et al., 2019</xref>), may be voluntary or involuntary (<xref rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr">Mach et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Farbotko and McMichael, 2019</xref>), and may increase or undermine community resilience (<xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">Huang, 2018</xref>). Unlike CM, MR programs often discourage affected persons from returning to risk-prone areas (<xref rid="b0440" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Carr and Marter-Kenyon, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0465" ref-type="bibr">McAdam and Ferris, 2015</xref>). We argue that both MR and CM reveal human vulnerabilities to climate change; while MR establishes a monocausal and more direct link, CM suggests a more complex relationship is at play (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Black et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Black et al., 2013</xref>).</p>