<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The study area covers 12 states in the western and central US (Figure&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We accessed the human mobility patterns to the parks from the SafeGraph data set (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.safegraph.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.safegraph.com/</ext-link>). This data set provided an aggregated and anonymized foot traffic patterns at over 4.5 million businesses and consumer point&#8208;of&#8208;interest (POI) across the US based on mobile phone records. Here, we collected the monthly aggregated human mobility patterns to parks from SafeGraph in June&#8211;September 2020. The six&#8208;digit North American Industry Classification System (NAICS) codes &#8220;712130&#8221; and &#8220;712190&#8221; (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.naics.com/search/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.naics.com/search/</ext-link>) which identify as park POIs were used to filter for the park&#8208;related location from the SafeGraph Data set. A total of 42,211 park&#8208;related POI locations were selected based on the study area. To investigate the people's mobility pattern to parks, we use three metrics that attached to the park&#8208;related location to describe human mobility and usage of public parks, including (a) the number of visits to POIs, (b) median distance to park traveled by visitors, and (b) median minimum dwell time that people spent at POIs. Due to the increasing concern and interests in human movements and social behaviors during the pandemic, those three metrics from SafeGraph have been increasingly used to describe human mobility patterns recently, including the stay&#8208;at&#8208;home behaviors and daily activities to restaurants/bars, groceries, healthcare facilities, and parks (e.g., Atkinson et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Jiao et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Juh&#225;sz &amp; Hochmair,&#160;<xref rid="gh2287-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). We aggregated the park&#8208;related POIs with those three metrics to the county level into each month of June &#8208;September using SpatialJoin Tools ArcGIS 10.8 (ESRI Inc.). We standardized the number of visits to parks in each county into the unit of number of visits per capita.</p>