<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In 2021, Kieft and Bendell published a broad review of psychological literature on crises faced by individuals (e.g. natural disasters, financial crises, terminal illness, terrorism, pandemics, house&#8208;fires) to investigate the impact crisis has on mental health and protective measures that can support good mental health through these experiences.<xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref> Despite the variety of scenarios investigated, three themes were consistently identified, which provide a framework for supporting mental health through crises. Firstly, supporting emotional engagement of crisis events allowed individuals to process their experiences, leading to post&#8208;traumatic growth and capacity to support others through similar experiences. When emotion&#8208;focused coping was not utilised, individuals were more likely to develop PTSD and depression. It was noted that children and adolescents were particularly vulnerable to refraining from expressing their emotional experiences to their parents/guardians, to protect loved ones from their own pain. This was different to avoidance &#8211; young people were aware of their own emotional experiences but were emotionally isolated. Secondly, mental health could not be solely supported by families and individuals, and a systemic approach from grassroots through to legislation was required. When systemic aspects were overlooked (e.g. adequate mental health policy), the global burden of disease due to mental health increased. Thirdly, transparent and comprehensive communication regarding the crisis was paramount for how individuals navigated the crisis. When communication clearly explained what was to be expected and scaffolded responses prior to the event, disaster&#8208;related losses reduced by a half. When communication from governing bodies was not available, individuals sought information from their neighbours.</p>