<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In 2015, our Australasian colleagues<sup><xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> proposed the &#8216;CARM&#8217; approach &#8211; to collaborate, advocate, research (and educate) and mitigate &#8211; as a framework for psychiatrists to join with a growing number of medical entities to act on climate change. We have proposed our recommendations within this same framework (<xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box1">Box 1</xref>), and with the emphasis that interventions need to be &#8216;coordinated and rooted in active hope&#8217; to tackle the problem in a holistic and effective way.<sup><xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Alongside growing recognition that we should practice psychiatry more sustainably,<sup><xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> we should acknowledge it as our professional and ethical responsibility to address the environmental, social and economic determinants of mental illness.<sup><xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>
<boxed-text id="box1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Box 1</label><caption><p>Framework for psychiatrists to act on climate change (adapted from the &#8216;CARM&#8217; approach<sup><xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>).</p></caption><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Collaborate
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Work with disadvantaged communities so that their voices and priorities are better heard, and help them influence policy decisions</p></list-item><list-item><p>Build on existing multidisciplinary work across specialties, and with patients and the public, to drive meaningful change on key issues relevant to climate and mental health</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>Advocate
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>For patients and communities&#8217; mental health and well-being</p></list-item><list-item><p>For actions that strengthen local community resilience and tackle global injustice</p></list-item><list-item><p>For policies and funding for appropriate and evidence-based interventions to support and protect mental health following climate-related extreme events</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>Research (and educate)
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>To improve understanding of mental health in relation to the causes of inequalities, climate vulnerability and resilience</p></list-item><list-item><p>Continue to build the evidence base for action, including through participatory and action research methods, and using mixed methods and systems approaches that recognise the interconnectedness and complexity of these subjects</p></list-item><list-item><p>Advocate for increased funding for research to improve understanding of how both structural inequalities and climate change affect mental health, including when they intersect and how we can address them in tandem</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>Mitigate
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Prioritise primary prevention for mental health across the life course</p></list-item><list-item><p>Strengthen mental health systems and links between healthcare services and local communities</p></list-item><list-item><p>Improve equity of access to quality care</p></list-item><list-item><p>Act within local services to reduce carbon and improve mental healthcare</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list></p></boxed-text></p>