<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Indigenous women, alongside ethnic Bengali women, have a long history of active militancy and passive resistance in Bangladesh. Alam (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) recounts how Santal and low-income ethnic Bengali women defied armed government troops during a demonstration against proposed mining activities in Phubari on 26 August 2006. Male demonstrators fled but women chased armed troops with choppers and brooms and blocked entrances to the village. The next day women organised a large demonstration at Phulbari municipality. The image of Santal and ethnic Bengali women working together to fight for the survival of their community drew the attention of the nation to the struggle. A national leader explained, &#8220;usually [women] do not participate in regular meetings but whenever there is an emergency they never hesitate because they have stronger feelings than men for livelihood, house, children and other kin relations&#8221; (Alam <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, 42&#8211;43). Women also resisted by refusing to provide information on households to mining company members and chasing them away (Alam <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Santal women were part of earlier struggles such as the Tebhaga movement of indigenous sharecroppers, particularly in northern Bangladesh (our study location) to reduce the share given to powerful landowners from one-half to one-third (Hashmi 1994, as cited in Alam <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Indigenous and ethnic Bengali women were active militants and fought alongside men in the Bangladesh Liberation War of 1971 (Harrington <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Harrington argues that male-dominated narratives of this war still find it too difficult to assimilate the transgressive nature of women guerrilla fighters, preferring to cast them as war heroines (<italic>birangona</italic>), defined as women who were sexually victimised as a consequence of the struggle, rather than as active fighters.</p>