<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par12">The RFC framework and the burning embers diagram were first introduced in the IPCC Third Assessment Report (TAR) in 2001 (see Fig.<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Their development was indeed meant to inform discussions about at what level of global temperature climate change might be considered dangerous (see Mahony and Hulme <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2012</xref>; Mahony <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2015</xref>). The RFC framework is to aggregate the global risks of climate change into five categories and evaluate the risk level of each category according to global temperature change (O&#8217;Neill et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2017</xref>). A different level of risk is then indicated by the colour scale of the burning embers, shifting gradually from white (undetectable) to yellow (moderate), red (high) and purple (very high). The burning embers diagram is arguably one of the most iconic figures of IPCC reports, which has been widely used to communicate the risk of anthropogenic climate change.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The burning embers diagram for five reasons for concern in the IPCC&#8217;s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2001</xref> Third Assessment Report (TAR) (Source: IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2001</xref>). While the original version of the burning embers appeared in greyscale in Chapter 19 of the Working Group (WG) II TAR, the first coloured edition was published in the WGII TAR Summary for Policy Makers (SPM). It is worth noting that the original figure in the TAR only showed temperature change relative to 1990 levels. It was during the approval of the Fifth Assessment Report (AR5) SPM that the updated version added a &#8216;second thermometer&#8217; to illustrate temperature change since pre-industrial times (Tschakert <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2015</xref>). Since the Paris Agreement, the default reference period shifted from 1990 levels to pre-industrial levels.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10584_2021_3185_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>