<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para0028">The dataset presented here brings two data sources together: the NASA satellite imagery and the Dutch comprehensive socioeconomic dataset of the residential zone. The five dates for satellite imagery were chosen based on three criteria: as many as non-polluted cells, roughly similar time intervals, and inclusion of as many as possible images. To aggregate the satellite images at the scale of residential zones, the raster file is resampled, as some of the rasters were located on the borders of two or more zones. Each raster is divided into 400 smaller rasters (50&#160;m&#8239;&#215;&#8239;50&#160;m), and the fine-grained raster file is used for spatial aggregation. Ultimately, the current dataset offer opportunities for experimental, explorative studies on environmental justice, climate adaptation and energy transition. Given the abundance of clean pixels, i.e. not polluted with obstacles such as clouds, of satellite imagery in the summer of 2014, the combination of the two datasets provides reliable data for studying the environmental justice of exposure to summer surface temperature for different socioeconomic groups (similar to <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>). The data could be used for setting urban cooling strategies at the most crucial location (see <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>). The dataset can further be utilised for studying the impact of urban heat islands on energy consumption (similar to <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>) and energy poverty (similar to <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>). The data could be combined with spatial data at the regional scale using principal component analysis method to set the context for the impact of summer surface temperature on energy consumption (similar to <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>). Ultimately, the dataset can be used to analyse different spatial scales (similar to <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>) and fuel consumption types (similar to <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>).</p>