<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Asia Eur J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Asia Eur J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Asia Europe Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1610-2932</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1612-1031</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8741530</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35035337</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">643</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10308-021-00643-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Understanding China&#x02019;s changing engagement in global climate governance: a struggle for identity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8471-0493</contrib-id><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Jilong</given-names></name><address><email>y.j.l.yang@vu.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12380.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1754 9227</institution-id><institution>Department of Political Science and Public Administration, </institution><institution>Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2021</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">This article offers a novel understanding of China&#x02019;s changing engagement in global climate governance over the past decade. This article argues that China has embedded the construction of its international identity, which has been transforming towards what this article conceptualizes to be a &#x02018;Yinling leading power&#x02019;, in promoting and leading global climate governance. China&#x02019;s transforming identity construction has contributed to changing its construction of climate justice and led China to proactively undertake more responsibilities, provide international public goods and promote international climate cooperation. Global climate governance has become one of China&#x02019;s prototypical discursive frames in constructing its new international identity, an important platform where China seeks to share leadership with other major powers and the climate leadership in turn constitutes China&#x02019;s new identity. However, China&#x02019;s inadequate response to international expectations and lack of self-reflection in its climate policy have influenced international recognition on its climate leadership and new identity. In general, China&#x02019;s transforming identity construction and its reconstruction of climate justice have far-reaching implications for China and Europe to cooperate and coordinate in strengthening global climate justice and promoting global climate governance.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004543</institution-id><institution>China Scholarship Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>201506040034</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Jilong</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2022</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">
<disp-quote><p id="Par3">China &#x02018;will never accept the idea that the Chinese people can only enjoy one third, one fourth or even one fifth of the rights and interests of the people of developed countries&#x02019;. China &#x02018;cannot blindly accept that protecting the climate is humanity&#x02019;s common interest&#x02019; (Yu Qingtai, China's special envoy on climate change, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2009b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">2010</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">We have acted as a responsible major power and played an important leadership role in enhancing global cooperation on climate change (Wang Yi, China&#x02019;s Foreign Minister, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2015</xref>).</p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par5">From the failure of the Copenhagen Climate Summit in 2009 to the adoption of the Paris Climate Agreement in 2015, global climate governance (GCG) has entered into a new phase with &#x02018;a decisive break from the unsuccessful Kyoto regime&#x02019; (Keohane and Oppenheimer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2016</xref>: 142). Global climate justice is an underlying issue and &#x02018;unavoidable&#x02019; part of international climate politics (Audet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>; Harris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2013</xref>; Okereke and Coventry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2016</xref>; Shue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">1992</xref>). The failures and successes of international climate negotiations on shaping the design and evolution of the climate regime have much to do with the social construction of climate justice and the idea of a fair climate deal (Audet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>). Within the process of constructing a fair global climate deal from Copenhagen to Paris, China&#x02019;s role has undergone a significant shift.</p><p id="Par6">At the Copenhagen Climate Summit in 2009, China insisted on its longstanding rigid stances of refusing to accept binding targets to reduce its greenhouse gas emissions and argued from the perspective of equity that developed countries caused the climate change problem and should take the lead in addressing climate change while developing countries have the right to development and should be exempted from binding emission reduction targets (Harris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2013</xref>). In the pre- and post-Paris era, however, China has actively engaged in considerable international cooperation to reach and implement the Paris Agreement, and at the same time has significantly increased domestic climate actions (Belis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2015</xref>). China has embraced international climate leadership (Engels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Tiberghien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par7">Given that China had persistently rejected international leadership in international affairs for decades, how can we understand China&#x02019;s changing engagement in global climate governance? Especially, China&#x02019;s embrace of international climate leadership is actually part of a much broader shift in its overall foreign policy and its positioning in global governance more generally. Over the past decade, China&#x02019;s foreign policy strategy has shifted from <italic>Tao Guang Yang Hui</italic> (keeping a low profile) to <italic>Fen Fa You Wei</italic> (striving for achievement) (Yan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2014</xref>).</p><p id="Par8">The existing scholarly work has identified a number of domestic and international factors that impact China&#x02019;s climate practices, including economic growth (Ong <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2012</xref>), energy security (Conrad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>), severe air pollution and environmental problems (Schreurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2016</xref>), international reputation and image (Belis and Schunz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2013</xref>), the &#x02018;New Normal&#x02019; of economic development (Dong <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2017</xref>; Hilton and Kerr <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2017</xref>), technological innovation and development in renewable energy (Heggelund <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2021</xref>) and the changing international negotiating context (Tiberghien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>). All these factors and their interplay have indeed contributed to China&#x02019;s changing climate practices. This article does not negate the importance of these factors in understanding China&#x02019;s presence in global climate governance. But this article will show that the qualitative change in China&#x02019;s international role as transpires from the case of global climate governance is also related to China&#x02019;s changing construction of its international identity. In international studies, constructivists stress that one cannot comprehensively understand a state&#x02019;s foreign policy behaviours without taking identity into account, and argue that identity can mediate and shape a state&#x02019;s understanding about international issues (such as global climate governance) and can shape, enable and constrain the state&#x02019;s policy behaviours (Wendt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1999</xref>). A state&#x02019;s foreign policy can be seen as its identity constructing performance (Messari <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2001</xref>: 235&#x02013;237). Many existing studies that focus on material circumstances treat China&#x02019;s changing climate practices as a mechanical act of rational adaptation to its domestic and external material circumstances, thus missing the meaning and implication of how China communicates itself to the world. In addition, the importance of China&#x02019;s presence in promoting justice in the climate governance regime is also neglected (Stalley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2013</xref>).</p><p id="Par9">Furthermore, climate justice is a &#x02018;discursive battlefield&#x02019; where states define themselves and others (Audet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>: 370). Namely, states define and justify their international identities through discursively constructing climate justice and related issues. During the early period of climate change governance, China had constructed its developing country identity and justified its rigid positions through persistently stressing historical responsibilities of developed/industrialized countries and framing developing countries as innocent and more vulnerable to climate change (Harris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2013</xref>: 298). Climate change was always framed by China as a problem that developed countries should address first and China kept a low profile in climate change governance. With China&#x02019;s transformation towards international climate leadership over the past decade, how has China constructed its international identity through discursively constructing issues of climate justice in shaping the climate regime?</p><p id="Par10">In order to address these questions, this article focuses on China&#x02019;s construction of its international identity in its climate policy discourses and practices and examines the ways in which identity and related political discourses are deployed in China&#x02019;s changing engagement in global climate governance from Copenhagen to Paris. The data mainly consist of Chinese political leadership&#x02019;s speeches and statements, China&#x02019;s high-level climate negotiators&#x02019; speeches, official documents, 1467 editorials of China&#x02019;s state-owned newspaper&#x02014;<italic>People&#x02019;s Daily</italic>, reports of third-parties such as Earth Negotiations Bulletin (ENB), secondary literatures and news reports. Additionally, 20 individual in-depth semi-structured expert interviews were conducted in 2017 and 2018. Interviewees were Chinese and the EU climate negotiators, diplomats, NGOs, scholars and experts of the United Nations Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change.</p><p id="Par11">This article finds that China has embedded the construction of its new international identity in leading global climate governance in the Paris era and beyond. This changing identity construction is both reflected in and partly constituted by the way China has come to take up its new leadership role in GCG. Climate change governance has become one of&#x000a0;China&#x02019;s prototypical discursive frames in constructing its new international identity. China has reconstructed issues of climate justice and GCG has become an important platform where China seeks to represent itself as a leading actor and share leadership with other major powers.</p><p id="Par12">This article is laid out as follows: The first section lays the theoretical basis of international identity and global climate justice. The second section presents research design. The third section investigates China&#x02019;s international identity construction from 2009 to 2019. In the fourth section, this article examines China&#x02019;s engagement in GCG on the road to Copenhagen. The fifth section analyses China&#x02019;s new identity construction through its changing engagement in GCG in the pre- and post-Paris era. Then, the sixth section discusses the implications of China&#x02019;s transformation and the last section concludes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Identity construction and global climate justice</title><p id="Par13">Constructivists in IR stress that identity tells a state who it is, defines the social relationships between the state and others, and offers relatively stable understandings of each state&#x02019;s motives, probable actions and roles in given situation (Hopf <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1998</xref>; Wendt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1999</xref>). Identity is not pre-given but socially constructed and always in a process of constructing and reconstructing (Wendt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1999</xref>). In this study, a state&#x02019;s foreign policy discourses and practices are regarded as a process of constructing its international identity (Messari <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2001</xref>; Wendt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1999</xref>). Identity is sustained by social interactions and a state has to seek recognitions from others so that its identity can be secured and it can maintain a relatively stable sense of Self (Wendt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1999</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">In international climate politics, climate justice is a &#x02018;discursive battlefield&#x02019; where states define themselves and others (Audet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>: 370). While the concept of climate justice does not exclusively look at states, the main discourses surrounding climate justice in international climate negotiations are rooted in a fundamental truth that developed countries have historically caused the climate change problem, the consequences of climate change on different countries and regions are uneven, and the ability of rich and poor countries to bear the cost of addressing climate change is immensely different (Audet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>; Harris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2013</xref>; Okereke and Coventry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2016</xref>). Despite a wide range of definitions and typologies of global climate justice, questions of fairness and equity in addressing climate change have dominated international climate negotiations for decades. But the perceptions of what constitutes a fair/just way to deal with climate change are often quite different between for instance the EU/the North and developing countries (Okereke and Coventry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2016</xref>; von Lucke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2021</xref>). Contestations for fairness and equity are also entangled with other factors such as economic interests and climate science (Okereke and Coventry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2016</xref>). Shaping the design and evolution of the climate governance regime is largely about addressing the issues regarding &#x02018;what to do, who should do it and how, and who would pay for it&#x02019; (Dimitrov <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2010</xref>: 800). States socially construct global climate justice through debating what global climate justice entails and how it can be achieved in solving these key issues. Within this social construction process of global climate justice, states communicate themselves to each other and define their identities.</p><p id="Par15">Climate justice concerns are reflected in the principles and provisions of the distinction between annex I and non-annex I countries incorporated in the established climate regime&#x02014;the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) and its Kyoto Protocol. Key elements such as the equity principle of common but differentiated responsibility (CBDR) between developed and developing countries, the notion of historic and per capita emissions, and the North-South technology and financial transfers constitute the cornerstones of the justice dimension of the climate regime (Okereke and Coventry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2016</xref>). Issues of climate justice remain crucial in shaping a fair climate regime deal for the post-Kyoto period in light of the changing emissions landscapes and national circumstances.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Research design</title><p id="Par16">In order to examine China&#x02019;s changing engagement in GCG through the lens of identity, this article will firstly examine the changes of China&#x02019;s overall construction of its international identity&#x02014;who China is in the international community. This is mainly done through a content analysis that provides both qualitative assessment of the Chinese leadership&#x02019;s view (how China is referred to and which characteristics are ascribed to it discursively) and quantitative measure (frequency of appearance in China&#x02019;s official narratives), given that the Chinese leadership within China&#x02019;s domestic political system holds the monopoly on defining China&#x02019;s international identity. This article will use those key Chinese-coined concepts offered and used by China&#x02019;s leaders in describing China&#x02019;s international presence as key terms to search in the two types of editorials of <italic>People&#x02019;s Daily</italic>&#x02014;the largest and most influential state-owned newspaper in China and then count their frequency. The two editorials named as <italic>Zhongsheng</italic> and <italic>Guojiping</italic> are the main editorials that <italic>People&#x02019;s Daily</italic> comments on China&#x02019;s foreign policy and international affairs. From 2009 to 2019, it issued 1413 <italic>Zhongsheng</italic> articles and 54 <italic>Guojiping</italic> articles.</p><p id="Par17">After characterising China&#x02019;s overall construction of its international identity, this article will examine China&#x02019;s changing engagement in shaping the post-Kyoto regime in two main dimensions. Firstly, China&#x02019;s discursive construction. In China&#x02019;s climate narratives, how China is referred to and what kind of characteristics are ascribed to China discursively, and how China frames climate change governance and issues of climate justice in particular. By focusing on these discursive aspects, this article will specifically examine speeches of China&#x02019;s leadership and climate negotiators, official policy documents, state-owned newspapers and interview data. Secondly, China&#x02019;s policy practice. By focusing on China&#x02019;s domestic and international climate policy behaviours and its climate diplomacy within international climate negotiations, this article will investigate how China&#x02019;s role in climate governance has changed, how China interacts with other actors and how the significance of climate change governance in China&#x02019;s global presence has changed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>China&#x02019;s transforming construction of international identity</title><p id="Par18">China has represented itself as a major developing country for decades. When China went into the first decade of 2000s, China&#x02019;s then President Hu Jintao (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2011</xref>) still firmly insisted to represent China as a &#x02018;major developing country&#x02019; with &#x02018;poor&#x02019; and &#x02018;underdeveloped&#x02019; material capability and mainly positioned China as a &#x02018;participant&#x02019; in international affairs. Hu&#x02019;s administration persistently opposed any suggestions for revising China&#x02019;s developing country identity and rejected the idea of &#x02018;G2&#x02019; that the USA and China co-lead the world (Brzezinski <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2009</xref>). In line with this developing country identity, China kept a low profile in international affairs (Men H&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2014</xref>; Pu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>).</p><p id="Par19">However, with China&#x02019;s rapid rise, domestic and international expectations for a greater global presence of China have greatly increased, and at the same time doubts towards China&#x02019;s developing country identity have significantly arisen (Pu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>; Shambaugh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2011</xref>). China&#x02019;s increasing material strength, unwillingness to take up more international responsibilities and assertive behaviours in its territorial disputes generated confusions, concerns and even fears to its Asian neighbours about its role in the region order as well as in the international order (Mearsheimer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2010</xref>; Yan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2014</xref>). With accession to power in 2012/2013, Xi Jinping attempted to offer a new definition of China&#x02019;s international identity. While the &#x02018;old&#x02019; discourses of developing country identity still have traction domestically (Pu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>), China&#x02019;s self-ascribed international identity has been frequently conveyed in a very new Chinese term&#x02014;&#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; (a leading state) which had seldom appeared in China&#x02019;s national narratives regarding its international presence in the past. Xi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2016a</xref>) repeatedly stressed that China should be a global &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; rather than just be a &#x02018;follower&#x02019; or &#x02018;bystander&#x02019; in &#x02018;defining international rules&#x02019; and &#x02018;reforming the global governance system&#x02019;. But interestingly, Xi did not use another more common Chinese term&#x02014;&#x02018;<italic>lingdao</italic>&#x02019; which has very similar meanings of the English word&#x02014;leader. In Chinese, the nuance between the term &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; and &#x02018;<italic>lingdao</italic>&#x02019; is that the latter highlights the hierarchy structure between a leader and followers while the former not. Moreover, &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; contains the meanings and connotations of pioneer, vanguard and leading actor, and the status that a &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; holds is not exclusive whereas with &#x02018;<italic>lingdao</italic>&#x02019;, it is exclusive. As a global <italic>yinlingzhe</italic>, emphasized by Xi, China will &#x02018;proactively undertake more international responsibilities&#x02019; (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2013</xref>), continue to support multilateralism and international multilateral institutions (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2015b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2016b</xref>), and cooperate with others in a way of &#x02018;extensive consultation, joint contribution and shared benefits&#x02019; (<italic>gongshang</italic>, <italic>gongjian</italic>, <italic>gongxiang</italic>) in order to establish a regional and global &#x02018;community of common destiny for mankind&#x02019; (<italic>renlei mingyun gongtongti</italic>) (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2017a, b</xref>)&#x02014;China&#x02019;s conception of international society. In Xi&#x02019;s vision, furthermore, a global <italic>yinlingzhe</italic> is very different from a hegemony because China aims to &#x02018;co-define international rules&#x02019; and &#x02018;co-govern global affairs&#x02019; with other international players and will &#x02018;never seek hegemony&#x02019; (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2017a</xref>). Xi actually discursively constructed China as a global leading actor who pursues a shared leadership. While some critics may just treat these discursive representations as China&#x02019;s propaganda, these official discourses do show how China communicates itself to the world and entail China&#x02019;s understanding about the relationship between itself and the existing international order.</p><p id="Par20">At the same time, the term <italic>yinlingzhe</italic> has also become a buzz word in China&#x02019;s official narratives. In September 2019, for instance, China issued a white paper <italic>China and the World in the New Era</italic> and framed itself as a <italic>yinlingzhe</italic> in &#x02018;reforming and developing the global governance system&#x02019; (State Council <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2019</xref>). Since Xi&#x02019;s rise to power in 2012/2013, as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, the term &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>/<italic>yinling</italic>&#x02019; (noun/verb) has been used much more frequently in <italic>Peoples&#x02019; Daily</italic>&#x02019;s editorials (<italic>Zhongsheng</italic> and <italic>Guojiping</italic>). The decrease in 2019 could be the side-result of the increasingly worsening US-China trade war which took up the most attention of the two editorials.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Term frequency of &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>/<italic>yinling</italic>&#x02019; (2009&#x02013;2019)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10308_2021_643_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">Chinese IR scholars contributed to the further explication and construction of the <italic>yinlingzhe</italic> concept: (1) China seeks to be a global leading power rather than a regional or global hegemony (Pang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2018</xref>); (2) shouldering international responsibility and offering international public goods (Men <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2017</xref>); (3) binding and constraining itself in international multilateral institutions (Pang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2018</xref>); (4) pursuing an open, stable and institutions-based global order (Chen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2017</xref>).</p><p id="Par22">To sum up, Chinese leaders and academics deliberately differentiated China from traditional hegemonies and superpowers and discursively constructed China as a new type of global leading power which exercises a shared leadership. Different from the pure self-centred and unilateral leadership, China&#x02019;s conceptions of a shared leadership particularly emphasize that international actors co-define international rules and co-govern global affairs through consensus-making, jointly promote the reform of the multilateral order of global governance and build a community of common destiny for mankind. Additionally, China&#x02019;s <italic>yinlingzhe</italic> style, which is partially in line with Robyn Eckersley&#x02019;s account of leadership, approaches leadership as a form of social interaction whereby leading states guide, attract or negotiate &#x02018;the consent or acquiescence of other parties&#x02019;, &#x02018;enable or facilitate collective action towards the achievement of a common purpose in a given community&#x02019; (Eckersley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>: 1184). In this article, I coin this new <italic>yinlingzhe</italic> representation as a new Yinling Leading Power identity. It should be noted that this Yinling Leading Power identity is an ideal-type. From a constructivist perspective, the ultimate result of this new identity construction heavily relies on the recognition of other international actors.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>The road to Copenhagen</title><p id="Par23">From 2005 onward, the international community debated on whether adopting a new single and comprehensive global agreement that addresses both developed and developing countries&#x02019; emissions when the Kyoto Protocol&#x02019;s first commitment period expired in 2012 or extending the Protocol with a second commitment period. A political deadline for reaching a solution was set in December 2009&#x02014;the Copenhagen Climate Summit. With its booming greenhouse gas emissions, China was &#x02018;pushed to the forefront&#x02019; in international climate politics (Men J&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2014</xref>: 54). The following sections will examine how China constructed and maintained its developing country identity on the road to Copenhagen.</p><sec id="Sec6"><title>Discursive construction</title><p id="Par24">From the onset of the &#x02018;Reform and Opening-up&#x02019; policy in the 1980s, integrating itself into the international community was a priority of China&#x02019;s foreign policy. After the Tiananmen incident in 1989, however, China&#x02019;s relations with Western countries sharply deteriorated. At that time, international climate negotiations under the UN were high profile international negotiations (Kobayashi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2003</xref>). Through joining the UNFCCC and showing its respect of international (environmental) norms, China alleviated the diplomatic tensions with the Western world (Conrad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">Nevertheless, from the very beginning, China approached climate change through climate equity, constructed climate change as a North-South issue and connected to global historical inequality, regarded international climate negotiations as a North-South struggle, and discursively differentiated the South from the North in negotiations (Conrad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>; Harris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2013</xref>). Since the 1990s, China&#x02019;s top leaders like the then Premier Li Peng (1992) and Wen Jiabao (2007) persistently represented China as a part of the developing world and stressed that the developing South was a &#x02018;poor&#x02019; and &#x02018;innocent victim&#x02019; of climate change and vulnerable to its adverse impacts while the North has the main historical responsibility to the climate change problem. Furthermore, besides stressing the equity principle through highlighting its own lower per capita emissions (Wen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2007</xref>), China framed the North&#x02019;s emissions as &#x02018;luxury emissions&#x02019; while recognising the emissions of the South as &#x02018;survival/development emissions&#x02019; (ENB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1997</xref>: 9; Wen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2007</xref>). This argument is compatible with Henry Shue&#x02019;s conceptions of climate justice regarding emissions (Shue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">1993</xref>). China repeatedly stressed that economic development and poverty eradication were &#x02018;top priorities&#x02019; of developing countries and the international efforts to fight climate change &#x02018;should promote, not block, the economic development and poverty eradication&#x02019; (Li <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1992</xref>; Wen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2007</xref>). Shouldering climate responsibility was actually seen by China and other developing countries as a heavy burden that would impact their economic development (Ong <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2012</xref>). China continued to keep and promote the CBDR principle at the forefront of international climate debates (Stalley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2013</xref>). China&#x02019;s discursive constructions of climate change were widely shared by developing countries (Stalley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2013</xref>). In particular, the G77&#x02014;a broad coalition of developing nations including many Asian countries&#x02014;stood with China, supported those constructions and regarded China as the leader of the G77/China group (Kasa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2008</xref>). China defended the shared developing country identity of the developing world and maintained climate change as a marginal issue on its agenda.</p><p id="Par26">On the road to Copenhagen, China attempted to maintain its developing country identity and defend its rigid positions through highlighting its construction of issues of climate justice. Before the Copenhagen Summit, for example, China&#x02019;s Special Envoy for climate change&#x02014;Yu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">2009a</xref>) emphasized that &#x02018;no matter China or Bahamas, as the developing countries, we are both victims&#x02019; and it is unfair to require developing countries to &#x02018;undertake similar obligations with those of developed countries&#x02019;. Yu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2009b</xref>) also argued that China &#x02018;will never accept the idea that the Chinese people should only enjoy one third, one fourth or even one fifth of the rights and interests of the people of developed countries&#x02019;. At the Summit, China&#x02019;s Premier Wen Jiabao stated:<disp-quote><p id="Par27">Developing countries only started industrialization a few decades ago and many of their people still live in abject poverty today. It is totally unjustified to ask them to undertake emission reduction targets beyond their due obligations and capabilities in disregard of historical responsibilities, per capita emissions and different levels of development. Developed countries, which are already leading an affluent life, still maintain a level of per capita emissions that is far higher than that of developing countries, and most of their emissions are attributed to consumption. In comparison, emissions from developing countries are primarily survival emissions and international transfer emissions (Wen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2009</xref>).</p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par28">The former European chief climate negotiator&#x02014;Bert Metz&#x02014;mentioned that China&#x02019;s climate negotiators had even claimed that &#x02018;China will always remain a developing country, and don&#x02019;t expect us ever to be one Annex I country&#x02019; (Interview 2018). The North-South divide remained as the core of China&#x02019;s understanding and construction of climate change. At the same time, China firmly rejected to represent itself as an international climate leader (Conrad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>). In Copenhagen, China&#x02019;s then Vice Foreign Minister He Yafei (2009) stressed that the so-called China-US co-leadership in climate governance has &#x02018;no legal basis&#x02019; and &#x02018;is far from the truth&#x02019; in reality.</p><p id="Par29">However, China&#x02019;s rapid development and booming carbon emissions changed many countries&#x02019; perceptions of China and China&#x02019;s developing country identity construction suffered challenges from both the North and South in Copenhagen (Conrad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>). The EU differentiated China from other &#x02018;ordinary&#x02019; developing countries and defined China as an &#x02018;economically more advanced developing country&#x02019; that should undertake more international responsibilities (European Commission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2009</xref>). Moreover, many G77 members, including Asian countries, and several major developing countries such as Mexico and Argentina also shared this perception and requested China and other major emitters to bear more international responsibilities (Kastner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2018</xref>; Stalley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Policy practice</title><p id="Par30">Since the 1990s, China has allied itself with the G77 which includes many Asian countries in international climate negotiations and operated the G77/China coalition as a coordinating body for developing countries to form common stances (Kasa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2008</xref>). At the Copenhagen Summit, however, the developing world split. For instance, many countries from the AOSIS, Latin America and Africa stood with many developed countries to demand for a new legally binding deal, while China responded with a rather harsh objection and urged a focus on implementing the existing commitments under the Convention and Protocol (ENB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2009</xref>). China established a new coalition&#x02014;the BASIC group with another three emerging economies and acted jointly to defend the CBDR principle and reject legally binding obligations on them (Hochstetler and Milkoreit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>). The Copenhagen Accord&#x02014;the final political text reached by the BASIC countries and the USA&#x02014;was just &#x02018;taken note&#x02019; by the Conference Plenary because of the opposition of some developing countries (Dimitrov <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2010</xref>).</p><p id="Par31">In negotiations, China insisted on the strict differentiation framework enshrined in the UNFCCC and the Protocol and steadfastly opposed any &#x02018;intrusive&#x02019; institutional arrangements that impose binding targets on the South (Christoff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2010</xref>; Conrad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>). In Copenhagen, China&#x02019;s Wen Jiabao (2009) and He Yafei (2009) insisted that its voluntary commitment under the UNFCCC was &#x02018;unnegotiable&#x02019; and the Copenhagen conference should &#x02018;stick to rather than obscure the basic principles enshrined in the Convention and the Protocol&#x02019;, and particularly, the CBDR principle &#x02018;must never be compromised&#x02019;. China resisted any initiatives that may directly or indirectly impose a cap for its emissions and restrict its future &#x02018;emissions space&#x02019; (Christoff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2010</xref>: 648). When developed countries requested China&#x02019;s mitigation actions to meet international &#x02018;measurable, reportable and verifiable&#x02019; standards, China strongly rejected international scrutiny on its voluntary mitigation actions and stuck to protecting its sovereignty (He <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2009</xref>). China insisted that developed countries should play the leadership role and pay for the costs for a cooperative solution (NDRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2009</xref>). At last, China&#x02019;s rigid and tough tactics in its climate diplomacy in Copenhagen received widely international criticism (Christoff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2010</xref>). China&#x02019;s developing country identity became hard to continue in GCG.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>The Paris era and beyond</title><p id="Par32">As showed above, China&#x02019;s overall construction of its international identity has transformed towards a new Yinling Leading Power identity. The following sections will show how China has constructed its new identity through its changing climate engagement in the Paris era and beyond.</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Discursive construction</title><p id="Par33">With the transformation of China&#x02019;s overall identity construction towards a new Yinling Leading Power, this part will show that climate change governance has been recognized and framed as an important platform where China can play as a leading state and China&#x02019;s self-representation of a &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; has accordingly dominated China&#x02019;s national narratives on its presence in global climate governance in the pre- and post-Paris period. Before the Paris Summit, China&#x02019;s former Vice-Foreign Minister and ambassador to France&#x02014;Jun Zhai (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2015</xref>)&#x02014;formally framed the Paris Summit as &#x02018;a platform in which China can play an international leadership role in global governance&#x02019;. China&#x02019;s climate negotiators such as Qimin Chai (Interview 2017), Qingchen Chao (Interview 2017) and an expert member (Interview 2017) stressed that global climate governance is the &#x02018;world stage&#x02019; of which China has been gradually at the &#x02018;centre&#x02019; since Xi Jinping&#x02019;s rise to power in 2013. China official narratives framed itself as a &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; in promoting international climate cooperation. For instance, China&#x02019;s state-owned newspaper People&#x02019;s Daily (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2015</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2016</xref>) repeatedly stressed that &#x02018;China&#x02019;s actions &#x0201c;<italic>yinling</italic>&#x0201d; global climate governance&#x02019; and the world expects China to be &#x02018;a pioneer and an example for global efforts in combating climate challenge&#x02019;. Chinese President Xi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2017b</xref>) concluded at the 19th Party&#x02019;s Congress: &#x02018;taking a driving seat in international cooperation to respond to climate change, China has become an important participant, contributor, and &#x0201c;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x0201d; in the global endeavour for ecological civilization&#x02019;. Xi particularly linked the concept &#x02018;ecological civilization&#x02019;, which is rooted in China&#x02019;s past ecological philosophy, with his vision for China&#x02019;s international leadership and aimed to distinguish Chinese leadership from the traditional Western paradigms (Hansen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>). China&#x02019;s top climate negotiator Xie Zhenhua also emphasized that China has become an important &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; in the global construction of ecological civilization (Chinanews <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2017</xref>). Moreover, China&#x02019;s climate negotiator Qimin Chai stressed that:<disp-quote><p id="Par34">China&#x02019;s self-positioning is transforming from a participant to a &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; in global climate governance. Since Xi Jinping became the President, China has become increasingly more proactive in global climate governance (Interview 2017). </p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par35">An expert member of China&#x02019;s climate negotiation team also emphasized that:<disp-quote><p id="Par36">In a long period, China insisted on representing itself as a developing country and avoided using &#x02018;leader&#x02019; to define its role in global climate governance. Since Xi became the President, China has always represented itself as a &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; (Interview 2017). </p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par37">While its &#x02018;old&#x02019; developing country discourses still exist, China&#x02019;s &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; narratives and discursive construction of its leadership in promoting international climate cooperation have constituted the crucial part of its overall construction of the Yinling Leading Power identity. In China&#x02019;s national narratives, climate change governance has been transformed from a problem that developed countries should focus on to one of the most prominent domains that China shows international leadership and contributes to promoting international multilateral cooperation. Global climate governance has become one of China&#x02019;s prototypical discursive frames in constructing its new international identity.</p><p id="Par38">China&#x02019;s identity reconstruction in climate governance is also discursively done through reconstructing issues of climate justice. Undertaking climate responsibility has been reconstructed from a heavy burden to China to its own positive duty and an important way to show its leadership. China&#x02019;s Xie Zhenhua (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2015</xref>) has repeatedly stressed that &#x02018;addressing climate change is what China needs to fulfil its due international obligation as a responsible power&#x02019;. Furthermore, China accepted, reconstructed and promoted a more flexible, balanced differentiation mechanism. For example, China and the USA together redefined the CBDR principle by adding a new qualifier&#x02014;&#x02018;in light of different national circumstances&#x02019; (Foreign Ministry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2014</xref>) and this new formulation was directly reiterated in the Paris Agreement. This new construction of the CBDR actually &#x02018;reduces the weight of the historical responsibility of developed countries&#x02019;, and its &#x02018;novel operationalization&#x02019;&#x02014;the Nationally Determined Contributions as a key mechanism in the Paris Agreement may ultimately result in &#x02018;the smallest common denominator in terms of climate justice&#x02019; (von Lucke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2021</xref>: 50&#x02013;51). In addition to the reconstruction of those specific justice-related norms and principles, China&#x02019;s construction of distributive climate justice in terms of a fair climate deal also transformed from strictly embedding fairness into the established top-down model for developed countries to linking fairness with all Parties&#x02019; voluntary contributions and highlighting inclusiveness. Moreover, by accepting and promoting the ideas of peaking emissions and carbon neutrality (see below), China&#x02019;s construction of climate justice regarding the right to emit and the exemption of developing countries from caps on emissions have also exhibited changes and flexibility.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Policy practice</title><p id="Par39">The following parts will show how China has constructed its new identity through its proactive climate diplomacy and leadership building in climate governance since Xi&#x02019;s rise to power in 2013, and how climate governance has become an important platform where China seeks to share leadership with other major powers.</p><p id="Par40">In the lead-up to Paris, China proactively cooperated with major powers to lead and promote international climate negotiations (Tiberghien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>). For instance, China issued three bilateral joint statements on climate change with the USA and the EU, which paved the way for the success of the Paris Summit. In the three statements, the three sides made their relatively strong commitments, agreed to reach &#x02018;a protocol, another legal instrument or an agreed outcome with legal force under the Convention applicable to all Parties&#x02019; (European Council <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2015</xref>; Foreign Ministry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2015</xref>), and supported to include an enhanced transparency system with reporting and reviewing framework in the Paris outcome (Foreign Ministry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2015</xref>). Their efforts laid the basis for the historical agreement and many wordings of these statements were even directly adopted by the agreement (Tiberghien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par41">Within the negotiations, just like the EU&#x02019;s bridge-building climate diplomacy (Oberth&#x000fc;r and Groen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2017</xref>), China bridged the South and North through bilateral and multilateral diplomacy. In the run-up to Paris, China launched a series of intensive bilateral diplomacy with major players from the South and North as well as multilateral diplomacy within the BASIC group, the G77/China and the Like-Minded developing countries group to push different sides to converge on the common ground in specific issues such as climate finance and the differentiation framework (Wu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2016</xref>). In particular, it was China and the USA that played a pivotal role in securing the Paris Agreement (Kastner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2018</xref>; Schreurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2016</xref>; Tiberghien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>). An EU high-level climate advisor argues that &#x02018;China is kind of a bridge between several worlds&#x02019; and &#x02018;also playing a big role as a strong link with many parts of the world either through negotiating groups or loose alliances&#x02019; (Interview 2018). In addition, China also proactively promoted climate change into other international multilateral institutions such as G20&#x02019;s Hangzhou Summit in 2016, where China and the USA announced the plans to ratify the Paris Agreement.</p><p id="Par42">When the USA under the Trump administration withdrew from the Paris Agreement and retreated from global multilateralism, China did not downgrade its climate efforts. On the contrary, China stepped up its cooperation with the EU and other major players and jointly offered leadership to reach the Rulebook that makes the Agreement into a functioning GCG regime (Gurol and Starkmann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2021</xref>; Parker and Karlsson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par43">Furthermore, China also wielded the climate leadership through two important approaches, i.e. leadership by example (Liefferink and Wurzel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2017</xref>) and providing international public goods (Dent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>), in the Paris era. China has become an undisputable world leader and champion in investing renewable energy (Andrews-Speed and Zhang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2019</xref>; REN21 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2021</xref>). Regarding emission mitigation, China has undertaken more international responsibilities. In Paris, for instance, China for the first time committed to an exact peaking time for CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (by around 2030) (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2015a</xref>). Aside from that, China has achieved its 2020 emission reduction target, which is a carbon intensity reduction of 40 to 45% below 2005 levels, 3 years in advance (UN Climate Change News <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2018</xref>). Furthermore, during the course of the COVID-19 pandemic in September 2020, Chinese President Xi revised the goal to peak emissions before 2030 and also announced that China will aim to achieve carbon neutrality before 2060 (Xinhuanet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2020</xref>). It is the first time that China committed to a long-term goal on emission reduction. China&#x02019;s Xie Zhenhua pointed out that &#x02018;this bold target may move global carbon neutrality ahead by 5-10 years&#x02019; and will also &#x02018;play a key role in promoting stronger global climate governance&#x02019; (China Dialogue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). Research published in Science magazine recently found that China&#x02019;s carbon neutrality target is largely consistent with the Paris Agreement goal of keeping global warming to 1.5&#x000b0;C (Duan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>). In addition, at the Leaders&#x02019; Summit on Climate hosted by the USA in April 2021, Xi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2021</xref>) announced that China would strictly control coal-fired power projects, strictly restrict the growth in coal consumption in the 14th Five-Year Plan period (2021&#x02013;2025) and gradually reduce it in the 15th Five-Year Period (2026&#x02013;2030). Moreover, China&#x02019;s economy has already entered into a decoupling process between growth and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (IEA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2018</xref>; Tiberghien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>). Regarding emission trading, China took experiences from the EU and established its own national Emission Trading System (ETS) in 2017 based on its national conditions and needs, which will become the world&#x02019;s largest ETS system once it is fully operational (Gippner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2020</xref>). China has not only offered considerable financial aids annually but also provided a large amount of projects around renewable energy technology transfer and offered personnel training courses to thousands of government officials, scholars and technicians from hundreds of developing countries (NDRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2015</xref>). Through these domestic and international efforts, China showed its leadership by example regionally and internationally. In addition, as Christopher Dent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>: 21) argued, providing international public goods is an important criteria of international leadership. At the 2015 China-US Summit and the Paris Summit, for example, President Xi announced that China will provide USD 3.1 billion to set up the <italic>China South-South Climate Cooperation Fund</italic> to support developing countries in combating climate change (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2015a</xref>). The money even exceeds the pledge of USD three billion made by the USA to the UN&#x02019;s Green Climate Fund. It is a historical breakthrough that China contributed to international climate finance.</p><p id="Par44">In brief, China has shown its leadership in the process of reaching and implementing the Paris Agreement. China&#x02019;s climate leadership has received a degree of international recognition. For instance, Charles Parker&#x02019;s research shows that China&#x02019;s climate leadership has received increasingly more recognitions from international negotiators and representatives of all delegations from 2009 to 2015 (Parker et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2017</xref>). The EU&#x02019;s Commissioner for climate action&#x02014;Miguel Arias Ca&#x000f1;ete&#x02014;also emphasized that the shared leadership of the EU and China in GCG is needed more than ever (European Commission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2017</xref>). An EU climate official pointed out that &#x02018;China is transiting from a developing country to a leading actor in climate governance&#x02019; (Interview 2018). An EU principal climate advisor concluded that &#x02018;China is showing leadership by taking on more responsibilities&#x02019; (Interview 2018). China&#x02019;s embrace of a shared leadership is quite similar to the EU&#x02019;s new approach since Paris that the EU acknowledged different pathways towards climate justice and wielded leadership through a more interactive way, i.e. being open to others&#x02019; suggestions and negotiating their consent (von Lucke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par45">Notwithstanding that, China&#x02019;s negotiating behaviour, domestic climate policies and international practices have not been without doubts and criticism. Despite China&#x02019;s contribution to securing the Paris Agreement, some scholars and participant observers have noted that China&#x02019;s negotiating behaviour in Paris also undermined and impeded ambitious international efforts (Christoff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2016</xref>; Dimitrov <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2016</xref>). Moreover, many scholars criticized that China&#x02019;s domestic climate policies are not being sufficiently ambitious (Harris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2017</xref>; Keohane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>). In particular, China&#x02019;s greenhouse gas emissions continue to increase, with an average annual growth of 3.3% over the period 2010&#x02013;2019 (Rhodium Group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2021</xref>), and new coal-fired power plants are still being built. In addition, as Robert Keohane emphasized, global climate leadership requires credibility and China has to endorse genuine transparency policies that make its climate commitments credible (Keohane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>). Similarly, the EU&#x02019;s climate negotiators repeatedly complained in the interview with the author about the transparency problem of China&#x02019;s climate data and particularly urged China to be more transparent (Interview 2018). Furthermore, China&#x02019;s overseas investments in fossil fuels energy projects have sparked international criticism (Gupta and Chu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>). For instance, in its newly released strategic document, the EU criticized China&#x02019;s construction of coal-fired power stations in many countries as undermining the global goals of the Paris Agreement (European Commission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>). In order to be fully recognized as a credible climate leader, therefore, China has to self-reflect and adjust its future climate behaviours domestically and internationally. As China&#x02019;s Xie Zhenhua stressed, being a &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; in GCG means China has to address climate change better at domestic, continually offer China&#x02019;s solutions on the basis of its evolving experience and practices, and provide &#x02018;bridging solution&#x02019; for different sides within the international multilateral process on climate change (Chinanews <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2017</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Implications</title><p id="Par46">China&#x02019;s transforming identity construction, changing engagement in global climate governance with its changing construction of issues of climate justice have far-reaching implications for China and other major actors such as the EU to cooperate and coordinate in strengthening global climate justice and promoting global climate governance.</p><p id="Par47">Firstly, China&#x02019;s new identity construction with the climate leadership as its key feature will continue to constrain and reshape China&#x02019;s regional, interregional and global behaviours. China&#x02019;s high-profile interregional &#x02018;Belt and Road&#x02019; initiative will be reviewed and assessed by the world in terms of its impacts on climate change. In order to gain wide participation and support, China has to put climate change into serious consideration in the projects of the &#x02018;Belt and Road&#x02019; initiative.</p><p id="Par48">Secondly, with China&#x02019;s transformation in climate governance, other emerging economies from the global South such as India and regional big developing countries are under increasing pressures to undertake greater but fairer responsibility for current and future emissions. Moreover, developed countries will suffer more moral and political pressures to essentially take the lead in addressing climate change and offer support to those poor and vulnerable developing countries.</p><p id="Par49">Thirdly, China&#x02019;s recent climate proactiveness and its embrace of international climate leadership have already promoted and will continue to promote the cooperation between China and the EU in promoting the multilateral order of global governance and climate change governance in particular. The shared leadership of China and the EU will contribute to bridging the North-South gap in the follow-up international climate negotiations. Furthermore, the good and enduring climate relationship between China and the EU brings stability, certainty and dynamic to their bilateral relationship in a global context that is in flux.</p><p id="Par50">Fourthly, China&#x02019;s reconstruction of climate change and issues of climate justice underpinned its convergence with developed countries especially the USA and contributed to breaking the complex &#x02018;dilemma&#x02019; between climate justice and climate governance order. While the Paris Agreement has weakened the differentiation principle and distributive justice, the temporary but necessary trade-off between distributive justice-related concerns and the formation of an acceptable new comprehensive climate regime has a strong potential of strengthening global climate justice in the long term. Against the backdrop that the USA had launched a trade war and imposed sanctions against China, China has recently resumed its climate cooperation with the USA and attended the Leaders&#x02019; Summit on Climate convened by the US administration under President Biden in April 2021, which provided new certainty and dynamic for promoting global climate governance and strengthening global climate justice in a world of uncertainty.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par51">This article offers an identity lens to understand China&#x02019;s changing engagement in global climate governance over the past decade. From the Copenhagen Climate Summit to the historical Paris Climate Summit, China has partially embedded the construction of its new Yinling Leading Power identity in leading global climate governance. This changing identity is both reflected in and partly constituted by the way China has come to take up its new leading role in global climate governance. Climate change governance has become one of China&#x02019;s prototypical discursive frames in constructing its new international identity through emphasising its role as a global leading actor.</p><p id="Par52">On the road to Copenhagen, China attempted to maintain its developing country identity and its construction of climate justice as distributive justice in a North-South context. However, it suffered challenges from both the developed and developing world. With Xi Jinping&#x02019;s accession to power, China&#x02019;s international identity construction has been transforming towards a Yinling Leading Power. In the Paris era and beyond, China has reconstructed issues of climate justice and climate governance has become an important platform where China seeks to represent itself as a &#x02018;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#x02019; (leading state) and share leadership with other major powers. China&#x02019;s embrace of a shared leadership is similar to the EU&#x02019;s new interactive way to wielding climate leadership since Paris. China&#x02019;s climate leadership constitutes its new identity construction and becomes a key feature. China&#x02019;s transformation has far-reaching implications for strengthening global climate justice and promoting global climate governance. This article also points out that China&#x02019;s inadequate response to international expectations and lack of self-reflection in its climate policy have influenced international recognition on its climate leadership and new identity. In the post-Paris era, whether or not China fulfills its climate commitments, takes the lead in promoting global climate cooperation and gains sufficient recognition from other parties will have profound consequences for the prospects of this new identity construction, which has not yet been stabilized and secured.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contribution</title><p>Sole author</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The author was funded by China Scholarship Council. Grant number 201506040034.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Not applicable</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p>Not applicable</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval</title><p id="Par53">Not applicable</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent to participate</title><p id="Par54">Not applicable</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par55">Not applicable</p></notes><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par56">The author declares no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews-Speed</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>China as a global clean energy champion: lifting the veil</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Audet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate justice and bargaining coalitions: a discourse analysis</article-title><source>International Environmental Agreements: Politics, Law and Economics</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10784-012-9195-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Joffe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerremans</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>China, the United States and the European Union: multiple bilateralism and prospects for a new climate change diplomacy</article-title><source>Carbon &#x00026; Climate Law Review</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schunz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>China and the European Union: emerging partners in global climate governance?</article-title><source>Environ Pract</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1466046613000276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brzezinski Z (2009) The group of two that could change the world. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ft.com/content/d99369b8-e178-11dd-afa0-0000779fd2ac">https://www.ft.com/content/d99369b8-e178-11dd-afa0-0000779fd2ac</ext-link>. Accessed 15 August 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen D (2017) Is China ready for global leadership. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://thediplomat.com/2017/02/is-china-ready-for-global-leadership/">https://thediplomat.com/2017/02/is-china-ready-for-global-leadership/</ext-link>. Accessed 10 February 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">China Dialogue (2020) China&#x02019;s new carbon neutrality pledge: what next? <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://chinadialogue.net/en/climate/chinas-new-carbon-neutrality-pledge-what-next/">https://chinadialogue.net/en/climate/chinas-new-carbon-neutrality-pledge-what-next/</ext-link>. Accessed 24 September 2020</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chinanews (2017) Zhuanfang Xiezhenhua: Zhongguo jiangruhe gaishan quanqiuqihouzhili &#x0201c;daqihou&#x0201d;? (Interview Xie Zhenhua: how will China improve the &#x02018;grand climate&#x02019; of global climate governance?). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chinanews.com/gn/2017/11-13/8375380.shtml">http://www.chinanews.com/gn/2017/11-13/8375380.shtml</ext-link>. Accessed 14 September 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christoff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cold climate in Copenhagen: China and the United States at COP15</article-title><source>Environ Polit</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644016.2010.489718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christoff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The promissory note: COP 21 and the Paris Climate Agreement</article-title><source>Environ Polit</source><year>2016</year><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644016.2016.1191818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>China in Copenhagen: reconciling the &#x0201c;Beijing climate revolution&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c;Copenhagen climate obstinacy&#x0201d;</article-title><source>The China Quarterly</source><year>2012</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0305741012000458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What region to lead? Developments in East Asian regionalism and questions of regional leadership</article-title><source>China, Japan and regional leadership in East Asia</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Cheltenham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Edward Elgar Publishing</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>33</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inside UN climate change negotiations: the Copenhagen conference</article-title><source>Rev Policy Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>27</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1541-1338.2010.00472.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Paris agreement on climate change: behind closed doors</article-title><source>Glob Environ Polit</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/GLEP_a_00361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dong&#x000a0;L (2017) Bound to lead? Rethinking China&#x02019;s role after Paris in UNFCCC negotiations Chinese. J Popul Resour Environ 15(1):32&#x02013;38</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessing China&#x02019;s efforts to pursue the 1.5&#x000b0; C warming limit</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2021</year><volume>372</volume><issue>6540</issue><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aba8767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33888636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckersley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rethinking leadership: understanding the roles of the US and China in the negotiation of the Paris Agreement</article-title><source>Eur J Int Rel</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1178</fpage><lpage>1202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1354066120927071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ENB (1997) Report of the meetings of the FCCC subsidiaries: 20-31 October 1997. The International Institute for Sustainable Development 12(66). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://enb.iisd.org/download/pdf/enb1266e.pdf">http://enb.iisd.org/download/pdf/enb1266e.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ENB (2009) Copenhagen highlights: Wednesday, 9 December 2009. The International Institute for Sustainable Development 12(451). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://enb.iisd.org/download/pdf/enb12451e.pdf">http://enb.iisd.org/download/pdf/enb12451e.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding how China is championing climate change mitigation</article-title><source>Palgrave Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1057/s41599-018-0150-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Commission (2009) Towards a comprehensive climate change agreement in Copenhagen <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=COM:2009:0039:FIN:EN:PDF">https://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=COM:2009:0039:FIN:EN:PDF</ext-link>. Accessed 17 December 2017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Commission (2017) Commissioner Arias Ca&#x000f1;ete in China to strengthen climate and clean energy ties. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/clima/news/commissioner-arias-ca%C3%B1ete-china-strengthen-climate-and-clean-energy-ties_en">https://ec.europa.eu/clima/news/commissioner-arias-ca%C3%B1ete-china-strengthen-climate-and-clean-energy-ties_en</ext-link>. Accessed 10 March 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Commission (2019) EU-China &#x02013; a strategic outlook. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/sites/beta-political/files/communication-eu-china-a-strategic-outlook.pdf">https://ec.europa.eu/commission/sites/beta-political/files/communication-eu-china-a-strategic-outlook.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 2 April 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Council (2015) EU-China joint statement on climate change. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.consilium.europa.eu/media/23733/150629-eu-china-climate-statement-doc.pdf">https://www.consilium.europa.eu/media/23733/150629-eu-china-climate-statement-doc.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 14 March 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Foreign Ministry (2014) China-US joint announcement on climate change. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mfa.gov.cn/chn//gxh/zlb/smgg/t1210034.htm">https://www.mfa.gov.cn/chn//gxh/zlb/smgg/t1210034.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 20 December 2017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Foreign Ministry (2015) U.S.-China joint presidential statement on climate change. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mfa.gov.cn/chn//gxh/zlb/smgg/t1300787.htm">https://www.mfa.gov.cn/chn//gxh/zlb/smgg/t1300787.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 20 December 2017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gippner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><source>Creating China&#x02019;s climate change policy: internal competition and external diplomacy</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>Cheltenham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Edward Elgar Publishing</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inclusive development and climate change: the geopolitics of fossil fuel risks in developing countries</article-title><source>African and Asian Studies</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/15692108-12341402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Starkmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New partners for the planet? The European Union and China in international climate governance from a role-theoretical perspective</article-title><source>J. Common Mark. Stud.</source><year>2021</year><volume>59</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcms.13098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Svarverud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological civilization: interpreting the Chinese past, projecting the global future</article-title><source>Glob Environ Chang</source><year>2018</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2018.09.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>China&#x02019;s Paris pledge on climate change: inadequate and irresponsible</article-title><source>J Environ Stud Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13412-017-0422-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>China and climate justice: moving beyond statism</article-title><source>International Environmental Agreements: Politics, Law and Economics</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10784-012-9189-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">He Y (2009) Zhongguo zizhu jianpaixingdong wufujiatiaojian yeburongtanpan (China&#x02019;s voluntary mitigation actions have no strings attached and are not negotiable). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://world.people.com.cn/GB/8212/14450/46162/10567346.html">http://world.people.com.cn/GB/8212/14450/46162/10567346.html</ext-link>. Accessed 17 January 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heggelund</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>China&#x02019;s climate and energy policy: at a turning point?</article-title><source>International Environmental Agreements: Politics, Law and Economics</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10784-021-09528-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33613133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilton</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Paris Agreement: China&#x02019;s &#x02018;New Normal&#x02019;role in international climate negotiations</article-title><source>Clim Pol</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14693062.2016.1228521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochstetler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Milkoreit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging powers in the climate negotiations: shifting identity conceptions</article-title><source>Polit Res Q</source><year>2014</year><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1065912913510609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The promise of constructivism in international relations theory</article-title><source>Int Secur</source><year>1998</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/isec.23.1.171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hu J (2004) Tuijin hezuogongying, shixian chixufazhan (Promote cooperation and win-win, achieve sustainable development). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/ce/cohk/chn/jb/zt/2004zt/APEC2004/t170951.htm">https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/ce/cohk/chn/jb/zt/2004zt/APEC2004/t170951.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 12 July 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hu J (2011) Zai Zhongguo jiaru shijiemaoyizuzhi 10 zhounian gaocengluntan shangde jianghua (Speech at the Forum to commemorate the 10th anniversay of China&#x02019;s entry into the WTO). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mofcom.gov.cn/article/ae/ai/201112/20111207873587.shtml">http://www.mofcom.gov.cn/article/ae/ai/201112/20111207873587.shtml</ext-link>. Accessed 12 July 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IEA (2018) Global energy &#x00026; CO<sub>2</sub> status report. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mehi.hu/sites/default/files/geco2017.pdf">https://mehi.hu/sites/default/files/geco2017.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 3 October 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gullberg</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Heggelund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Group of 77 in the international climate negotiations: recent developments and future directions</article-title><source>International Environmental Agreements: Politics, Law and Economics</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10784-007-9060-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kastner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rector</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kastner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rector</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change negotiations: from hold-up to invest</article-title><source>China&#x02019;s strategic multilateralism: investing in global governance</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>216</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keohane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The international climate regime without American leadership</article-title><source>Chinese Journal of Population Resources and Environment</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10042857.2017.1343905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keohane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppenheimer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paris: beyond the climate dead end through pledge and review?</article-title><source>Politics and Governance</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17645/pag.v4i3.634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Navigating between &#x0201c;luxury&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;survival&#x0201d; emission: tensions in China&#x02019;s multilateral and bilateral climate change diplomacy</article-title><source>Global warming and East Asia: the domestic and international politics of climate change</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>108</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li P (1992) Lipengzongli zai lianheguo huanfadahui shounaohuiyi shangde jianghua (Speech by Premier Li Peng divered at the United Nations summit conference on environment and development). General Office of the State Council of China, Beijing</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liefferink</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurzel</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental leaders and pioneers: agents of change?</article-title><source>J Eur Publ Policy</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13501763.2016.1161657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mearsheimer</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The gathering storm: China&#x02019;s challenge to US power in Asia</article-title><source>The Chinese Journal of International Politics</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cjip/poq016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Men</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>China&#x02019;s national identity in transition: domestic and international perspectives (1982&#x02013;2012)</article-title><source>Social Sciences in China</source><year>2014</year><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02529203.2014.900895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Men H (2017) Yingdui quanqiuzhili weiji yu biange de zhongguofanglve (China&#x02019;s strategy for approaching the crisis and reform of global governance). Zhongguo shehuikexue (Social Sciences in China)(10):36-46</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Men J (2014)&#x000a0;Climate change and EU&#x02013;China partnership: realist disguise or institutionalist blessing?&#x000a0;Asia Europe Journal 12(1&#x02013;2):49&#x02013;62</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Messari N (2001) Identity and foreign policy: the case of islam in US foreign policy. In: Kub&#x000e1;lkov&#x000e1; V (ed) Foreign policy in a constructed world. M. E. Sharpe, New York, pp 227-246</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NDRC (2009) Implementation of the Bali roadmap &#x000ad;China&#x02019;s position on the Copenhagen climate change conference. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.china-un.ch/eng/bjzl/t564324.htm">http://www.china-un.ch/eng/bjzl/t564324.htm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NDRC (2015) China&#x02019;s policies and actions for addressing climate change (2015). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.ccchina.org.cn/archiver/ccchinaen/UpFile/Files/Default/20151120095849657206.pdf">http://en.ccchina.org.cn/archiver/ccchinaen/UpFile/Files/Default/20151120095849657206.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oberth&#x000fc;r</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The European Union and the Paris Agreement: leader, mediator, or bystander?</article-title><source>WIREs Climate Change</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e445</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcc.445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okereke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Coventry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate justice and the international regime: before, during, and after Paris</article-title><source>Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Climate Change</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>851</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The apparent &#x0201c;paradox&#x0201d; in China&#x02019;s climate policies</article-title><source>Asian Surv</source><year>2012</year><volume>52</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1138</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/as.2012.52.6.1138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pang Z (2018) Zhongguo zaiquanqiuzhilizhong dangangshenmejuese? Zhongguoban &#x0201c;Feibaquan de guojilingdao&#x0201d; (What kind of role does China play in global governance? The Chinese version &#x0201c;non-hegemonic ledership&#x0201d;). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chinatimes.cc/article/73848.html">http://www.chinatimes.cc/article/73848.html</ext-link>. Accessed 27 March 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parker CF, Karlsson C (2018) EU climate leadership in Katowice helped deliver the deal on the Paris Agreement rulebook. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/europpblog/2018/12/20/eu-climate-leadership-in-katowice-helped-deliver-the-deal-on-the-paris-agreement-rulebook/">https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/europpblog/2018/12/20/eu-climate-leadership-in-katowice-helped-deliver-the-deal-on-the-paris-agreement-rulebook/</ext-link>. Accessed 20 September 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjerpe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the European Union&#x02019;s global climate change leadership: from Copenhagen to the Paris Agreement</article-title><source>J Eur Integr</source><year>2017</year><volume>39</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07036337.2016.1275608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">People's Daily (2015) Yinling quanqiuqihouzhili de Zhongguozuowei (China&#x02019;s practices in leading global climate governance). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://opinion.people.com.cn/n/2015/1208/c1003-27898232.html">http://opinion.people.com.cn/n/2015/1208/c1003-27898232.html</ext-link>. Accessed 29 July 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">People's Daily (2016) Jianding yinling quanqiuqihouzhili jincheng (Firmly leading the process of global climate governance). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cpc.people.com.cn/pinglun/n1/2016/0424/c78779-28299932.html">http://cpc.people.com.cn/pinglun/n1/2016/0424/c78779-28299932.html</ext-link>. Accessed 29 July 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controversial identity of a rising China</article-title><source>The Chinese Journal of International Politics</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cjip/pox004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">REN21 (2021) Renewables 2021 global status report. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ren21.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/GSR2021_Full_Report.pdf">https://www.ren21.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/GSR2021_Full_Report.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rhodium Group (2021) Preliminary 2020 greenhouse gas emissions estimates for China. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://rhg.com/research/preliminary-2020-greenhouse-gas-emissions-estimates-for-china/">https://rhg.com/research/preliminary-2020-greenhouse-gas-emissions-estimates-for-china/</ext-link>. Accessed 10 August 2021</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schreurs</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Paris climate agreement and the three largest emitters: China, the United States, and the European Union</article-title><source>Politics and Governance</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17645/pag.v4i3.666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shambaugh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coping with a conflicted China</article-title><source>Wash Q</source><year>2011</year><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0163660X.2011.537974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hurrell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsbury</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The unavoidability of justice</article-title><source>The international politics of the environment: actors, interests, and institutions</source><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>397</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subsistence emissions and luxury emissions</article-title><source>Law &#x00026; Policy</source><year>1993</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9930.1993.tb00093.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stalley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principled strategy: the role of equity norms in China&#x02019;s climate change diplomacy</article-title><source>Glob Environ Polit</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/GLEP_a_00150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">State Council (2019) China and the world in the new era. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xinhuanet.com/politics/2019-09/27/c_1125047331.htm">http://www.xinhuanet.com/politics/2019-09/27/c_1125047331.htm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiberghien</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Amighini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chinese global climate change leadership and its impact</article-title><source>China champion of (which) globalisation?</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Milan</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ledizioni LediPublishing</publisher-name><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>120</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UN Climate Change News (2018) China meets 2020 carbon target three years ahead of schedule. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/news/china-meets-2020-carbon-target-three-years-ahead-of-schedule">https://unfccc.int/news/china-meets-2020-carbon-target-three-years-ahead-of-schedule</ext-link>. Accessed 13 june 2021</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lucke von&#x000a0;F, Diez&#x000a0;T, Aamodt&#x000a0;S, Ahrens B 2021 The EU and global climate justice: normative power caught in normative battles Routledge New York</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang Y (2015) 2015: A year of flying colors for pursuing Major-Country Diplomacy with distinctive Chinese features. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/mfa_eng/wjdt_665385/zyjh_665391/t1329609.shtml">https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/mfa_eng/wjdt_665385/zyjh_665391/t1329609.shtml</ext-link>. Accessed 15 June 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wen J (2007) Wen Jiabao&#x02019;s speech at the Third East Asia summit. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gov.cn/ldhd/2007-11/22/content_812088.htm">http://www.gov.cn/ldhd/2007-11/22/content_812088.htm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wen J (2009) Build consensus and strengthen cooperation to advance the historical process of combating climate change. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/mfa_eng/wjdt_665385/zyjh_665391/t647091.shtml">https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/mfa_eng/wjdt_665385/zyjh_665391/t647091.shtml</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Social theory of international politics</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shaping China&#x02019;s climate diplomacy: wealth, status, and asymmetric interdependence</article-title><source>J Chin Polit Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11366-016-9404-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2012) Xieshouhezuo gongtongweihu shijieheping yu anquan (Work together to maintain the peace and security of the world). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/web/ziliao_674904/zyjh_674906/t948833.shtml">https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/web/ziliao_674904/zyjh_674906/t948833.shtml</ext-link>. Accessed 1 August 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2013) Jiang lianglichengdan gengduoguojizeren (China will undertake more international responsibility based on its capability). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://theory.people.com.cn/n/2013/0320/c49150-20848996.html">http://theory.people.com.cn/n/2013/0320/c49150-20848996.html</ext-link>. Accessed 1 August 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2014) Jiakuai ziyoumaoyiqu zhanlve jiakuai goujian kaifangxing jingji xintizhi (Accelerating the implementation of the strategy of free trade zone, speeding up the construction of an open economic system). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xinhuanet.com//politics/2014-12/06/c_1113546075.htm">http://www.xinhuanet.com//politics/2014-12/06/c_1113546075.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 3 September 2017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2015a) Work together to build a win&#x000ad;win, equitable and balanced governance mechanism on climate change. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/cop21cmp11_leaders_event_china.pdf">https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/cop21cmp11_leaders_event_china.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 3 September 2017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2015b) Xieshougoujian hezuogongying xinhuoban, tongxindazao renleimingyungongtongti (Work together to build a new partnership of win-win cooperation, build a community of shared future for mankind). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jhsjk.people.cn/article/27644987">http://jhsjk.people.cn/article/27644987</ext-link>. Accessed 3 September 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2016a) Jiandingxinxin gongmoufazhan (Firm up confidence and seek common development). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/web/ziliao_674904/zyjh_674906/t1406096.shtml">https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/web/ziliao_674904/zyjh_674906/t1406096.shtml</ext-link>. Accessed 3 September 2017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2016b) Zhongguofazhan xinqidian, quanqiuzengzhang xinlantu (A new start of China&#x02019;s development, a new blueprint of global growth). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xinhuanet.com/mrdx/2016-09/04/c_135658789.htm">http://www.xinhuanet.com/mrdx/2016-09/04/c_135658789.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 3 September 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2017a) Gongtonggoujian renleimingyungongtongti (Jointly build a community of shared future for mankind). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xinhuanet.com/world/2017-01/19/c_1120340081.htm">http://www.xinhuanet.com/world/2017-01/19/c_1120340081.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 1 August 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2017b) Secure a decisive victory in building a moderately prosperous society in all respects and strive for the great success of socialism with Chinese characteristics for a new era. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/download/Xi_Jinping's_report_at_19th_CPC_National_Congress.pdf">http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/download/Xi_Jinping's_report_at_19th_CPC_National_Congress.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xi J (2021) For Man and nature: building a community of life together. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/2021-04/22/c_139899289.htm">http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/2021-04/22/c_139899289.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 25 April 2021</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xie Z (2015) Quanqiuqihouzhili xunqiu zuidagongyueshu (Global climate governance seeks &#x0201c;the greatest common divisor&#x0201d;). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://theory.people.com.cn/n/2015/1130/c136457-27870970.html">http://theory.people.com.cn/n/2015/1130/c136457-27870970.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xinhuanet (2020) Xi Focus: Xi announces China aims to achieve carbon neutrality before 2060. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/2020-09/23/c_139388764.htm">http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/2020-09/23/c_139388764.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 10 December 2020</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From keeping a low profile to striving for achievement</article-title><source>The Chinese Journal of International Politics</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cjip/pou027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yu Q (2009a) Ambassador Yu Qingtai holds a briefing for Chinese and foreign media. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/ce/cein/eng/zgbd/t577413.htm">https://www.fmprc.gov.cn/ce/cein/eng/zgbd/t577413.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 17 January 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yu Q (2009b) Yu Qingtai dashi juxing zhongwaimeiti chuifenghui (Ambassador Yu Qingtai holds a briefing for Chinese and foreign media). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ipc.fmprc.gov.cn/chn/cfh/t629331.htm">http://ipc.fmprc.gov.cn/chn/cfh/t629331.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 17 January 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yu Q (2010) China&#x02019;s interests must come first. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.chinadialogue.net/article/show/single/en/3792-China-s-interests-must-come-first">https://www.chinadialogue.net/article/show/single/en/3792-China-s-interests-must-come-first</ext-link>. Accessed 20 May 2017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhai J (2015) Responsibility and opportunities at the Paris climate conference. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://politics.people.com.cn/n/2015/1127/c1001-27862366.html">http://politics.people.com.cn/n/2015/1127/c1001-27862366.html</ext-link>. Accessed 20 July 2018</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>