<p>Finally, refinement includes any modifications to animal care or procedures that can minimize negative impacts. Refinements in feeding animals may include a consideration of pet food ingredients as well as the quantity of food fed. Owners overfeeding their pets also have a negative impact on both the environment (<xref rid="icab025-B125" ref-type="bibr">Rushforth and Moreau 2013</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B141" ref-type="bibr">Swanson et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B130" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz 2014</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B99" ref-type="bibr">Martens et al. 2019</xref>) and pet health. Replacement of high GHG emitting and high EPP meat sources (such as beef) in companion animal food with other sources such as poultry and fish (<xref rid="icab025-B150" ref-type="bibr">Vale and Vale 2009</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B130" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz 2014</xref>), lab-grown meat equivalents (<xref rid="icab025-B140" ref-type="bibr">Su et al. 2018</xref>), insect-based protein (<xref rid="icab025-B63" ref-type="bibr">Han et al. 2017</xref>), or plant-based sources in diets have been considered (<xref rid="icab025-B115" ref-type="bibr">Pimentel and Pimentel 2003</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B119" ref-type="bibr">Reijnders and Soret 2003</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B157" ref-type="bibr">Wirsenius et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B108" ref-type="bibr">Okin 2017</xref>). Alternative diets such as a vegetarian or insect-based diets may be a more environmentally conscious food source for companion animal diets (<xref rid="icab025-B81" ref-type="bibr">Knight and Leitsberger 2016</xref> ; <xref rid="icab025-B62" ref-type="bibr">Halloran et al. 2017</xref>). Furthermore, utilizing by-products that are not suitable for human consumption may significantly reduce the EPP (<xref rid="icab025-B3" ref-type="bibr">Alexander et al. 2020</xref>). Refinement in this context may include increasing bioavailability and digestibility of food (<xref rid="icab025-B141" ref-type="bibr">Swanson et al. 2013</xref>) or processing human food waste into companion animal food (<xref rid="icab025-B118" ref-type="bibr">Rastogi 2010</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B25" ref-type="bibr">Castrica et al. 2018</xref>). In fact, free ranging dogs utilize both human food waste as well as human excrement effectively (<xref rid="icab025-B21" ref-type="bibr">Butler et al. 2018</xref>), so reversal of the modern approach of using commercial dog food may be additionally considered. However, understanding the complete environmental impacts of food production and the determination of associated species-specific nutritional adequacy is needed. Further refinements, which may include reducing and replacing plastic toys and waste disposal bags, could be other simple changes to decrease environmental damage. Strategies to reduce predation by owned cats include restricting or managing outdoor access, wearable predation prevention devices such as specialized collars and bells, and nutrition and activity interventions (<xref rid="icab025-B167" ref-type="bibr">Cecchetti et al. 2020</xref>). However, developing humane cat predation prevention procedures while simultaneously meeting cat welfare needs remains an urgent need in both feline and climate research. Finally, appropriate selection of a companion animal to match the owner&#8217;s current climate may reduce impacts. For example, purchasing a long-coated dog with cold climate origins in a hot climate will likely result in the owner providing additional air conditioning in the home, trips to a groomer, and using a personal vehicle for safe exercise opportunities&#8212;all of which will likely have negative environmental impacts.</p>