<p>Overall, considering the growing population of companion animals worldwide and the resulting widespread use of natural resources, developing strategies for both individuals and industries to mitigate the effect of companion animals is vital. Furthermore, gaining a better understanding of feasibility and impact of mitigation strategies is needed. It is possible, for example, that switching from one pet food to another may reduce EPP, but is this reduction negligible or meaningful on a global scale (see discussion in <xref rid="icab025-B3" ref-type="bibr">Alexander et al. 2020</xref>)? Likewise, companion animal ownership and caretaking behaviors must be considered in the full array of human activity. When considering overall harms and benefits of companion animal ownership, it is important to consider whether pet ownership itself improves pro-environmental behaviors in society. Attachment to pets positively influences children&#8217;s later attitudes toward animals (<xref rid="icab025-B113" ref-type="bibr">Paul and Serpell 1993</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B67" ref-type="bibr">Hawkins and Williams 2017</xref>), but the relationship between pet ownership in childhood and later concerns for environmental issues is less clear (<xref rid="icab025-B113" ref-type="bibr">Paul and Serpell 1993</xref>). However, pet-owning children that practiced more pet-caring behaviors were also more environmentally concerned (<xref rid="icab025-B146" ref-type="bibr">Torkar et al. 2020</xref>). Likewise, having a high attachment to the pet, rather than being an owner, was a determinant of subsequent vegetarian or vegan diets in adulthood (<xref rid="icab025-B124" ref-type="bibr">Rothgerber and Mican 2014</xref>). Pet owners, generally, are more supportive of wildlife management strategies that prevent species extinction, but are also opposed to wildlife conservation strategies that restrict pet ownership or associated behaviors (<xref rid="icab025-B22" ref-type="bibr">Shuttlewood et al. 2016</xref>)&#8212;such as controlling free roaming cat populations (<xref rid="icab025-B56" ref-type="bibr">Grayson et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="icab025-B95" ref-type="bibr">McDonald et al. 2015</xref>) and leashing dogs (<xref rid="icab025-B156" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 2009</xref>). Similarly, while dog owners tend to walk more (<xref rid="icab025-B34" ref-type="bibr">Christian et al. 2018</xref>), they also tend to rely on private cars for getting to the exercise location (<xref rid="icab025-B80" ref-type="bibr">Kent and Mulley 2017</xref>). Finally, whereas popular media frequently suggests that pets are child substitutes and may lead to a decreased human population, research has not found a difference in the number of children by pet ownership (<xref rid="icab025-B127" ref-type="bibr">Saunders et al. 2017</xref>); in fact, having a child positively predicted dog ownership (<xref rid="icab025-B154" ref-type="bibr">Westgarth et al. 2007</xref>). Ultimately, more research is needed to better understand whether there is a causal link between pet ownership and environmentally-conscious behaviors. These questions further highlight the importance of systems thinking in the creation of mitigation and adaptation plans in our field.</p>