<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par3">There are various reasons to be concerned about climate activists&#8217; engagement not just with mitigation but also with adaptation. Adaptation fits within the boundaries of climate change movements&#8217; (CCM) demands for firmer government action and justice in the face of climate crisis, and it resonates with observations about an increasing concern among climate activists that it might be &#8216;too late&#8217; to prevent major climate impacts (Stuart <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2020</xref>; Casseg&#229;rd and Th&#246;rn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2018</xref>). While the impacts of such concerns are often more contradictory (Friberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2021</xref>; de Moor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2021</xref>), one observable effect is that some activists shift from trying to prevent impacts through climate mitigation to imagining what responses to those impacts could entail once they become accepted as unavoidable (e.g. Bendell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>). (It is worth noting that this change particularly presents a recent phenomenon in the global North, as &#8216;frontline&#8217; and indigenous communities have been forced to deal with actual climate impacts and other environmental disruptions for much longer (Whyte <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2017</xref>)). There are furthermore normative arguments for the involvement of climate movements with adaptation, as critical adaptation scholars are increasingly putting forward arguments about its political nature (O&#8217;Brien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2012</xref>; Adger <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2016</xref>), the concurrent need to democratize it ((Mikulewicz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2018</xref>; Schlosberg et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2017</xref>), and the role that social movements could play in that process (Schlosberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2013</xref>). This situation clearly calls for a closer look at the role of adaptation in recent climate activism.</p>