<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">All of the articles in our dataset followed a relatively similar structure where
journalists pose a question related to COVID-19 that is relevant to the public,
then attempt to answer this question using either computer simulations,
mathematical, or epidemiological models that convey to the public possible
future outcomes. For example, on 13 March 2020, 2 days after the declaration of
COVID-19 as a global pandemic by the WHO and prior to any public conversation
about rolling out the vaccine, Nicholas Kristof and Stuart Thompson published in
collaboration with infectious disease epidemiologists an online opinion article
titled &#8220;How Much Worse the Coronavirus Could Get, in Charts.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="fn4-14614448221135632" ref-type="fn">4</xref></sup> The discourse
in this article was mainly focusing on potential policies and actions that could
help in curbing the number of infections due to COVID-19. The article showcases
an interactive simulation tool that allows readers to visualize how swift
actions by U.S officials could make a difference in controlling the pandemic.
The interactive tool starts by displaying simulated numbers of COVID-19
infections and fatalities in the United States from April 2020 until July 2021
if no action was taken by U.S officials to control the pandemic (<xref rid="fig1-14614448221135632" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>). As the reader
scrolls down through the article, different scenarios were displayed to
demonstrate that implementing interventions is not only important, but the
timing and immediacy of when these interventions are implemented could have
consequences on the number of infections and fatalities. For example, based on
results from the interactive tool for one of the shown scenarios, implementing
intervention measures (e.g. ending public gatherings, closing workplaces and
schools, and mass testing) as early as June 2020 could reduce the number of
infections in July 2020 from 9.4 million, if no action was taken, to 4.5 million
cases and reduce the number of fatalities from 1 million, if no action was
taken, to 475,000 deaths by July 2021 (<xref rid="fig1-14614448221135632" ref-type="fig">Figure 1b</xref>). Readers can modify the
timing and level of aggressiveness in implementing additional measures to better
understand the impact of these factors on the course of the pandemic (<xref rid="fig2-14614448221135632" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p>