<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par3">The mechanisms through which food security can be affected by climate change are many and often complex, and include the stability of and access to food supplies; impacts on prices, markets, and infrastructure across the the food chain; reduced incomes; and increases in the incidence of infectious and diarrhoeal diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Yet while the potential links between food security and climate change have long been addressed in the academic literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, a closer look reveals three important features. First, most articles purporting to identify links between climate change and food security focus on the narrower relationship between climate shocks and climate variability on agricultural output and food production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. For example, a reduction in consumable food calories has been attributed to changes in temperature and precipitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Other more complex mechanisms linking climate and food production are also being identified: for example, locust outbreaks, that can be devastating for crop production, have been found to be linked to long-term droughts, warm winters, and high spring and summer precipitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Links between pollinators and food security have also been identified<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Second, much of the literature is qualitative, focusing on pathways between climate change, food production, and food security. Third, most quantitative papers focus on future, rather than current impacts. For example, many papers use crop models, computable general equilibrium (CGE) models, and/or integrated assessment models (IAM) combined with with general circulation models (GCMs) to project the impact of future climate change on the population at risk of hunger<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. However, there is a gap in the literature with respect to the identification of a plausible causal relationship between climatic stressors and food security indicators.</p>