<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Educ Curric Dev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Med Educ Curric Dev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MDE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmde</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Medical Education and Curricular Development</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2382-1205</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8637707</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/23821205211061019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_23821205211061019</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Climate Change and Human Health ECHO: Global Telementoring for Health
Professionals</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katzman</surname><given-names>Joanna G</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="corresp1-23821205211061019" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schramm</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tomedi</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maury</surname><given-names>John-Michael</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalishman</surname><given-names>Summers</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kazhe-Dominguez</surname><given-names>Briana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jinyang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Chamron</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>Sanjeev</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-23821205211061019" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-23821205211061019">
<label>1</label>University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center, Albuquerque, New
Mexico, USA</aff><aff id="aff2-23821205211061019">
<label>2</label>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, Silver Spring,
Maryland, USA</aff><aff id="aff3-23821205211061019">
<label>3</label>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia,
USA</aff><aff id="aff4-23821205211061019">
<label>4</label>University of California School of Medicine, San Diego, California,
USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-23821205211061019">Joanna G Katzman, Neurosurgery, University
of New Mexico Health Sciences Center, Albuquerque, New Mexico, USA. Email:
<email xlink:href="JKatzman@salud.unm.edu">JKatzman@salud.unm.edu</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Dec</season><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>23821205211061019</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>OBJECTIVE</title><p>To increase the knowledge and communication skills of health professionals
related to climate change and human health (CCHH).</p></sec><sec><title>METHODS</title><p>From February to April 2021, Project ECHO (Extension for Community Healthcare
Outcomes) created an 8-week, synchronous and virtual, CCHH ECHO
telementoring series for health professionals. Didactics, simulated cases,
and climate change tools were used to educate the interprofessional group of
participants.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>During this CCHH ECHO pilot series, 625 unique participants represented 45 US
states and 25 countries. The participants reported that they increased their
knowledge, skills, and communication techniques regarding climate change and
health.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>The human health effects of climate change is an emerging field, and
increasing knowledge and communication skills among health practitioners is
of critical importance. The CCHH ECHO is one potential platform that may
reach a diverse community of health professionals globally due to the
diffusion and demonopolization of knowledge.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Climate change curriculum</kwd><kwd>health professional</kwd><kwd>postlicensure education</kwd><kwd>medical education</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts19</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-23821205211061019"><title>Introduction</title><p>Scientists are convinced that greenhouse gas emissions are causing our world to warm
at an unusually rapid rate, resulting in climatic changes and extreme weather
events.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>
In a recent United Nations poll of 50 countries, over 65% of one million respondents
agreed that climate change is a global threat.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr3-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
</sup> Extreme heat, drought, extreme precipitation, air pollution, wildfires, and
sea level rise are among the climate-related changes potentially affecting morbidity
and mortality, especially for low-income residents with underlying health conditions.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr4-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</sup></p><p>Health professionals are among the most trusted sources of scientific information and
represent a critical voice to raise awareness regarding the health impacts of
climate change.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bibr7-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
Many medical, nursing, and public health organizations recognize climate change as a
global health crisis and endorse the need for climate change and health
education.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bibr16-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> There are increased calls for nursing education related to
climate change, climate justice, and climate action.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr17-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
</sup> Similarly, there is now deliberate development of a framework for climate
change competencies for community and other public health workers, one of the
largest groups of healthcare workers worldwide.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr18-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
</sup> In a recent survey of 2817 medical schools in 112 countries, less than 15%
incorporated climate change and health into their curriculum.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr19-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
</sup></p><p>Although health professionals are interested in learning about the congruence of
climate change and human health (CCHH), they often lack the time and resources to
increase their knowledge and capacity to address these issues.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr7-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup> Most receive little prelicensure training in communication skills.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="bibr21-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> To gain
expertise in having difficult conversations, some health professionals have
participated in &#x0201c;Breaking Bad News&#x0201d; trainings.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr22-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
</sup> However, few are trained to communicate sensitively about topics such as gun
safety, suicide, intimate partner violence, and immunization safety, which impact
both individual and community health.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr23-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
</sup> Now health professionals are strongly encouraged to communicate about
weather-related disaster preparedness and health adaptations due to climate change
as these topics affect the health of the individual, the community, and the future
of the planet.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr24-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
</sup></p><p>Project ECHO (Extension for Community Healthcare Outcomes) is a peer-learning network
for health professionals. In February 2021, University of New Mexico's Project ECHO
launched a CCHH program for training postlicensure health professionals. The goals
of the CCHH ECHO were 3-fold: to increase health professionals&#x02019; (1) knowledge, (2)
self-efficacy, and (3) communication skills related to human health impacts of
climate change. Evaluation of this program can help to inform effective strategies
for preparing health professionals to understand and communicate the impacts of
climate change.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section2-23821205211061019"><title>Methods</title><sec id="section2A-23821205211061019"><title>The ECHO model</title><p>Project ECHO, launched in 2003, was designed to increase the capacity of health
professionals working in rural and urban underserved areas to provide better
care to their patients and communities where they live.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr25-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
</sup> ECHO is a virtual and synchronous learning program that freely shares
up-to-date best practices using case-based learning with the goal to improve
lives around the world. Today, the ECHO model is being used by more than 536
partners in 48 US states and 44 countries to address urgent public health
challenges, such as substance use disorder, chronic pain, diabetes, and autism.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr26-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
</sup> An estimated 461&#x02005;310 health professionals, public health experts,
teachers, and other professionals have received training and mentorship through
the ECHO model globally.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr27-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
</sup></p><p>The ECHO model is a cost-effective method for providing ongoing training and
mentorship for frontline health professionals.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr28-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
</sup> In ECHO programs, interprofessional experts (the &#x0201c;hub&#x0201d;) connect with
community-based or local members of a given workforce (the &#x0201c;spokes&#x0201d;) to learn
from and with one another. All knowledge is demonopolized and shared at no-cost.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr29-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
</sup> A plethora of research has demonstrated that the ECHO Model is successful
at bringing significant practice change to the participant health professional's
worksite to improve patient care.<sup><xref rid="bibr30-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="bibr31-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="section2B-23821205211061019"><title>CCHH ECHO series</title><p>The CCHH ECHO Series consisted of one cohort, meeting weekly for 75&#x02005;min, via a
virtual and synchronous platform. The weekly sessions were open to all health
professionals (physicians, nurses, public health professionals, community health
workers, etc). Each session consisted of 2 brief (15-25&#x02005;min) evidence-based
didactic lectures, including moderated question and answer sessions. In 5 of the
sessions, a simulated case was also included to match the session's content and
illustrate the relationship between climate change and health. Project ECHO's
staff entered evidence-based journal articles and other pertinent information
into the online platform chat box that the subject matter experts discussed
during the session presentations. Participants were offered an &#x0201c;opt-in&#x0201d;
community of practice directory at the end of the course, receiving the name and
contact information for other participants. Course presentation slides, video
recordings, and digital librarian resources were also made available each week
to the participants on the Project ECHO CCHH webpage. No-cost continuing
education units (CEU) were provided for each session. Course participants also
received a certificate of completion if they attended 75% of the sessions (6 out
of 8) in the series.</p></sec><sec id="section2C-23821205211061019"><title>Attendance and registration</title><p>Participants registered prior to the program via an online survey (REDCap secure
web application) and provided demographic information (gender, age,
race/ethnicity, location, and scope of practice). Attendance data were tracked
using reports generated by the Zoom platform. Unique attendees were defined as
people who attended at least once and for at least 10&#x02005;min. Registration and
attendance data were linked together using name and email. Geographic
information was mapped using QGIS Version 3.18.3 and natural breaks, using the
Jenks method, were used.</p></sec><sec id="section2D-23821205211061019"><title>Zoom poll</title><p>Beginning week 4 of the CCHH ECHO, participants were polled during sessions to
gauge their confidence and understanding. Questions were designed to assess
participants&#x02019; self-reported knowledge change, and included: &#x0201c;Today's session
increased my understanding of the role climate change plays in water- and
vector-borne diseases,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Today's session increased my confidence in my ability
to talk to others about the mental health effects of our changing climate,&#x0201d; and
&#x0201c;I feel more confident in discussing the human health effects of climate change
with my patients and others.&#x0201d; Response options ranged from strongly agree to
strongly disagree.</p></sec><sec id="section2E-23821205211061019"><title>Postsession evaluation</title><p>Following each session, participants were invited to complete a postsession
evaluation survey, linked to the acquisition of CEUs. Questions included whether
the objectives of the course were met, the content was evidence-based, and if
participants were able to ask questions to the SMEs. Additionally, participants
were asked if they are likely to use the knowledge they gained and if they felt
they were better able to communicate after the training. Response options ranged
from strongly agree to strongly disagree. Lastly, participants were asked (in a
free text field) what changes they might consider making to their practice after
the training. These responses were grouped into broad categories (eg, improve my
health education techniques; increase my climate change education to my
patients, etc). The 7 most common response categories are reported.</p></sec><sec id="section2F-23821205211061019"><title>Curriculum development: evidence-based didactics</title><p>The 8-week curriculum was developed by Joanna Katzman, MD, MSPH, Director of
Public Health Initiatives, ECHO Institute, and David Herring, MA, Chief of the
Communication and Education Division within the National Oceanic and Atmospheric
Association's (NOAA) Climate Program Office. The Co-Chairs of the US Global
Change Research Program's Interagency Working Group on Climate Change and Human
Health (CCHHG) gave input and feedback on the curriculum.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr32-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
</sup> Learning objectives for each week were created by answering the
questions: (1) What is the science of climate change?, (2) How does climate
change impact human health: biopsychosocially and with vulnerable populations?,
(3) What are the most common climate-related health risks and how are they best
managed?, (4) What are the current best adaptation practices related to extreme
weather events and disaster preparedness?, and (5) How can health professionals
improve communication with their patients and communities regarding climate
change and health?</p><p>This introductory course gave health professionals a better understanding of each
of these subjects, while suggesting to them that to gain expertise, the
complexity, skill, and knowledge associated with each topic will require more
study and practice.</p></sec><sec id="section2G-23821205211061019"><title>Curriculum development</title><sec id="section2G1-23821205211061019"><title>Case-based learning using standardized patients</title><p>Using the successes of medical simulation and standardized patients, 5
patient cases were developed as an integral part of the curriculum to both
illustrate the importance of climate change communication and to share
climate messaging strategies. Dr Katzman (the CCHH ECHO medical director)
collaborated very closely with the medical simulation lead at the University
of California, San Diego, John-Michael Maury (JMM). After Dr Katzman created
the 5 simulated patient cases, JMM worked with 5 different professional
actors to play the standardized patients. A mock session between one of the
hub team members (portraying the clinician) and the actor (portraying the
standardized patient) took place virtually the week prior to the live CCHH
ECHO session. During the CCHH ECHO, the standardized patient/actor connected
to the session as the ECHO patient in &#x0201c;full character.&#x0201d; The ECHO IT team
spotlighted both the standardized patient and the clinician to fully engage
the course participants.</p><p>Simulation has been defined as &#x0201c;a model of a set of problems that can be used
to teach someone how to do something.&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr33-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
</sup> Most postlicensure health professionals learn optimally and develop
self-efficacy from iterative presentations of content and case-based learning.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr34-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
</sup> The course participants in the CCHH ECHO benefitted from both
didactics and cases, with ample time to ask questions. Cases were also
developed to illustrate the diversity (people experiencing homelessness,
rural and urban, range of ethnicities, gender and ages, etc) of patients
seeking care for various climate related illnesses, and to model
communication strategies that health professionals might consider when
approaching a patient suffering from an illness provoked or worsened by the
climate. Because the hallmark of the ECHO model is clinician to clinician
telementoring with case-consultation, and patients are not part of the
network, medical simulation with standardized patients comes very close to
teaching best practices communication strategies with the Project ECHO
platform.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section3-23821205211061019"><title>Results</title><sec id="section3A-23821205211061019"><title>Curriculum</title><p>To meet the learning objectives, the 8-week series began with introductory
presentations on the science of climate change and the gaps in climate change
education and communication in the health professions (see <xref rid="table1-23821205211061019" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The second
week connected climate change to human health outcomes, including global
warming, extreme heat, and vulnerable populations. Weeks 3 through 7 addressed
air quality, excessive precipitation, water- and vector-borne disease, mental
health, extreme weather events, and disaster preparedness. Week 8 focused on the
importance of climate communication and future solutions, including health
professional advocacy and policy involvement. The rich contextual experience
offered in this introductory course followed the educational principles and
guidance provided by health and science, technology, engineering and math educators.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr35-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>
</sup></p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-23821205211061019"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Climate change and human health ECHO-series 1 presentations and simulated
cases.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_23821205211061019-table1" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Topics</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 17, 2021</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Gaps in Climate Change Education; The Science of
Climate Change</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 24, 2021</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Connecting Climate Change and Human Health
Outcomes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 3, 2021</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Global Warming, Extreme Heat, and Vulnerable
Populations</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 10, 2021</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Climate Change, Air Quality, and Respiratory
Illness</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 17, 2021</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Climate-driven Ecological Change and Water- and
Vector-borne Diseases</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 24, 2021</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Climate Change and Mental Health; Animal
Agriculture, Greenhouse Gas Emissions, and the Co-benefits
of a Plant-based Diet</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 31, 2021</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Extreme Events, Impacts to Healthcare
Facilities, and Disaster Preparedness</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 7, 2021</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Climate Change Communication and Future
Solutions</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Presentation</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Opening questions from &#x0201c;Patients&#x0201d;</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Climate communication strategies</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Case 1- Extreme Heat</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#x02005;yr old white male, mail carrier by profession brought to
urgent care for possible heat stroke</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>&#x0201c;What's happening to me? Am I going to be
okay?&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x0201c;It's so hot outside. What can I do to prevent
this from happening to me again?&#x0201d;</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Discuss extreme heat due to climate change.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Discuss how to prearrange for hydration, frequent
breaks, cooling stations, wide-brim hat.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Return to clinic if symptoms recur.</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Case 2- Urban Heat</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34&#x02005;yr old Hispanic mother of 4 with asthma, seasonal
allergies and fibromyalgia who lives in a large city near
freeway intersection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>&#x0201c;What is happening with my breathing? It is so
much worse lately.&#x0201d;</p><p>&#x0201c;I cannot seem to keep me or my family cool
enough, especially in the summer months.&#x0201d;</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Communicate the connection between climate and
air quality and heat.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Encourage clinic visits to improve asthma and
allergy control.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Discuss cooling strategies.</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Case 3- Air Pollution</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41&#x02005;yr old African American woman, history of asthma,
depression, anxiety, insomnia living near CA forest fire
region</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>&#x0201c;My breathing is worse and my stress level is
through the roof. Can you help me?&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x0201c;How do I know if the air outside is going to be
clear or not?&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x0201c;Why do you think my nerves and sleep are so much
worse lately?&#x0201d;</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Communicate the connection between climate and
air quality</p></list-item><list-item><p>Encourage clinic visits to improve asthma</p><p>Discuss behavioral health options</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Case 4- Mental Health</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#x02005;yr old white male firefighter with low back pain, PTSD,
insomnia, and increased stress aggravated by teenage
daughter's anxiety related to climate change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>&#x0201c;Why am I so irritable all of the time?&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x0201c;My daughter's obsessed with the fires and
climate change. She uses the computer all-day. How
can I help her?&#x0201d;</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Educate patient regarding PTSD symptoms and
encourage him to engage in self-care.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Encourage patient to engage daughter and learn
about climate change and possible solutions.</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Case 5- Hurricanes</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 year Native American male and member of the Choctaw
Nation, in Mississippi, with heart disease,
insulin-dependent diabetes and low back pain recently
experienced a local flood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>&#x0201c;What's going on with my stomach?&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x0201c;What can I do to better protect my family?&#x0201d;</p></list-item></list>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Discuss extreme weather events and associated
risks (water- and vector-borne diseases), offer
resources to consult.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Encourage patient to create an evacuation plan in
case of flood.</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section3B-23821205211061019"><title>Demographics and attendance</title><p>During the 8-week CCHH ECHO series, there was a total of 1838 attendances with
625 unique participants (see <xref rid="table2-23821205211061019" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). There was an average of 230
nonunique and 78 unique attendees joining each session. Nearly 7% of
participants attended all 8 sessions and a total of 41.5% of participants
attended regularly (3-8 sessions). Four hundred fifty-two (72.3%) of these
attendees had submitted registration information and the majority of
participants were women. Over half the participants were white, while almost 14%
of participants were Hispanic. Nearly half of the participants had terminal
degrees (MD, DO, or PhD) and participants were from around the globe, with 25
countries represented (see <xref rid="fig1-23821205211061019" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The majority of participants hailed from 45 of the US
states, most commonly New Mexico (95), where the program is located, along with
Western and Northwestern states including California (21), Oregon (29),
Washington (10) and Colorado (10); Southern states of Texas (15) and Louisiana
(12); and Northeastern states such as Connecticut (14), Maryland (17) and
Virginia (12). Roughly 13% (58) of participants resided in countries outside the
United States, most commonly from Canada (13), Austria (4), Argentina (4), Peru
(4), and Saint Kitts (4).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-23821205211061019"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Climate change and human health ECHO attendance by United State (a) and
country (b) among attendees with registration information, February 17,
2021 through April 7, 2021, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;452.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_23821205211061019-fig1" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="table2-23821205211061019"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Climate change and human health ECHO attendance and characteristics,
February 17, 2021 through April 7, 2021.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_23821205211061019-table2" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Number of sessions attended among all
participants, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;625</italic>
</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (8.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (8.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (6.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (6.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (6.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Characteristics among participants with
registration informations, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;452</italic>
</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Gender</italic>
</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (61.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (22.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonconforming</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (15.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Race/Ethnicity</italic>
</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">American Indian/Alaskan Native</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">African American/Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian/Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (6.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (13.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (53.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (4.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (12.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Scope of practice</italic>
</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical Doctor or Doctor of Osteopathic Medicine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (20.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse practitioner or physician assistant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (3.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (7.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PhD (all disciplines)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (28.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Masters Public Health</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (11.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community Health Worker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (3.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (10.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Country of origin</italic>
</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">394 (87.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outside of the United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (12.8)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section3C-23821205211061019"><title>Certificate of completion</title><p>The CCHH ECHO course offered a certificate for participants who completed at
least 75% (6 out of 8 sessions) of the course. Almost 17% (106 of the 625 unique
attendees) completed at least 6 of the CCHH ECHO sessions and within 1 week of
the course completion, each of these participants was sent a Certificate of
Completion.</p></sec><sec id="section3D-23821205211061019"><title>Postsession evaluation</title><p>The number of responses to the postsession evaluation each week ranged from 50
(78%) to 66 (85%) respondents out of an average of 78 unique attendees per
session (see <xref rid="table3-23821205211061019" ref-type="table">Table
3</xref>). The large majority of survey respondents reported that the
objectives of the training were met and that the sessions delivered balanced,
objective, and evidence-based content, and rated opportunities to ask questions
as very good or excellent. Additionally, participants reported that they
intended to apply the knowledge they acquired and that they were better able to
communicate with other interprofessional team members. The most common practice
change reported was that participants used skills they learned to improve their
climate-related health discussions with patients.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table3-23821205211061019"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Climate change and human health ECHO postsession evaluation responses,
February 17, 2021 to April 7, 2021, mean N&#x02009;=&#x02009;58.6.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_23821205211061019-table3" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Mean percent (range)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very good</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excellent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How well were the stated objectives met?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0-0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0-2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 (2-10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1 (28-46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.3 (52-65)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How well did the session deliver balanced and objective,
evidence-based content?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0-0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0-2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 (2-9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8 (23-34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8 (55-70)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How were opportunities to ask questions?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0-2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (0-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 (8-23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1 (24-41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8 (45-53)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strongly Disagree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disagree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strongly Agree</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I intend to apply the knowledge and/or skills I have
acquired from this activity to my work when in a team
environment.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0-0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0-2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (3-14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.1 (42-60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5 (34-55)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I am better able to communicate with other members of a
multidisciplinary team as a result of what I learned in this
activity.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0-0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0-2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 (2-17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9 (42-58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3 (33-53)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Changes that I am going to make in my
practice</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Response category</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Number (%) of responses</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Improve my health education techniques</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">104 (38.2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Increase my climate change education to my
patients</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">43 (15.8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Share climate change information with colleagues
and community</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">28 (10.2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Ask patients about climate change-related health
effects</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">20 (7.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">No changes</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">19 (6.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Not in clinical practice</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">19 (6.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Improved my climate change knowledge</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9 (3.3)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section3E-23821205211061019"><title>Zoom polls</title><p>An average of 123.3 (range: 114-137) participants responded to the polls during
weeks 4 through 8. Over 90% of participants reported that they strongly agreed
or agreed that the sessions increased their understanding of or confidence in
each session's topic (see <xref rid="fig2-23821205211061019" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The session on water- and vector-borne diseases and
climate change had the highest number of participants reporting that they
strongly agreed that the session increased their understanding. Participants
were more likely to report that they agreed (rather than strongly agreed) that
their confidence increased in all of the Zoom poll sessions. Only in the first 2
weeks of the polls did some of the participants (less than 10) respond that they
strongly disagreed. Beginning in week 6, the course facilitator explained the
answer key format before the zoom poll began and there were no longer any
&#x0201c;Strongly Disagree&#x0201d; responses.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2-23821205211061019"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Climate change and human health ECHO zoom polls, weeks 4 to 8.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_23821205211061019-fig2" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="section3F-23821205211061019"><title>Community of practice opt-in directory</title><p>A Community of Practice Opt-In Directory was offered to all participants in week
3 of the CCHH ECHO. Participants were given the opportunity to stay connected
with fellow participants after the CCHH ECHO session by filling out a
confidential survey listing their name, email address, and optional cellular
telephone number. During the last week of the CCHH ECHO, 55 participants (8% of
625 unique participants) who signed up for this directory were sent information
to their ECHO classmates as a method to connect with one another after the
course.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section4-23821205211061019"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="section4A-23821205211061019"><title>Success of the CCHH ECHO</title><p>This CCHH ECHO series proved to be highly satisfying for the vast majority of
health professionals who participated in the 8-week series. Strengths of the
CCHH ECHO include: (1) the large number of unique participants returning each
week from throughout the United States and abroad, (2) the bi-directional,
moderated question/answer sessions, (3) the simulated clinical climate change
cases, (4) the course certificate and community of practice options, and (5) the
benefits of a digital librarian. Some health professionals also identified areas
of improvement for this CCHH ECHO series. Suggestions included: allowing more
time for questions/answers, adding didactic presentations on climate and mental
health, sustainability and climate justice.</p></sec><sec id="section4B-23821205211061019"><title>The ECHO model: diffusion of knowledge, capacity building, and community of
practice</title><p>The postsession evaluations and zoom polls suggest that the goals of this 8-week
CCHH ECHO series (increasing health participant knowledge, confidence, and
communication) were successfully achieved. In light of the current climate
emergency, the ECHO Model is an invaluable platform for demonopolization and
effective diffusion of evidence-based knowledge to build capacity among
professionals, patients, and communities. The ECHO Model also has a strong
history of developing communities of practice and reducing feelings of isolation
among many health professionals.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr27-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
</sup> This may benefit health professionals seeking to expand their engagement
with communities and organizations addressing the health impacts of climate
change.</p></sec><sec id="section4C-23821205211061019"><title>Demographics and geographic distribution</title><p>The majority of participants were women, which is not surprising considering that
women are slightly more likely to be concerned about the environment compared to men.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr36-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
</sup> In terms of race and ethnicity, Hispanics/Latinos and African Americans
are more likely to be alarmed about climate change than Whites, however the
majority of participants in this CCHH ECHO were white.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr37-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
</sup> This may be reflective of the racial/ethnic distribution of the
healthcare field.</p><p>It is also possible that course participants, who reside in jurisdictions
(West/Northwest and Southeast) which have acutely been affected by extreme
weather events (wildfires and extreme precipitation), are participating in this
course in larger numbers.</p></sec><sec id="section4D-23821205211061019"><title>Curriculum: evidence-based didactics and case-based learning</title><p>The CCHH ECHO curriculum deliberately included both broad and more narrowly
focused elements critical for health professionals to best understand the
relationship between CCHH. The postsession survey and Zoom poll results suggest
that the majority of participants increased their knowledge and confidence in
the topics presented. They also reported that they plan to change their practice
based on the information learned in the CCHH ECHO sessions. Specifically, they
plan to communicate more with their patients, applying the knowledge they have
learned and the tools they have gained.</p><p>Live simulated cases between a health professional and a standardized patient
were part of 5 of the sessions. There are many benefits to simulation including
&#x0201c;practice of complex clinical situations; rehearsal of serious and&#x02044;or rare
events; rehearsal of planned, novel or infrequent interventions; and induction
into new clinical environments.&#x0201d;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr37-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
</sup> Use of simulation with standardized patients or public health scenarios
reduces risks to patients, communities, and learners. Educationally, simulation
supports principles of active learning, safe application of knowledge and
skills, and opportunity for iterative practice with feedback, incorporating
evidence-based knowledge within each case or scenario.<sup><xref rid="bibr38-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="bibr39-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup></p><p>The advantages of using simulated cases for the CCHH ECHO are numerous. The
cases: (1) can be adjusted for different types and levels of health
professionals, (2) can be modified to educate health professionals regarding how
to approach patients with varying levels of climate change knowledge and belief,
(3) can be shifted to benefit the specific geographic region and culture of the
population affected, and (4) the cases can be recorded and used for future
training sessions.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr29-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
</sup></p><p>Most ECHO programs include course participants sharing real, de-identified
patient cases. Therefore, creating simulated cases for the CCHH ECHO is a novel
adaptation of ECHO's successful case-based learning approach. Because patients
do not join ECHO sessions, the use of simulated cases allows for climate change
cases to be developed for a variety of health professionals as well as diverse,
rural, underserved, and disproportionately impacted populations globally.
Project ECHO has used simulated learning for many years in their MOCK ECHO
trainings, whereby health professionals can practice their skills repeatedly in
a safe environment before they launch a live ECHO session.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr40-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
</sup></p><p>There are many other complementary climate change educational offerings for
health professionals. These include a growing number of evidence-based,
peer-reviewed climate change, and environmental journal articles, webinars from
NOAA, CDC, the Medical Consortium on Climate and Health, Physicians for Social
Responsibility and other highly regarded organizations, as well as other
academic medical centers providing postlicensure trainings.<sup><xref rid="bibr41-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="bibr46-23821205211061019" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="section4E-23821205211061019"><title>Scaling up and moving forward</title><p>Due to the success of the 8-week CCHH ECHO series, the authors decided to launch
a weekly 60&#x02005;min CCHH ECHO &#x0201c;Continuous Conversation Office Hours,&#x0201d; beginning in
August 18, 2021. Changes to the original format include shortening each session
to 60&#x02005;min, allowing more time for questions and answers, and planning for
presentations on mental health, climate justice and environmental stewardship.
The authors are also planning to begin a similar program in India, in addition
to an 8 to 10 week &#x0201c;train the trainer&#x0201d; program, so that highly motivated health
professionals may deliver a climate change course at their own institution.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section5-23821205211061019"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Because the ECHO model is capacity-building, low-cost, and easy to deploy, the CCHH
ECHO has the potential to reach many thousands of people globally due to the
diffusion of knowledge between patients, colleagues, and communities. The human
health effects of climate change is a necessarily emerging field, and increasing
knowledge and communication skills among health practitioners is of critical
importance. Given the climate crisis, a robust climate and health curriculum is
needed in both pre and postlicensure settings for all health professionals. Future
CCHH ECHO telementoring programs may explore avenues to equip health professionals
with the competencies needed to teach climate-related health effects at their own
public health programs and healthcare institutions.</p><p>The findings and conclusions in this report are those of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the official position of the Centers for Disease Control and
Prevention.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to thank the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention for
review of the manuscript. The authors are grateful to Kent Norsworthy, our Project
ECHO digital librarian, to Shalin Prabhat Luitel, BA, BS at Project ECHO, for
creating the maps for the manuscript, and to Hunter Jones, PhD from the National
Oceanic Atmospheric Association for his thoughtful consultation.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>DECLARATION OF CONFLICTING INTERESTS:</bold> The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>FUNDING:</bold> The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or
publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> JGK created the idea for the program and the evaluation; JGK, DH, PH, LT, JMM
developed the curriculum and evaluation; LT, JL, BKD, JGK collected and analyzed
the data; JGK, DH, PS, LT, SK, CM, SA wrote and edited the article; JMM, BKD, JL
edited the article.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="bibr1-23821205211061019"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>IPCC, 2021</collab>. <comment>Sixth
Assessment Report, Climate Change 2021: the Physical Science
Basis</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/assessment-report/ar6/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ipcc.ch/assessment-report/ar6/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-23821205211061019"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>USGCRP</collab>, 2018:
<article-title>Impacts, risks, and adaptation in the United States: fourth
national climate assessment, volume II</article-title>: Report in Brief.
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Reidmiller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>Avery, CW, Easterling DR, Kunkel KE, Lewis KLM, Maycock
TK, et al</etal>. (eds.) <source>U.S. Global Change Research
Program</source>
<year>2018</year>, pp. <fpage>1515</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7930/NCA4.2018.RiB</pub-id>. Published by U.S. Government Publishing
Office Internet: bookstore.gpo.gov</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-23821205211061019"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>United Nations Development
Programme</collab>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>The Peoples&#x02019; Climate
Vote</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/librarypage/climate-and-disaster-resilience-/The-Peoples-Climate-Vote-Results.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/librarypage/climate-and-disaster-resilience-/The-Peoples-Climate-Vote-Results.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-23821205211061019"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spirandelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Broad threat to humanity from cumulative climate hazards
intensified by greenhouse gas emissions</article-title>. <source>Nature Clim
Change</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>8(12)</volume>:<fpage>1062</fpage>-<lpage>1071</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41558-018-0315-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-23821205211061019"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maibach</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahdoot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health professionals and the climate crisis:
trusted voices, essential roles</article-title>. <source>World Med Health
Policy</source>.
<year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wmh3.421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-23821205211061019"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rabin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laney</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Philipsborn</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The unique role of medical students in
catalyzing climate change education</article-title>. <source>J Med Ed Curric
Dev</source>. <comment>2020</comment>;7: pp1-7. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2382120520957653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-23821205211061019"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kotcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maibach</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Views of health professionals on climate change and health: a
multinational survey study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet
Health</source>. <comment>2021
May</comment>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e316</fpage>-<lpage>e323</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(21)00053-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33838130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-23821205211061019"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>American Medical
Association</collab>. <year>2020</year>. <comment>Doctors demand
presidential action on climate change</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ama-assn.org/delivering-care/public-health/doctors-demand-presidential-action-climate-change" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ama-assn.org/delivering-care/public-health/doctors-demand-presidential-action-climate-change</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-23821205211061019"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>American Public Health Association,
Climate Change</collab>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.apha.org/Topics-and-Issues/Climate-Change" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.apha.org/Topics-and-Issues/Climate-Change</ext-link>
(<year>2021</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-23821205211061019"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>American Academy of
Pediatrics</collab>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Climate Change and
Children's Health</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.aap.org/en-us/advocacy-and-policy/aap-health-initiatives/climate-change/Pages/Climate-Change-and-Childrens-Health.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.aap.org/en-us/advocacy-and-policy/aap-health-initiatives/climate-change/Pages/Climate-Change-and-Childrens-Health.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-23821205211061019"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>American Psychiatric
Association</collab>. <year>2019</year>. <comment>Climate change and mental
health connections</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.psychiatry.org/patients-families/climate-change-and-mental-health-connections" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.psychiatry.org/patients-families/climate-change-and-mental-health-connections</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-23821205211061019"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Canadian Public Health
Association</collab>. <year>2019</year>. <comment>Climate Change and Human
Health</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cpha.ca/climate-change-and-human-health" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cpha.ca/climate-change-and-human-health</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-23821205211061019"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Canadian Medical
Association</collab>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Climate change and
health</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cma.ca/climate-change-and-health" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cma.ca/climate-change-and-health</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-23821205211061019"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>World Medical Association</collab>.
<year>2019</year>. <comment>Physicians demand accelerated action on climate
change</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.wma.net/news-post/physicians-demand-accelerated-action-on-climate-change/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.wma.net/news-post/physicians-demand-accelerated-action-on-climate-change/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-23821205211061019"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>European Public Health
Alliance</collab>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>A green European Health Union
will ensure a healthy recovery from the pandemic</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://epha.org/a-green-european-health-union-will-ensure-a-healthy-recovery-from-the-pandemic/" ext-link-type="uri">https://epha.org/a-green-european-health-union-will-ensure-a-healthy-recovery-from-the-pandemic/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-23821205211061019"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Australian Medical
Association</collab>. <year>2019</year>. <comment>Climate change is a health
emergency</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://ama.com.au/media/climate-change-health-emergency" ext-link-type="uri">https://ama.com.au/media/climate-change-health-emergency</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-23821205211061019"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <comment>&#x0201c;Climate Change, Climate Justice,
and a Call for Action&#x0201d;. Articles, Abstracts, and Reports. 1279</comment>.
<ext-link xlink:href="https://digitalcommons.psjhealth.org/publications/1279" ext-link-type="uri">https://digitalcommons.psjhealth.org/publications/1279</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-23821205211061019"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jagals</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Core competencies for health workers to deal
with climate and environmental change</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ
Res Public Health</source>. <comment>2021 Apr
7</comment>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>3849</fpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18083849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33916887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-23821205211061019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Omrani O</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dafallah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paniello Castillo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Envisioning planetary health in every medical curriculum: an
international medical student organization's Perspective</article-title>.
<source>Med Teach</source>.
<year>2020</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1107</fpage>-<lpage>1111</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0142159X.2020.1796949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32757869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-23821205211061019"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lavey</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Teaching the health impacts of climate change in
many American higher education programs</article-title>. <source>Int J
Sustain Higher Educ</source>.
<year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/IJSHE-04-2018-0062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-23821205211061019"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blashki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Teaching about climate change in medical
education: an opportunity</article-title>. <source>J Public Health
Res</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>673</fpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/jphr.2016.673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27190980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-23821205211061019"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>VandeKieft</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Breaking bad news</article-title>. <source>Am
Fam Physician</source>.
<comment>2001</comment>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1975</fpage>-<lpage>1978</lpage>.
<comment>PMID: 11775763.
https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11775763/</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11775763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-23821205211061019"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lorenzetti</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Managing difficult encounters: understanding
physician, patient, and situational factors</article-title>. <source>Am Fam
Physician</source>.
<comment>2013</comment>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>419</fpage>-<lpage>425</lpage>.
<comment>PMID: 23547575.
https://www.aafp.org/afp/2013/0315/p419.html</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23547575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-23821205211061019"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Philipsborn</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheffield</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Osta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Climate change and the practice of medicine:
essentials for resident education</article-title>. <source>Acad
Med.</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACM.0000000000003719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32910006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-23821205211061019"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Outcomes of treatment for hepatitis C virus infection by primary
care providers</article-title>. <source>NEJM</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>364</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>2199</fpage>-<lpage>2207</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1009370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21631316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-23821205211061019"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalishman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dion</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Partnering urban academic medical centers and rural primary care
clinicians to provide complex chronic disease care</article-title>.
<source>Health Aff</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1176</fpage>-<lpage>1184</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2011.0278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-23821205211061019"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Project ECHO</collab>.
<year>2021</year>. <comment>ECHO Movement Overview Dashboard</comment>.
<ext-link xlink:href="https://hsc.unm.edu/echo/data-marketplace/interactive-dashboards/movement-overview.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://hsc.unm.edu/echo/data-marketplace/interactive-dashboards/movement-overview.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-23821205211061019"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hager</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hasselberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arzubi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Leveraging behavioral health expertise: practices and potential
of the project ECHO approach to virtually integrating care in underserved
areas</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>366</fpage>-<lpage>369</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.201700211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29446334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-23821205211061019"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Komaromy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalishman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katzman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duhigg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Demonopolizing medical
knowledge</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACM.0000000000000051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24280860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-23821205211061019"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Azuara Blanco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Creating a virtual community of practice: an evaluation of
ophthalmology-optometry project ECHO</article-title>. <source>Eye</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>32(12)</volume>:<fpage>1910</fpage>-<lpage>1911</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41433-018-0184-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30068927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-23821205211061019"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katzman</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fore</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Evaluation of American Indian health service training in pain
management and opioid substance use disorder</article-title>. <source>Am J
Pub Health</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1427</fpage>-<lpage>1429</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2016.303193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27196642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-23821205211061019"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>U.S. Global Research
Program</collab>. <year>2017</year>. <comment>Interagency Crosscutting Group
on Climate Change and Human Health (CCHHG)</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.globalchange.gov/about/iwgs/cchhg" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.globalchange.gov/about/iwgs/cchhg</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-23821205211061019"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Cambridge University
Press</collab>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Cambridge Dictionary</comment>.
<ext-link xlink:href="https://dictionary.cambridge.org/us/dictionary/english/simulation" ext-link-type="uri">https://dictionary.cambridge.org/us/dictionary/english/simulation</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-23821205211061019"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Perceived self-efficacy in cognitive development
and functioning</article-title>. <source>Educ Psychol</source>.
<year>1993</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/s15326985ep2802_3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-23821205211061019"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Points of view: a survey of survey courses: are
they effective?</article-title>
<source>Cell Biol Educ</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>137</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1187/cbe.05-01-0055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15917871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-23821205211061019"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leiserowitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maibach</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roser-Renouf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kotcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Climate change in the American mind: March 2018. Yale
University and George Mason University</source>. <publisher-name>Yale
Program on Climate Change Communication</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>.
https://climatecommunication.yale.edu/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Climate-Change-American-Mind-March-2018-1.pdf</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-23821205211061019"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ballew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maibach</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kotcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<source>Which racial/ethnic groups care most about climate change? Yale
University and George Mason University</source>. <publisher-name>Yale
Program on Climate Change Communication</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.
https://climatecommunication.yale.edu/publications/race-and-climate-change/</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-23821205211061019"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Issenberg</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGaghie</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petrusa</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee Gordon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scalese</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Features and uses of high-fidelity medical
simulations that lead to effective learning: a BEME systematic
review</article-title>. <source>Med Teach</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01421590500046924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16147767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-23821205211061019"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Case-based learning and its application in
medical and health-care fields: a review of worldwide
literature</article-title>. <source>J Med Educ Curric Dev</source>.
<comment>2016 Apr 27; Vol. 3</comment>, pp39-49. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4137/JMECD.S20377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-23821205211061019"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katzman</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Comerci</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Mock ECHO: a simulation-based medical education
method</article-title>. <source>Teach Learn Med</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>423</fpage>-<lpage>432</lpage>.
doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10401334.2018.1442719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29658798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-23821205211061019"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>National Oceanic and Atmospheric
Administration</collab>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Upcoming and archived
webinars</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.noaa.gov/education/resource-collections/education-at-home/upcoming-and-archived-webinars" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.noaa.gov/education/resource-collections/education-at-home/upcoming-and-archived-webinars</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-23821205211061019"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and
Prevention</collab>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Climate and Health Science
Webinar Series</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/climateandhealth/science-webinar-series.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/climateandhealth/science-webinar-series.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-23821205211061019"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>The Medical Society Consortium on
Climate &#x00026; Health, CME &#x00026; Webinars</collab>. <year>2021</year>.
<ext-link xlink:href="https://medsocietiesforclimatehealth.org/category/continuing-medical-education/" ext-link-type="uri">https://medsocietiesforclimatehealth.org/category/continuing-medical-education/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-23821205211061019"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Physicians for Social
Responsibility, Environment and Health</collab>. <year>2021</year>.
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.psr.org/issues/environment-health/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.psr.org/issues/environment-health/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-23821205211061019"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Yale School of Public
Health</collab>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Climate Change and Health
Certificate</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://ysph.yale.edu/cchcert/program/" ext-link-type="uri">https://ysph.yale.edu/cchcert/program/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46-23821205211061019"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Harvard University</collab>.
<year>2021</year>. <comment>The Health Effects of Climate Change</comment>.
<ext-link xlink:href="https://online-learning.harvard.edu/course/health-effects-climate-change?delta=1" ext-link-type="uri">https://online-learning.harvard.edu/course/health-effects-climate-change?delta=1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>