<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurpub</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The European Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1101-1262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-360X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8574576</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckab164.003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ckab164.003</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Parallel Programme</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>1.B. Round table: Biological, socioeconomic, legal and environmental health determinants in the COVID-19 pandemic</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC01210</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02610</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>1.B. Round table: Biological, socioeconomic, legal and environmental health determinants in the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>Organised by: EUPHA-IDC, EUPHA-LAW, EUPHA-INJ, WHO Venice Office</collab></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><collab>Chair persons: Elena Petelos (EUPHA-HTA), Lara Tavoschi (Italy)</collab><!--elena.petelos@med.uoc.gr--></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ckab164.003-cor1">Contact: <email>elena.petelos@med.uoc.gr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-10-20"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>31</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><issue-title>Supplement 14th European Public Health Conference Public health futures in a changing world</issue-title><elocation-id>ckab164.003</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Public Health Association. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is published and distributed under the terms of the Oxford University Press, Standard Journals Publication Model (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model">https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model</ext-link>)</license-p></license><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the COVID-19 pandemic or until permissions are revoked in writing. Upon expiration of these permissions, PMC is granted a perpetual license to make this article available via PMC and Europe PMC, consistent with existing copyright protections.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ckab164.003.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s3"><title>&#x02002;</title><p>COVID-19 represents a concrete global health threat that has resulted in exacerbated inequalities, threatening progress towards SDG3, and particularly SDG 3.8, i.e. UHC - leave no one behind. Underlying differences in terms of health and social care system organisation, service provision models and pre-existing epidemiological context have resulted in heterogeneous scenarios for burden of disease (BoD) distribution, both in terms of COVID-19-specific outcomes, and because of collateral damage, not only across, but also within countries and regions. Individual proximal factors such as age, gender, ethnicity, socioeconomic position, underlying comorbidities and perception of risk have contributed to increased individual risk of acquiring the infection and of developing severe disease complications, including death. In addition, systemic issues, i.e., individual financial capacity, legal status, and acute versus chronic care needs have affected access both to care and commodity. From the global health perspective, we are also witnessing determinants threatening sustainable development, with tremendous differences in terms of capacity to combat the disease and deploy disease control measures, as well as ensure financial stability, economic growth and societal resilience. Ensuring equitable allocation of test, vaccines and medicines, and the development of comprehensive strategies necessitates a deeper understanding of those at most at risk, with due protection to those most vulnerable across the world. A comprehensive approach to tackle all these challenges, whilst ensuring due consideration is paid to ethical and legal issues, necessitates sound understanding of determinants, vulnerability with systematic measurement and interdisciplinary, cross-sectoral collaboration. This RT will bring the perspective of academia, researchers and practitioners in the field, and NGOs, offering insights on emerging research, practice and strategies. It aims to broker dialogue, to identify key steps to counter the damaging effect of inequities to social cohesion and system resilience, and to inform policy making and global public health actions.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Key messages</title><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Biological, socioeconomic, legal and geographical determinants are at interplay, affecting the COVID-19 pandemic dynamics both in terms of immediate and delayed health outcomes.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Assessing and weighing the links of various determinants and COVID-19 is essential to inform current and future policy decisions towards attaining UHC and to ensure an equitable, resilient society.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>