<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The purpose of using an ecosophy to evaluate examples of language is to determine which narratives are aligned with the ecosophy and are therefore ecologically beneficial, and which ones are in conflict with the ecosophy and therefore considered harmful. Based on what we have so far observed in the findings discussed in this article, and also taking into account the findings reported in the literature, we propose the following preliminary recommendations (Rs) for communications around plastics and reuse.<list list-type="simple" id="j_jwl-2022-0017_list_002"><list-item id="j_jwl-2022-0017_li_005"><label>&#8211;</label><p>R1: An ecosophy should be explicitly drawn up and its tenets strongly foregrounded in proposed messaging strategies. In the case of our ecosophy and for our communicative purposes, this could lead to constructions such as: <italic toggle="yes">Let&#8217;s all work together to protect our environment</italic> [protection, systems thinking]; <italic toggle="yes">Being fair means securing a future for everyone</italic> [fairness, rights]; <italic toggle="yes">Thank you for thinking of others and bringing your reusable container</italic> [fairness, protection]; <italic toggle="yes">We all have a role to play in making sure plastics don&#8217;t reach our oceans</italic> [systems thinking, protection].</p></list-item><list-item id="j_jwl-2022-0017_li_006"><label>&#8211;</label><p>R2: In line with previous findings on framing and polarity, and keeping in mind the largely negative valence of consumer language related to plastics and ecological practices (see Corpus 2 <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> phrases), positively and negatively framed messages should be used mindfully. Positive messages are preferred for high-level, abstract purposes, with negatively framed messages kept for low-level, concrete actions. In the case of promoting reusable plastic packaging systems, this translates to a positive framing of the phenomenon of reuse, combined with a negative framing of concrete (non-)reuse actions, e.g. <italic toggle="yes">Reuse is the new recycling; don&#8217;t get caught out without your container!</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="j_jwl-2022-0017_li_007"><label>&#8211;</label><p>R3: Messaging strategy should be data-driven and tailored to the language of its target audience. In this study, we have identified discursive patterns indicating that both companies and consumers perceive institutions to be holding the key authority and power to make change in plastic packaging systems. This coincides with a narrative of impotence and hopelessness on the part of consumers. A tailored counter-narrative for a pro-reuse campaign might involve positive stories that subvert this view, e.g. <italic toggle="yes">Corporations need your permission to create plastic waste; why give it to them?</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Don&#8217;t wait for companies to act on plastics&#160;&#8211; you hold the power to make that change.</italic> When it comes to responsible brand management and in-store messaging, companies might opt to disrupt the <sc>corporation is a parent</sc> metaphor by emphasizing the customer&#8217;s agency and adulthood instead. This might sound like: <italic toggle="yes">Thank you for enabling us to do better</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">Should we switch to reuse? We&#8217;re waiting on you to give us the signal.</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="j_jwl-2022-0017_li_008"><label>&#8211;</label><p>R4: As supported by much of the literature, pro-environmental messaging should&#160;not be too forceful or assertive, unless it is safe to assume that the reader/hearer has already accepted the urgency of the problem. Our Corpus 1 analysis of <italic toggle="yes">our</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">customers</italic>) demonstrated that customers are currently used to being approached very gently with regard to their environmental responsibilities. To achieve our aims with circular packaging systems, we should be reminding citizens of reasons and opportunities to engage in reuse and encouraging their participation without promoting it too repetitively or aggressively.</p></list-item><list-item id="j_jwl-2022-0017_li_009"><label>&#8211;</label><p>R5: Narratives and stories, e.g. of empowerment, fairness, rights, and protection, should be prioritized over attempts to merely educate or convey &#8220;facts&#8221;. Facts are not nearly as salient in the minds of hearers and readers as stories, and we must first establish the stories being perpetuated in the public sphere before devising counter-stories that fit these mental models. Public &#8220;education&#8221; campaigns should therefore be centered around a prototypical story involving, e.g. a hero, an obstacle, and a path to victory. Such themes, or text worlds, can be encoded in relatively little text.</p></list-item></list>
</p>