<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par19">Governance for sustainable development is crucially deficient, characterized by fragmented policy implementation and deficiencies in stakeholder cooperation and engagement (Leal Filho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2016</xref>). Participation is a key factor when considering issues of sustainable development, specifically in relation to SDGs achievement (Glass and Newig <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>). Despite a lack of capacity at present, there is potential for multiple benefits from empowering communities and realizing meaningful community involvement through participatory models (Middlemiss and Parrish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2010</xref>). Participation of diverse societal actors in the governance of complex, long-term challenges such as the climate crisis can potentially make planning trade-offs and equity considerations clearer in policy design (Cavaleri Gerhardinger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2020</xref>). Such approach can enhance legitimacy and acceptability. Governance decisions arrived at through participatory processes are more likely to be acceptable to communities, in contrast to uneven outcomes typical of top-down governance. Jasanoff&#8217;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2018</xref>) &#8216;humble approach&#8217; to just energy transitions emphasizes a move away from traditional top-down command and control hierarchal governance models and argues for an explicit acknowledgement and prioritization of procedural justice principles in particular. Genuine participatory models to empower communities can result in policy and planning decisions that are more likely to be acceptable as well as more effective in the long-term (Garland et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2019</xref>; Heidkamp et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2021</xref>). Transdisciplinary action research is a promising avenue for collaborative learning and decision making in this context (Nicolescu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2002</xref>). Such an approach also calls for academic humility, necessitating a radical rethink on how scholars communicate academic knowledge to the public.</p>