<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0080">Different rights regimes and protections apply to CM and MR. Property rights and associated funding mechanisms underscore many MR efforts. For example, in the United States, people&#8217;s right to housing and property are recognized and protected through buyouts of individual properties (<xref rid="b0580" ref-type="bibr">Siders, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">Flavelle, 2019</xref>) and financing of relocation of entire villages (<xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Davenport and Robertson, 2016</xref>). Strategies employed elsewhere include the provision of social housing in the Philippines (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Carrasco et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Ajibade, 2019</xref>), government-provided interest-free loans in Vietnam (<xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Dun, 2011</xref>), allocation of farming plots in Rwanda (<xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Gebauer and Doevenspeck, 2015</xref>), and the purchase of land in foreign countries by Kiribati (<xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">Hermann and Kempf, 2017</xref>). While these incentives and mechanisms are not always satisfactory (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Carrasco et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Dun, 2011</xref>; Collins et al., 2017) and may exacerbate economic and social inequalities (<xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Farbotko and Lazrus, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Ajibade, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr">Mach et al., 2019</xref>), no recognition of property rights exists under CM. Instead, migrants struggle to have their rights to life and freedom of movement recognized. Many migrants face physical threats as they make the treacherous journey to cities or new countries. If they survive this journey, there is no compensation for losses related to climate impacts, no &#8216;officially designated&#8217; financial or economic assistances for resettlement, no guarantees of free entry into their preferred country of resettlement and certainly no right to citizenship even when granted entry (in the case of international CM).</p>