<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par8">To be sure, we have done some very exceptional things in the course of human history&#8212;for example, the move away from hunter-gatherer foraging to agriculture; the industrial revolution that transformed the means of production, communication, and transportation; the present digital technology revolution, with the stunning development and rapid advance of artificial intelligence and machine learning; and the emergence of the field of astrobiology, focusing on the origins and ultimately the future of life in the universe. As I am writing this paper, <italic>Perseverance</italic> is already beginning to collect rock and soil samples on Mars, searching for signs of ancient microbial life in the Jezero Crater. All of this is quite extraordinary when we stop to consider that it has been accomplished in a relatively brief span of time, the blink of an eye, when viewed geologically. But humans&#8217; remarkable progress in having dominion &#8220;over all the earth&#8221; carries with it an element of risk, which the writers of Genesis in retrospect could have made much more explicit &#224; la Greek mythology. For example, in our unrelenting quest to tame nature, sometimes for good reason while other times just because we can, in our quest to go to places in the solar system and beyond, where human beings have never gone before, we sometimes forget that for all our stunning technological achievements, we are still very much motivated by the more primitive forces of our biological hardwiring. All of this has prompted the biologist Wilson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2012</xref>) to issue a word of caution, if not a warning, in his important book, <italic>The Social Conquest of Earth</italic>: &#8220;We have created a Star Wars civilization, with Stone Age emotions, medieval institutions, and godlike technology. . we are terribly confused by the fact of our existence, and a danger to ourselves and to the rest of life&#8221; (p. 7).</p>