<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par10">Humans, in the relatively brief span of time we have walked the earth, have become a formidable evolutionary force to be reckoned with so that our global impact is &#8220;already on a par with that of ice ages and tectonic movements&#8221; (Harari, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2017</xref>, p. 73). Our impact on the planet, therefore, cannot be overstated, for it has ushered in nothing less than a new epoch of time: the <italic>Anthropocene</italic> age. It is an age characterized, first and foremost, by the rapid advance and flourishing of human civilization across the globe. But in our unbridled quest to have dominion over all the earth, we have not been mindful enough of the consequences of our collective actions, of how the extinction crisis and the steep decline of species, in particular the loss of other mammals, has largely been of our own making. In fact, it is now being said that evolution cannot keep up with us:<disp-quote><p id="Par11">Humans will cause so many mammal species to go extinct in the next 50 years that the planet&#8217;s evolutionary diversity won&#8217;t recover for 3 to 5&#160;million years, a team of researchers has found. The earth may be entering its sixth mass extinction: an era in which the planet&#8217;s environments change so much that most animal and plant species die out. The International Union for the Conservation of Nature predicts that 99.9% of critically endangered species and 67% of endangered species will be lost within the next 100 years. The five other times a mass extinction has occurred over the past 450&#160;million years, natural disasters were to blame. But now, human activity is killing mammal species.. .. Scientists from Aarhus University in Denmark calculated how fast extinctions are happening, and how long it would take for evolution to bring Earth back to the level of biodiversity it currently has. The scientists concluded that in a best-case scenario, nature will need 3&#8211;5&#160;million years to get back to the level of biodiversity we have on Earth today. Returning to the state Earth&#8217;s animal kingdom was in before modern humans evolved would take 5&#8211;7&#160;million years. (Kotecki, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>)</p></disp-quote></p>