<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Community Dev J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Community Dev J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cdj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Community Development Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0010-3802</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1468-2656</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8436391</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cdj/bsab028</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bsab028</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC00010</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Community development and social work teaching and learning in a time of global
interruption</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>Deborah</given-names></name><!--d.lynch@uq.edu.au--><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lathouras</surname><given-names>Athena</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Forde</surname><given-names>Catherine</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><italic toggle="yes">Address for correspondence:</italic> Deborah Lynch, School of
Nursing, Midwifery and Social Work, University of Queensland, St Lucia, Brisbane, Queensland
4072, Australia; email: <email>d.lynch@uq.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-08-03"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><elocation-id>bsab028</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Oxford University Press and Community Development Journal. 2021
All rights reserved. For permissions, please email:
journals.permissions@oup.com</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is published and distributed under the terms of the Oxford University
Press, Standard Journals Publication Model (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model">https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model</ext-link>)</license-p></license><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the COVID-19 pandemic or until permissions are revoked in writing. Upon expiration of these permissions, PMC is granted a perpetual license to make this article available via PMC and Europe PMC, consistent with existing copyright protections.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bsab028.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>In a rapidly changing and unpredictable global environment, there is new impetus to draw on
community development approaches in the face of complex practice challenges that include the
long-term impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic. As social work and community development educators
in Ireland and Australia, the question becomes how can we respond in a time of major
&#x02018;disruption&#x02019; where there are both opportunities and constraints? This paper
settles on this pause and uncertainty to seek new approaches to prepare social work students
for changing conditions. Long-standing questions re-surface in relation to social, economic,
political and environmental structures and conditions that are located in a neoliberal
framework. The paper explores challenges and opportunities facing educators and social work
students through a core set of principles&#x02014;critical, relational and connected&#x02014;that
underpin our community development pedagogy. Within these themes, we explore teaching practices
which seek to create a &#x02018;Community of Learners&#x02019;, generate a process of
collaborative critical inquiry, engage students in reflective praxis enriched by contemporary
theory and research, and foster a deep, connected and adaptive perspective on global and local
issues. This stimulates creativity and meets the need for critical and adaptable practitioners
capable of practical action through this period of disruption and crises of governance, climate
and technologies of the future.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="21"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>article-lifecycle</meta-name><meta-value>PAP</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>In the contemporary socio-geopolitical environment, there is impetus to innovate and adapt
pedagogical practices. Social work educators are seeking to empower a new generation of
practitioners who are adaptable to changing conditions and circumstances and are critical
thinkers, capable of practical action in disrupted times. This paper focuses on social work
knowledge, practice and pedagogies to explore some new spaces, and on opportunities as well as
constraints in preparing social work students for the contemporary practice context. The link
between social justice and environmental and community sustainability is a central theme and
connects to developments in social work education internationally (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Beltr&#x000e1;n, Hacker and Begun, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Papadopoulos, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Naranjo, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Ranta-Tyrkk&#x000f6; and N&#x000e4;rhi, 2021</xref>). We are in an
era of geopolitics and currently in the midst of new challenges as we face the repercussions of
a global pandemic and an impending climate emergency. Community development writers urge
immediate action to respond to these challenges drawing on a community development approach
(<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Ife, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Kenny,
2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Meade, 2020</xref>). Social work academics and
educators have long argued that social workers play a crucial role in working with groups and
communities using fundamental practice principles of community empowerment and social and
environmental justice (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Forde and Lynch, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Bay,
2020</xref>).</p><p>In the contemporary &#x02018;disrupted&#x02019; conditions, deep concerns such as crises of
governance, a changing climate and the use of technologies come to the fore, and these are
developing areas for practice, education and research in both social work and community
development. As university educators who teach community development on social work programmes
in Irish and Australian universities, we draw on these critical themes and our own pedagogical
practices developed over many years to advance conversations about community development
teaching and learning in the contemporary context. In this paper, we focus on principles and
pedagogies that can enable us to attune social work education to this changing practice context.
We examine a set of principles that underpins our community development pedagogy and demonstrate
how we seek to generate a process of collaborative critical inquiry, engage students in
reflective praxis enriched by contemporary theory and research, and facilitate &#x02018;going
deeper&#x02019; on global and local issues in a connected and adaptive way. Grounding social work
teaching and learning in values such as social justice and human rights, critical thinking and
working collectively advances dynamic, innovative forms of practice that can respond to
community and societal issues.</p><p>The broader context of our paper is a contemporary one: the global pandemic. While we
acknowledge the complexity of the global, regional and local forces that underlie and propel
significant practice challenges, our focus is to seek opportunities in this COVID-19
&#x02018;interruption&#x02019; to prepare social work students for changing conditions and revisit
some long-standing questions that re-surface in these times. Attuning social work education to
current conditions begins with key themes that are emerging in contemporary international
scholarship around a changing climate, governance (the dominant neoliberal discourse and
authoritarian regimes/conflict and intrusions), technologies for the future, the critical
circumstances of a global pandemic and the interconnections between these themes. This
scholarship articulates urgent and substantial challenges facing both social work and community
development (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Ife, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Fong <italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Kenny, 2020</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>A &#x02018;perfect storm&#x02019;: 21st century social work</title><p>As we enter a new decade, social work faces a perfect storm of challenges. These wide-ranging
issues&#x02014;socio-economic, political, cultural, environmental, educational and
technological&#x02014;have been discussed at some length in the social work and wider literature.
In this section, we seek to identify key aspects of these issues and discuss the social work
response.</p><sec id="sec3"><title>Socio-economic, political, cultural and environmental challenges</title><p>Since the turn of the millennium the world has experienced a set of crises that have
threatened social and economic stability. The <xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">World Economic
Forum (2021)</xref> lists the highest impact risks of the next decade as infectious diseases,
climate action failure and other environmental risks; livelihood crises, debt crises; weapons
of mass destruction and IT infrastructure breakdown. Additional and related challenges include
growing gender and racial inequality (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Elliott,
2021</xref>).</p><p>Social work writers have identified the significance of these entrenched problems for social
work policy and practice. <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Healy (2017)</xref> posits that
&#x02018;the profession&#x02019;s engagement in global processes and policy dialogs&#x02026;is
essential&#x02019; and suggests that social workers should engage both as individuals and via
organizations such as the International Association of Schools of Social Work (IASSW), the
International Council on Social Welfare (ICSW) and the International Federation of Social
Workers (IFSW). <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Maglajlic and Ioakimidis (2020</xref>, p.
1941) stress that the &#x02018;need for social workers who are confident advocates for human
rights and social change is becoming even more important&#x02019;.</p><p>In a provocative piece, <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Maylea (2020)</xref> isolates a
number of key problems to which social work has to face up. These include historical
&#x02018;stains&#x02019; (p. 9) from social work&#x02019;s paternalistic past and a failure to
meet &#x02018;contemporary challenges&#x02019; (p. 11), including climate change and justice,
racism and gender inequality. Maylea calls social work &#x02018;paternalistic&#x02019; due to its
historical involvement in racial oppression of First Nations people in Australia, New Zealand,
the USA and Canada, and perpetuation of exclusionary treatment of these communities. He argues
that &#x02018;by staying very still and moving very slowly&#x02019; (p. 11) social work has
failed to make a significant contribution to addressing contemporary challenges like climate
change and race and gender inequality. Maylea&#x02019;s ideas have provoked a spirited response
in defence of social work (see <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Garrett, 2021</xref>), and we
seek to contest this framing as &#x02018;failures&#x02019; and recast them as future challenges
for the profession.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Educational and technological challenges</title><p>In an educational context, social work authors note some adverse impacts of neoliberalism on
social work university education in Australia and internationally. Neoliberal approaches to
education promote individual success in an economy that rewards competition, self-interest and
self-reliance, undermining the critical and emancipatory vision of higher education (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Evans, 2020</xref>). In Australia, these impacts are evident
through the alignment of universities with the national government&#x02019;s performance-based
funding model (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Tehan, 2019</xref>) and the pursuit of
&#x02018;employability&#x02019;, &#x02018;job-ready graduates&#x02019; and &#x02018;career and
future focused&#x02019; teaching.</p><p>Technology is playing a growing role in the social and caring professions (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">Salman, 2018</xref>). There are emerging concerns about the
commercialization of education and the rapid growth of a profitable &#x02018;Ed-tech&#x02019;
industry in the COVID-19 situation due to the expeditious transition to online education (<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Williamson <italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2020</xref>). These
authors highlight the need for a stronger critique and research into &#x02018;pandemic
pedagogy&#x02019; so that changes to teaching and learning systems can be located within
&#x02018;the broader political economy of the COVID pandemic, its antecedents and long-term
consequences&#x02019; (p. 108). Most notably, these changes have occurred in the context of
pre-existing digital &#x02018;disparities&#x02019; in access, use and knowledge of information
and communication technologies (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Rigney, 2017</xref>).</p><p>We now turn to examine social work&#x02019;s responses to changing conditions.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Social work responses</title><p><xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Maylea&#x02019;s (2020)</xref> assertion that social work has
done little to address the long-standing and intractable problems that confront it and that
&#x02018;the profession of social work has continued to focus on parochial issues of the last
century and avoiding the reckoning demanded by this one&#x02019; (2020, p. 2) is problematic in
two principal ways. Firstly, it fails to acknowledge long-standing radical, critical and
eco-critical (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">N&#x000e4;rhi and Matthies, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Maglajlic and Ioakimidis, 2020</xref>) perspectives in social work
theory and practice that seek to effect social and environmental justice outcomes. Further,
Maylea&#x02019;s statement is contradicted by the development within the last 10 years of a
number of significant strategies that seek to position social work at the centre of responses
to several of the key challenges facing the globe. Let us examine the evidence.</p><p>The wicked problems of growing socio-economic inequality and climate change led to the
establishment of the UN Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) in 2015, but also prompted a
response from national and international social work organizations. Prior to the development of
the SDGs, the International Association of Schools of Social Work (IASSW), the International
Council on Social Welfare (ICSW) and the International Federation of Social Workers (IFSW) had
already established the Global Agenda for Social Work and Social Development (2012). The Global
Agenda, which was re-imagined in 2020, seeks to promote global social justice based on social
work and social development values. In March 2021, the IFSW and the United Nations Research on
Social Development agency (UNRISD) called for a new global social contract based on
&#x02018;solidarity, social cohesion and the need to work together&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">IFSW, 2021</xref>, online). Some national social work associations
have identified concomitant sets of agendas for the profession. National responses include the
12 &#x02018;grand challenges&#x02019; for social work developed by the American Academy of Social
Work and Social Welfare (AASWSW) (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Fong
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2018</xref>). The challenges span individual and family
issues such as promotion of the healthy development of young people and eradication of domestic
violence; social and community concerns such as the eradication of social isolation, ending
homelessness and creating social responses to a changing environment; and societal challenges
including reducing extreme economic inequality and achievement of equal opportunity and
justice. National developments elsewhere include the launch in February 2021 of the Irish
Association of Social Workers&#x02019; (IASW) inaugural Social Work Anti-Racism Strategic
Plan.</p><p>The Global Agenda emphasizes the need for social work practice grounded in the values of
social and economic equality, dignity and worth of peoples, environmental sustainability and
strengthening human relationships (<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Truell and Jones,
2015</xref>). These values are both universal and holistic and underscore the need for social
work ideas and practice that cross local and national boundaries and address issues in a global
context. This positioning of social work at the nexus of the local and global is emphasized by
<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Healy (2017</xref>), <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Garrett (2021)</xref> and <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Lombard and Viviers (2020)</xref>
who point out that social work needs to consider &#x02018;its local&#x02013;global obligation and
commitment to people and the planet, towards policy advocacy, development and
implementation&#x02019; (p. 2268).</p><p>Rather than privileging macro over micro, the Global Agenda points to the symbiosis between
the two. Local actions can have global impact, the experiences of groups or communities in one
part of the world can have resonance elsewhere, and many key issues exceed national borders.
One of the impacts of this &#x02018;glocal&#x02019; perspective is the deprivileging of
previously dominant Western ideas and the indigenization of knowledge and practices. Another is
that to be effective social work needs to operate on a glocal basis, taking both local and
global circumstances into account and seeking to influence policy in both spheres.</p><p>The idea of the &#x02018;connectedness&#x02019; of the local and global leads us to a
consideration of the importance of human relationships, which are fundamental to building and
maintaining sustainable connections. A theme common to the Global Agenda and much social work
literature is the need to place human relationships at the centre of action. As Garrett
expresses &#x02018;we live in an interconnected world that can only be economically and
relationally sustained if we are collectively committed to socialist ethics and values rooted
in interdependency, mutual caring and solidarity&#x02019; (2021, p. 15).</p><p>Developing human relationships refers to a number of activities. In the first place, it
refers to the interpersonal relationships between workers and service users and between workers
themselves. <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Gillinson (2017)</xref> writes about
&#x02018;incentivising a new balance between risk management and relational support&#x02019; (no
page number) and advocates a focus on preventative, empathetic and creative approaches. Equally
important is the reality that meaningful human relationships facilitate social work advocacy
and intervention in the policy process. <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Healy (2017)</xref>
reminds us that social workers can &#x02018;be the bridge&#x02019; (p. 13) between the
individuals and groups with whom they work and decision-makers. In order to occupy this bridge
social workers need to engage with communities &#x02018;in the initial (re)claiming and
(re)framing of problems, rather than during the later policy making stages&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Barretti, 2019</xref>, p. 39). Social workers&#x02019; engagement
with policy-making processes needs to be built from the bottom up and not from the top down. It
is through connecting with and understanding services users&#x02019; experiences that social
workers can identify and sketch paths to policy engagement and influence, not through
identifying policy as something objective, separate and &#x02018;other&#x02019;. This crucial
aspect of practice has become apparent during the COVID-19 pandemic when evidence suggests that
social and community workers across the globe have worked to develop systems, networks and
supports for communities in crisis, prompting the suggestion that social work is
&#x02018;returning to its community-based roots&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">Truell, 2020</xref>, online).</p><p>Turning now to the educational context, the changing teaching and learning environment has
led to a call to reinvigorate critical pedagogy (with its deep roots in critical theory)
&#x02018;to counter the subordination of social work education and practice to market demands
and public austerity&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Morley
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2020</xref>, p. 1). As community development educators, we
have rich, critical pedagogical traditions to draw on in shaping teaching and learning
practices.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Critical, relational and connected: Towards a community development pedagogy</title><p>A number of key themes emerge from social work&#x02019;s &#x02018;perfect storm&#x02019; and the
contemporary debates about social work and community development. For us, the central question
is: what can community development knowledge and ideas bring to these enduring and new
challenges facing social work? The contemporary context grounds and advances our thinking as
educators, and we now move to discuss a core set of principles and ideas that underpin our
community development teaching and learning in social work programs. Firstly, we draw on the
groundwork of theorists who articulate critical and eco-critical perspectives in contemporary
social work theory and practice. Secondly, we recognize the importance of relational practices
with individuals, groups and communities to build purposeful relationships for social change
that are mutual and interdependent. Thirdly, we recognize the solidarity that emerges from the
&#x02018;connectedness&#x02019; of the local and global.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>A critical pedagogy</title><p>Internationally, there is renewed focus on critical pedagogies to &#x02018;reinvigorate social
work education as an emancipatory practice&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Morley
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2020</xref>, p. 1). At a meta-theoretical level, we lean
towards a critical realist perspective because it is community orientated and encompasses a
range of transformative theoretical approaches and practices (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Forde and Lynch, 2015</xref>). We argue that this perspective broadens the scope of practices
for transformative social change. It challenges the polemic of ideology versus practice which
supports conditions for a reflective praxis, i.e. the integration of theory, research and
practice in social work education. It seeks to uncover oppressive structures and fully
recognizes the role of critical thinking and purposeful actions to tackle oppression and
activate meaningful change with groups and communities. We align with Brookfield&#x02019;s
critical pedagogy which is located in the tradition of critical social theory. This approach
demonstrates the clear connections between critical theorizing, analysis and critical reflection
in teaching and learning which emphasizes human agency and underpins actions for social change
(<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Brookfield, 2005</xref>; see <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Morley, 2020</xref>).</p><sec id="sec8"><title>Connecting theory, analysis and critical reflection</title><p>The role of critical reflection to deconstruct power in practice is crucial and influences
our pedagogy. Drawing on the work of Hannah Arendt, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Bay&#x02019;s (2020)</xref> analysis elucidates the place of critical reflection as part of
critical situated thinking that can be taught to students to raise their awareness of self and
develop others&#x02019; reference points or frameworks. This is a means to identify dominant
discourses in meaning-making, disrupt assumptions, rethink categories of
&#x02018;identity&#x02019; and reflect on the ways power is operating (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Bay, 2020</xref>). Drawing on Arendt, Bay makes the point that &#x02018;no-one is
tied to their identity in order to be included in politics; rather, political action asks us
not &#x0201c;what&#x0201d; we are but &#x0201c;who&#x0201d; we are&#x02019; (p. 448) in
participating and acting collectively. It is a pedagogy that promotes situated critical
thinking and political action as a consequence. An example of this is the &#x02018;Black Lives
Matter&#x02019; movement where people of all ethnic and racial identities join together to
protest injustice in the wake of the police killing of George Floyd in Minnesota (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Fisher, 2020</xref>).</p><p>For us, this critical positioning informs the importance of creating a &#x02018;Community of
Learners&#x02019; in the classroom where we work with students to co-construct safe and
supported learning spaces. We draw on the idea of co-creating &#x02018;brave spaces&#x02019;
which <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Arao and Clemens (2013)</xref> describe as
&#x02018;intentional places for activating curiosity, critical thinking and pursue
&#x0201c;challenging dialogues&#x0201d; about power, oppression, privilege and justice&#x02019;
(p. 149) within the learning environment. Our approach also seeks to empower students to
challenge injustices such as racism and sexism in their future practices as social workers.
Writing in the context of neoliberal policies and structures in India, <xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">Yvas (2021)</xref> argues that pedagogies that reignite political analysis are
urgently needed to respond to issues facing communities such as poverty, internal displacement
and migration. Likewise, we seek to demonstrate how critical and intellectual engagement in the
classroom can lead to practical actions for social change (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Forde and Lynch, 2015</xref>). Methodologies such as political story telling underpinned by a
critical pedagogy offer tools for educators (see <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Bay,
2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Marlowe and Chubb, 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Methodological tools in the classroom</title><p>Here we offer some examples of how we apply these methodologies in the classroom. For
example, social work students in one community development course at The University of
Queensland use political storytelling drawing on &#x02018;Poverty finds a Voice&#x02019;, which
is a woman&#x02019;s participatory theatre project in Melbourne in Australia (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Landvogt, 2012</xref>). The story is about a group of women who
perform a series of plays to an audience of bankers and policy makers about living on low
incomes, and of &#x02018;not having enough money to live with dignity&#x02019; (p. 55). The story
draws on Paulo <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Freire&#x02019;s critical pedagogy
(1972)</xref> and Augusto <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Boal&#x02019;s Theatre of the
Oppressed (1979)</xref> to identify and collectively analyse how change to transform
relationships of power and oppression can occur. In a group presentation assignment, one social
work student group brought this story to life. They engaged the class in an outdoor
&#x02018;theatre&#x02019; experience drawing on some of their own experiences of financial
struggle in their performance inviting class participation as &#x02018;spect-actors&#x02019; to
engage in a critical and collaborative problem-solving process.</p><p>Another example of the use of political and cultural methodologies in learning about
community development is demonstrated by a group of social work students who engaged in a
walking conversation (&#x02018;Defying Boundaries Walk&#x02019;) which is the walk from Boundary
Street in Spring Hill to Boundary Street in West End in Brisbane, Queensland that marks the
former borders enforced by policies of exclusion towards Aboriginal Australians that existed
until 1967. The students posed the question &#x02018;what can we do to contribute to
reconciliation on an everyday level?&#x02019; They aimed to educate and break down barriers
between Indigenous and non-Indigenous Australians. They walked, conversed with passers-by and
captured key words and ideas on a communing board. Touraine&#x02019;s work on social activism
reinforces this idea of human agency where civil society actors engage in social change
practices which may be cultural rather than overtly political (see <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Ottman and Noble, 2020</xref>). With a focus on climate change, social work
students at University College Cork engaged in critical reflection by walking through their
neighbourhoods and answering a series of pre-determined questions about what they saw there, in
environmental, social and economic terms. In class the students shared their reflections in
small groups and explored the implications of climate change for social work practice across
the three domains.</p><p>We are aware of a geopolitical turn in social work education and the need for urgent
responses to a changing climate and the adverse and ongoing devastating impacts of climate
change on human well-being and livelihoods in countries throughout the world. These approaches
recognize the interconnections between social work and the natural environment in definitions
and agendas (see <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">IFSW, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Truell and Jones, 2015</xref>) and integrate critical awareness, knowledge and
impetus to pursue social and environmental action into social work education. As educators, we
are interested in current theoretical developments in social work that seek shifts at the
ontological level and are beginning to re-shape fundamental practice understandings. These
approaches include Heather <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Boetto&#x02019;s transformative
ecosocial work model (2017)</xref> and Indigenist ontologies (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Martin, 2008</xref>) that are characterized by understandings of the
interdependence of humans and the natural world, and community sustainability. We define
sustainability in a community development context as working with people at local, regional and
global levels to reconnect, restore, repair and regenerate life-sustaining global ecosystems
which are vital to support health, well-being, empowerment and the livelihoods of communities
(<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Lynch, 2020</xref>). Ecosocial approaches are beginning to
influence social work interventions, driven by practitioner awareness and connection to the
environment at personal and political levels (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Boetto
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2020</xref>). While actions remain at individual level, this
movement foreshadows collective responses to tackle environmental injustices at group,
community, structural and policy levels. Aligned with this new emphasis on ecosocial work
models and the role of social workers in environmental practices with communities, we
incorporate practice scenarios in the classroom. For example, we discuss a scenario where a
rural social worker engages with members of the community to explore their deep concerns about
changes in the environment. The social worker provides support to a community group formed to
research how the biodiversity of their region could be restored (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Ramsay and Boddy, 2017</xref>). Another contemporary example for use in the
classroom is the Australian &#x02018;Buy from the Bush&#x02019; campaign which connects people
living in urban and rural communities to support economic sustainability (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Buy from the Bush Queensland, 2018</xref>). In this way, we aim to pursue a
critical pedagogy which draws on contemporary themes and instils collaborative thinking and
deep critical inquiry as well as reflective praxis enriched by contemporary research, practice
and theory into the social work curriculum.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>A relational pedagogy</title><p>Processes of collective, critical and reflective analysis can drive practical actions for
change. We now move to explicitly recognize the importance of relational practices with
individuals, groups and communities to build purposeful relationships for social change that are
mutual and interdependent.</p><sec id="sec11"><title>Understandings of &#x02018;relational&#x02019;</title><p>Our understandings of &#x02018;relational&#x02019; are linked to Samkange&#x02019;s theory of
<italic toggle="yes">Ubuntu</italic>, which informs a decolonized pedagogy that resists dominant Western
models of education and promotes an African (political) philosophy that is relational:
&#x02018;we become human through others&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Samkange and
Samkange, 1980</xref>; <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Mugumbate, 2020</xref>, p. 419).
Notably, Ubuntu was the theme of the 2021 World Social Work Day. This idea is expressed more
completely as &#x02018;I am because we are, and since we are, therefore I am&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Mbiti, 1969</xref>, p. 106). The philosophy places value on the
principles of collectivity, mutual support and communalism which we seek to reflect in our
teaching practice. We also link &#x02018;relational&#x02019; to the Indigenist ontology of
&#x02018;relatedness&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Martin, 2008</xref>) where
relatedness does not only refer to people but the relationship between People and Climate, or
People and Land and includes accountability within these relationships. Of significance here is
that all experiences are tied to relatedness, irrespective of contexts.</p><p>We cannot separate the relational and critical so we now move to explore what we term a
&#x02018;critical-relational&#x02019; approach. The nexus between the two terms explores how we
build purposeful, meaningful and helpful relationships with people, whilst coming from a
&#x02018;critical&#x02019; standpoint. Through relational practices and a process of dialogue
with groups and communities, trust, mutuality and respect is central to praxis, and oppressive
structures and practices in society are critically examined to find more egalitarian,
supportive and sustainable alternatives (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Freire, 1972</xref>;
<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Ledwith, 2011</xref>). A critical-relational paradigm
insists social workers avoid doing things &#x02018;to&#x02019; community members/citizens, or
&#x02018;for&#x02019; them such as when in a service role, but rather works &#x02018;with&#x02019;
participants, enabling a journey of community-led support and change. In this regard, social
work is a &#x02018;bottom-up&#x02019; practice that is led by the people with whom we are
working.</p><p>This kind of relational approach is modelled and applied in a university context when drawing
on community development approaches. Research reported by <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Lathouras (2020)</xref> sought to investigate if the university context could be a site for
developing a sense of &#x02018;community&#x02019; for international students whose well-being,
learning outcomes and retention were being compromised by a commodified education system. Using
Paulo <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Freire&#x02019;s (1972)</xref> critical consciousness
through dialogue approach, students were brought together and exposed to a social learning
agenda that enabled them to perceive social, political and economic contradictions and
collectively support each other to respond to the issues they were facing. The 2-year
action-research project resulted in the creation of a peer support program (called Dialogue
Circles) that enabled a community-oriented and inclusive co-learning environment for students
in a cross-cultural classroom. The research demonstrated that a university perceived to be more
like a &#x02018;community&#x02019; supports students&#x02019; academic, cultural, emotional and
social connectedness needs and translates into positive educational outcomes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec12"><title>A connected pedagogy</title><p>We recognize the solidarity that emerges from in the &#x02018;connectedness&#x02019; of the
local and global, and our pedagogy aims to foster student perspectives on local and global
issues with an approach that is connected and adaptive. We support students to be more
&#x02018;connected to the world&#x02019; and each other as learners and emerging professionals.
Here, we link with existing scholarship that positions social work at the nexus of the local and
global to expand opportunities for a connected form of practice. We seek to enable students to
engage with civil society actors (individuals, groups, communities and organizations) and
develop policy responses for social change across local, state, regional and international
borders.</p><p>Our pedagogy embeds course content that makes significant connection to contemporary or
emerging social issues or trends at local and global levels. <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Ife (2019</xref>, p. 9) argues we are living at a time of significant change and multiple
crises&#x02014;ecological, economic, social and political. Globalization and neoliberal ideology
have together created a global economy that is inequitable, unsustainable and has created
&#x0201c;obscene levels of inequality&#x0201d; (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Ife,
2019</xref>, p. 9). The current Coronavirus pandemic is a new crisis facing communities and
societies, one which is amplifying existing social inequalities (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Drane, Vernon and O&#x02019;Shea, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Kenny, 2020</xref>). Moreover, the current context for social work practice, which is
ensconced in neoliberalism, is one that emphasizes individualism or individual achievement
rather than the social sources of oppression which perpetuate poverty, exclusion and
disadvantage (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Lathouras, 2016</xref>). As social work posits
an aim to work for social justice at local and global levels (recognizing these
interconnections), it therefore needs to commit to identifying and questioning harmful divisions
of unequal power relations (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Morley
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2014</xref>, pp. 2&#x02013;4).</p><p>In relation to the theme of connectedness, using technology for social good is a contemporary
challenge. We have discussed the pre-existing digital &#x02018;disparities&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Rigney, 2017</xref>) that have resurfaced during the pandemic for
individuals and communities. Working at the meta-level creates opportunities for social workers
to forge new alliances, coalitions and networks for broader social change. Information and
communication technology (ICT) such as digital media expand spaces for socio-political
networking and collective forms of advocacy to respond to issues affecting communities locally,
regionally and internationally (see <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Lynch, 2020</xref>). In
the classroom, we seek to incorporate examples of social workers undertaking advocacy across
international borders on a range of global social issues such as child sex trafficking.</p><sec id="sec13"><title>Responding to challenges to connectedness</title><p>A contemporary challenge to the principle of connectedness is the widening social and
economic disparities brought about by the COVID-19 pandemic (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Drane, Vernon and O&#x02019;Shea, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Kenny,
2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Meade, 2020</xref>). Kenny notes heightened
community development activity during the pandemic such as efforts &#x02018;to shore up social
connectedness&#x02019; (p. 1) and renewed value placed on community collaboration and
co-operation. However, she also expresses concerns about the immediate shift by community
development organizations to a welfare model, that is &#x02018;as agents of a
&#x0201c;benign&#x0201d; state&#x02019; (p. 2) and &#x02018;othering&#x02019; through fear and panic
directed at people who may pose a threat such as refugees and people experiencing
homelessness.</p><p>Critical thinking and practice skills can be translated into the university setting and
foreground the theme of connectedness. For example, we use The Spiral Model of Community
Education (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Bell, Gaventa and Peters, 1990</xref>) as a
pedagogical tool to enhance small group work as a community of learners and to support
students&#x02019; critical thinking skills. This model is used with social work students at the
University of the Sunshine Coast to explore contemporary or emerging social issues or trends
such as &#x02018;Working for Climate Justice&#x02019;; &#x02018;Working for First Nations
Justice&#x02019;; and &#x02018;Working for Justice in Welfare and Bureaucratic Contexts&#x02019;.
Contemporary documentaries or fictional movies are used as a &#x02018;code&#x02019; to stimulate
dialogue. <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Freirean &#x02018;codes&#x02019;, or what Paulo
Freire called &#x02018;codification&#x02019; (1974/2005)</xref> are a way to trigger dialogue,
supporting emancipatory knowledge development. Any stimulus can be a code&#x02014;a movie, a
poem, a reading, a song, a painting or drawing. An example for the theme of &#x02018;Working for
First Nations Justice&#x02019; is the 2019 documentary <italic toggle="yes">In My Blood Runs It
Runs</italic>, directed by Maya Newell. It tells the story of an Arrernte/Garrawa boy, Dujun
and his family and reveals the challenges Dujun faces both in his school and on the streets of
Alice Springs. For the theme of &#x02018;Working for Justice in Welfare and Bureaucratic
Contexts&#x02019;, the 2016 feature length movie, <italic toggle="yes">I, Daniel Blake</italic>, directed by
Ken Loach tells the story of a 59-year-old carpenter who must fight the bureaucracy of the
system in order to receive Employment and Support Allowance. Students learn to use The Spiral
Model process to develop their own structural analyses about the issues dramatized or presented
through the codes, and the deep engagement with the process aims to empower them to use this
model with community members in their future work.</p></sec><sec id="sec14"><title>Authentic assessment processes</title><p>Our community development pedagogy employs authentic assessment processes, thus ensuring that
students develop practical skills that they can utilize post-university. Authentic assessment
processes ensure students connect theory and practice through presenting them with real-world
challenges and standards of performance that professionals typically face in the field. This
requires students to demonstrate higher-order thinking and complex problem solving (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Koh, 2017</xref>). For example, in the community development
course at the University of the Sunshine Coast, students undertake a &#x02018;practice
review&#x02019;. Students take a &#x02018;first person&#x02019; stance and write to the community
development practitioner/s of a published case study; this helps students to critically reflect
on practice with a theory-informed analysis. Another example is an assessment piece called a
&#x02018;Community Development Process Plan&#x02019; where students write a plan for a piece of
community development work they intend to undertake. Based on the community development theory
which takes &#x02018;private concerns into public action&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Kelly and Westoby, 2018</xref>, p. 90), students identify a personal concern. This
could be related to their local neighbourhood or community, or something about the state of the
world in general. Using the participatory developmental method (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Kelly and Westoby, 2018</xref>), they demonstrate their structural analysis of the
root causes of the situation and identify with whom they intend to build relationships for
collective action. These analyses range from activist type actions such as neighbours banding
together to lobby local government for better community infrastructure, to creating their own
community infrastructure where none currently exists, such as community gardens or actions to
clean up a creek. For other students who develop an analysis about their own sense of
&#x02018;community&#x02019; and the impact of declining social capital, their process plan can
simply be to connect with their neighbours for a street barbecue or other social event to start
the process of building relationships. In many instances, student groups have followed through
with these planned activities, supporting the practical action component of the pedagogy.</p></sec><sec id="sec15"><title>The power of story: Teaching and learning in a global pandemic</title><p>Now we draw on a recent example of critical pedagogy which sought to incorporate the
principles of relational practice and connectedness during the COVID-19 pandemic. At the
University of the Sunshine Coast, non-traditional social work placements in the form of online
student units were set up to provide alternate field education placement opportunities for
students. Simultaneously, an action-research project with the placement students as
co-researchers was conducted to explore students&#x02019; learning experiences in student units
and how they were developing a social work identity under the new conditions effected by
COVID-19. A student unit is defined as a group of supervised students placed at one institution
or organization to work collaboratively on a particular task or project. Student units provide
students with a network of colleagues through which to engage in collective learning processes
(<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Anand, 2007</xref>).</p><p>The research employed a collective narrative practice theory called the Double-Story
Testimony (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Denborough, 2012</xref>). Alongside the dominant
story of struggle co-exists another story of which the participant may not be conscious (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Dulwich Centre, 2004</xref>). The narrative practice employs a
purposeful and contextualized framing of questions which emphasizes one&#x02019;s subjective
reality and assists the person to change their viewpoint about the problem or difficulties they
have faced (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Dulwich Centre, 2004</xref>).</p><p>The narrative technique enabled the students to relate their own &#x02018;first story&#x02019;
of struggle. This included themes about significant stressors during periods of lock-down, and
general uncertainty about the virus spreading to communities across the world. More specific
stressors included: working from home, responding to home-schooling of their children, loss of
income due to loss of work (often in hospitality and tourism industries not allowed to operate
during lock-down periods), switching to on-line learning for academic coursework, and increased
caring responsibilities of older or extended family members.</p><p>The &#x02018;second story&#x02019; elicited significant stories of resistance or sustenance as
they responded to their challenges expressed in the &#x02018;first story&#x02019;. Many lessons
were learned about how people can cope through times of struggle and themes included the values
that students drew from: Hope, Optimism/Positivity, Reciprocity, Gratefulness, Patience,
Adaptability and Acceptance. Students were also drawing on critical thinking, especially as so
much misinformation about COVID-19 was on social media and which tended to make them feel
overwhelmed. They reported that they committed to their own self-care and chose to focus on
activities to help sustain their physical, emotional and mental health. They also found a well
of support through their cultural or faith communities and drew on faith traditions and other
spiritual practices to help get them through this difficult time. Importantly, staying
connected to close friends and extended family became vital, especially for international
students who were unable to return home with national borders closed. Most significantly, these
are stories of connection, cooperation, mutuality and reciprocity despite the COVID-19
circumstances. Employing the biographical double-listening narrative process highlighted how
powerful story telling can be when people feel respected and experts in their own lives. It
proved its usefulness to elicit stories of resilience during a time of significant challenge,
as well as its applicability as a qualitative research tool.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec16"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this paper, we draw on newly emerging as well as enduring challenges for contemporary
social work and community development practice in Ireland, Australia and internationally.
Dramatically altered practice conditions culminate in what we have described as a
&#x02018;perfect storm&#x02019;. We analyse the constellation of factors that intersect to create
unpredictable conditions and acknowledge the complex forces that underlie and propel significant
practice challenges for future practitioners in this period of both interruption and
disruption.</p><p>Our paper draws on critical themes (governance, a changing climate, technology and a global
pandemic) and our own pedagogy to advance conversations about community development teaching and
learning in the contemporary context. We revisit core principles&#x02014;critical, relational and
connected&#x02014;that underpin our pedagogies and facilitate us to attune social work education
to this challenging practice context. Our examples from the classroom discussed in the paper
bring to light a critical pedagogy that engages students in analysis and reflection. However,
this is not purely an intellectual exercise, it is a pedagogy that seeks to forge practice
understandings and deeply consider what actions are possible in constrained times.</p><p>Building on the work of educators before us, and as reflected in this themed section on social
work education, our pedagogy aims to reignite analysis, creativity and higher order thinking and
learning for practical action in these contemporary conditions. Deepening analysis of the
COVID-19 context and critical situated thinking through engaging students in research and praxis
strengthens ideas about what is possible and opens up opportunities and avenues previously
undiscovered. This provides new confidence, impetus and forward looking future practitioners who
can innovate and adapt. Working collectively in the classroom opens up possibilities and
supports the development of dynamic and innovative forms of practice alongside groups and
communities to respond to the issues that they face in the present context.</p></sec></body><back><notes id="AN1"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Deborah Lynch PhD is a Senior Lecturer in Social Work at the University of Queensland,
Australia. She teaches community development in both undergraduate and post-graduate social
work programs and contributes to research scholarship in collaborative projects and journal
publications in social work and community development.</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Catherine Forde PhD is a Lecturer in Social Policy at University College Cork,
Ireland, where she teaches community development on Community Development and Social Work
qualifying programmes. Her current research interests include environmental education and
practice and she has published widely in the areas of community development and social
work.</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Athena Lathouras PhD is a Senior Lecturer in the Social Work program at the University
of the Sunshine Coast, Australia. She engages in community work practice and research working
to weave the links between these spaces so one informs the other and to promote better
teaching, research and practice in community issues.</italic>
</p></notes><ref-list id="bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Anand</surname>, <given-names>J.
C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Social work
student units: a case study in group learning and supervision</article-title>,
<source>Advances in Social Work and Welfare Education</source>, <volume>9</volume>
(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arao</surname>, <given-names>B</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Clemens</surname>,
<given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>)
<part-title>From safe spaces to brave spaces: a new way to frame dialogue around diversity
and social justice</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>L.</given-names><surname>Landreman</surname></string-name></person-group>, ed., <source>The Art of Effective
Facilitation: Reflections from Social Justice Educators</source>, <publisher-name>Stylus
Publishing</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>150</lpage>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ssw.umich.edu/sites/default/files/documents/events/colc/from-safe-spaces-to-brave-spaces.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://ssw.umich.edu/sites/default/files/documents/events/colc/from-safe-spaces-to-brave-spaces.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Barretti</surname>, <given-names>M.
A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Same problem,
different policies: a framework for examining social problem constructions over
time</article-title>, <source>Advances in Social Work</source>, <volume>19</volume>
(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bay</surname>,
<given-names>U.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<part-title>Teaching community development with Hannah Arendt. Enabling new emancipatory
possibilities</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Morley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Ablett</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Noble</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Cowden</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>The Routledge Handbook of
Critical Pedagogies for Social Work</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>449</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Bell</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gaventa</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Peters</surname>,
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> eds (<year>1990</year>) <source>We
Make the Road by Walking: Conversations on Education and Social Change</source>,
<publisher-name>Myles Horton and Paulo Freire, Temple University Press</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beltr&#x000e1;n</surname>,
<given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hacker</surname>,
<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Begun</surname>,
<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>)
<article-title>Environmental justice is a social justice issue: incorporating environmental
justice into social work practice curricula</article-title>, <source>Journal of Social Work
Education</source>, <volume>52</volume> (<issue>4</issue>),
<fpage>493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>502</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boal</surname>,
<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <source>Theatre
of the Oppressed</source>, <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boetto</surname>,
<given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>)
<article-title>A transformative eco-social model: challenging modernist assumptions in social
work</article-title>, <source>British Journal of Social Work</source>, <volume>47</volume>
(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>48</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boetto</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bowles</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>N&#x000e4;rhi</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Powers</surname>,
<given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Raising awareness of transformative ecosocial work: participatory action
research with Australian practitioners</article-title>, <source>International Journal of
Social Welfare</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>300</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ijsw.12445</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brookfield</surname>,
<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>The
Power of Critical Theory for Adult Learning and Teaching</source>, <publisher-name>Open
University press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Maidenhead</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Buy
from the Bush</collab></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <source>Buy from the Bush
Queensland</source>, Buy from the Bush Queensland, Queensland, Australia, <comment>accessed
at:</comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.buyfromthebushqld.com.au/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.buyfromthebushqld.com.au/</ext-link>
<comment>(24 April 2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Denborough</surname>,
<given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)
<article-title>A storyline of collective narrative practice: a history of ideas, social
projects and partnerships</article-title>, <source>The International Journal of Narrative
Therapy and Community Work</source>, <volume>1</volume>,
<fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Dulwich Centre Publications</collab></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)
<article-title>Narrative therapy and research</article-title>, <source>The International
Journal of Narrative Therapy and Community Work</source>, <volume>2</volume>,
<comment>accessed at:</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.dulwichcentre.com.au" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.dulwichcentre.com.au</ext-link>
<comment>(20 April 2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Drane</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Vernon</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Shea</surname>,
<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <source>The
Impact of &#x02018;Learning at Home&#x02019; on the Educational Outcomes of Vulnerable Children
in Australia During the COVID-19 Pandemic</source>, <publisher-name>National Centre for
Student Equity in Higher Education, Curtin University</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Elliott</surname>,
<given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>)
&#x02018;<source>The Covid Crisis Is Doing What the 2008 Crisis Didn&#x02019;t: Ending the Old
Economic Orthodoxies</source>&#x02019;, <publisher-name>The Guardian</publisher-name>
<comment>8 April, accessed at:</comment>, The Covid crisis is doing what the 2008 crash
didn&#x02019;t: ending the old economic orthodoxies | Economic policy | The Guardian (8 April
2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>,
<given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Navigating the neoliberal university: reflecting on teaching practice as a
teacher-researcher-trade unionist</article-title>, <source>British Journal of Sociology of
Education</source>, <volume>41</volume> (<issue>4</issue>),
<fpage>574</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>590</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01425692.2020.1748572</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>,
<given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <source>The
Diversity of the Recent Black Lives Matter Protests Is a Good Sign for Racial Equity</source>,
<publisher-name>Brookings Institute</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington,
DC</publisher-loc>, <comment>accessed at:</comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/how-we-rise/2020/07/08/the-diversity-of-the-recent-black-lives-matter-protests-is-a-good-sign-for-racial-equity/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.brookings.edu/blog/how-we-rise/2020/07/08/the-diversity-of-the-recent-black-lives-matter-protests-is-a-good-sign-for-racial-equity/</ext-link>
<comment>(18 April 2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name>Fong, R., Lubben, J. and Barth, R.P.</string-name></person-group>
(<year>2018</year>) <source>Grand Challenges for Social Work and Society</source>,
<publisher-name>Oxford Scholarship Online</publisher-name>, <comment>accessed at:</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oso/9780190858988.003.0001</pub-id>
<comment>(1 July 2020)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Forde</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Lynch</surname>,
<given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>)
<article-title>Critical practice for challenging times: social workers&#x02019; engagement with
community work</article-title>, <source>British Journal of Social Work</source>,
<volume>44</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>2078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2094</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bct091</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Forde</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Lynch</surname>,
<given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <source>Social
Work and Community Development: A Critical Practice Perspective</source>,
<publisher-name>Palgrave MacMillan</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Freire</surname>,
<given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)
<source>Pedagogy of the Oppressed</source>, <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Freire</surname>,
<given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1974/2005</year>)
<source>Education for Critical Consciousness</source>,
<publisher-name>Continuum</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London and New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Garrett</surname>, <given-names>P.
M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>A world to
win&#x02019; &#x02013; in defence of (dissenting) social work: a response to Chris
Maylea</article-title>, <source>British Journal of Social Work</source>, <volume>51</volume>,
<fpage>1131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bcab009</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gillinson</surname>,
<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <source>Why
Relationships Are Key to Good Social Work</source>, <publisher-name>The
Guardian</publisher-name>, <comment>Tuesday 21 March, accessed at:</comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.theguardian.com/social-care-network/2017/mar/21/why-relationships-are-key-to-good-social-work" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.theguardian.com/social-care-network/2017/mar/21/why-relationships-are-key-to-good-social-work</ext-link>
<comment>(10 March 2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Healy</surname>, <given-names>L.
M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Situating
social work within the post-2015 global agenda</article-title>, <source>European Journal of
Social Work</source>, <volume>20</volume> (<issue>1</issue>),
<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13691457.2016.1168788</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ife</surname>,
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>)
<source>Community Development in an Uncertain World: Vision, Analysis and Practice</source>,
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ife</surname>,
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>)
<part-title>Foreword</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>R.</given-names><surname>Munford</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>O&#x02019;Donoghue</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>New Theories
for Social Work Practice: Ethical Practice for Working with Individuals, Families and
Communities</source>, <publisher-name>Jessica Kingsley Publishers</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Federation of Social Workers</collab></person-group>
(<year>2012</year>) <source>Globalization and the Environment</source>, <comment>accessed
at:</comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ifsw.org/policies/globalization-and-the-environment/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ifsw.org/policies/globalization-and-the-environment/</ext-link>
<comment>(3 April 2021).</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Federation of Social Workers</collab></person-group>
(<year>2021</year>) <italic toggle="yes">&#x02018;</italic><source>New Social Contract Needed Says UN and
Social Work Forum</source><italic toggle="yes">&#x02019;</italic>, <comment>18 March, accessed at:</comment>
<publisher-name>New Social Contract Needed says UN and Social Work Forum &#x02013; International
Federation of Social Workers</publisher-name>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://ifsw.org" ext-link-type="uri">http://ifsw.org</ext-link>
<comment>(5 April 2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kelly</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Westoby</surname>,
<given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>)
<source>Participatory Development Practice: Using Traditional and Contemporary
Frameworks</source>, <publisher-name>Practical Action</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kenny</surname>,
<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Reflections. Covid-19 and community development</article-title>,
<source>Community Development Journal</source>, <volume>55</volume> (<issue>4</issue>),
<fpage>699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>703</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cdj/bsaa020</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Koh</surname>,
<given-names>K.H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>)
<source>Authentic Assessment in Education</source>, <publisher-name>Oxford Research
Encyclopedias</publisher-name>, <comment>accessed at:</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/acrefoe/9780190264093.013.22</pub-id>
<comment>(5 April 2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Landvogt</surname>,
<given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)
<part-title>Poverty has a voice</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Westoby</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names><surname>Shevellar</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>Learning and
Mobilising for Community Development. A Radical Tradition of Community-Based Education and
Training</source>, <publisher-name>Ashgate Publishing</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lathouras</surname>,
<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>)
<article-title>A critical approach to citizen-led social work: putting the political back into
community development practice</article-title>, <source>Social Alternatives</source>,
<volume>35</volume> (<issue>4</issue>),
<fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lathouras</surname>,
<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<part-title>A critical-relational approach to community development that increases
well-being, learning outcomes and retention of international students</part-title>, in
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>Crimmins</surname></string-name></person-group> ed, <source>Strategies for
Supporting Inclusion and Diversity in the Academy: Higher Education, Aspiration and
Equality</source>, <publisher-name>Palgrave MacMillan</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Switzerland</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ledwith</surname>,
<given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)
<source>Community Development: A Critical Approach</source>, <edition>2nd</edition> edn,
<publisher-name>Policy Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bristol,
UK</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lombard</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Viviers</surname>,
<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>The micro&#x02013;macro nexus: rethinking the relationship between social work,
social policy and wider policy in a changing world</article-title>, <source>British Journal of
Social Work</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>2261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2278</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bcaa180</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lynch</surname>,
<given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<part-title>Community practice and social development in a global world: critical
engagement and practical action</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Todd</surname></string-name> and <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Drolet</surname></string-name></person-group>, eds, <source>Community Practice and
Social Development in Social Work</source>, <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>,
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-13-1542-8_19-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Maglajlic</surname>, <given-names>R. A.</given-names></string-name>
and <string-name><surname>Ioakimidis</surname>,
<given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Editorial: new beginnings and enduring concerns&#x02014;inequalities, social
justice and understanding of structural issues in social work practice, education and
knowledge production</article-title>, <source>British Journal of Social Work</source>,
<volume>50</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1937</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1941</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bcaa197</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Martin</surname>,
<given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Please
Knock Before you Enter. Aboriginal Regulation of Outsiders and the Implications for
Researchers</source>, <publisher-name>Post Pressed</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Queensland</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marlowe</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Chubb</surname>,
<given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>)
<article-title>Social media and (im)mobility: implications for community
development</article-title>, <source>Community Development Journal</source>,
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Maylea</surname>,
<given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>The end of social work</article-title>, <source>British Journal of Social
Work</source>, <volume>51</volume> (<issue>2</issue>),
<fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>789</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bcaa203</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mbiti</surname>,
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <source>African
Religions and Philosophy</source>, <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Meade</surname>,
<given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Editorial&#x02014;What is this Covid-19 crisis?</article-title>
<source>Community Development Journal</source>, <volume>55</volume> (<issue>3</issue>),
<fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>381</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cdj/bsaa013</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morley</surname>,
<given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<part-title>Stephen Brookfield&#x02019;s contribution to teaching and practicing critical
reflection in social work</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Morley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Ablett</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Noble</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Cowden</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>The Routledge Handbook of
Critical Pedagogies for Social Work</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morley</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Ablett</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Noble</surname>,
<given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<part-title>Introduction. The imperative of critical pedagogies for social
work</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Morley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Ablett</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Noble</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Cowden</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>The Routledge Handbook of
Critical Pedagogies for Social Work</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morley</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Macfarlane</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Ablett</surname>,
<given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>)
<source>Engaging with Social Work: A Critical Introduction</source>, <publisher-name>Cambridge
University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Port
Melbourne</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mugumbate</surname>,
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<part-title>Samkange&#x02019;s theory of <italic toggle="yes">Ubuntu</italic> and its contribution to a
decolonised social work pedagogy</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Morley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Ablett</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Noble</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Cowden</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>The Routledge Handbook of
Critical Pedagogies for Social Work</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>412</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>423</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Naranjo</surname>,
<given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Environmental issues and social work education</article-title>, <source>The
British Journal of Social Work</source>, <volume>50</volume> (<issue>2</issue>),
<fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>463</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bcz168</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>N&#x000e4;rhi</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>
and <string-name><surname>Matthies</surname>,
<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>)
<part-title>Conceptual and historical analysis of ecological social work</part-title>,
in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>McKinnon</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Alston</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>Ecological Social Work:
Toward Sustainability</source>, <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ottman</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Noble</surname>,
<given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<part-title>The politics of collective action</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Morley</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Ablett</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Noble</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Cowden</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>The Routledge Handbook of
Critical Pedagogies for Social Work</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>475</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname>,
<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>)
<article-title>Integrating the natural environment in social work education: sustainability
and scenario-based learning</article-title>, <source>Australian Social Work</source>,
<volume>72</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0312407X.2018.1542012</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ramsay</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Boddy</surname>,
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>)
<article-title>Environmental social work: a concept analysis</article-title>, <source>British
Journal of Social Work</source>, <volume>41</volume> (<issue>1</issue>),
<fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bcw078</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ranta-Tyrkk&#x000f6;</surname>,
<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>N&#x000e4;rhi</surname>,
<given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>)
<article-title>Striving to strengthen the ecosocial framework in social work in
Finland</article-title>, <source>Community Development Journal</source>, <volume>56</volume>,
<fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rigney</surname>,
<given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>)
<part-title>Aboriginal community development and digital inclusion: hope, haves and
have-nots</part-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Kickett-Tucker</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>Bessarab</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Coffin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Wright</surname></string-name></person-group> eds, <source>Mia Mia Aboriginal
Community Development: Fostering Cultural Security</source>, <publisher-name>Cambridge
University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, pp.
<fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Salman</surname>,
<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <source>The
Rise of Technology in Care: How Will it Affect Workers?</source>
<publisher-name>The Guardian</publisher-name>
<comment>4 December, accessed at:</comment>, <comment>The rise of technology in care: how will
it affect workers? | Social care careers and training | The Guardian (25 April
2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Samkange</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Samkange</surname>,
<given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)
<source>Hunhuism or Ubuntuism: A Zimbabwean Indigenous Political Philosophy</source>,
<publisher-name>Graham Publishing</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Salisbury</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tehan</surname>,
<given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>)
<source>&#x02018;The Future of Australian Universities Focuses on Achievement&#x02019;, Media
Release</source>, <comment>2 October 2019</comment>, <publisher-name>The Honourable Dan Tehan
MP, Minister for Education, Ministers&#x02019; Media Centre, Department of Education, Skills
and Employment</publisher-name>, <comment>accessed at:</comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ministers.dese.gov.au/tehan/future-australian-universities-focuses-achievement" ext-link-type="uri">https://ministers.dese.gov.au/tehan/future-australian-universities-focuses-achievement</ext-link>
<comment>(10 April 2021).</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Truell</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Jones</surname>, <given-names>D.
N.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <source>Global Agenda for
Social Work and Social Development, Encyclopedia of Social Work</source>,
<publisher-name>Global Agenda for Social Work and Social Development | Encyclopedia of Social
Work, accessed at: oxfordre.com</publisher-name>, <comment>(11 March
2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Truell</surname>,
<given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <source>Back to
Basics: How Social Workers Returned to their Roots During Covid</source>, <publisher-name>The
Guardian</publisher-name>
<comment>16 December, accessed at:</comment>, <comment>Back to basics: how social workers
returned to their roots during Covid | Social care | The Guardian (21 March
2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Williamson</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Eynon</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Potter</surname>,
<given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Pandemic politics, pedagogies and practices: digital technologies and distance
education during the coronavirus emergency</article-title>, <source>Learning, Media and
Technology</source>, <volume>45</volume> (<issue>2</issue>),
<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17439884.2020.1761641</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World
Economic Forum</collab></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <source>The Global Risks Report
2021</source>, <edition>16th</edition> edn, <publisher-name>World Economic
Forum</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>, <comment>accessed
at:</comment>, <comment>WEF_The_Global_Risks_Report_2021.pdf (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://weforum.org" ext-link-type="uri">weforum.org</ext-link>) (8 April 2021)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yvas</surname>,
<given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>)
<article-title>An orderly curriculum for a messy field? Classroom-field tensions in community
organisation in India</article-title>, <source>Community Development Journal</source>,
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>