<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0265">The period of 2018&#8211;2020 saw unprecedented levels of controversy around pipeline expansion in Canada and globally, with diverse narratives, power relations and frames for de-/re-contextualising protest, civil disobedience and direct action associated with defending Indigenous rights, earth, land, water and future generations. In January of 2020, the United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination implored Canada to immediately stop the construction of TMX and two other large projects until it obtains approval from affected First Nations; failing to engage with this urging, government leaders responded that enforcing injunctions is the first priority, reflecting its primary commitment not to climate justice nor to Indigenous rights but to the fossil fuel industry. Given rising tensions created by court injunctions as systemic weapons of structural racism and injustice (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Pasternak &amp; King, 2019</xref>), courtroom ethnography offers an increasingly needed terrain for witnessing and critically understanding state violence, subtleties of brute instruments of power, and also nuances of resistance and affective landscapes both <italic>within</italic> and <italic>surrounding</italic> courthouses. Such approaches require learning through being present &#8211; with eyes open &#8211; paying careful attention to various scales of spatial politics and the inter-linkages of different jurisdictional propositions, affects and struggles. The TMX hearings illustrate how contemporary judicial uses of injunctions in Canada's settler-colonial state do not bear anything resembling a &#8220;reconciliation&#8221; era with Indigenous people; and <italic>experiencing</italic> injunction hearings over time, over the protracted proceedings, offers a vantage point for seeing vast resources dedicated by state institutions to suppressing issues fundamental to both UNDRIP and the Paris Climate Accord. In this age of fossil fuel violence,<xref rid="fn18" ref-type="fn">18</xref>
the task for critical geographers is to engage with the various positionalities, struggles and identities at play, as well as the plethora of mobilisations and articulations of science, history and local knowledge that &#8211; in theory &#8211; could guide fundamentally different understandings of &#8220;irreparable harm&#8221; &#8211; and of care.</p>