<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par45">Domestically, the Chinese approach to climate finance has undergone significant change. For many years, China was reluctant to commit to mitigation actions that were perceived as economically costly and disruptive, including to employment (Richerzhagen and Scholz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2008</xref>, 314). Over time, however, the conditions for policy changed. The relative prices of renewable energies dropped precipitously as against fossil fuels&#8212;a phenomenon led in part by the scaling of solar and wind industries in <xref rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec">China</xref>. By 2015, China&#8217;s annual investment in renewable energy constituted 36 per cent of the global total (Manner and Niedermaier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2018</xref>, 87). Public concerns about air quality incentivised officials to shutter the most polluting installations and encourage electric transportation. Renewables also contribute to national energy security (Miles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2018</xref>, 376&#8211;77). Moreover, as Chinese industries moved up the value chain, state economic planning placed increasing emphasis on innovation (Magnus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2018</xref>, 146). Priorities for technological leadership included renewables, electric vehicles and sustainable urbanisation. &#8216;Green development&#8217; became an important component of China&#8217;s economic reform and modernisation (State Council/World Bank <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">2013</xref>). The domestic turn to cleaner energy has a complex relationship with China&#8217;s external footprint. There have been concerns that China is using its Belt and Road Initiative to &#8216;dump&#8217; excess steel and coal capacity in participating countries (Magnus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2018</xref>, 182). Internally, however, encouragement of &#8216;green finance&#8217; became a key enabler of both &#8216;ecological civilisation&#8217; and broader economic goals.</p>