<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Our analysis encompassed 281 wards in the NCT of Delhi for which complete data on the aforementioned independent variables from the 2011 Census of India were available. The Delhi Cantonment was the only ward excluded due to data unavailability. We used a multivariable approach to analyze each of our dependent variables (May UHRI, September UHRI, May NVDI, and September NDVI) as a function of all independent variables in a single model. Our multivariable models are based on generalized estimating equations (GEEs) with robust covariance estimates, which extend the generalized linear model [<xref rid="B65-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] to accommodate clustered data [<xref rid="B66-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. GEEs are suitable for this study because they relax several assumptions of traditional regression models, impose no strict distributional assumptions such as normality for the variables analyzed, and consider variable clustering across units of analysis&#8212;in this case, wards [<xref rid="B67-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="B68-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,<xref rid="B69-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="B70-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. For estimating a GEE, clusters of observations must be specified which assume that observations from within a cluster are statistically related, while observations from different clusters are independent. Our cluster definition was based on the zone within which each ward is located (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-18-04800-f001">Figure 1</xref>), based on the assumption of dependence of wards within a specific zone. This approach yielded 13 clusters of wards, with a range of 6 to 36 wards per cluster. GEEs also require an intracluster dependency correlation matrix to be specified [<xref rid="B70-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. After considering several correlation structure specifications, the &#8216;unstructured&#8217; specification was chosen for GEEs using UHRI as the dependent variable, and the exchangeable specification was chosen for GEEs using NDVI as the dependent variable.</p>