<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0060">The pandemic has caused some rethinking of traditional supply-chain practices.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;1</xref>
illustrates some supply-chain weaknesses and potential resilence measures, which include the following:<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>1.</label><p id="p0065">Supply chains need to be more agile. The ability for supply chains and manufacturers to switch markets&#8212;to supply high-demand products and materials&#8212;has been an important part of the response to COVID-19. For example, Dyson in the UK&#160;started developing ventilators,<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> and L&#8217;Or&#233;al in Europe switched to manufacturing hand sanitizers.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>2.</label><p id="p0070">Globalized supply chains have shortcomings&#8212;in the short run. The globalization of production and the optimization of supply chains have increased systemic efficiencies in the global economy with observable global economic benefits, but they have exacerbated the speed and scope of contagion.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> COVID-19 has prompted calls for supply chains to be closer to key customers; arguments for reshoring and insourcing have been heard.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>3.</label><p id="p0075">Upstream supply chains need greater transparency and visibility. Early in the pandemic, ventilators and other protective equipment were in great demand, but buyers didn&#8217;t know the location of upstream bottlenecks. Supply-chain obscurity limited the ability to respond.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0025"><label>4.</label><p id="p0080">Active engagement with upstream suppliers is critical. When problems manifest, companies need to respond by managing sub-suppliers, levering relational capabilities, imposing new requirements, or ultimately switching sub-suppliers.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0030"><label>5.</label><p id="p0085">&#8220;Smart and nimble&#8221; supply chains hold up. The World Economic Forum has led calls for diversifying supply chains to reduce reliance on single-sourcing models driven exclusively by cost control, for example, away from &#8220;China only&#8221; toward other manufacturing hubs such as Vietnam, Mexico, and India. Going forward, increased digitalization will be an important aspect of supporting better and more flexible buyer-supplier relationships.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="o0035"><label>6.</label><p id="p0090">Not fully understanding downstream demand shifts and a lack of effective stress tests have left supply chains woefully unprepared. Observations 3 and 4 also apply to the downstream supply chain.</p></list-item></list>
<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#160;1</label><caption><p>Significant Weaknesses that Can Stress Supply-Chain Activities and Proposed Resilience Measures in Supply-Chain Designs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p>