<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Legal epidemiology is the study of law &#8220;as a factor in the cause, distribution, and prevention of disease and injury&#8221; [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. The impact of tax and employment law on public health [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>] has been studied. In the 65 public health cases included, there is an expectation from plaintiffs that government and economic actors will prioritize human health and planetary survival over economic profit. In the case of Youth Verdict v Waratah Coal, youth argue that the government has a duty of care to protect the health of its citizens. Further, in the 2020 ruling on modification to ethanol [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>], the Mexican Supreme court decided an agency was restricted from raising the ethanol content in fuel, as the &#8216;right to a healthy environment&#8217; must be prioritized over economic profit. Research has shown that &#8220;carbon-only&#8221; approaches to mitigating climate change that do not explicitly integrate air and water pollution and environmental justice considerations could fail to alleviate the public health harms and disproportionate burdens of fossil fuel production and use or even exacerbate them [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Considering that in response to the Covid-19 crisis, many (though not all) governments acted forcefully to prevent a public health emergency, including by deprioritizing the economy, it is likely that the expectation of prioritizing planetary health will only rise. With global fiscal support for the pandemic already amounting to a sheer $9 trillion by April 2020 [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>], the Covid-19 crisis also further demonstrated the financial capacity for large-scale investment when imminent threats arise. At a minimum, to prevent a climate-health crisis, there is an expectation for the risk to be fully priced into the financial markets. Yet, eco-centric laws can go further. The concept of ecocide is a way of protecting the environment and health, which goes beyond civil liability, and makes it a crime to harm nature [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. As highlighted in the 2020 status report on global climate litigation, there is mounting evidence of an increased appetite by the general public to crack down on corporate irresponsibility, requiring greater climate disclosure and an end to &#8220;corporate greenwashing&#8221; on the subject of climate and the energy transition.</p>