<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">As shown in <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_tab_003" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> was the top keyword for Corpus 2 when comparing frequencies against those of Corpus 1. We suspected that this result may be due to genre differences (first-person pronouns like <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">me</italic> are typical in social media, and less typical in public-facing, corporate texts) and so we ran a second keywords analysis against an ad hoc reference corpus comprising texts from more similar genres (social media posts, website comments, focus group transcripts, etc.). This second analysis confirmed that while <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> is statistically salient in Corpus 2 when we compare it against Corpus 1, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> does not feature in the top 20 keywords when compared against the corpus of texts from similar genres, suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> is indeed a genre feature. When compared against the ad hoc corpus, the statistically key pronouns were found instead to be <italic toggle="yes">we</italic> (ranked #6), <italic toggle="yes">they</italic> (#8), and <italic toggle="yes">them</italic> (#18). Nonetheless, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> is still a distinctive marker of our corpus of the language of members of the public concerning plastics, packaging, and reuse; it is the third most frequent word overall in Corpus 2 (see the wordlist in <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_app_001" ref-type="app">Appendix D</xref>), occurring more frequently even than words such as <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">and</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">of</italic>. For this reason, and for the purposes of demonstrating the application of our ecosophy in a limited space, we will discuss here just the pronoun <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> in Corpus 2. We discuss <italic toggle="yes">we</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">they</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">them</italic> in a separate article, forthcoming.</p>