<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par23">A total of seven land cover maps (1990, 1994, 2002, 2007, 2010, 2015, 2019) derived from Landsat images at a spatial resolution of 30&#160;m were used to evaluate the socio-environmental changes that occurred between 1990 and 2019. Land cover data from between 1990 and 2015 was obtained from previous studies (Vasconcelos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2015</xref>; Cabral &amp; Costa, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>; Temudo &amp; Cabral, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>), in which the second author worked on the satellite images processing and analysis. The 2019 land cover map was built specifically for this article. All maps followed the same methodology. Images were downloaded from the United States Geological Survey<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref> and used the same selection criteria: minimal cloud cover, high quality images, and date of acquisition in the late dry season when available. For each year, Guinea-Bissau is covered by five Landsat scenes, pre-processed (geometrically and radiometrically) to obtain clean and homogeneous mosaics. These mosaics were used to obtain the respective land cover maps by applying a supervised classification technique based on the maximum likelihood classifier (Lillesand et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015</xref>). For that, a simplified legend of 11 land cover classes was adopted according to field knowledge and ancillary information: Forest, Woodland, Savanna woodland, Mangrove, Grasslands, Swamp rice field, Burnt, Mud, Water, Sand, and Clouds. Although Landsat images were selected for their minimal cloud cover, some Landsat mosaics showed some clouds and cloud shadows. Thus, where clouds existed, they were manually digitized over the image (visually on-screen) and a common mask was built and applied to each classified map to quantify only the area occupied by each class. Classification accuracy was assessed for 2010, 2015 and 2019 through a formal comparison between the corresponding classified image and a reference dataset composed by field data from 2010 (Vasconcelos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2015</xref>) or by data collected for high-resolution images in Google Earth (GE). All validation datasets followed a stratified sampling strategy based on a 250&#8201;&#215;&#8201;250&#160;m systematic grid of points with a random origin (Vasconcelos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2015</xref>). The remaining maps produced were not subject to a formal accuracy assessment since there was no ground validation data or GE high-resolution images (near or) of the same dates. However, when a consistent methodological procedure is followed during the entire period under analysis, it can be assumed that the validation accuracy of the most recent map is enough to support the validity of the historical dataset (Cabral et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2010</xref>; Vasconcelos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2015</xref>). Two accuracy measures were calculated: the overall accuracy and the Kappa coefficient (Foody, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2002</xref>).</p>