<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par52">The EU bioeconomy, like the green economy to which it is closely associated, is embedded within the global trade, power and economic relations, which are in turn embedded within colonial and neo-colonial legacies of racially driven domination, extraction of labour and &#8216;natural resources&#8217; and exploitation and dispossession of people in the Global South (Harcourt and Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">b</xref>). If the EU leadership is to respond to growing pressure including from its own especially younger and increasingly protesting citizens and civil society organizations, demanding climate justice and an end to fossil capitalism, it is not the global competitiveness the EU should be concerned about. Rather efforts should be made towards recognition of responsibilities and commitment to reparations for the wrongdoing of the past and change of the current trends and politics. Yet not only is there a shortage of such commitments and change but policies like the EU bioeconomy signals continuity and escalation of neo-colonial domination and plunder in the Global South (Fuchs et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2020</xref>; Hickel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2021</xref>; Zografos and Robbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>). It is not sufficient to promote use of &#8220;domestically available sustainable renewable resources&#8221; if they are not defined or elaborated upon (Kurki and Ahola-Launonen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2021</xref>). To avoid reproduction of green sacrifice zones (Zografos and Robbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2020</xref>), EU policies with relations to and implications for the Global South need to change course radically, and here are just a few suggestions: (1) reinvent EU relations with and role in the world, with the humility of a former coloniser, where responsibilities for historical/colonial and modern/neo-colonial debt, burdens and injustices are acknowledged and acted upon; (2) reform EU policy and institutional framework with an aim to fostering reconciliation, reciprocity, respect, care and solidarity with the Global South and marginalized groups across the peripheries, as opposed to exploitation and violence; (3) abandon the &#8216;imperial mode of living&#8217; by tackling non-proportional and wasteful consumption and extraction and thus alleviate pressure on lands, peoples, and &#8216;natures&#8217; at home and elsewhere; (4) implement reforms for redistribution of wealth and power in a way that addresses current inequalities and repairs historic, as well as contemporary injustices and violence associated with the EU corporate extraction and dispossession; (5) implement policy reforms that allow the EU to operate in full recognition of domestic and, where relevant, local indigenous and customary territorial rules and rights, including cultural and political self-determination and self-governing authority. Relying on the state as the only legitimate actor tends to reinforce marginalization and violence against indigenous and/or rebellious groups (Dunlap <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2021a</xref>; Pellow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">2018</xref>; Ramcilovic-Suominen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2021</xref>).<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(v)</label><p id="Par53">Beyond dominant actor coalitions, top-down initiatives and state coercion towards decentralised bottom-up leadership that promotes direct democracy, local autonomy and sovereignty</p></list-item></list></p>