<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par43">Once we see ourselves as interconnected, embedded in, and dependent on other forms of life and species, and accept the sentiency of other forms of life (i.e. that they are morally equal to us), not only our relations with them but also our policy goals are more likely to shift from dominance, extraction and competition to those of care, respect, reciprocity, responsibility and nourishment (Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">b</xref>). But how do we get there? My argument is not for the EU bioeconomy and EU societies to adopt animism, but for human&#8211;nature narrowly framed relations to be re-examined (Gebara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>). I also do not suggest that European or any other society ceases to use other forms of life, as this contradicts the (co)existence and the very existence of societies in question. Besides, examples from Latin America, where the neoliberal grab and commodification of nature have continued despite indigenous ontologies being recognized and given space in the countries&#8217; laws and constitutions, suggest the need for radical change in practice as well. Yet, I argue that rethinking the ways we relate and interact with and use other forms of life, by embracing reciprocal relationality, is the first and necessary step to radical change. Reciprocity here implies taking not more than you need and returning the favour. Returning can be done by regeneration or replenishing the forms of life that we interact with (e.g. forest, land), which ensures continuity of their regenerative capacities; an example would be regenerative agroecological practices (Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2020a</xref>). Any efforts aiming to support a transition to a post-fossil economy that can be sustained in the long run, as the EU bioeconomy strategy and other similar policies claim to intend to, must go beyond colonising, exploiting and extracting other forms of life. Such attempts and policies need to urgently rethink and abolish human&#8211;nature duality, promote reciprocal relationality between humans and other species and forms of life.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="Par44">Beyond green growth and technoscientific solutions, towards institutionally supported, sufficiency-oriented lifestyles and means of production that respect and prioritize planetary limits and planetary justice</p></list-item></list></p>