<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par47">Supporting local(ized) production and consumption of resources and services is also important because such local and small-scale activities perform better ecologically owing to their shorter value chains. Being embedded within sociocultural and socioecological systems, local(ized) systems of economic exchange are potentially more sustaining and regenerating of socioecological systems (Parrique <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2019</xref>), and for the same reason of place embeddedness, they are also likely to be more democratic (Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>; Parrique <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2019</xref>). However, such local initiatives require policy and institutional support that a bioeconomy policy can provide. Such support includes, for example, reforming and democratising the monetary system and tax relief to support public goods, local producers and livelihoods (Douthwaite <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2012</xref>; Mellor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2017</xref>). Examples of alternative and local initiatives and cooperatives for providing collective goods and services exist throughout Europe (Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>) and the world (Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>). Promotion and support of cooperatives and community-led projects for provision of food, clothes, cosmetics, shared transportation and housing, and renewable energy is needed in the EU bioeconomy policies and discourses as a complement to the narrow focus on innovation and technologies. This in turn implies more self-reliance and local autonomy to decide, and less dependence on private and industry-led provision of new materials and technologies.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p id="Par48">Beyond stakeholder participation and equitable distribution of economic opportunities, towards climate and epistemic justice, local autonomy, self-determination, and self-governing authority</p></list-item></list></p>