<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par7">The second proposition speaks to our allegiances. Put plainly, principles of equity that are so central to public health are fundamentally incompatible with our institutional positioning within the very capitalist systems that we might see as the culprit in the global ecological crisis. It needs to be emphasized that public health&#8217;s core modus operandus, risk management, is by design conservative in nature: it is about managing the fallout of existing systems without fundamentally challenging those systems, and it emphasizes the kind of resilience that is about bouncing back from adversity in a manner that returns us to a highly inequitable normal. This is perhaps not surprising: an emphasis on transformative change and the capacity to bounce forward to new ways of thinking and doing would be out of step with the political masters to which public health is, by virtue of being a publicly funded institution, largely beholden. Not that brave public health leaders have not spoken truth to power, during the pandemic as well as before, on this and other issues. But we need to do more, and that includes deep reflection on our ongoing inability to commit to fundamentally different, that is decolonizing, forms of practice inherent within Indigenous public health (Lewis et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2020</xref>). Rather than doing risk management better to respond to the escalating fallout of the dominant system, we need to be doing better things, such as hastening and supporting the transition to a low-carbon &#8220;Symbiocene&#8221;, &#8220;bouncing forward&#8221; to new ways of seeing and doing that reflect a relational worldview, working with unusual allies to champion racial/climate justice, community-centred resilience, relocalization, and more (Poland et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>).</p>