<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par8">The third proposition speaks to our preparations, and particularly the need to prepare the public health workforce for a more ecologically centred practice suited to the challenges that are now upon us. Although post-secondary education and training programs in public health have proliferated over the past two decades following the last pandemic, i.e., SARS (Mass&#233; &amp; Moloughney, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2011</xref>), recent analysis shows significant omissions (Yassi et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>) and institutional apathy (Castleden et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2020</xref>) when it comes to social, ecological, and colonial determinants and dimensions of well-being and health equity. This finding is striking, given that social and ecological determinants of health have been positioned centrally in public health concepts for nearly a half-century (WHO, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1986</xref>; CSDH, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>). Yet, the double exclusion of public health silence in COP26 and of ecologically focused actions in the response to COVID-19 (Hancock et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>) belies such a legacy. It reflects a training-to-practice gap created by the pressure to produce job-ready graduates that limits the inclination (among students as much as educators) to go very far in terms of political economy, political ecology, degrowth, Indigenous ways of knowing, doughnut economics (Raworth, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2017</xref>), feminist ethics of care, deep adaptation, sustainability transitions, or peak oil. To be frank, while we observe that such topics are sought after by more and more students in our programs, most public health jobs rarely encompass any of these domains of action. As pointed out by Hancock and McLaren (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2021</xref>), public health still &#8220;plays into the hands of the critics who have always wanted to curtail public health to a biomedical focus on communicable diseases; to have us &#8216;stay in our lane&#8217; and not discuss economic and social injustice or ecological limits&#8221; (p. 792).</p>