<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">The need to develop rural communities in terms of productivity and convenience, so as to curb urban migration has received much attention in the last decade. First, the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE), as part of its mission, commenced the installation of solar-powered bulbs in many rural communities worldwide [<xref rid="B1-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This was followed in 2016 by the Cork Declaration, agreed amongst 340 representatives of European states towards ensuring that rural communities enjoy better lives. These efforts culminated into the coining of the word &#8220;smart village&#8221;, defined as a community that tries to develop current strength and resources, while making futuristic developmental plans on the basis of technology [<xref rid="B2-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. While there are several thematic areas of priority within the smart village development framework, agriculture is seen as the most important of them all [<xref rid="B3-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Furthermore, the need to bridge the digitization gap between cities and villages, is also an important aspect, so that lives and livelihood can be improved. Since a smart village is one that seemingly accepts new technologies, precision agriculture uses ultra-modern techniques for animal and crop production, which saves time and reduces wastage, and meets the requirements of smart villages. This is crucial for the sustainability of smart villages [<xref rid="B4-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. This is because improved food production and efficient animal management systems must be at par with village development, and must be continually transformed to influence the different aspects of smart villages, in terms of policy and practice [<xref rid="B5-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. </p>