<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">All of the collected comments were analyzed using a qualitative thematic analysis
approach (<xref rid="bibr4-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Braun and Clarke,
2006</xref>). The authors started with the earliest published article to
sequentially open code all comments. The objective was to allow themes to emerge
from the data while following the method of constant comparison to continuously
assess the fit and organization of comments into stable conceptual groupings
across comments. To code the comments, the authors read comments while
summarizing and pulling excerpts that could be grouped together to fit into an
evolving set of possible thematic clusters of comments or potentially be the
basis for new themes. Throughout the coding process, the authors wrote memos to
articulate and clarify the evolving definitions of concepts that the themes
represent. The authors also periodically discussed and assessed the conceptual
organization of themes, a process often referred to as analyst triangulation
(<xref rid="bibr28-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Patton, 2014</xref>).
This contributed to the refinement of the overall organization of the emerging
themes. Per the constant comparison process in qualitative research, all
emerging themes and their definitions were continuously revised and assessed
throughout the coding process to ensure that the themes made conceptual sense
and decide whether they needed to be reorganized, merged, or further broken into
more themes (<xref rid="bibr39-14614448221135632" ref-type="bibr">Strauss and
Corbin, 1990</xref>). After coding 768 comments on five articles, the themes
were largely saturated and stable with small amounts of new information still
being added depending on the specific context of the article being coded.
However, this new information did not require any reorganization or revisions of
the concepts that defined the saturated themes. To be sure that the authors
reached a suitable level of thematic saturation, an additional article from the
list of sampled articles (described in <xref rid="table1-14614448221135632" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), titled &#8220;Where The Latest
COVID-19 Models Think We&#8217;re Headed&#8212;And Why They Disagree,&#8221; was coded bringing
the total number of coded comments to 885. The newly coded comments did not
contribute to the formation of new themes or necessitate the revision of the
conceptual organization of themes, but rather supported the already existing
themes and how they were organized. As a qualitative analysis, we focus our
results on describing and elaborating themes rather than on considering the
salience or prevalence of those themes.</p>