<p xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Access to services, facilities, and goods has been an overarching theme within the social and environmental justice movements and extends to the realm of climate justice as well, with particular relevance for the Southeastern U.S. Accessibility to health facilities and services often encompasses three categories of access: financial access, behavioral access, and spatial access [<xref rid="B82-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. <italic>Financial access</italic> is tied to the ability of people to receive adequate health care under personal cost constraints. <italic>Behavioral access</italic> refers to how people utilize health services, including doctor visits, medications, and emergency care. <italic>Spatial access</italic> addresses the geographic distribution and subsequent travel times to health care facilities, especially in remote, rural areas. Health disparities among the most vulnerable rural inhabitants&#8212;including children, adolescents, and the elderly&#8212;are often attributed to inequity in the distribution of health care providers, especially access to physicians relative to other providers (e.g., nurse practitioners and midwives) [<xref rid="B83-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. There are areas in the Southeastern U.S., predominantly in rural locations, that are identified as primary care health professional shortage areas (PC-HPSAs) [<xref rid="B84-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. For example, Thomas <italic>et al.</italic> identified a rural area in Georgia where no pediatricians were accepting new Medicaid (health care program for those with low incomes and limited resources) patients and there was less than one family/general practitioner per every 2000 individuals per county. As the climate-induced health outcomes outlined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-13-00189-t002">Table 2</xref> (e.g., asthma attacks, heat strokes, and psychological stress disorders) increase, the need for health care services that are equitable, affordable, and positioned appropriately for Southeastern rural communities will be essential.</p>