<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par48">If this target is adopted, then the logical implication is that fossil-fuelled vessels should not be used after 2050, and a policy approach will be needed to achieve this goal. An alternative to the current focus on MBMs would be direct regulation of carbon emissions at source by banning the use of fossil fuels by 2050 and gradually phasing out fossil-fuelled activities up to that date. In order to phase them out by 2050, the sale of new fossil-fuelled vessels would need to be banned by an earlier date. Setting this date is difficult, given that the commercial life of many ships is well over 20&#160;years. Vessels can in fact be retrofitted with different engines or fuel systems but this is costly, time-consuming and causes its own problem of environmental waste. Setting a date of 2035&#8211;40 would send a signal to ship owners that they are only going to obtain 10&#8211;15&#160;years value of their investment, unless they retrofit it for renewables at a later date. Some countries (e.g. France and the UK) are already banning the sale of new fossil-fuelled cars and trucks by 2040. Such policies are easier to enact when these emissions are included in national emission accounts, whereas international shipping is not, although this arrangement may itself change if the IMO impasse continues long enough (discussed in the next section). Such clear timescales would give certainty to the market, provide a level playing field, leave the choice of technology paths to industry and not require all the complicated regulation and administration of market-based mechanisms. The technology for zero-carbon shipping fuels such as green hydrogen already exists but needs to be scaled up. Carbon levies can be used to raise funds to support research and development, but will not on their own bring about an industry-wide fuel transition as long as fossil fuels are abundantly available. The details of alternative fuels can be left to industry actors but the role of policy makers is to provide the right conditions to transition away from the current system.</p>