<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par30">In conclusion, halfway into the <italic>Agenda 2030</italic>, the ambitious goals and targets are far from their realisation. Safety for people and planet are not yet guaranteed. More rapid transformation is urgently needed to create environmental sustainability and promote peaceful, socially fair, and prosperous societies. Undoubtedly, many of us need to make challenging shifts of core values and priorities as a basis for our personal transformation towards sustainability. Likewise, policy makers, stakeholders, and decision makers in the business sector must transform their activities in accordance with scientifically based advice from international research organisations and groups such as Clark et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2020</xref>), ICCP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2021</xref>), WMO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2022</xref>) or Steffen et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>) who continuously prove that business as usual is not an option. The Covid-19 pandemic has shown that when a serious crisis is recognised, strong actions and new resources are activated. Communities, societies, and nations need to urgently transform (Rockstr&#246;m &amp; Gaffney, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2021</xref>; Thunberg, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2019</xref>). As Humanity, we need to consider both human and the more-than-human life. We argue that the multiple languages used within sustainability and the UNSDGs can guide us on this endeavour, despite their inconsistencies and contradictions. The ECEC practises of collaborative exploration carry a valuable transformational power as they are emanating from within the ECEC context. Based on the articles in this special issue, young children and their teachers, on their premises, are well apt to step up as &#8216;custodians of the planet&#8217; (Robinson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>).</p>