<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Alexander K&#246;nsler urges the social sciences to attend to recent climate protests and their development, as they exhibit new forms of mobilisation. Drawing on his own research, he argues that doing research in rural areas is just as important as focusing on urban activism. Mario Kr&#228;mer describes primarily leftist climate activism as a rather new phenomenon and deals with traditionalist origins of environmental conservation, as the former often causes scepticism among traditionalist groups. Due to the emergence of new narratives about environmental and climate protection, even among moderate ecological traditionalists as well as the far right, Kr&#228;mer appeals for the anthropological exploration of those groups and their strategies. Despite growing commitment to renewable energy in Germany, Werner Krau&#223; highlights the importance of place&#8208;based efforts to cope successfully with global climate change. In their everyday conversations and daily routines, some concerned citizens suggest departures from a carbon&#8208;intensive way of life, making hidden climate costs visible. Based on observations in Bali, Indonesia, Annette Hornbacher talks about nascent environmental activism on the island, finding a local understanding of climate change that markedly differs from Western views. In Bali, representations of climate change include both meteorological shifts and societal change. Hornbacher thus points to a general &#8216;mood of crisis&#8217; in the wake of the island&#8217;s turn to a modern, consumerist lifestyle. In Sophie Mahakam Anggawi&#8217;s account of the Balinese punk collective &#8216;Denkol&#8217;, she shows how activists spring into action in the face of a careless and unreliable state response to the pandemic. The piece shows how civil efforts to protect the environment create an alternative support infrastructure that re&#8208;enfranchises abandoned parts of society.</p>