<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">Current debates surrounding the cruise industry in other cities also place contemporary issues in their historical contexts. In Hamburg, for example, the artist collective <italic>Geheimagentur</italic> (&#8220;secret agency&#8221;) carried out a&#160;project entitled &#8220;A&#160;Cruise Terminal&#8221; in 2015. Motivated by the opening of the third cruise terminal in the city, it led to discussions about who owns the&#160;&#8220;Right-to-the-Sea&#8221;, as well the prospect of &#8220;another cruise and another port&#8221; (Geheimagentur 2021).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn24">24</xref> In doing so, the participants positioned themselves in opposition to the hegemonic discourse, since the arrival of cruise ships in Hamburg tends to be an important event that attracts thousands of people. Their aim was to put other kind of mobilities in perspective. Furthermore, the deepening of the river Elbe, which connects the city with the North Sea, has led to debates over ecological impacts since decades. Projects like the one led by <italic>Geheimagentur</italic> intend to bring untouched issues into focus. An intense transnational European collaboration has been carried out by the <italic>Naturschutzbund Deutschland </italic>(NABU), a&#160;German conservation group. NABU initiated a&#160;pilot study of atmospheric nitrogen oxide levels in the Mediterranean Sea, with the goal of analyzing the air quality in port cities. This campaign included experts and researchers from several European countries. Together with the Italian environmental association Citizens for the Air (<italic>Cittadini per l&#8217;Aria</italic>), the <italic>Comitato No Grandi Navi, AmbienteVenezia</italic>, and the group <italic>We are here Venice</italic> came together in a&#160;transnational campaign to &#8220;Let the Mediterranean breathe&#8221; (<italic>Facciamo respirare il mediterraneo</italic>). In March 2017, with the &#8220;Declaration of Rome,&#8221; European environmentalists called for Emission Control Areas (ECAs, special shipping zones defined by the International Maritime Organization) for the Mediterranean (Cittadini per l&#8217;Aria 2021).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn25">25</xref> As of now, it is mostly ports located in Northern Europe which belong to such zones. The central demand of the declaration was the inclusion of all European seas in ECAs, which could be achieved by 2025.</p>