<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0115">We are living amid an ecological crisis (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Kissling &amp; Bell, 2020</xref>). While teaching ecological issues within social studies is not necessarily a new concept (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Hepburn, Shrum, &amp; Simpson, 1978</xref>), the topic is currently a fringe topic within the field due to the notion that &#8220;climate change is solely a scientific issue, that there is already much other social studies content with which to engage, and that climate change is politically controversial in the United States&#8221; (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Kissling &amp; Bell, 2019</xref>, p. 20). However, there has been a recent push within the field to bring these issues to the forefront of the subject. <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Houser (2009)</xref> discussed the importance of &#8220;citizenship education being located within a broader context of environmental sustainability&#8221; (p. 204) through the teachings of an &#8220;ecological democracy&#8221; (p. 207). An ecological democracy would have students contemplate their place within the environmental matrix that supports human life. <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Kissling and Barton (2013)</xref> build on the concept of ecological democracy and argue for social studies teachers to include ecological citizenship to their traditional teachings of citizenship in social studies classrooms. Furthermore, there have been several practitioner-focused articles published to give teachers concrete lesson ideas on how to incorporate these issues in their classes. <italic>Rising</italic>, when read through the lens of social studies education, presents unique first and second person accounts of the climate crisis and how it impacts citizens throughout the country. These stories could complement studying climate issues surrounding the COVID-19 pandemic, including reports of pollution exacerbating the severity of the infection (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Kann, 2020</xref>) as well as air quality improvements due to less burning of fossil fuels (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Goldbaum, 2020</xref>). Using these examples and stories can give students the chance to see the human impacts of climate change and rising seas, and humanize an issue that often gets lost in scientific data.</p>