<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Climate change is used by dominant actors &#8211; state and non-state, corporate and non-corporate &#8211; to revive the old claims that some agrarian systems are ecologically destructive, in order to justify the use of extra-economic coercion and radically shift the land use to capitalist production systems that they deem offer a greater degree of economic efficiency in allocative, distributive and technical terms. This is a concrete manifestation of the vital importance of understanding climate change <italic toggle="yes">not only</italic> in terms of biophysical links and in terms of projects and policies, <italic toggle="yes">but equally importantly</italic>, in terms of politics. The dominant understanding of climate change mitigation and adaptation is framed within the capitalist economic development framework of endless capital accumulation, which sees land and nature as a productive input and a waste sink. Even before Climate Smart Agriculture was popularized in the UNFCC Conference of the Parties (COP) events, the <italic toggle="yes">WDR 2008</italic>, released in the same year as the COP Bali in 2007, had already established the framework for the relationship between land/nature and climate change mitigation and adaptation, and how the free market should govern such a relationship. The <italic toggle="yes">WDR 2008</italic> states:
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p>Based on the polluter-pays principle, it is the responsibility of the richer countries to compensate the poor for costs of adaptation&#8201;&#8230;&#8201;. Developing country agriculture and deforestation are also major sources of greenhouse gas emissions: they contribute&#8201;&#8230;&#8201;up to 30 percent of total emissions, more than half of which is from deforestation&#8201;&#8230;&#8201;caused by agricultural encroachment (13 million hectares of annual deforestation globally). (World Bank, <xref rid="CIT0109" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, p. 17)</p></disp-quote>It concludes by emphasizing market-based solutions: &#8216;Carbon-trading schemes &#8211; especially if their coverage is extended to provide financing for avoided deforestation&#8201;&#8230;&#8201;offer significant untapped potential to reduce emissions from land-use change in agriculture&#8217; (World Bank, <xref rid="CIT0109" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, p. 17). It has to be pointed out, however, that in the era of financialization, corporate investments are far more transnational. It is thus problematical to talk about &#8216;developing country agriculture and deforestation&#8217; as if <italic toggle="yes">global</italic> capital, that is, especially North-based capital, is not deeply involved in such transformation (Clapp &amp; Isakson, <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Fairbairn, <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Visser et al., <xref rid="CIT0103" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p>