<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par19">However, with China&#8217;s rapid rise, domestic and international expectations for a greater global presence of China have greatly increased, and at the same time doubts towards China&#8217;s developing country identity have significantly arisen (Pu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>; Shambaugh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2011</xref>). China&#8217;s increasing material strength, unwillingness to take up more international responsibilities and assertive behaviours in its territorial disputes generated confusions, concerns and even fears to its Asian neighbours about its role in the region order as well as in the international order (Mearsheimer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2010</xref>; Yan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2014</xref>). With accession to power in 2012/2013, Xi Jinping attempted to offer a new definition of China&#8217;s international identity. While the &#8216;old&#8217; discourses of developing country identity still have traction domestically (Pu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2017</xref>), China&#8217;s self-ascribed international identity has been frequently conveyed in a very new Chinese term&#8212;&#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; (a leading state) which had seldom appeared in China&#8217;s national narratives regarding its international presence in the past. Xi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2016a</xref>) repeatedly stressed that China should be a global &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; rather than just be a &#8216;follower&#8217; or &#8216;bystander&#8217; in &#8216;defining international rules&#8217; and &#8216;reforming the global governance system&#8217;. But interestingly, Xi did not use another more common Chinese term&#8212;&#8216;<italic>lingdao</italic>&#8217; which has very similar meanings of the English word&#8212;leader. In Chinese, the nuance between the term &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; and &#8216;<italic>lingdao</italic>&#8217; is that the latter highlights the hierarchy structure between a leader and followers while the former not. Moreover, &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; contains the meanings and connotations of pioneer, vanguard and leading actor, and the status that a &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; holds is not exclusive whereas with &#8216;<italic>lingdao</italic>&#8217;, it is exclusive. As a global <italic>yinlingzhe</italic>, emphasized by Xi, China will &#8216;proactively undertake more international responsibilities&#8217; (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2013</xref>), continue to support multilateralism and international multilateral institutions (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2015b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2016b</xref>), and cooperate with others in a way of &#8216;extensive consultation, joint contribution and shared benefits&#8217; (<italic>gongshang</italic>, <italic>gongjian</italic>, <italic>gongxiang</italic>) in order to establish a regional and global &#8216;community of common destiny for mankind&#8217; (<italic>renlei mingyun gongtongti</italic>) (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2017a, b</xref>)&#8212;China&#8217;s conception of international society. In Xi&#8217;s vision, furthermore, a global <italic>yinlingzhe</italic> is very different from a hegemony because China aims to &#8216;co-define international rules&#8217; and &#8216;co-govern global affairs&#8217; with other international players and will &#8216;never seek hegemony&#8217; (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2017a</xref>). Xi actually discursively constructed China as a global leading actor who pursues a shared leadership. While some critics may just treat these discursive representations as China&#8217;s propaganda, these official discourses do show how China communicates itself to the world and entail China&#8217;s understanding about the relationship between itself and the existing international order.</p>