<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">We then developed inclusion and exclusion criteria that was used to screen for titles and abstracts. We included studies that were both peer-reviewed and grey literature from the past 10 years (November 2010&#8211;2020) that were published in OECD countries (Canada, Australia, US, UK, Netherlands, Sweden, Portugal, and Finland) as our intention was to include any relevant studies and not limit to Canada. Articles could have a global focus so long as the topic related to Canada as well. Records needed to explicitly address at least two of the following themes in the abstract or title: climate change, youth/children, and mental health. Inclusion criteria were left relatively open to include relevant studies on a novel topic; however, this could be considered a limitation of our study. For this specific review, papers were not included if they were non-English or had a COVID-19 or biomedical focus, unless it explicitly considered an Ecological Determinants of Health. Furthermore, articles were examined to consider inclusion of Equity, Diversity and Inclusion and Gender-Based Analysis Plus relevant terms. A total of 386 records were identified through database searches, and 170 titles were identified for abstract screening. The abstracts of 116 articles were deemed relevant and 58 articles were retained for our analysis, as identified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-18-04573-f002">Figure 2</xref>. Duplicates were removed after abstract review instead of in the title screening phase so that both researchers could ensure that relevant articles were not removed at an earlier phase by another team member. This allowed the researchers to develop a high degree of agreeability in finding the same articles relevant. Both researchers worked independently for the initial screening to reduce bias and mistakes, justifying the relevance of the studies included. In situations where researchers disagreed on article inclusion, the PI (MKG) heard their views and made the final decision.</p>