<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par43">Furthermore, China also wielded the climate leadership through two important approaches, i.e. leadership by example (Liefferink and Wurzel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2017</xref>) and providing international public goods (Dent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>), in the Paris era. China has become an undisputable world leader and champion in investing renewable energy (Andrews-Speed and Zhang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2019</xref>; REN21 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2021</xref>). Regarding emission mitigation, China has undertaken more international responsibilities. In Paris, for instance, China for the first time committed to an exact peaking time for CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (by around 2030) (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2015a</xref>). Aside from that, China has achieved its 2020 emission reduction target, which is a carbon intensity reduction of 40 to 45% below 2005 levels, 3 years in advance (UN Climate Change News <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2018</xref>). Furthermore, during the course of the COVID-19 pandemic in September 2020, Chinese President Xi revised the goal to peak emissions before 2030 and also announced that China will aim to achieve carbon neutrality before 2060 (Xinhuanet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2020</xref>). It is the first time that China committed to a long-term goal on emission reduction. China&#8217;s Xie Zhenhua pointed out that &#8216;this bold target may move global carbon neutrality ahead by 5-10 years&#8217; and will also &#8216;play a key role in promoting stronger global climate governance&#8217; (China Dialogue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). Research published in Science magazine recently found that China&#8217;s carbon neutrality target is largely consistent with the Paris Agreement goal of keeping global warming to 1.5&#176;C (Duan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>). In addition, at the Leaders&#8217; Summit on Climate hosted by the USA in April 2021, Xi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2021</xref>) announced that China would strictly control coal-fired power projects, strictly restrict the growth in coal consumption in the 14th Five-Year Plan period (2021&#8211;2025) and gradually reduce it in the 15th Five-Year Period (2026&#8211;2030). Moreover, China&#8217;s economy has already entered into a decoupling process between growth and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (IEA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2018</xref>; Tiberghien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>). Regarding emission trading, China took experiences from the EU and established its own national Emission Trading System (ETS) in 2017 based on its national conditions and needs, which will become the world&#8217;s largest ETS system once it is fully operational (Gippner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2020</xref>). China has not only offered considerable financial aids annually but also provided a large amount of projects around renewable energy technology transfer and offered personnel training courses to thousands of government officials, scholars and technicians from hundreds of developing countries (NDRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2015</xref>). Through these domestic and international efforts, China showed its leadership by example regionally and internationally. In addition, as Christopher Dent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>: 21) argued, providing international public goods is an important criteria of international leadership. At the 2015 China-US Summit and the Paris Summit, for example, President Xi announced that China will provide USD 3.1 billion to set up the <italic>China South-South Climate Cooperation Fund</italic> to support developing countries in combating climate change (Xi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2015a</xref>). The money even exceeds the pledge of USD three billion made by the USA to the UN&#8217;s Green Climate Fund. It is a historical breakthrough that China contributed to international climate finance.</p>