<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par45">Notwithstanding that, China&#8217;s negotiating behaviour, domestic climate policies and international practices have not been without doubts and criticism. Despite China&#8217;s contribution to securing the Paris Agreement, some scholars and participant observers have noted that China&#8217;s negotiating behaviour in Paris also undermined and impeded ambitious international efforts (Christoff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2016</xref>; Dimitrov <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2016</xref>). Moreover, many scholars criticized that China&#8217;s domestic climate policies are not being sufficiently ambitious (Harris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2017</xref>; Keohane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>). In particular, China&#8217;s greenhouse gas emissions continue to increase, with an average annual growth of 3.3% over the period 2010&#8211;2019 (Rhodium Group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2021</xref>), and new coal-fired power plants are still being built. In addition, as Robert Keohane emphasized, global climate leadership requires credibility and China has to endorse genuine transparency policies that make its climate commitments credible (Keohane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>). Similarly, the EU&#8217;s climate negotiators repeatedly complained in the interview with the author about the transparency problem of China&#8217;s climate data and particularly urged China to be more transparent (Interview 2018). Furthermore, China&#8217;s overseas investments in fossil fuels energy projects have sparked international criticism (Gupta and Chu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>). For instance, in its newly released strategic document, the EU criticized China&#8217;s construction of coal-fired power stations in many countries as undermining the global goals of the Paris Agreement (European Commission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>). In order to be fully recognized as a credible climate leader, therefore, China has to self-reflect and adjust its future climate behaviours domestically and internationally. As China&#8217;s Xie Zhenhua stressed, being a &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; in GCG means China has to address climate change better at domestic, continually offer China&#8217;s solutions on the basis of its evolving experience and practices, and provide &#8216;bridging solution&#8217; for different sides within the international multilateral process on climate change (Chinanews <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2017</xref>).</p>