<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par22">Although on the front lines of many crises, Extension is not centered in discussions of economic and energy transitions, such as the Green New Deal. This is unfortunate, given Extension&#8217;s potential relevance to these conversations, but it likely reflects the conservatism of 1862 Extension programs, typically encountered in the dominant framing of Extension&#8217;s role as the apolitical transfer of technology and information, application of proven programs, and evidence-based approaches. Extension often reflexively frames social and political problems as technical ones, and avoids contentious debates to maintain the perception of neutrality (Peters et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>, p. 26). Extension also promotes entrepreneurialism and resiliency, training communities to navigate markets and risk in an economic system in which corporations have more and more control, opening limited spaces of freedom within unequal and often hostile structures (Rose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">1999</xref>). Guatemalan Extension programs played a key role in implementing &#8220;apolitical&#8221; counterinsurgency development programs Indigenous communities (Copeland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2019</xref>). Under the guise of neutrality, such programs support the status quo, offering a limited vision of what Extension could accomplish. Extension tends to reproduce historic inequalities and systemic harms, not necessarily on purpose, but by not challenging them, and because of affinities with existing partners and approaches as well as discomfort with expanding to new communities or seeming political. 1862 Extension programs have historically had mostly white leadership and most have only recently begun earnest internal conversations around race in the wake of Black Lives Matter protests. Extension professionals recognize the limitations of the tech transfer model, and many struggle to address systemic issues, but best practices alone cannot address these problems. Doing so requires engaging in dialogue about values, thinking critically about partners, and recognizing that there is no neutral stance outside of these issues (Kim Niewolny, personal communication; Colasanti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2009</xref>).</p>