<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Research in this area has mostly focused on broader environmental concerns, with only a few studies specifically related to climate change. Based on a non-systematic review [<xref rid="RSOS210006C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], we identified a dozen psychological factors that relate to self-reported environmental activism, where this includes joining events organized by ecologically oriented groups, and engaging in environmental education and leadership behaviors (such as circulation of petitions, raising awareness about climate issues, outreach and community organizing; [<xref rid="RSOS210006C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="RSOS210006C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]). The findings emerged in diverse geographical locations (although predominantly white, developed western nations were studied), ranging across Germany [<xref rid="RSOS210006C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], Austria [<xref rid="RSOS210006C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], the USA [<xref rid="RSOS210006C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210006C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], Australia [<xref rid="RSOS210006C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and other countries such as Argentina, Chile, South Korea, Mexico, Russia, Turkey and others [<xref rid="RSOS210006C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. We identified psychological factors including affective engagement (i.e. anxiety, sense of threat, worry and concern about the environment and ecological extinction), worldviews, i.e. egalitarian [<xref rid="RSOS210006C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210006C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], nature-loving [<xref rid="RSOS210006C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and anti-consumerist beliefs [<xref rid="RSOS210006C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], collective efficacy (i.e. the perception that the actions of one's group can have an impact) and social norms (i.e. the perceived approval of one's engagement in activism from people in one's social circle; [<xref rid="RSOS210006C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210006C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210006C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]).</p>