<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par20">A warming level of over 1.5&#160;&#176;C will be unavoidable, if national emissions reductions commitments are not radically increased in the immediate short-term (UNEP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2019a</xref>). Gleeson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR500">2018</xref>) warns of a &#8220;tsunami of human and global change&#8221; of overwhelming scale and magnitude. However, sustainable development policy responses to date assume the stability of the political-economic structure and aim for socio-technical transition rather than any fundamental system transformation. Bradshaw et al.&#8217;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2021</xref>) dire predictions of &#8216;a ghastly future&#8217; of mass extinction, resource conflicts and climate-disruption upheavals are a stark reminder of the challenges. The application of justice principles is vital in navigating the decision-making of this complex milieu and to facilitate public reasoning on what is considered to be legitimate (Forsyth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2014</xref>). &#8220;Bounce forward&#8221; resilience concepts frame disruption as an opportunity to radically address social issues (Manyena et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2011</xref>), with a central recognition of the importance of justice considerations (Popke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2016</xref>). However, while climate related disruptions may prompt a transformative change of socio-economic systems, whether recovery will be characterized by a return to the <italic>status quo ante</italic> or a transition to enhanced sustainability is uncertain. In this context, justice principles can help to address the question, &#8220;What is the right thing to do&#8221;? as posed by Sandel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2009</xref>). Adaptive and resilience focused responses can be informed by rights-based and capabilities-based approaches to justice in conjunction with principles of procedural and distributive justice, to frame 'just disruptions' (Morrissey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2021</xref>).</p>