<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">One of the primary concerns with the disparity in urban heat exposure is the increased risk of heat-related impacts on human health. Heat is a leading weather-related cause of mortality and morbidity [<xref rid="B8-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Heat-related illness is a spectrum of conditions that are brought about by exposure to extreme temperatures, including heat edema, dehydration, heat syncope, and life-threatening heat stroke [<xref rid="B10-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Heat is also known to exacerbate or contribute to a number of chronic and acute health conditions that can lead to amplified illness or death. Cardiovascular disease, Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD), asthma, chronic kidney disease, rheumatoid arthritis, type 2 diabetes, migraines, and mental illness are only a sample of the more prevalent conditions exacerbated by extreme heat [<xref rid="B8-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B11-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. These and other health impacts from thermal exposure, especially during extreme heat events, can quickly overload emergency medical management centers [<xref rid="B20-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Further complicating matters, populations that are frequently exposed to extremes in temperature, especially in urban areas, are more prone to the effects of extreme heat due to sociodemographic characteristics known to increase vulnerability [<xref rid="B21-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B23-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24-ijerph-19-12314" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Therefore, further understanding and lessening the disparity in urban thermal exposure should tend to lower the risks of heat-related morbidity and mortality.</p>