<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par50">For example, Colin Macleod argues that there are several ways in which the family is a source of value, some of which focus on the interests of the parents: the intimate relationships that parents have with their children; the identity that having children provides; and the care that parents may receive from their children when they age.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn27">27</xref> Harry Brighouse and Adam Swift argue that the parent-child relationship has distinctive value that makes an important contribution to the flourishing of the parents. The relationship with children has an intimacy that is qualitatively different to other relationships, given the uncontrolled passions, emotions, and interests that children reveal to their parents. Moreover, parents have an interest in the fiduciary role they play for their children.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn28">28</xref> Crucially, they conclude that parenting is an incommensurable relationship. According to Brighouse and Swift, &#8220;the intimacy one can have with one&#8217;s children is quite different from the intimacy one can have with other adults. It makes a contribution to one&#8217;s flourishing of a different kind, and, for many, is not substitutable by relationships of other kinds&#8221;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn29">29</xref> Christine Overall also highlights the uniqueness of the kind of relationship that occurs due to procreative decisions, and stresses that this relationship is key to understanding what is valuable about procreation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn30">30</xref> Luara Ferracioli, extending Overall&#8217;s views, has developed an account of the value of procreative parenting based on the deepness and robustness of the love between parents and children. Her account also highlights how the love between a procreator and the child is distinct from other types of relationships, such as between friends or lovers.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn31">31</xref> Rivka Weinberg stresses that procreation should be understood as an act by adults who want to enrich their lives by engaging in the parent-child relationship.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn32">32</xref> While each of these authors is asking the question what is valuable about procreation as part of slightly different philosophical projects, they all point to the central importance of the unique relationship between parents and children for understanding procreative parenting.</p>