<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par44">Looking now at the carbon tax option, this choice would be less complex to administer than an ETS but there is no way of knowing in advance at what level to set the tax as it may just be absorbed and not result in any reduction of carbon. There are also objections to bodies such as the IMO exerting tax-raising powers, hence the preference to use terminology such as &#8220;contribution&#8221; rather than tax (Kosmas &amp; Acciaro, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>; Psaraftis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2012</xref>). It is also politically difficult to set a suitably high price, which is why political bodies (e.g. the EU) tend to prefer an ETS. Lee et al., (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2013</xref>: 87) analysed the impact of a carbon tax on the economy, concluding that &#8220;imposing a maritime carbon tax on international container shipping will not lead to a significant economic impact unless the tax level is high&#8221;. A 2018 industry survey found that 75% of industry agreed that a carbon price was needed but that they would only be willing to pay a maximum of 50 USD per tonne of CO<sub>2</sub> (Lloyd&#8217;s Register and University Maritime Advisory Services, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2018</xref>). According to the World Bank, a carbon tax of 10&#8211;50 USD per tonne of CO<sub>2</sub> would potentially increase shipping costs by between 0.4&#8211;16 per cent, but only increasing the final goods price by less than 1 per cent (Halim et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2019</xref>). Therefore, industry actors support a price but only one that would produce less than 1% change in the overall price of the goods thus not high enough to cause any change in behaviour, surely a logical contradiction in a supposedly Pigouvian tax. The 2021 capacity crisis in shipping as a result of COVID-19 saw maritime freight rates jump by an average of around 600%, from around 1,000&#8211;3,000 USD per container to 7,000&#8211;10,000 USD (depending on the route) and there is little evidence so far of trade declining, which suggests that demand for maritime transport (at least, container transport) is relatively inelastic. Thus shipping lines would have little trouble passing a tax on to their customers, or they could choose to accept a small reduction in the record profits they are currently earning through these price rises. In order either for the shipping lines not to pass the tax on, or for it to influence customer demand if they did, a carbon tax would therefore need to be of at least a similar level of magnitude, which is far above any existing proposals.</p>