<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="book-review"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Am Hist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Am Hist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jahist</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of American History (Bloomington, Ind.)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-8723</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1945-2314</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7798953</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jahist/jaaa455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jaaa455</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public History Reviews</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/AHU01040</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Documenting COVID-19</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>Kathleen</given-names></name><role>Associate Editor</role><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gudis</surname><given-names>Catherine</given-names></name><role>Associate Editor</role><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution and American, University, Washington, D.C., <email>kathleengfranz@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">University of California, Riverside, <email>cagudis@ucr.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2020-12-01"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>107</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2020. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Organization of American Historians. All rights reserved. For permissions, please e-mail: <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email>.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the COVID-19 pandemic or until permissions are revoked in writing. Upon expiration of these permissions, PMC is granted a perpetual license to make this article available via PMC and Europe PMC, consistent with existing copyright protections.</license-p></license><license license-type="publisher-standard" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model"><license-p>This article is published and distributed under the terms of the Oxford University Press, Standard Journals Publication Model (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model">https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="jaaa455.pdf"/><counts><page-count count="4"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>With closures caused by the COVID-19 pandemic, many public history organizations are facing a tidal wave of change in how they engage audiences and community members now and how they will do so in the future. At the same time, and more than ever in recent memory, we read in the mainstream press and across social media platforms of people's keen awareness of the &#x0201c;historic&#x0201d; moment in which we are living. Global uprisings in response to racialized, state-sanctioned violence and white supremacy in the aftermath of the Memorial Day 2020 police murder of George Floyd have further crystallized the necessity of historical reckoning. This is, in other words, a moment ripe for consideration of how public historians and memory workers can ethically document our current social, public health, and economic crises, and help dismantle structural inequalities through these efforts.</p><p>For this issue's public history reviews, we held three round table discussions with administrators, curators, and organizers of museums and community archives:</p><p>
<bold>R<sc>Icia</sc> A<sc>Nne</sc> C<sc>Hansky</sc></bold> is a professor of literature at the University of Puerto Rico at Mayag&#x000fc;ez and the director of the public humanities project Mi Mar&#x000ed;a: Puerto Rico after the Hurricane.</p><p>
<bold>A<sc>Nna</sc> N. D<sc>Hody</sc></bold> is a forensic anthropologist, the curator of the M&#x000fc;tter Museum of the College of Physicians of Philadelphia, and the director of the M&#x000fc;tter Research Institute.</p><p>
<bold>M<sc>Eredith</sc> E<sc>Vans</sc></bold> is an archivist, historian, and the director of the Jimmy Carter Presidential Library and Museum in Atlanta.</p><p>
<bold>P<sc>Eter</sc> L<sc>Iebhold</sc></bold> is a curator in the Division of Work and Industry of the Smithsonian Institution National Museum of American History.</p><p>
<bold>A<sc>Lexandra</sc> L<sc>Ord</sc></bold> is the chair and a curator of the Division of Medicine and Science of the Smithsonian Institution National Museum of American History.</p><p>
<bold>A<sc>Manda</sc> L. M<sc>Ahoney</sc></bold> is the chief curator of the Dittrick Museum of Medical History at Case Western Reserve University in Cleveland.</p><p>
<bold>L<sc>Ouise</sc> E. S<sc>Haw</sc></bold> is a curator of the David J. Sencer <sc>Cdc</sc> Museum in Atlanta. The finding and conclusions in this report do not necessarily represent the official position of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention/Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry.</p><p>
<bold><sc>Gabriel Solis</sc></bold> is the director of the Texas After Violence Project.</p><p>
<bold>S<sc>Am</sc> V<sc>Ong</sc></bold> is the curator of Asian Pacific American history in the Division of Work and Industry of the Smithsonian Institution National Museum of American History.</p><p>During three days of Zoom conversations, we asked these participants how they and their organizations are documenting the twin pandemics of COVID-19 and racial inequality, and what we can learn from the past. What follows are edited transcripts from our conversations, in three sections: &#x0201c;Precedents to Documenting COVID-19,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Viral Lessons,&#x0201d; related to how current collection efforts might serve public health and medical science, and &#x0201c;Viral Inequalities and an Ethics of Care.&#x0201d;</p><p>These seemingly discrete categories belie the thematic threads that weave the sections together. For instance, the 1918&#x02013;1919 influenza pandemic is an obvious precedent to today's pandemic, but that connection proved challenging for Anna N. Dhody at the M&#x000fc;tter Museum, Peter Liebhold at the Smithsonian's National Museum of American History (<sc>Nmah</sc>), and Amanda L. Mahoney at the Dittrick Museum of Medical History, as their institutions, despite having been founded in the nineteenth century, have few holdings on the earlier pandemic. The omissions reflect collecting patterns that prioritized the white male elite; doctors determined what would be collected, and most were off at war. But the flu was battled largely in the home, with care provided by the invisible ranks of family, nurses, neighbors, and volunteers. These archival silences are loud for participants in all three of our discussions. They consider here the challenges of documenting the experiences of those who provide the bulk of care today&#x02014;the heavily immigrant, often-undocumented, and largely female home health aides, nursing home workers, and nurses&#x02014;the laboring bodies along our food supply chains, as well as the refugee communities that the <sc>Nmah</sc> curator Sam Vong has worked with, who create networks of care out of necessity and outside health care systems and the state. He asks: Are museums doing enough? Are they the correct institutions to help in some way other than sharing stories?</p><p>From the start, we realized, and participants underscored, that protests and the pandemic cannot be disentangled. &#x0201c;The pandemic on the pandemic,&#x0201d; as Louise E. Shaw at the David J. Sencer <sc>Cdc</sc> Museum put it, &#x0201c;lays bare issues of health equity and health disparity&#x0201d; common to both. And it makes apparent the state-sponsored violence underlying both. Whereas many people have never thought much about medicine having a history&#x02014;as Alexandra Lord, of the Division of Medicine and Science at the <sc>Nmah</sc>, points out&#x02014;or being political, the pandemic has offered an education. It has brought into public view the cracks in our public health infrastructure, and its multigenerational and disproportionate effects on black people, indigenous groups, and other peoples of color&#x02014;many also suffering from underlying health conditions born out of poverty and from living amid environmental and industrial pollution. For the same reasons, the pandemic has ravaged people in jails and prisons. The historical imperative to shine a light on these structural inequities is matched by the necessity to responsibly document and center the experiences of those who are most affected, and whose stories have not typically been valued or told.</p><p>To address these past inequities and plan current approaches, we saw collaboration across institutions. For instance, Dhody, Lord, Mahoney, Shaw, and their colleagues in medical museums and federal history offices across the United States have talked biweekly since April to share resources and address collecting efforts. Ricia Anne Chansky, whose Mi Mar&#x000ed;a mass-listening project documents the effects of Hurricane Maria on the people of Puerto Rico, realized that the protocols she had developed could be shared with the partner universities and community groups of the Humanities Action Lab, to link first-person narratives of COVID-19 to climate justice.</p><p>Chansky and others also explore ways to resist the extractive research model that serves researchers (or museums) rather than their subjects, including trauma-informed oral history work that can re-empower people who have been &#x0201c;disempowered by disaster.&#x0201d; Gabriel Solis of the Texas After Violence Project uses stories similarly, as Vong describes, as &#x0201c;tools to counter state discourses.&#x0201d; With Meredith Evans, whose work with digital archives documenting the 2015 shooting of Michael Brown in Ferguson, Missouri, and the <italic>Documenting the Now</italic> project has built community practices that support ethical collection of social media content, Chansky and Solis share the goal of ensuring that people have control over the content they generate. All acknowledge that once these stories are out in the world, control over how they might be used can be lost&#x02014;as has been the case, as Evans explains, with police forces using posts about and photographs of events in Ferguson for surveillance.</p><p>A flurry of crowdsourcing, social media gathering, and other digital collecting was initiated throughout the country after many public historians began teleworking in March, totaling over one hundred projects by the beginning of May. These efforts increased dramatically as protests raged. For instance, numerous public history professors and their students have been participating in the digital curatorial collaborative on Covid-19, <italic>A Journal of the Plague Year</italic>, initiated by Arizona State University (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.covid-19archive.org">http://www.covid-19archive.org</ext-link>). (Note that in a future Public History Reviews section, we will address public history, protests, and the Black Lives Matter movement.) These digital initiatives highlight what Shaw describes here as &#x0201c;the dearth of material culture in the COVID-19 response,&#x0201d; accentuated by our inability to be in physical proximity to one another. Yet, many institutions and groups are collecting&#x02014;mostly stories but also objects&#x02014;and thinking about inclusion, equity, and the ethics of collecting. We also hear from Dhody about how she and others are uncovering &#x0201c;viral histories,&#x0201d; using new technologies to mine the M&#x000fc;tter Museum's specimen collections and &#x0201c;accidental&#x0201d; biorepositories, such as envelopes from the 1918&#x02013;1919 period, sealed with senders' spit and containing letters that narrate their flu experiences&#x02014;a treasure trove of medical history.</p><p>Organizations such as the New-York Historical Society have long collected from significant events, including the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001&#x02014;an experience that Liebhold also recounts here. Yet rapid-response collecting, so named for its aim to salvage artifacts during or just after events occur, pose other challenges and ethical concerns. Mahoney describes these as predatory, and archivists of color often decry them as a form of institutional exploitation and opportunism. In a blog post, the archivist Eira Tansey raises a related concern: How might stories of trauma become &#x0201c;commodities for outsiders to consume every time hurricane season rolls around or a new anniversary&#x0201d; occurs?&#x000a0;Such practices fly in the face of what scholars advocate as a decolonizing process of &#x0201c;slow archiving&#x0201d; that demands time to establish relationships of trust, listening, and an ethics of care.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref></sup></p><p>All three of our conversations indicate deference to community archives, which many believe ought to stay in their communities. Yet dominant institutions should also invest in these archives through funding, training workshops in archival practices, and partnerships that might enable their sustainability. The conversations that follow thus highlight the ways public historians need to address how museums, libraries, and archives can move forward to meet the challenges of functioning in the face of new limitations on social engagement and finally upend the exclusivity of our most well-endowed cultural institutions.</p><p>Though this small sampling of work being conducted nationwide is necessarily limited and is heavily focused on individuals working within large institutions and universities, we hope it will jump-start additional conversations that we can represent in future issues. We welcome comments and reactions to these round table discussions and invite suggestions for ways we might further address in the <italic>JAH</italic> the challenges and potential for public history going forward.</p><p>Please contact:</p><p>Kathleen Franz</p><p>National Museum of American History</p><p>Smithsonian Institution and American</p><p>University</p><p>Washington, D.C.</p><p>
<email>kathleengfranz@gmail.com</email>
</p><p>Catherine Gudis</p><p>University of California, Riverside</p><p>
<email>cagudis@ucr.edu</email>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><title>Footnotes</title><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p>Eira Tansey, &#x0201c;No One Owes Their Trauma to Archivists, or, the Commodification of Contemporaneous Collecting,&#x0201d; June 5, 2020, blog post, <italic>Eira Tansey</italic>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://eiratansey.com">eiratansey.com</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>