<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par4">Global anthropogenic greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions continue to grow, the 2019 level of 52.4 Gt CO<sub>2</sub>e being 59% higher than 1990 and 44% higher than 2000 (PBL Netherlands Environmental Assessment Agency, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2020</xref>). The share of this total contributed by international shipping is increasing, from 2.76% in 2012 to 2.89% in 2018, and the total level of maritime emissions is projected to rise by anything up to 50% by 2050 (IMO, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2020</xref>). While domestic transport emissions are included in nationally determined contributions (NDCs), international maritime emissions are not; responsibility for these was devolved to the International Maritime Organisation (IMO). Existing carbon regulations at the IMO focus only on reducing carbon emissions per tonne-kilometre via efficiency improvements, but the potential for applying market-based mechanisms (MBMs) has been under consideration for some time. Yet MBMs for maritime transport have failed on two levels. First, the forms proposed (regional emission trading schemes and very low carbon taxes) are too weak to achieve decarbonisation of the sector without additional supply-side measures. Second, despite over a decade of discussion, there is little sign of any agreement to implement them at the global level. While many studies have analysed the potential outcomes of MBMs, alternatives are rarely proposed, as solutions to climate change in the transport sector are dominated by market approaches and neoliberal governance (Schwanen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2011</xref>). Equally, the policy literature on MBMs has documented many technical failures such as accurate measurement, equivalence of emissions, free permits and offsets, which, even if addressed, would not resolve fundamental problems such as the prioritisation of efficiency that locks in the existing system and disincentivises a transition away from fossil fuels (Bryant, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2017</xref>; Lohmann, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2010</xref>; Pearse &amp; B&#246;hm, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2014</xref>). The aim of this paper is to explore the continued attraction of MBMs to achieve decarbonisation of the maritime transport sector, despite these well-known shortcomings. This question will be explored in the context of business and market ethics, seeking to understand the continued legitimisation of market-based approaches and the exclusion of alternatives.</p>