<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par20">Under the aegis of a development model that attempts to reconcile new patterns of production, consumption and carbon finance, the repertoire of climate negotiations broadened its themes (e.g., gender, food, and labour), concepts (adaptation, resilience, climate justice), cooperation mechanisms (investments in local funds and projects, monitoring, capacity building) and economic instruments (carbon pricing, emission trading). The economic models promising to expand sustainable development and regulating commercial relations based on mitigation standards and geoengineering constitute another step in the climate change agenda&#8217;s increased degree of sophistication (not without contradictions) when it comes to capitalist transformations. Sustainability, the green economy, clean transition, net zero carbon, decarbonization and bioeconomy are all concepts that are part and parcel of the semantic field of the climate agenda. They unfold in the historical materiality of new modernity and capitalist experiences, thus producing key effects on the economic and social life of both China and the EU, who share the commonality of being capitalist powers and political supporters of multilateral practices in the construction of a planetary pro-climate collective action:<disp-quote><p id="Par21">III. Fundamental thinking and strategy about socialism with Chinese characteristics in the new era: 4. Persist in new concepts of <italic>development</italic>. [...] IX. Accelerate institutional reform of eco civilisation to build a beautiful China: 1. Increase green development. We must accelerate the implementation of a legal system and policy orientation in relation to green production and consumption, establishing and improving a green, circular and low-carbon economic development system. [&#8230;] We must advocate a simple, adequate, green and low-carbon lifestyle [&#8230;], to foster green ways of life. (Xi Jinping, Report of the 19th National Congress of the Communist Party of China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2017</xref>)</p><p id="Par22">Climate change and the environmental degradation affect every human being. This needs a global solution. The EU is committed to: Leading by example, through the European Green Deal; Using diplomacy, trade and development cooperation to advance climate action; Setting standards for <italic>sustainable growth</italic> across global value chains [&#8230;]. The European Green Deal is our plan to make the EU's economy sustainable. We can do this by turning climate and environmental challenges into opportunities [&#8230;]. (The European Green Deal, European Commission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2019</xref>)</p></disp-quote></p>