<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Second, the central preoccupation of this research community is linking theoretical analyses to action on the ground, from allocating responsibilities to developing evaluation means. For example, while both waves are characterized by a combination of a variety of methods, from case studies to quantitative and comparative analyses (Figure <xref rid="wcc643-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), they differ in their research objectives. In the first wave, quantitative analyses supported the development of frameworks to quantify and measure indicators relevant in adaptation research. This quantification focused, for example, on mapping vulnerabilities alongside climate risk (De Sherbinin, Schiller, &amp; Pulsipher, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0106" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Douglas et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0115" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Hardoy &amp; Pandiella, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0143" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; McGranahan, Balk, &amp; Anderson, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0203" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Muller, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0208" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Revi, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0235" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Romero Lankao, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0242" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Romero&#8208;Lankao et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0244" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), grounding indicator systems for assessing adaptation options (Chandra &amp; Gaganis, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0090" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Chang &amp; Huang, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0091" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Chelleri, Waters, Olazabal, &amp; Minucci, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0092" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Haque, Grafakos, &amp; Huijsman, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0141" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Jabareen, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0162" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Malakar &amp; Mishra, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0198" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Restemeyer, Woltjer, &amp; van den Brink, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0234" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Tyler &amp; Moench, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0282" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) and supporting adaptation planning (Albers &amp; Deppisch, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Johnson &amp; Blackburn, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0164" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Lu &amp; Stead, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0192" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Spaans &amp; Waterhout, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0273" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In contrast, in the second wave, quantitative analysis has been developed following a growing interest in comparison of actions across regions and cities, which goes beyond the traditional focus of the discipline in case study research (but see a contrasting analysis in van der Heijden, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0285" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The shift between the two waves represents a move from exploring the &#8220;hows&#8221; and &#8220;whys&#8221; of climate action to engage with the &#8220;so what&#8221; aspects that interrogate both the efficacy and impact of climate action in urban areas. From a perspective of science as a theory&#8208;testing enterprise, this shift appears as a sign of maturation of the field, as it gradually moves from theory building to theory testing and attempts to establish a shared basis for actionable ideas. However, we see this change as the product of the coevolution between scientific analyses and policy discourses, in the context of a policy&#8208;responsive field of research.</p>