<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">These two periods of acceleration correspond to two waves in the literature of climate change governance: the first wave of <italic toggle="yes">urban optimism</italic> and the second wave of <italic toggle="yes">urban pragmatism</italic>. The first wave coincides with the rise of &#8220;urban optimism&#8221; in global sustainable development agendas (Barnett &amp; Parnell, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0056" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) that led to the publication of major policy reports that sought to mobilize cities and urban areas in international events and high policy forums (Atkins, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0048" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Hoornweg, Freire, Lee, Bhada&#8208;Tata, &amp; Yuen, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0154" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; UN&#8208;Habitat, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0284" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). This wave followed changes in mainstream thought about climate action. Until the mid&#8208;2000s, debates on climate change and cities focused on the reduction of carbon emissions. Around 2006, interest in climate change adaptation led to an increase in climate change adaptation studies that explicitly incorporated considerations of justice, equity, informality, poverty, and gender as embedded in risk, vulnerability, and resilience agendas (Dodman &amp; Satterthwaite, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0113" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Kovats &amp; Akhtar, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0176" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Satterthwaite, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0254" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). These pioneering adaptation scholars, who mostly conducted their research in rapidly growing urban areas in the Global South, were concerned with the structural drivers of vulnerability as a means to develop their theoretical inquiry (defining vulnerability and resilience), and frameworks for urgently needed action. Scholars focused on mitigation tended to study large cities in the North with significant carbon footprints, focused on assessments of policy instruments, effective management, and drivers of action (Betsill &amp; Bulkeley, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0066" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Bulkeley &amp; Kern, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0076" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). A concern was that growing interest in mitigation deviated attention from adaptation or vice versa (Davoudi, Crawford, &amp; Mehmood, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0105" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). During the first wave of <italic toggle="yes">urban optimism</italic> these two approaches came together. Our analysis shows that rather than turn attention away from each other, the cross&#8208;fertilization of work across the adaptation and mitigation divide led to a diversification of research topics and the expansion of the authorship&#8208;base. Cross&#8208;cutting topics, such as urban informality, nature&#8208;based approaches, and community&#8208;based, collaborative, and participatory approaches supported the accelerated growth of scholarship, leading to calls for more research on practical outcomes. This process led to the emergence of new concerns that eventually consolidated into a second wave of <italic toggle="yes">urban pragmatism</italic>.</p>