<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par52">In response to scepticism that the project was a ploy for the mayor to put up &#8220;big sticks&#8221; &#8211; a moniker for the supertall luxury residential skyscrapers going up elsewhere in the neighborhood &#8211; the city saw it as essential to appeal to the objectivity of engineering to regain its legitimate authority. Max Weber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2004</xref>) contended that the authority of bureaucratic agencies is based on their perceived objectivity, so it was essential for New York city agencies to distance themselves from political motivations: &#8220;Bureaucracy,&#8221; Weber wrote, &#8220;develops the more perfectly, the more it is &#8216;dehumanized,&#8217; the more completely it succeeds in eliminating from official business love, hatred, and all purely personal, irrational, and emotional elements which escape calculation.&#8221; The city&#8217;s leaning on technical experts was meant to approach this ideal of bureaucratic objectivity, to distance itself from politics, and to regain its authority. As Theodore Porter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">1996</xref>) argues, bureaucratic agencies are expected to show &#8220;mechanical objectivity,&#8221; and so to avoid seeming biased, &#8220;expertise should be mechanized and objectified. It should be grounded in specific techniques sanctioned by a body of specialists.&#8221; Moreover, this mechanical objectivity, Porter argues, is especially important for weak agencies in controversial situations that must demonstrate the objectivity of how they make decisions: &#8220;objectivity lends authority to officials who have very little of their own&#8221;&#160;(see also Lakoff &amp; Klinenberg, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2010</xref> for another example of the difficult entanglement between politics and mechanical objectivity). But the city&#8217;s appeals to objectivity were not convincing in indicating their adherence to rationality over politics in the eyes of the public, since the professional relations of civil engineers, consultants, and climate scientists with city agencies tainted their technical expertise.</p>