<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par41">In September 2018, near the 6th year anniversary of Sandy, the Mayor&#8217;s Office announced a new design for the ESCR based on internal reviews by the city&#8217;s own agencies without collaborating with either private design firms or the public&#8217;s input. During a Community Board Parks Committee meeting, on a late September evening after several months of silence, city officials from the Department of Design and Construction (DDC) and the Parks Department presented a plan drastically different than the previous plan of public consensus. The new proposal moved far from the original BIG design that had gone through years of collaborative processes, and did away with the inland berms and the idea of a park as a sponge designed to absorb floodwaters (see Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Instead, it will be built around a dirt fill, raising the current park and rebuilding the park on top of this fill. Rather than the sponge-like storm-surge-absorbing soft slopes, the project would involve traditional hard seawalls near the river supporting the several feet of fill. The new project is also budgeted at $700 million dollars more than the original plan, lifting not only the park by around 8 or 10&#160;ft, but also the price tag to $1.45 billion. This change sparked public outrage and confusion at the notion of getting extensive public input and then building a different, more expensive project.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Schematic cross-section illustrating difference between previous plan and current plan. Source: &#8220;Interactive Community Engagement Meeting&#8221; at Gouverneur Health on December 10, 2018</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11186_2021_9459_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Hypothetical storm conditions illustrating differences in flooding between previous plan (left) and current plan (right). Source: &#8220;Interactive Community Engagement Meeting&#8221; at Gouverneur Health on December 10, 2018</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11186_2021_9459_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>