<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par43">Two official explanations were put forth, one from DDC and another from the Department of Parks &amp; Recreation. Jamie Torres-Springer, a white middle-aged Deputy Commissioner of DDC, explained to a crowd in early summer of 2019 that about 6 or 7&#160;months previously a number of engineering reviews looked at whether DDC could deliver the plan. DDC is responsible for the construction of the project. Torres-Springer holds a Master&#8217;s degree in public policy from Harvard University and was wearing business-casual attire. &#8220;And look,&#8221; he said, &#8220;this is hard stuff, there have been engineers from all around the world that have looked at this challenge, and it took a while.&#8221; Upon close inspection, engineers found a number of problems with the public plan. First, to build a structural wall on the western, inside part of the park, DDC would have to work with &#8220;big powerlines,&#8221; ConEdison utility lines, under the area where the concrete edge was supposed to go (see the concrete wall represented as a dark orange edge in the old plan in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), making construction a delicate affair and potentially extending the timeline of the project. Second, DDC would have to build the wall adjacent to the FDR. The Deputy Commissioner explained: &#8220;And not that we&#8217;re all about cars all the time, but to ensure safety when you&#8217;re building a structural flood wall, you can&#8217;t have cars passing by overhead. And you have to close portions of the highway. And to prevent cars from using that portion of the highway and getting into the neighborhood, we had to do that work at night.&#8221; The Deputy Commissioner stated that the construction period would then entail four years of nighttime work next to the FDR, where contractors would have to be driving piles into the ground. He finished his explanation by saying: &#8220;So okay, we would have had to drive this floodwall into the ground, next to where people were living, adjacent to the FDR, in the middle of the night, every night for four years. We came to the conclusion that that wasn&#8217;t gonna work.&#8221;</p>