<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par48">The substance of what was up for debate in the new plan was also different than before. Take the following example: At a public hearing in early summer of 2019, a white woman in her 30&#8217;s asked city officials about visual connectivity from the neighborhood to the East River. &#8220;There&#8217;s a lot of places now in the LES and East Village, where you can see the park and the river,&#8221; she said, &#8220;so I&#8217;m picturing... if the park is 8 feet higher, will we be looking at the wall? And are there ways that you&#8217;re going to pull the park into the city, so that those who are not using the park on a daily basis nevertheless feel drawn into it?&#8221; As described above, the issue of park access points and visual connectivity was previously up for deliberation. Now, Jamie Torres-Springer, the DDC Deputy Commissioner, responded in a way that acknowledged her concern while invoking long-term climate change as a reason to legitimize the current plan:<disp-quote><p id="Par49">&#8220;The way I&#8217;d ask people to think about it is that we&#8217;re dealing with climate change, and we have our waterfront edge, and sometimes there&#8217;s a conflict. We see this in cities across the country, where you have people who really want to see the water all the time, but then we are realizing that that&#8217;s actually a threat to us.&#8221;</p></disp-quote>At another meeting earlier in the year, an attendee asked a similar question and received a similar answer. &#8220;We need to acknowledge that we&#8217;re entering a very different era of living in waterfront cities,&#8221; said the Deputy Commissioner. As a result, participants who remained involved in the process increasingly felt that decisions had already been made, that their input was now symbolic, and that they would not see their contributions reflected in how the plans evolved.</p>