<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">During the two-year teaching-learning period, the multi-disaster context regionally, nationally, and internationally formed an ideal platform for engaging GSW in teaching and training. This multi-disaster context features all three types of hazards, namely, natural hazards, technological hazards, and intentional and willful hazards. Notably, the global public health emergency of the COVID-19 pandemic, progressing from local zoonotic disease (a natural hazard) to an international catastrophe, profoundly impacted international communities, uncovering tremendous societal injustices, and jeopardized inhabitants and co-inhabitants&#8217; physical health, mental wellness, and overall well-being [<xref rid="B44-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="B45-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="B46-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Throughout Canada, climate change-induced natural hazards, such as annual wildfires, floods, extreme high and low temperatures, snowstorms, and hurricanes, further increased environmental and social injustices for vulnerable and marginalized groups and negatively affected their health and well-being [<xref rid="B47-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="B48-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="B49-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Furthermore, technological hazards, such as lead water pipe and power outage [<xref rid="B50-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="B51-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], and willful hazards, including the 2020 Nova Scotia attacks [<xref rid="B52-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and Russia&#8217;s invasion of the Ukraine and refugees [<xref rid="B53-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], directly and indirectly, have caused negative tolls on the health and well-being of residents and co-residents in Canada and beyond. These domestic and international extreme events propel international social workers to contextualize their micro-, mezzo-, and macro-level interventions within the community, regional, national, and international milieus, reflecting environmental justice, advancing social justice, and contributing to global citizen&#8217;s health and well-being [<xref rid="B54-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="B55-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].</p>