<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Climate laws and policies are concerned with &#8216;mitigating, regulating or adapting&#8217; industrial activity which causes climate change. The United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) was signed by 154 states in 1992 acknowledging &#8220;that the global nature of climate change calls for the widest possible cooperation by all countries and their participation in an effective and appropriate response&#8221; [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Both the Paris Agreement [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] adopted by the Conference of the Parties (COP21) and the &#8220;UN Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs)&#8221; have guided development in this field. Although, health is not always specifically articulated in national laws and policies that address economic regulations on energy, electric utilities, construction, agriculture and industry, it is commonly implicit that the objective of these policies is human and planetary ecosystem survival. The evidential failure of <italic toggle="yes">implied</italic> protection of planetary health, stability of the climate and human health through existing laws provides a powerful argument that such protections must be made <italic toggle="yes">explicit</italic> and legally binding. For most nations the legal basis exists as in 2015, 193 nations endorsed the SDGs including SDG 3, which aims to &#8220;ensure healthy lives and to promote well-being for all ages&#8221; [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and the Paris Agreement, endorsed by 196 countries, emphasizes the &#8220;right to health&#8221;. Whereas the SDGs are not legally binding, the Paris Agreement is. [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Yet with few legal teeth, it does not impose penalties, such as fees or embargos, for parties that violate its terms, and there is no international court or governing body ready to enforce compliance. Experts argue that in reality, the Paris Agreement is not legally binding [<xref rid="pone.0268633.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</p>