<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.3"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Can J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Can J Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Canadian Journal of Public Health = Revue Canadienne de Sant&#x000e9; Publique</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0008-4263</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1920-7476</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8803277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35102529</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">608</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17269/s41997-022-00608-w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial/&#x000c9;ditorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COP26: what is the message for public health?</article-title><trans-title-group><trans-title xml:lang="fr">CdP-26 : quel est le message pour la sant&#x000e9; publique?</trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>Jeffrey</given-names></name><address><email>jeffmasuda@uvic.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>Lindsay</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>Blake</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.143640.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9465</institution-id><institution>School of Public Health and Social Policy, </institution><institution>University of Victoria, </institution></institution-wrap>Victoria, BC Canada </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.22072.35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7697</institution-id><institution>Department of Community Health Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Calgary, </institution></institution-wrap>Calgary, AB Canada </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.439960.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2180 0865</institution-id><institution>Canadian Centre for Policy Alternatives (National Office), </institution></institution-wrap>Ottawa, ON Canada </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.17063.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2157 2938</institution-id><institution>Dalla Lana School of Public Health, </institution><institution>University of Toronto, </institution></institution-wrap>Toronto, ON Canada </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) under exclusive license to The Canadian Public Health Association 2022</copyright-statement></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) under exclusive license to The Canadian Public Health Association 2022</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1">From October 31 to November 12, 2021, Glasgow, Scotland, hosted the 26th United Nations Climate Change conference, known as Conference of the Parties (COP) 26. Expectations were at an all-time high as this negotiation was widely seen to be the last best chance for governments to come to an agreement that would hold global temperature increases to 1.5&#x000b0;&#x000a0;Celsius in accordance with the 2015 Paris Agreement. In an effort to ensure that the Paris Agreement&#x02019;s commitment for a &#x0201c;right to health&#x0201d; would be meaningfully implemented in the pact, the World Health Organization-hosted Pavilion saw 10 days of presentations and discussions dedicated to placing health and equity &#x0201c;at the centre of climate negotiations&#x0201d; (World Health Organization [WHO], <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2021</xref>; p.VIII).</p><p id="Par2">Yet, to the dismay of many in the public health community, the final outcome of COP26 was largely devoid of substantive content with regard to the public health dimensions of climate change. In fact, &#x0201c;health&#x0201d; only appears once in the final COP26 pact, and only then in reference to healthcare institutions committing to reduce emissions by half by 2030. Such a paucity of recognition was particularly ironic given that COP26 had already been postponed by a year due to the COVID-19 pandemic, which itself has been inextricably linked with ecological change (Poland &#x00026; Ziolo, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2021</xref>; Wu, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2021</xref>; Canadian Public Health Association, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>).</p><p id="Par3">While the ecological crisis of the COVID-19 pandemic ought to bolster the relevance of public health within global climate discussions, it seems that in the present moment, the tendency is to have only one eye open. Rather than expanding our remit, COVID-19 has narrowed the government&#x02019;s agenda and dominated public health system capacity even while population-level health impacts of a changing climate are unfolding before our eyes. We need both eyes to see the full picture. Furthermore, we need a global perspective more than ever. While climate events like atmospheric rivers washing out highways and flooding farms in BC are having tremendous significance locally, such climate events pale in comparison to droughts and flooding across the Global South that are devastating large populations of people in the form of famines, forced migration, and political conflict (Leal Filho et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2021</xref>; Kelley et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2015</xref>; Chowdhury et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2020</xref>). Barbados Prime Minister Mia Mottley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>) posed the question most succinctly at COP26, &#x0201c;Can there be peace and prosperity in one third of the world if two thirds are under siege and facing calamitous threats to their well-being?&#x0201d;</p><p id="Par4">What should we make of this double lacuna toward the public health dimensions of the climate crisis and toward the ecological basis of the COVID-19 crisis? We offer three propositions that may move the conversation forward.</p><p id="Par5">The first speaks to our principles. It seems clear that we need to do a better job of walking the talk when it comes to a core principle of a socioecological approach to public health. Unfortunately, both the proximal discussions of incremental, industry-centred focused solutions that dominate climate change discourse and the equally incremental, pharmaceutically centred solutions that dominate COVID-19 discourse suggest we have a long way to go. What is missing is a structural critique of the underlying systems that produce crisis in the first place, that is, the antecedent causes of the causes (Commission on Social Determinants of Health [CSDH], <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>) that might get us toward a structural whole-of-society <italic>transformation</italic>.</p><p id="Par6">We refer specifically to the need to shift away from a global political economic system that, over the past 400 years, and certainly after the advent of fossil-fueled capitalism in the past century, has manifested as a regime of obstruction (Carroll, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2021</xref>) in Canada and across the globe to maintain an unsustainable status quo of perpetual economic growth. Undoing the path dependency that global capitalism has put us on&#x02014;one that has literally colonized the planet&#x02014;requires that we direct focus on the inequitable distribution of power that, while global in reach, has been highly localized in function and consequence. That power, which coincides with the highest carbon-emitting nations of the world, has served to accumulate unsustainable wealth through the dispossession of the world&#x02019;s poor from their own lands, resources, and traditions (Lee &#x00026; Masuda, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par7">The second proposition speaks to our allegiances. Put plainly, principles of equity that are so central to public health are fundamentally incompatible with our institutional positioning within the very capitalist systems that we might see as the culprit in the global ecological crisis. It needs to be emphasized that public health&#x02019;s core modus operandus, risk management, is by design conservative in nature: it is about managing the fallout of existing systems without fundamentally challenging those systems, and it emphasizes the kind of resilience that is about bouncing back from adversity in a manner that returns us to a highly inequitable normal. This is perhaps not surprising: an emphasis on transformative change and the capacity to bounce forward to new ways of thinking and doing would be out of step with the political masters to which public health is, by virtue of being a publicly funded institution, largely beholden. Not that brave public health leaders have not spoken truth to power, during the pandemic as well as before, on this and other issues. But we need to do more, and that includes deep reflection on our ongoing inability to commit to fundamentally different, that is decolonizing, forms of practice inherent within Indigenous public health (Lewis et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2020</xref>). Rather than doing risk management better to respond to the escalating fallout of the dominant system, we need to be doing better things, such as hastening and supporting the transition to a low-carbon &#x0201c;Symbiocene&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;bouncing forward&#x0201d; to new ways of seeing and doing that reflect a relational worldview, working with unusual allies to champion racial/climate justice, community-centred resilience, relocalization, and more (Poland et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par8">The third proposition speaks to our preparations, and particularly the need to prepare the public health workforce for a more ecologically centred practice suited to the challenges that are now upon us. Although post-secondary education and training programs in public health have proliferated over the past two decades following the last pandemic, i.e., SARS (Mass&#x000e9; &#x00026; Moloughney, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2011</xref>), recent analysis shows significant omissions (Yassi et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>) and institutional apathy (Castleden et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2020</xref>) when it comes to social, ecological, and colonial determinants and dimensions of well-being and health equity. This finding is striking, given that social and ecological determinants of health have been positioned centrally in public health concepts for nearly a half-century (WHO, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1986</xref>; CSDH, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>). Yet, the double exclusion of public health silence in COP26 and of ecologically focused actions in the response to COVID-19 (Hancock et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>) belies such a legacy. It reflects a training-to-practice gap created by the pressure to produce job-ready graduates that limits the inclination (among students as much as educators) to go very far in terms of political economy, political ecology, degrowth, Indigenous ways of knowing, doughnut economics (Raworth, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2017</xref>), feminist ethics of care, deep adaptation, sustainability transitions, or peak oil. To be frank, while we observe that such topics are sought after by more and more students in our programs, most public health jobs rarely encompass any of these domains of action. As pointed out by Hancock and McLaren (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2021</xref>), public health still &#x0201c;plays into the hands of the critics who have always wanted to curtail public health to a biomedical focus on communicable diseases; to have us &#x02018;stay in our lane&#x02019; and not discuss economic and social injustice or ecological limits&#x0201d; (p. 792).</p><p id="Par9">To conclude, our ongoing failure to align our principles, our allegiances, and our preparations to the existential ecological crises we face today will ultimately lead to the further deterioration of our relevance, far beyond COP26. Relinquishing our commitment to social and ecological justice contributes to a pernicious tendency, by members of the public, politicians, and indeed many within our public health communities, to conflate health and healthcare, and to fail to make the connection between health and its broader contexts and determinants (The Lancet, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2019</xref>; McLaren &#x00026; Hennessy, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2020</xref>). We invite, and indeed plead for, broader discussion from and with our communities around &#x0201c;equity-focused and decolonizing public health actions that prevent, mitigate, and recover from climate and other ecological impacts in ways that promote health and sustainability from community to planetary levels&#x0201d; (Canadian Journal of Public Health, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">n.d.</xref>).</p><p id="Par10">Jeff Masuda, CJPH Senior Editor; School of Public Health and Social Policy, University of Victoria</p><p id="Par11">Lindsay McLaren, CJPH Senior Editor; Department of Community Health Sciences, University of Calgary; Canadian Centre for Policy Alternatives</p><p id="Par12">Blake Poland, CJPH Associate Editor; Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto</p><sec id="Sec1"><title>&#x000c9;ditorial</title><p id="Par13">Du 31 octobre au 12 novembre 2021, la ville de Glasgow, en &#x000c9;cosse, a accueilli la 26<sup>e</sup> Conf&#x000e9;rence des Parties &#x000e0; la Convention-cadre des Nations Unies sur les changements climatiques, ou CdP-26. Les attentes &#x000e9;taient plus &#x000e9;lev&#x000e9;es que jamais, cette n&#x000e9;gociation &#x000e9;tant g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;ralement per&#x000e7;ue comme la derni&#x000e8;re grande chance pour les gouvernements de s&#x02019;entendre sur le maintien des hausses de la temp&#x000e9;rature mondiale &#x000e0; 1,5 degr&#x000e9; Celcius&#x000a0;comme convenu dans l&#x02019;Accord de Paris de 2015. Pour que l&#x02019;engagement de l&#x02019;Accord de Paris en faveur d&#x02019;un &#x000ab; droit &#x000e0; la sant&#x000e9; &#x000bb; soit v&#x000e9;ritablement appliqu&#x000e9; dans le pacte, le Pavillon de la sant&#x000e9; de l&#x02019;OMS a consacr&#x000e9; 10 jours de pr&#x000e9;sentations et de discussions &#x000e0; placer la sant&#x000e9; et l&#x02019;&#x000e9;quit&#x000e9; &#x000ab; au centre des n&#x000e9;gociations sur le climat &#x000bb; (World Health Organization [WHO], <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2021</xref>; p.VIII).</p><p id="Par14">Pourtant, au grand d&#x000e9;sespoir de nombreux membres de la communaut&#x000e9; de la sant&#x000e9; publique, la CdP-26 s&#x02019;est sold&#x000e9;e dans une large mesure par l&#x02019;absence de contenu substantiel quant aux aspects sanitaires de la lutte contre les changements climatiques. En fait, le mot &#x000ab; sant&#x000e9; &#x000bb; ne figure qu&#x02019;une seule fois dans le pacte de Glasgow, et seulement en lien avec l&#x02019;engagement des &#x000e9;tablissements de soins de sant&#x000e9; &#x000e0; r&#x000e9;duire leurs &#x000e9;missions de moiti&#x000e9; d&#x02019;ici 2030. Une reconnaissance aussi t&#x000e9;nue est particuli&#x000e8;rement ironique, sachant que la CdP-26 avait d&#x000e9;j&#x000e0; &#x000e9;t&#x000e9; repouss&#x000e9;e d&#x02019;un an en raison de la pand&#x000e9;mie de COVID-19, elle-m&#x000ea;me inextricablement li&#x000e9;e aux changements &#x000e9;cologiques (Poland &#x00026; Ziolo, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2021</xref>; Wu, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2021</xref>; Canadian Public Health Association, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>).</p><p id="Par15">La crise &#x000e9;cologique de la pand&#x000e9;mie de COVID-19 aurait d&#x000fb; rendre la sant&#x000e9; publique encore plus pertinente dans les discussions mondiales sur le climat, mais il semble que pour l&#x02019;instant, la tendance est de n&#x02019;ouvrir qu&#x02019;un &#x00153;il. Au lieu d&#x02019;&#x000e9;largir les attributions de la sant&#x000e9; publique, la COVID-19 a r&#x000e9;tr&#x000e9;ci le programme d&#x02019;action du gouvernement et domin&#x000e9; la capacit&#x000e9; du syst&#x000e8;me de sant&#x000e9; publique, alors m&#x000ea;me que les effets sanitaires des changements climatiques sur les populations se d&#x000e9;ploient devant nos yeux. Nous avons besoin de nos deux yeux pour voir la situation dans son ensemble. Nous avons aussi plus que jamais besoin d&#x02019;une perspective mondiale. Des ph&#x000e9;nom&#x000e8;nes climatiques comme les rivi&#x000e8;res atmosph&#x000e9;riques qui ont emport&#x000e9; des routes et inond&#x000e9; des fermes en Colombie-Britannique sont d&#x02019;une tr&#x000e8;s grande importance localement, mais ces ph&#x000e9;nom&#x000e8;nes font pi&#x000e8;tre figure face aux s&#x000e9;cheresses et aux inondations dans les pays du Sud, qui ont des cons&#x000e9;quences d&#x000e9;vastatrices pour les populations : famines, migrations forc&#x000e9;es et conflits politiques (Leal Filho et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2021</xref>; Kelley et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2015</xref>; Chowdhury et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2020</xref>). C&#x02019;est la premi&#x000e8;re ministre de la Barbade, Mia Mottley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>), qui a pos&#x000e9; la question le plus succinctement &#x000e0; la CdP-26 : &#x000ab; Peut-il y avoir paix et prosp&#x000e9;rit&#x000e9; si un tiers du monde vit dans la prosp&#x000e9;rit&#x000e9; et que les deux tiers vivent sous les mers et font face &#x000e0; des menaces catastrophiques pour notre bien-&#x000ea;tre? &#x000bb;</p><p id="Par16">Que penser de cette double lacune, face aux aspects sanitaires de la lutte contre les changements climatiques et face aux fondements &#x000e9;cologiques de la crise de la COVID-19? Nous sugg&#x000e9;rons trois propositions pour faire avancer le d&#x000e9;bat.</p><p id="Par17">La premi&#x000e8;re porte sur nos principes. Il semble clair que nous ne joignons pas le geste &#x000e0; la parole sur un principe fondamental : celui d&#x02019;une approche socio&#x000e9;cologique de la sant&#x000e9; publique. Malheureusement, tant les discussions proximales de solutions progressives ax&#x000e9;es sur l&#x02019;industrie, qui dominent le discours sur les changements climatiques, que les solutions pharmaceutiques, tout aussi progressives, qui dominent le discours sur la COVID-19 montrent que nous avons un long chemin &#x000e0; parcourir. Ce qui manque, c&#x02019;est une critique structurelle des syst&#x000e8;mes sous-jacents &#x000e0; l&#x02019;origine de la crise, autrement dit, des causes ant&#x000e9;c&#x000e9;dentes des causes (Commission on Social Determinants of Health [CSDH], <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>) qui pourraient nous conduire &#x000e0; une <italic>transformation</italic> structurelle de toute la soci&#x000e9;t&#x000e9;.</p><p id="Par18">Nous faisons sp&#x000e9;cifiquement r&#x000e9;f&#x000e9;rence au besoin de nous &#x000e9;loigner du syst&#x000e8;me politico-&#x000e9;conomique mondial qui, depuis 400 ans et certainement depuis l&#x02019;av&#x000e8;nement du capitalisme des 100 derni&#x000e8;res ann&#x000e9;es, aliment&#x000e9; par les combustibles fossiles, se manifeste par un r&#x000e9;gime d&#x02019;obstruction (Carroll, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2021</xref>), au Canada et dans le monde, pour maintenir le statu quo intenable d&#x02019;une croissance &#x000e9;conomique perp&#x000e9;tuelle. Pour nous d&#x000e9;faire de la &#x000ab; d&#x000e9;pendance envers la voie choisie &#x000bb; impos&#x000e9;e par le capitalisme mondial&#x02014;une voie qui a litt&#x000e9;ralement colonis&#x000e9; la plan&#x000e8;te&#x02014;nous devons porter attention &#x000e0; la distribution in&#x000e9;quitable du pouvoir qui, bien que de port&#x000e9;e mondiale, est tr&#x000e8;s localis&#x000e9;e dans son fonctionnement et ses cons&#x000e9;quences. Ce pouvoir, concentr&#x000e9; dans les pays qui &#x000e9;mettent le plus de carbone, a servi &#x000e0; accumuler une richesse non durable en d&#x000e9;poss&#x000e9;dant les pauvres de leurs terres, de leurs ressources et de leurs traditions (Lee &#x00026; Masuda, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par19">La deuxi&#x000e8;me proposition porte sur nos all&#x000e9;geances. &#x000c0; dire bien franchement, les principes d&#x02019;&#x000e9;quit&#x000e9; si importants pour la sant&#x000e9; publique sont fondamentalement incompatibles avec le positionnement de nos institutions au sein de ces m&#x000ea;mes syst&#x000e8;mes capitalistes en qui nous voyons les coupables de la crise &#x000e9;cologique mondiale. Il faut souligner la gestion des risques &#x02013; qui est le mode de fonctionnement de base de la sant&#x000e9; publique &#x02013; est conservatrice de nature : elle vise &#x000e0; g&#x000e9;rer les retomb&#x000e9;es des syst&#x000e8;mes existants sans vraiment les remettre en cause, et elle met l&#x02019;accent sur le genre de r&#x000e9;silience qui consiste &#x000e0; se remettre rapidement de l&#x02019;adversit&#x000e9; et &#x000e0; revenir &#x000e0; la situation normale, si in&#x000e9;quitable soit-elle. Il ne faut pas s&#x02019;en &#x000e9;tonner : un accent sur le changement transformateur et sur la capacit&#x000e9; de saisir au bond de nouvelles fa&#x000e7;ons de penser et de faire les choses serait en d&#x000e9;calage avec la volont&#x000e9; des ma&#x000ee;tres politiques auxquels la sant&#x000e9; publique est en grande mesure redevable en tant qu&#x02019;institution subventionn&#x000e9;e par l&#x02019;&#x000c9;tat. Bien s&#x000fb;r, de braves responsables de la sant&#x000e9; publique ont donn&#x000e9; l&#x02019;heure juste aux tenants du pouvoir, durant la pand&#x000e9;mie et avant, sur cette question et sur d&#x02019;autres. Mais nous devons faire plus, et notamment r&#x000e9;fl&#x000e9;chir s&#x000e9;rieusement &#x000e0; notre incapacit&#x000e9; continue de souscrire aux formes de pratique fondamentalement diff&#x000e9;rentes, c&#x02019;est-&#x000e0;-dire d&#x000e9;colonisantes, inh&#x000e9;rentes &#x000e0; la sant&#x000e9; publique autochtone (Lewis et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2020</xref>). Au lieu d&#x02019;am&#x000e9;liorer notre gestion des risques pour faire face aux retomb&#x000e9;es grandissantes du syst&#x000e8;me dominant, nous devons faire de meilleures choses, comme de h&#x000e2;ter et d&#x02019;appuyer la transition vers un &#x000ab; Symbioc&#x000e8;ne &#x000bb; sobre en carbone, de &#x000ab; saisir au bond &#x000bb; de nouvelles fa&#x000e7;ons de voir et de faire qui refl&#x000e8;tent une vision relationnelle du monde, de travailler avec des alli&#x000e9;s inhabituels pour d&#x000e9;fendre la justice raciale/climatique, la r&#x000e9;silience centr&#x000e9;e sur la communaut&#x000e9;, la relocalisation et plus (Poland et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par20">La troisi&#x000e8;me proposition porte sur nos pr&#x000e9;paratifs, en particulier sur le besoin de pr&#x000e9;parer la main-d&#x02019;&#x00153;uvre en sant&#x000e9; publique pour une pratique plus centr&#x000e9;e sur l&#x02019;&#x000e9;cologie, mieux adapt&#x000e9;e aux difficult&#x000e9;s qui nous attendent. Les programmes d&#x02019;enseignement et de formation postsecondaires en sant&#x000e9; publique prolif&#x000e8;rent depuis la derni&#x000e8;re pand&#x000e9;mie, celle du SRAS, il y a 20 ans (Mass&#x000e9; &#x00026; Moloughney, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2011</xref>), mais des analyses r&#x000e9;centes font &#x000e9;tat d&#x02019;omissions importantes (Yassi et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>) et de l&#x02019;apathie des institutions (Castleden et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2020</xref>) lorsqu&#x02019;il s&#x02019;agit des d&#x000e9;terminants et des aspects sociaux, &#x000e9;cologiques et coloniaux du bien-&#x000ea;tre et de l&#x02019;&#x000e9;quit&#x000e9; en sant&#x000e9;. Ces constatations sont frappantes, sachant que les d&#x000e9;terminants sociaux et &#x000e9;cologiques de la sant&#x000e9; sont des notions centrales de la sant&#x000e9; publique depuis pr&#x000e8;s d&#x02019;un demi-si&#x000e8;cle (WHO, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1986</xref>; CSDH, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>). Pourtant, la double exclusion que repr&#x000e9;sentent le silence sur la sant&#x000e9; publique pendant la CdP-26 et l&#x02019;absence de mesures ax&#x000e9;es sur l&#x02019;&#x000e9;cologie dans la riposte &#x000e0; la COVID-19 (Hancock et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>) d&#x000e9;ment un tel h&#x000e9;ritage. C&#x02019;est le signe d&#x02019;un foss&#x000e9; entre la formation et la pratique, cr&#x000e9;&#x000e9; par la pression de produire des dipl&#x000f4;m&#x000e9;s pr&#x000ea;ts pour le march&#x000e9; du travail, qui limite la tendance (chez les &#x000e9;tudiant&#x000b7;es comme chez les enseignant&#x000b7;es) &#x000e0; aller plus loin en mati&#x000e8;re d&#x02019;&#x000e9;conomie politique, d&#x02019;&#x000e9;cologie politique, de d&#x000e9;croissance, de modes de savoir autochtones, de th&#x000e9;orie &#x000e9;conomique du &#x000ab; doughnut &#x000bb; (Raworth, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2017</xref>), d&#x02019;&#x000e9;thique f&#x000e9;ministe des soins, d&#x02019;adaptation profonde, de transitions durables ou de pic p&#x000e9;trolier. &#x000c0; vrai dire, m&#x000ea;me si nous observons que ces sujets int&#x000e9;ressent de plus en plus d&#x02019;&#x000e9;tudiant&#x000b7;es de nos programmes, la plupart des emplois en sant&#x000e9; publique touchent rarement &#x000e0; ces domaines d&#x02019;action. Comme l&#x02019;ont fait remarquer Hancock and McLaren (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2021</xref>), la sant&#x000e9; publique fait encore &#x000ab; le jeu des critiques qui ont toujours voulu la r&#x000e9;duire &#x000e0; une focalisation biom&#x000e9;dicale sur les maladies transmissibles et qui souhaitent que nous "restions dans notre voie" au lieu de parler des injustices &#x000e9;conomiques et sociales ou des limites &#x000e9;cologiques &#x000bb; (p. 794).</p><p id="Par21">En conclusion, notre incapacit&#x000e9; permanente d&#x02019;harmoniser nos principes, nos all&#x000e9;geances et nos pr&#x000e9;paratifs avec les crises &#x000e9;cologiques existentielles qui nous attendent nous m&#x000e8;nera, &#x000e0; terme, &#x000e0; une nouvelle diminution de notre pertinence bien au-del&#x000e0; de la CdP-26. Le renoncement &#x000e0; notre engagement envers la justice sociale et &#x000e9;cologique alimente la tendance pernicieuse, chez les personnes du public, dans la classe politique et m&#x000ea;me chez beaucoup de membres de nos communaut&#x000e9;s de la sant&#x000e9; publique, de confondre la sant&#x000e9; et les soins de sant&#x000e9; et de ne pas faire le lien entre la sant&#x000e9;, ses contextes plus larges et ses d&#x000e9;terminants (The Lancet, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2019</xref>; McLaren &#x00026; Hennessy, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2020</xref>). Nous appelons avec insistance &#x000e0; un d&#x000e9;bat plus large, dans et avec nos communaut&#x000e9;s, sur &#x000ab; des mesures de sant&#x000e9; publique ax&#x000e9;es sur l&#x02019;&#x000e9;quit&#x000e9; et la d&#x000e9;colonisation pour pr&#x000e9;venir et att&#x000e9;nuer les impacts climatiques et autres impacts &#x000e9;cologiques, et pour nous en remettre, d&#x02019;une mani&#x000e8;re qui favorise la sant&#x000e9; et la durabilit&#x000e9;, de l&#x02019;&#x000e9;chelon local &#x000e0; l&#x02019;&#x000e9;chelle plan&#x000e9;taire &#x000bb; (Canadian Journal of Public Health, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">n.d.</xref>).</p><p id="Par22">Jeff Masuda, R&#x000e9;dacteur scientifique adjoint, RCSP; School of Public Health and Social Policy, University of VictoriaLindsay McLaren, R&#x000e9;dactrice scientifique adjointe, RCSP; Department of Community Health Sciences, University of Calgary; Canadian Centre for Policy AlternativesBlake Poland, R&#x000e9;dacteur associ&#x000e9;, RCSP; Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References/R&#x000e9;f&#x000e9;rences</title><ref id="CR1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Canadian Journal of Public Health (n.d.). Call for papers related to public health, climate change, and ecological futures (open-ended). https://www.springer.com/journal/41997/updates/18965522</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Canadian Public Health Association. (2015). <italic>Global change and public health: Addressing the ecological determinants of health.</italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cpha.ca/sites/default/files/assets/policy/edh-discussion_e.pdf">https://www.cpha.ca/sites/default/files/assets/policy/edh-discussion_e.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carroll, W. K. (Ed.). (2021). <italic>Regime of obstruction: How corporate power blocks energy democracy</italic>. Athabasca University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castleden</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Darrach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The public health emergency of climate change: How/are Canadian post-secondary public health sciences programs responding?</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>111</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17269/s41997-020-00386-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32761542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Younos</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change impacts and adaptations on health of internally displaced people (IDP): An exploratory study on coastal areas of Bangladesh</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e05018</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33024856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Commission on Social Determinants of Health [CSDH] (2008). <italic>Closing the gap in a generation: Health equity through action on the social determinants of health. Final report of the Commission on Social Determinants of Health.</italic> World Health Organization. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-IER-CSDH-08.1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hancock, T., Kershaw, P., McLaren, L., MacDonald, J., Turner, S., &#x00026; Jackson, S. F. (2020). There is much more to public health than COVID-19. <italic>Healthydebate Opinions</italic>. https://healthydebate.ca/opinions/more-to-public-health-than-covid</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Putting the horse back in front of the cart: A critical reflection on the CIHR-IPPH dialogue on the future of Canada&#x02019;s public health systems</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>112</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>796</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17269/s41997-021-00548-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34642855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Lancet (2019). Health and climate change: Making the link matter [editorial]. <italic>Lancet, 394</italic>(10211), 1780. 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)32756-4</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohtadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Seager</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushnir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change in the Fertile Crescent and implications of the recent Syrian drought</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3241</fpage><lpage>3246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1421533112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25733898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leal Filho</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Matandirotya</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;tz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brearley</surname><given-names>FQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baidoo</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbih</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of climate change to African indigenous communities and examples of adaptation responses</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-26540-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33397941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee, E. Y., &#x00026; Masuda, J. (2021). The &#x02018;freedom&#x02019; to pollute? An ecological analysis of neoliberal capitalist ideology, climate culpability, lifestyle factors, and population health risk in 124 countries. <italic>Canadian Journal of Public Health, 112</italic>(5), 877&#x02013;887.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lewis, D., Williams, L., &#x00026; Jones, R. (2020). A radical revision of the public health response to environmental crisis in a warming world: Contributions of Indigenous knowledges and Indigenous feminist perspectives. <italic>Canadian Journal of Public Health, 111</italic>(6), 897&#x02013;900.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mass&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moloughney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New era for schools and programs of public health in Canada</article-title><source>Public Health Rev</source><year>2011</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03391633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McLaren, L., &#x00026; Hennessy, T. (2020). A broader vision of public health. <italic>The Monitor</italic>, <italic>27</italic>(5), 16&#x02013;21<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.policyalternatives.ca/publications/monitor/broader-vision-public-health">https://www.policyalternatives.ca/publications/monitor/broader-vision-public-health</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mottley, M. (2021). WLS - Opening ceremony, remarks by Mia Amor Mottley, Prime Minister of Barbados, November 1. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/resource/BARBADOS_cop26cmp16cma3_HLS_EN.pdf">https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/resource/BARBADOS_cop26cmp16cma3_HLS_EN.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Poland, B., Parkes, M. W., Hancock, T., McKibbon, G., &#x00026; Chircop, A. (2020). A changing role for public health in the Anthropocene: The contribution of scenario thinking for reimagining the future. In K. Zywert &#x00026; S. Quilley (Eds.), <italic>Health in the Anthropocene: Living well on a finite planet</italic> (pp. 172&#x02013;190). University of Toronto Press. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://utorontopress.com/ca/health-in-the-anthropocene-2">https://utorontopress.com/ca/health-in-the-anthropocene-2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Poland, B., &#x00026; Ziolo, M. (2021). Environment and COVID-19: Unpacking the links. In G. J. Andrews, V. A. Crooks, J. R. Pearce, &#x00026; J. P. Messina (Eds.), <italic>COVID-19 and similar futures: Pandemic geographies</italic> (pp. 213&#x02013;223). Springer. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.springer.com/gp/book/9783030701789">https://www.springer.com/gp/book/9783030701789</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Raworth, K. (2017). <italic>Doughnut economics: Seven ways to think like a 21st-century economist</italic>. Vermont: Chelsea Green Publishing.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. (2021). <italic>The health argument for climate action: COP26 special report on climate change and health</italic>. Geneva: World Health Organization.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. (1986). <italic>The Ottawa Charter for Health Promotion, 1986</italic>. World Health Organization.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The socioeconomic and environmental drivers of the COVID-19 pandemic: A review</article-title><source>Ambio</source><year>2021</year><volume>50</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13280-020-01497-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33507498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yassi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is public health training in Canada meeting current needs? Defrosting the paradigm freeze to respond to the post-truth era</article-title><source>Crit Public Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09581596.2017.1384796</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>