<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par4">Going further, we must also acknowledge how issues of power and privilege are heightened to new levels of severity as the COVID-19 pandemic deepens the gap of food access and availability injustice. How to address the current moment and future crises through an intersectional justice and human rights lens is what requires our immediate attention. A pandemic-informed report published by the International Panel of Experts (IPES) on Sustainable Food Systems in April 2020 is a stark reminder that the time for serious discussions and honest assessments of what is and is not working in the food system is long overdue. Yet a year after the outbreak took hold, concerns about the food supply chain continue to make headlines pointing out the many vulnerabilities in the system. Large economies of scale and vertically integrated production systems are still too rigid to nimbly move, leaving many farmers with hardships and difficult decisions for their farms and communities. At the same time, the emergency food system in the U.S. continues to be strained in demanding ways as individuals and families struggle with limited incomes, affordable housing, healthcare costs, and caregiving responsibilities, disproportionally impacting women and communities of color. We also see increasing concerns for the health and safety of frontline food and farm workers as they seek to make a livelihood in kitchens, meat processing plants, and crop fields with few safeguards or fair wages for their &#8220;essential&#8221; labor. Taken further, these concerns for protecting the most vulnerable during the pandemic remain largely unheard by those in positions of power on the national and global front despite grassroot mobilization. As people have pointed out for decades, our domestic and global food economy was established on the labor of enslaved people and the foundation of stolen Indigenous land. The current moment reveals how these legacies of oppression linger as the systematic exploitation of Brown and Black bodies continues in order to reach the goals of productivity and efficiency through domestic and transnational capital markets.</p>