<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par5">This unfathomable health event has indeed exposed weaknesses, challenges, disparities, and underlying inequities in the U.S. and global food system with little to no accounting for environmental justice, health equity, and human rights. As an academic with teaching, research, and extension responsibilities in a U.S land-grant university, I feel these and other points of vulnerability and crisis are not nearly stressed enough in our teaching, research, and outreach efforts. The opportunity to better understand and address the food system as a dynamic system that takes on a number of issues, politics, and priorities has never been more significant. Of importance, this opportunity requires us to embrace Anderson&#8217;s claim of reexamining and resisting the current emphasis on measures of efficiency and productivity. It also means illustrating and dismantling how these discourses and practices intersect with neoliberalism, settler colonialism, white supremacy, and patriarchal frames and actions. For example, the privileging of neoliberal discourse with technocratic and productivist measures in the food system is far from new. A focus on efficiency alone reifies a strong tendency to reduce, flatten, and distill the complexities of our food system from soil to plate down to a specific suite of linear and technocratic solutions and practices (Pimbert 2018; Alkon and Guthman). Going further, the reification of neoliberal efficiency and technocratic problem solving in agriculture fails to bring to light the interdependence and depth of our socio-eco relations or the larger political ecology of food and agriculture (Galt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2016</xref>). Mary Hendrickson, Philip Howard, Emily Miller, and Doug Constance take this point further in their November 2020 report to the Family Farm Action Alliance titled, &#8220;The Food System: Concentration and its Impacts.&#8221; They caution that the current agricultural trajectory, with its overemphasis on measures of efficiency and productivity, callously operates to concreate power in the hands of a few, further obfuscating the material and discursive possibilities to re-imagine our global food system as one where all may benefit and thrive:<disp-quote><p id="Par6">&#8220;The distribution of power in the food system, embodied in the power to make decisions about what food is produced, how, where and by whom, as well as who gets to eat&#8212;and what they get to eat, is our major focus of concern because of the negative impacts of those decisions to farmers, workers, communities and our ecology. Without a rebalancing of economic and political power within the global food system, humanity confronts a crisis over our very sustenance (p 2).</p></disp-quote></p>