<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par7">Food scholars and activists continue to grapple with these these and other social change critiques and possibilities. Reflecting on the current moment allows us to reengage with such critical questions that have been asked many times before: What does a humane, resilient, and fair system actually look like? How do we build equity in the fabric of our food system today and for future generations? How do we move toward a restorative food future? What strategies of resistance, disruption, prevention, and repair make sense? For Anderson, the answers to some of these questions lie in places that are beyond our mainstream ways of knowing and acting. We need to explore more deeply, widely, and compassionately to learn how people near and far are meeting their food system challenges. In this spirit, she recommends three strategies to push the boundaries &#8220;that are holding back progress&#8221; on addressing some our greatest food system issues. These approaches include: 1) engaging more intentionally with international opportunities and colleagues from governmental to civil society organizations to refine our critiques of the globalized food system, 2) interacting and organizing with global social movements to build new alternatives, and 3) committing to anti-racist work to seek a deeper understanding of the way structural and institutional racism in our food system operates while also developing a pathway to action to help dismantle the attitudes, practices, and structures that hold racism in place. While each of these opportunities may look a little different from each other, they equally demand we engage with an astute critique of the current conditions to better problem solve. They also require an examination of our professional motivations and trajectories so that &#8220;boundary work&#8221; is more possible. Anderson also recommends we take the meaning of solidarity seriously by illustrating greater commitments to social movement actors and communities who first-hand experience systems of oppression and violence.</p>