<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par46">Quantitative and qualitative results suggest that CCA is impacting emerging adults broadly. While experiencing CCA in of itself does not constitute a clinical disorder, the experience of CCA may contribute to clinical disorders and, simply given the prevalence of both CCA and mental health disorders among emerging adults, they are likely to co-occur. In such cases, clinical intervention may be merited, and it is important for mental health professionals to have sufficient climate literacy to be able to effectively address CCA in therapeutic settings (Clayton et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2021</xref>). For example, it is important that therapists acknowledge that even severe worries about climate change are legitimate and normative among emerging adults, rather than viewing them solely as a symptom of a disorder. Existential therapies and third-wave cognitive-behavioral approaches focusing on meaning, values, and acceptance may be an especially good fit for emerging adults experiencing CCA and&#160;seeking treatment. Additionally, proponents of ecotherapy have suggested that developing an environmental identity and engaging in environmental conservation may be an effective approach to treating climate anxiety (Doherty, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2016</xref>; Palinkas et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2020</xref>). More broadly, whether in the context of formal treatment or community, work, and educational contexts, creating opportunities to engage in collective action and, by doing so, build agency and connection, may be particularly beneficial for addressing emerging adults&#8217; CCA. In fact, since the majority of our sample reported significant worries in their open-ended responses but scored low on the measure of CCA, community-based approaches focusing on building agency may be most appropriate, with avenues to connect those with greater mental health needs to clinical services as needed.</p>