<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par11">Recent writing on climate justice has emphasised the need to address inter-country, intra-country and intergenerational levels simultaneously. Such an approach is deemed necessary given the sometimes competing claims of different levels of climate justice (von Lucke <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2019</xref>: 4). The European Economic and Social Committee&#8217;s (EESC) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2017</xref> Opinion on Climate Justice highlighted the &#8216;need to consider the fairness of the often disproportionate impact of climate change on citizens and communities in both developing and developed economies&#8217; (European Economic and Social Committee <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2017</xref>, 3.2). A Liberal International declaration issued in the context of the 2019 New York climate summit, the &#8216;Citizens Pact to Fight Climate Injustice&#8217;, reiterated these themes and added the need to &#8216;ensure that young people are integrated and represented across all aspects of decision-making&#8217;. Also at the New York summit, the Foundation for European Progressive Studies (FEPS) issued a declaration on the theme of &#8216;United for Climate Justice&#8217;. The FEPS document acknowledged that climate change is a &#8216;triple injustice&#8217; between countries, within countries and across generations (Billingham <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2019</xref>, 10). It defined climate justice as &#8216;any social justice issue associated with either the impacts of climate change [or] the preventive measures to address the consequences&#8217; (Ibid). The FEPS project also explicitly linked climate justice with the financial aspect, with a call to &#8216;[c]limate-proof global investment, finance and trade&#8217;, in order to &#8216;channel finance to activities which support climate mitigation and adaptation, while denying funds to activities which further harm the climate&#8217;. These outputs of political parties and party-aligned foundations arguably inform policy-making, as in the context of the informal, three-way coalition of Conservatives, Social Democrats and Liberals in the European Commission and Parliament.</p>