<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Heavy rainfall was measured using the Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI) for each calendar year in each survey enumeration area. The SPI is a widely used tool for detecting and characterizing heavy rainfall anomalies and SPI data were accessed from the Columbia Climate School International Research Institute Climate Data Library.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220857r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220857r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The SPI is the number of SDs that observed cumulative precipitation deviates from the climatologic average. The index is computed by fitting long-term raw precipitation time series data (since 1979) of 1 frequency distribution (eg, &#947;) to another probability distribution (eg, normal or gaussian), then calculating the number of SDs by which short-term precipitation data (past year) deviates from the long-term mean in a given area.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220857r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220857r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Additional details about the SPI models and methods are described elsewhere.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220857r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220857r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> We generated a binary categorization of heavy rain, defined as an annual SPI greater than or equal to 1.5. Standardized Precipitation Index values above 1.5 correspond to moderately wet or extremely wet on the European Drought Observatory classification scheme.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220857r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> We estimated the count of years that each survey respondent was exposed to heavy rainfall in the 10 years before the survey date when the outcomes were measured. Heavy rainfall was estimated at the enumeration-area level. This process is similar to a study examining rainfall exposures and HIV outcomes,<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> to maximize the chance that the exposure preceded the outcome.</p>