<p>Critical thinking and practice skills can be translated into the university setting and
foreground the theme of connectedness. For example, we use The Spiral Model of Community
Education (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Bell, Gaventa and Peters, 1990</xref>) as a
pedagogical tool to enhance small group work as a community of learners and to support
students&#8217; critical thinking skills. This model is used with social work students at the
University of the Sunshine Coast to explore contemporary or emerging social issues or trends
such as &#8216;Working for Climate Justice&#8217;; &#8216;Working for First Nations
Justice&#8217;; and &#8216;Working for Justice in Welfare and Bureaucratic Contexts&#8217;.
Contemporary documentaries or fictional movies are used as a &#8216;code&#8217; to stimulate
dialogue. <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Freirean &#8216;codes&#8217;, or what Paulo
Freire called &#8216;codification&#8217; (1974/2005)</xref> are a way to trigger dialogue,
supporting emancipatory knowledge development. Any stimulus can be a code&#8212;a movie, a
poem, a reading, a song, a painting or drawing. An example for the theme of &#8216;Working for
First Nations Justice&#8217; is the 2019 documentary <italic toggle="yes">In My Blood Runs It
Runs</italic>, directed by Maya Newell. It tells the story of an Arrernte/Garrawa boy, Dujun
and his family and reveals the challenges Dujun faces both in his school and on the streets of
Alice Springs. For the theme of &#8216;Working for Justice in Welfare and Bureaucratic
Contexts&#8217;, the 2016 feature length movie, <italic toggle="yes">I, Daniel Blake</italic>, directed by
Ken Loach tells the story of a 59-year-old carpenter who must fight the bureaucracy of the
system in order to receive Employment and Support Allowance. Students learn to use The Spiral
Model process to develop their own structural analyses about the issues dramatized or presented
through the codes, and the deep engagement with the process aims to empower them to use this
model with community members in their future work.</p>