<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par01">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>A.</label><p id="Par02">Stage 1. Student Involvement (Role of Grassroots)</p><p id="Par52">The ultimate goal of the course is to produce graduates from schools of education worldwide who can serve as leaders in the twenty-first century global movement on the pressing issue of climate change mitigation, adaptation, impact reduction and early warning.</p><p id="Par53">The theory of action on which this proposal is based is:</p><p id="Par54"><bold>If</bold> a curriculum on climate change is implemented and offered for a minimum of 3&#160;years at HGSE <bold>and</bold> a substantial number of students show interest in enrolling, <bold>then</bold> the course will produce numerous graduates active in various education sectors that have the knowledge, skills, and attitude to help mitigate climate change.</p><p id="Par55"><bold>If</bold> some HGSE graduates become transformative leaders in education <bold>and</bold> the innovative teaching solutions can be widely replicated (Harvard Office for Sustainability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2016</xref>), <bold>then</bold> the course can impart knowledge, skills, and values to the broader community and serve as the blueprint for other education schools.</p><p id="Par56">More specifically, our curriculum set out to attempt the following objectives:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><label/><p id="Par57">First, to help students develop knowledge on climate change and the role of different education sectors and educators in overcoming the issue.</p></list-item><list-item><label/><p id="Par58">Second, to ingrain the value of being active agents of change, planning and acting to mitigate climate change.</p></list-item><list-item><label/><p id="Par59">Third, to build skills and competencies in collaboratively solving problems related to climate change through education.</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list>
</p>