<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par05">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>B.</label><p id="Par04">Stage 2. Faculty-Student Exchange (Interaction Zone)</p><p id="Par60">Previous efforts to reorient teacher education to address sustainability and innovations related to ESD were carried out on a personal scale and were short-lived, unable to last beyond personnel and changes in innovation (Hopkins and McKeown <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2014</xref>). It became evident that our curriculum would also need sustainable support from the institution.</p><p id="Par61">We approached a professor at HGSE, a cognitive scientist whose work centers around ecology, climate change, and the use of virtual and augmented reality in the classroom. In particular, her research identifies ways in which understandings about the nature of causality impact our ability to deal with complexity in our world. Her extensive expertise and experience on the topic made her our top candidate as we approached her with the idea of implementing a climate change curriculum at HGSE.</p><p id="Par62">This exchange indicated that for a curriculum to be introduced at HGSE, we would have to identify and demonstrate the need for a course on climate change. If and only then, faculty could move forward with the motion, and the course would be examined for approval. To aid that process, we administered a needs assessment to demonstrate the existing gaps between current course offerings and student demand for the intended curriculum. Data we collected could paint a better picture of the status quo.</p><p id="Par07">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>i.</label><p id="Par06">Survey Administration and Interpretation</p><p id="Par63">In order to assess preliminary needs and interest in a climate change curriculum for the twenty-first century at HGSE, we administered a Knowledge, Attitude, and Practice (KAP) survey to 66 respondents comprised mostly of HGSE students. A randomized sample was collected through an online survey soliciting students within HGSE and the greater Harvard community. Limitations of the survey include probable bias towards climate activism due to its opt-in design, as well as its small sample size, representing less than 10% of the overall HGSE student population. The 66 participants were affiliated with various programs at HGSE and planned to go into different sectors in education, reflecting the diverse student composition in education sectors that our curriculum targets. Each question was designed specifically to correspond with a Knowledge, Attitude, or Practice (KAP) assessment of student&#8217;s understanding and interest of climate change. (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">6.1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 6.1</label><caption><p>KAP survey to understand HGSE student&#8217;s interests of climate change</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Question</th><th>Respondents</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Affiliation</td><td>State your school affiliation</td><td>Among 66 graduate students within the wider Harvard network, 94% of the sample (62)&#160;were comprised of students at the Harvard Graduate School of Education</td></tr><tr><td>Which education sector do you plan on going into after graduation?</td><td><p>(33.3%) Non Profit Organization</p><p>(17.5%) K-12 School System</p><p>(12.7%) Media/Technology</p><p>(12.7%) Consulting</p><p>(7.9%) Government</p><p>(6%) Higher Education</p><p>(9.9%) Other</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Knowledge</td><td><p>How would you rate your knowledge about climate change?</p><p>Self-assessed knowledge on ESD</p></td><td><p>(66.2%) I have gathered some information about the subject.</p><p>(16.9%) I have been studying the effects of climate change</p><p>(15.4%) Very limited; I have heard about it, but I am not aware of the fact</p><p>(1.5%) I am an expert on climate change</p></td></tr><tr><td>What do you think is the cause of climate change?</td><td>22 out of 66 respondents (33.3%) replied correctly</td></tr><tr><td>What are some of the direct effects of global warming?</td><td><p>29 out of 66 respondents (43.9%) answered correctly</p><p>*13 respondents (19.7%) answered correct for both questions assessing current knowledge of climate change</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Attitude</td><td>Do you think climate change is happening?</td><td><p>(90.5%) Very certain</p><p>(7.9%) Somewhat certain</p><p>(1.6%) Not very certain</p></td></tr><tr><td>How concerned are you about climate change?</td><td><p>(64.6%) Very concerned</p><p>(30.8%) Somewhat concerned</p></td></tr><tr><td>How big of a role do you think <italic>education</italic> plays in mitigating climate change?</td><td><p>(64.6%) Very big</p><p>(30.8%) Somewhat big</p><p>(3.1%) Not very big</p><p>(1.5%) Not at all big</p></td></tr><tr><td>How big of a role do you think <italic>educators</italic> plays in mitigating climate change?</td><td><p>(49.2%) Very big</p><p>(35.4%) Somewhat big</p><p>(13.8%) Not very big</p><p>(1.5%) Not at all big</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Practice</td><td>What are some efforts you&#8217;ve undertaken to mitigate climate change?</td><td><p>(80.7%) Reducing one&#8217;s own carbon footprint (including&#160;taking public transportation, recycling, reducing plastic use, buying sustainable products, limiting the consumption of meat, etc.)</p><p>(11.5%) Raising awareness (sharing information with families and talking to coworkers regarding the issue etc.)</p><p>(7.7%) Engaging in political action (voting for leaders who demonstrate&#160;concern for climate change, putting pressure on leadership to encourage compost, and joining climate strikes)</p><p>(5.8%) No effort</p><p>(3.8%) Skepticism of individual efforts in mitigating climate change</p></td></tr><tr><td>What are some efforts you&#8217;ve undertaken to mitigate climate change <italic>through education</italic>?</td><td><p>(25.5%) Informal conversations</p><p>(23.4%) Teaching students</p><p>(6.4%) Using social media</p><p>(6.4%) Organizing events</p><p>(6.4%) Advocacy</p><p>(6.4%) No attempts</p></td></tr><tr><td>Interest</td><td>Would you be interested in taking a course at HGSE on climate change and education?</td><td><p>(52.3%) Yes</p><p>(47.7%) No</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par09">
<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p id="Par08">Knowledge</p><p id="Par64">A survey of the participants&#8217; self-assessed knowledge on climate change revealed 66.2% of the respondents reporting they had gathered some information about the subject, and 15.4% claiming to have very limited knowledge on climate change. To test the actual knowledge of climate change, two multiple-choice questions were administered, questioning the causes and effects of climate change. Only 13 respondents, comprising 19.7% of the total sample answered correctly on both questions, demonstrating a significant gap in students&#8217; <italic>actual</italic> knowledge of climate change.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par011">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>b.</label><p id="Par012">Attitudes</p><p id="Par65">90.5% of the respondents were very certain that climate change was happening, showing a strong consensus on the existence of the phenomenon. 95.4% of respondents expressed concerns regarding climate change, with 64.6% of the respondents responding that they were very concerned about climate change. There was a general consensus with regards to whether <italic>education</italic> had a significant role in mitigating climate change, with 95.4% of respondents selecting 4 or 5 on a scale of 5, with higher numbers indicating greater significance.&#160;Strong agreement (84.6% of respondents who answered a 4 or 5 on a scale of 5)&#160;was also observed in responses to the question of whether <italic>educators</italic> were significant in mitigating climate change.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par014">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>c.</label><p id="Par013">Practice</p><p id="Par66">By analyzing qualitative responses to questions asking one&#8217;s efforts taken to mitigate climate change, we could extract five general themes that represented the responses: reducing one&#8217;s own carbon footprint, raising awareness, engaging in political action, no effort, and skepticism of individual effort in mitigating climate change. The majority of the respondents (90.4%) have made efforts in mitigating climate change, with the most common responses related to reducing their own carbon footprint (80.7%).</p><p id="Par67">Next, an analysis of one&#8217;s attempt to mitigate climate change through education yielded six different themes: informal conversations, teaching students, using social media, organizing events, and advocacy. The most common attempts were engaging in informal conversations (25.5%) and teaching students on the topic of climate change (23.4%).</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par018">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>d.</label><p id="Par017">Interest</p><p id="Par68">Thirty-four students, or 52.3% of the total number of respondents, showed an interest in taking a course on climate change and education.</p><p id="Par69">Whereas needs assessments like the one we conducted are not meant to be generalizable nor predictive of actual behavior, this figure provides some indication that there is considerable interest in CCE among students at the Harvard Graduate School of Education. We shared the results of the survey with the academic leadership of the school, and the feedback was immediately positive. The urgency of the situation and the demand from the student population clearly demonstrated the need for this class.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list>
</p>