<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par022">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>D.</label><p id="Par021">Stage 4. Faculty Planning (Role of Institution)</p><p id="Par72">Each institution charts out a curriculum implementation process, systematically organizing what will be taught, who will be taught, and how it will be taught. At HGSE, there is a three-step process that aids faculty in planning a course curriculum.<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><label/><p id="Par73">Phase 1: One on One Conversation</p></list-item><list-item><label/><p id="Par74">Phase 2: Course Preparation</p></list-item><list-item><label/><p id="Par75">Phase 3: Teaching Team Meeting.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par027">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>i.</label><p id="Par026">Phase 1: One on One Conversation</p><p id="Par76">In this phase, faculty review<strike>s</strike> the course planning guide and forms a teaching team. Together, they discuss and agree on due dates.</p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>ii.</label><p id="Par028">Phase 2: Course Preparation</p><p id="Par77">In the course preparation phase, design elements of the course are carefully considered. The scope (breadth of knowledge, skills, attitudes, and behaviors) and the sequence (order) of the course would be discussed. Appropriate materials, pedagogy, and effective class activities are chosen within the design of the curriculum (Brundiers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2014</xref>). Formative and summative evaluation methods are examined which will measure the effectiveness of the curriculum.</p><p id="Par78">Faculty members are supported by the Harvard Graduate School Course Planning Team. The Teaching and Learning Lab provides faculty support through individual consultations and group professional opportunities to craft intelligent and thoughtful course designs as well as producing instructional resources (HGSE Teaching and Learning Lab <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>).</p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>iii.</label><p id="Par063">Phase 3: Tea+ching Team Meeting</p><p id="Par79">Faculty assistants, faculty, and teaching fellows are determined and meet to discuss the facilitation of the class.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list>
</p>