<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par0285">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>E.</label><p id="Par029">Stage 5. Implementation (Interaction Zone)</p><p id="Par80">The authors participated in the faculty driven process of the implementation by offering assistance and support in the ideation and design of an ESD curriculum aimed at the school of education. Two prototype lessons of the curriculum can be accessed in the <xref rid="Sec13" ref-type="sec">Appendix B</xref>.</p><p id="Par030">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>i.</label><p id="Par031">Standards</p><p id="Par81">Our curriculum seeks to meet standards provided by the 2030 Sustainable Development Goal, target 13 Climate Action. In particular, goal 13.3 focuses on improving education, awareness-raising, and building institutional capacity related to climate change mitigation, adaptation, impact reduction and early warning. Furthermore, we have aligned our curriculum to accommodate the four pillars of HGSE foundational elements of Learning, Development, and Teaching; Evidence; Equity and Opportunity; Organizations and Systems (Harvard Graduate School of Education <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">b</xref>). In order to emphasize the importance of making knowledgeable behavioral decisions, we included the five basic competencies as defined by Wiek et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2011</xref>): Systems thinking competency, Anticipatory competency, Normative competency, Strategic competency, and Interpersonal competency.</p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>ii.</label><p id="Par032">Format</p><p id="Par82"><italic>Climate Change for Educators</italic> will be a 12-week semester long course, comprised of two 90-min classes focusing on a weekly theme. We based the overarching framework of the curriculum design using the UN SDG aligned curriculum <italic>Empowering Students to Improve the World in Sixty Lessons</italic> (Reimers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2017</xref>) in addition to <italic>Becoming Global Thinkers: Thinking about Distant Causes and Effects, Causal Learning in the Classroom (CLIC)</italic> (Grotzer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2015</xref>).</p><p id="Par83">Furthermore, our lesson plan prototype has been designed so that each of the weekly topics and units can function independently of one another. Thus, they can be separated and blended into existing structures of curricula units to impart knowledge, skills, and values that teach educators about the critical issue of climate change.</p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>iii.</label><p id="Par034">Pedagogical Design<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p id="Par84">Knowledge Transfer</p><p id="Par86">In 1956, Bloom categorized cognitive learning objectives in a progressive hierarchy from least to most complex levels which include: knowledge, comprehension, application, analysis, synthesis, and evaluation. Based on his taxonomy, this curriculum devotes the first class of each week building upon basic, fundamental skills such as &#8216;knowledge,&#8217; and &#8216;comprehension&#8217; via lectures and engaging discussions. A knowledge-based start will help to foster an atmosphere of intellectual discourse in the classroom (Fook <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2012</xref>), and specifically of accumulating, deepening, and transferring knowledge of the environment to a large mass of educators (Radakovi&#263; et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2017</xref>).</p><p id="Par87">After a short lecture, faculty will engage students in a lively discussion, which will foster student engagement.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>b.</label><p id="Par040">Engagement</p><p id="Par88">Lectures are followed by an invigorating student led discussion, for students to &#8216;synthesize&#8217; (Bloom <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">1956</xref>) what they have learned. Discussions help bring out the importance of engagement and fostering a culture of student-centered learning (Anderson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2012</xref>). Discussion prompts will center around the essential questions posed by faculty, and this active facilitation is enhanced as faculty demonstrate the changing role of a teacher; from &#8220;content expert&#8221; to &#8220;curriculum facilitator,&#8221; in this new era of learning (Godsey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2015</xref>). Active listening is encouraged, and main points are organized on a board framing the argument and building insights.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>c.</label><p id="Par041">Cross-Disciplinary</p><p id="Par89">Climate change education inevitably requires having to incorporate a blend of multi-disciplinary academic subjects (Lindblom-Yl&#228;nne et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2006</xref>; Lueddeke <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2003</xref>; Nevgi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2004</xref>; Singer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">1996</xref>). Topics within the scope of this curriculum include socio-political issues surrounding the scientific facts of climate change, innovative technology serving as possible solutions, as well as the role of education in mitigating climate change. Week 3 will touch upon the cognitive function of how people learn, with regards to understanding that climate change requires an &#8216;action-at-a-distance&#8217; approach. Weeks 4&#8211;11 will cover a myriad of ways in which education can help mitigate the impact of climate change. Some topics include curriculum design, professional development of teachers, school operations, informal education, measurements, education policy, and climate justice. In the final week of class, students will give their presentations and share the takeaways from the course.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>d.</label><p id="Par042">Project Based</p><p id="Par90">The second class each week will consist of &#8216;applying,&#8217; &#8216;synthesizing,&#8217; and &#8216;evaluating&#8217; (Bloom <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">1956</xref>) what they know via engaging projects. Numerous studies have highlighted the benefits of active, project-based learning (Leigh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2009</xref>). The semester-long project involves a group of 3&#8211;5 students (Henke <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1985</xref>) with varying levels of experience in multiple education sectors, collaborating to craft a holistic educational strategy to mitigate climate change. Students are asked to formulate project groups around a jurisdiction with meaningful personal ties, helping to contextualize learning as local, tangible, and personally relevant (Cone et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2012</xref>; Anderson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2012</xref>). Each jurisdiction will highlight the different agenda and perspectives present today in the twenty-first century global climate change movement. Students will give presentations in the final week and submit a 20-page-paper as a final project. Throughout the project, students are active participants in their own learning which will include the design of their experiences and the realization of their learning outcomes. Ultimately, students can take full ownership of their own learning. This class will involve weekly group assignments (Monroe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2017</xref>) that students will start in the class but finish as collaborative homework.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>e.</label><p id="Par043">Situated</p><p id="Par91">The second half of the week additionally focuses on student-centered activities, guest lecturers, simulations, and excursions to provide a thought-provoking experience for students to experience real life perspectives in the topic of climate change. In week 7, students will take an excursion to a nearby environmental institution. With multiple studies revealing the importance of making the distant threat of climate change personally relevant and meaningful (Shome et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2009</xref>; Fook <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2012</xref>; Moser and Dilling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2007</xref>; Wibeck <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2014</xref>), excursions can help make the threat of climate change real, tangible and immediate (Cone et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2012</xref>). We also bring in local guest speakers committed to the field to bring expert knowledge into the classroom (Leigh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2009</xref>; Theobald et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2015</xref>) serving as a relevant local source of inspiration to the students all the while minimizing carbon footprint expenditure.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>f.</label><p id="Par044">Real World Situations</p><p id="Par92">Our audience are adult learners, who see themselves as capable of self-direction and incentivized by tasks that will prepare for social and occupational role competency (El Sawi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1996</xref>). Each week, we provide assignments that carry out practical exercises that encourage learners to put into practice the theories they learned. Our adult learners have the autonomy to carry out their given task, on very practical elements that can be utilized in the workforce.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>g.</label><p id="Par045">Faculty Involvement</p><p id="Par93">Students will be encouraged to meet with instructors at least once every 3&#160;weeks so that expectations and standards from both sides of the teaching team and the students are well integrated, coherent, and harmonized. Intimate feedback from the teaching team enhances student learning, and the instructor takes away with a solid knowledge and understanding of student&#8217;s progress.</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>h.</label><p id="Par046">Accountability</p><p id="Par94">Students will be assessed on a weekly basis, with weekly projects consisting 60% of the total grade, and the semester long final projects being worth 40%. As students are working in groups, accountability measures such as self-assessments and peer-evaluation sheets will be collected by every member of the group. Student projects would be assessed via a rubric.</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list>
</p>