<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">First, HPSR is crucial to understanding the impact and implications of climate change. HPSR seeks to analyse how different actors interact in policy and implementation processes to improve health outcomes. It draws on a blend of public health, economics, sociology, anthropology, political science and epidemiology and can serve as a multidisciplinary bridge to these various fields. HPSR seeks to analyse how health systems respond and adapt to health policies, and how health policies can shape and be shaped by health systems and broader determinants of health like climate change (<xref rid="czaa165-B1" ref-type="bibr">AHPSR, 2007</xref>). The interdisciplinary nature of HPSR makes it well positioned to tackle the complexity of climate change and can improve the analysis of linkages between health and climate. Until now, the climate change and health literature have focused on infectious diseases (<xref rid="czaa165-B7" ref-type="bibr">Hosking and Campbell-Lendrum, 2012</xref>), along with deaths and injuries from extreme weather events, the adverse health effects of extreme heat (<xref rid="czaa165-B7" ref-type="bibr">Hosking and Campbell-Lendrum, 2012</xref>), and risks of under-nutrition due to declines in food yields (<xref rid="czaa165-B4" ref-type="bibr">Friel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="czaa165-B7" ref-type="bibr">Hosking and Campbell-Lendrum, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="czaa165-B27" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). These studies show how climate change affects health outcomes; HPSR could augment ongoing efforts and widen this understanding by applying a systems approach. There is an urgent need to take a broader health systems and health policies perspective; this is the role of the HPSR community. Researchers can help policymakers appreciate, anticipate and work to prevent the effects of climate change on human health and well-being. For example, most efforts to achieve primary health care (PHC) do not sufficiently consider the implications of the climate crisis (<xref rid="czaa165-B10" ref-type="bibr">Kadandale <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). There is a need to revise the discourse, policy and practice on efforts to achieve PHC, but also universal health coverage to include explicit consideration of climate change and its health effects.</p>