<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par43">In addition to the Government package, below are some additional actions needed:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par44">Food safety and nutrition: Government warehouses with 71 million tons of rice and wheat are overflowing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. For the avoidance of exclusion errors, it is better to offer universal distribution coverage in the next few months. Nutrition programs such as Integrated Child Development Services (ICDS), mid-day meals, and rural childcare centers (&#8220;Anganwadis&#8221;) should continue to function as essential services and provide recipients with rations and meals at home. To enhance nutrition for children and women, eggs can be added. Innovative programs have been started by several State Governments to assist informal workers and the poor. For example, at the doorsteps of households, the Kerala Government is providing meals with diversified diets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par45">Cash transfers: Unemployed informal workers need funding for cash income. Through the &#8220;Jan Dhan&#8221; financial inclusion program, the Government has provided INR 500 (USD 6.60) per month to the bank accounts of 200 million women, but this is also inadequate. For the next 3 months, we need to have a minimum of INR 3000 (USD 40) per month in cash transfers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par46">Migrant workers: There are some 40&#8211;50 million seasonal migrant workers in India. In recent days, global media have broadcast images of hundreds of thousands of migrant workers from several states traveling miles and miles on highways; some have traveled more than 1,000 km to return to their home villages. Both cash transfers and nutritious food should be provided [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p></list-item></list></p>