<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par82">As a global scientific consensus warns of potential catastrophic impacts from climate change, social researchers interested in identifying the potential roles for citizens, scientists, and the state in crafting policy decisions will have to grapple with the tensions between participatory democracy and technical expertise. Decisions made through social consensus may not be technically feasible or fast, and on the flip side, decisions made solely through appeals to &#8220;mechanical objectivity&#8221; and expert judgement may find no political legitimacy and produce strong resistance. In the New York case we can see the legitimizing effects of a participatory process coupled with <italic>influence</italic>, that is, the ability of participants to recognize their own input reflected in plans. Without it, the state can produce for itself a legitimacy crisis and social conflict that cannot be resolved with any amount of appeals to objectivity or rationality. Importantly, residents of the Lower East Side were not inherently anti-expert throughout the process, but rather mobilized in resistance of the project once they felt they had lost the thread of influence on the plans and that their expectations had been subverted. This paper ultimately argues that solutions to complex problems will require political legitimacy gained through a public that can recognize their own influence on plans, as well as the input of technical experts necessary to arrive at feasible solutions within the time-frame demanded by the fast-approaching problem of climate change. This article does not provide a roadmap to achieve such legitimacy. I follow Eyal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>) in arguing that &#8220;when it comes to public, political debate, the main contribution of [works of dry scholarship] cannot be to offer solutions, or to tell people what they ought to do.&#8221; Rather, such scholarship, Weber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">1946</xref>, quoted in Eyal, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>) argues in his &#8220;Science as a Vocation&#8221; lecture, should force the different sides to &#8220;recognize inconvenient facts &#8211; I mean facts that are inconvenient for their party opinions.&#8221;</p>