<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nlm2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Trop Med Hyg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Trop Med Hyg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">tropmed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0002-9637</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-1645</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9490666</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35895350</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd220189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.22-0189</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Why Climate Action Is Global Health Action</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene (ASTMH) Green Task Force Members</collab></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Address correspondence to Kate Whitfield. E-mail: <email>kate.whitfield@isglobal.org</email></corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Disclosure: This piece was developed by the ASTMH Green Task Force members and not by the ASTMH organization. All authors declare that they have no real or perceived conflicts of interest.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>107</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2022</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="ajtmh.22-0189.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT.</title><p>The impacts of climate change on global health and populations are far-reaching, yet they disproportionately affect vulnerable groups, thereby exacerbating disparities. As humanity reckons with the emergency of climate change, our global health community needs to contend with our own contributions to greenhouse gas emissions. We know that transformation is possible and that climate action is the antidote to the existential challenge. As a global health community, we have an immense opportunity, responsibility, and commitment to lead, support, inspire, and empower climate action, research, and innovation that align deeply with our mission and core values.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="4"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE</title><p>The average global surface temperature was 1.09&#x000b0;C higher (observed range: 0.95&#x02013;1.20) in 2011&#x02013;2020 than in preindustrial times.<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> This increase is causing extreme weather that threatens human life and human health.<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> The physical impacts of climate change, such as extreme heat events, worsen with increasing temperatures. At present, extreme heat events are occurring 4.8 times (range: 2.3&#x02013;6.4) more commonly than in preindustrial times.<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> It is predicted that, in the next 20 years, the average global surface temperature will reach or exceed 1.5&#x000b0;C of warming compared with preindustrial levels, and, of concern, the likelihood of extreme heat events, compared with preindustrial rates, is predicted to increase by 8.6 times (range: 4.3&#x02013;10.7 times) with an average temperature increase of 1.5&#x000b0;C and 13.9 times (range 6.9&#x02013;16.6 times), with an average temperature increase of 2&#x000b0;C.<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></p><p>Climate change impacts, such as extreme heat, contribute to myriad health problems including dehydration, pregnancy complications, infectious diseases, and cardiorespiratory morbidity and mortality.<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> The physical effects of climate change such as flooding, droughts, and fires threaten lives and communities directly and can also cause human conflicts over increased scarcity of resources and/or population displacement. Displaced populations are often at greater risk of poor health as well as poor access to health care services, creating humanitarian crises.<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Climate change&#x02013;related damage to ecosystems coupled with declining biodiversity have been linked to emerging infectious diseases.<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Changes in temperature, humidity, rainfall, and land use affect the transmission of vector-borne diseases.<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr"/><sup>&#x02013;</sup><xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Greenhouse gas emissions, particulates, waste from the fossil fuel industry, and vehicle exhausts contribute to pulmonary and other diseases.<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Climate change impacts have detrimental effects on mental health, including increased anxiety, depression, acute stress, and posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD).<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></p><p>Some people are harmed by climate change more than others, and as a result, climate change is exacerbating inequalities around the world (<xref rid="BOX1" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref>).<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Health impacts of climate change disproportionately affect those with underlying vulnerabilities, including pregnant women, the elderly, and people with comorbidities, and communities underserved by the health system including mobile groups and migrant workers. Children and adolescents are at particular risk of increased anxiety, depression, acute stress, and PTSD associated with climate change.<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Communities most at risk of negative health impacts caused by air pollution are those living or working closest to congested roads, fossil fuel industrial sites, and incinerators. In the United States, African Americans, people of Latin American heritage, and young people are disproportionately exposed to poor air quality.<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> In low and middle income countries (LMICs) people&#x02019;s health is also often at risk from burning fuels indoors. Economic hardship exacerbated by climate change is most likely to affect people who are already poor and marginalized or who rely on economies that are threatened, such as smallholder farmers. Disruptions in the aftermath of extreme weather events are associated with increased violence against women, girls, and other vulnerable people.<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Additionally, climate change disproportionately disadvantages young people; it has been predicted that children born in 2020 will experience 2- to 7-fold more extreme weather events than those born in 1960.<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>OUR OWN EMISSIONS ARE HARMING GLOBAL HEALTH</title><p>The activities and operations of global health institutions generate greenhouse gas emissions and contribute to global warming. In our field, greenhouse gas emissions come from energy used to power laboratories, clinics, data centers, animal facilities, and other buildings; fuel burned during commuting and air travel; embodied carbon in equipment and consumables; and emissions supported by financial holdings associated with the fossil fuel industry. Health care accounts for approximately 5% of national carbon footprints.<xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> In 2019, the total greenhouse gas emissions associated with air travel to the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene (ASTMH) annual meeting was an estimated 8,646 metric tons of carbon dioxide equivalents, which is approximately the same amount of carbon dioxide released from burning 20,017 barrels of oil.<xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> In comparison, the emissions associated with the virtual conference in 2021 was approximately 1.3 metric tons or 3 barrels of oil.<xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>THE BENEFITS OF ACTION</title><p>Reducing our carbon emissions aligns with our mission and core values to improve global health and equality. There are also further benefits. Reducing air pollution improves the respiratory health of local populations. Preserving biodiversity and environmental ecology mitigates against risks of emerging infectious diseases and future pandemics.<xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Decarbonization to limit warming to no greater than 1.5&#x000b0;C above preindustrial levels prevents even more dangerous climate change, even worse health impacts, and increased inequality. We need to embark on a collective effort to rapidly and significantly reduce these emissions.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>WHAT ARE THE OPPORTUNITIES FOR THE GLOBAL HEALTH COMMUNITY?</title><p>There are opportunities for climate action for all global health organizations. The actions we take should be guided by the principles of climate justice and a &#x0201c;just transition.&#x0201d; Historically, high-income countries (HICs) have made the largest contribution of greenhouse gasses to the atmosphere and as such need to rapidly decarbonize to help mitigate the worst effects of climate change. LMICs have contributed less and are often more at risk, but while they may still rely heavily on fossil fuels as a source of energy, they should not be left behind in the global transition to clean energy and environmentally sustainable economies.<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref></p><p>Institutions need to develop ambitious decarbonization goals and implementation plans that reduce emissions used to power buildings and transportation, embodied carbon in equipment and consumables, and financial investments in the fossil fuel industry. Decarbonization goals should align with the latest evidence-based recommendations from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, the United Nations body for assessing the science related to climate change.<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The short-term goal is to halve emissions by 2030, and institutions in HICs should make further and more rapid reductions. The United Nations&#x02013;backed Race to Zero initiative provides strategic guidance and an accountability framework for reducing emissions in public and private sector organizations.<xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Currently more than 5,000 businesses and 1,000 academic institutions have joined the Race to Zero. The Alliance for Sustainability Leadership in Education provides guidance for higher education institutions.<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref></p><p>For ASTMH, the ASTMH Green Task Force recommends building on the Society&#x02019;s Green Statement (<xref rid="BOX2" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 2</xref>) by including an ambitious decarbonization goal in the next strategic plan. We also recommend including members with expertise in sustainability on the Board of Directors and including young people from both HIC and LMIC settings to help develop the implementation plan and deliver on the goal. ASTMH has a unique opportunity and a positive role to play by providing a platform for ASTMH members to learn from one another in terms of decarbonization and carbon literacy.</p><p>Working in global health often involves international travel both for field activities and sharing of scientific results. We need to approach travel in a way that is mindful of the greenhouse gas emissions it generates while recognizing that travel can be essential to building global health partnerships and performing needed research.<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> In addition, many societies depend on in-person annual meetings for financial viability. We should prioritize virtual meetings and, when travel is necessary, opt for low-carbon means of transport (e.g., trains and electric vehicles as opposed to planes and vehicles with internal combustion engines). When flying is necessary, we can minimize emissions by flying direct, choosing economy class, and bundling meetings to reduce the frequency of flying. Finally, it is possible to offset the greenhouse gas emissions generated from air travel by capturing and storing greenhouse gases that would not otherwise be captured&#x02014;for example, through reforestation. Online tools exist that calculate the amount of carbon dioxide equivalents emitted from a given flight and the number of trees needed to absorb the same amount. However, it takes approximately 20 years of tree growth to absorb the emissions.<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref></p><p>Most electricity is generated from a mix of renewable and fossil fuel sources. Institutions can switch to electricity suppliers that link directly to renewable energy generators (e.g., wind turbines), if available, or install their own renewable energy systems (e.g., solar panels and battery storage). Over time, gas heating systems can be replaced by electric systems that can be powered with renewable energy sources.</p><p>Laboratories consume significant amounts of energy, water, and other resources. The Laboratory Efficiency Assessment Framework (LEAF) and My Green Laboratory platforms offer evidence-based guidance and online frameworks for laboratory personnel and researchers to implement actions that limit waste and reduce the carbon footprint of laboratory work, such as switching ultra-low temperature freezers from &#x02013;80 to &#x02013;70&#x000b0;C.<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr"/><sup>&#x02013;</sup><xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> It is estimated that the LEAF platform saves on average the equivalent of 2.9 tons of CO<sub>2</sub> per laboratory per year.<xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref></p><p>Institutions may have investments in fossil fuels&#x02014;for example, through holdings, endowments, or pension funds. The number of universities selling these investments and divesting from coal, oil, and gas is growing.<xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref><xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr"/><sup>&#x02013;</sup><xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Divesting from fossil fuels would align with the goal of global health institutions to improve global health.</p><p>A study of the decarbonization initiatives of 10 European global health institutions found that engaging internal stakeholders and collaboration with partners were important factors that facilitated progress.<xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> The ASTMH Green Task Force proposes that climate action within ASTMH and across the global health community can accelerate progress toward a healthier, more environmentally sustainable, and more equitable world.</p><boxed-text id="BOX1" position="float"><label>Box 1</label><caption><title>The impacts of climate change worsen existing inequalities</title></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Health-related risks are greater for those already vulnerable, such as children, pregnant women, the immunocompromised, and the elderly.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Extreme weather affects different geographies of the world disproportionately.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Poorer groups and people living in low and lower middle-income countries are at higher risk of climate impacts.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The disruption caused by extreme weather events is associated with increased violence against women, girls, and other vulnerable people.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><boxed-text id="BOX2" position="float"><label>Box 2</label><caption><title>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene (ASTMH) Green Statement adopted in 2021<xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref></title></caption><p>Global climate change directly and indirectly impacts the spread of infectious diseases and threatens the public health progress made since the founding of our society. ASTMH membership recognizes that our activities, both individual and collective, influence climate change and that we can leverage our strengths to be better stewards of our interconnected planet.</p><p>To successfully carry out our society&#x02019;s goals, we commit to the following:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Holding ourselves responsible as a community for our impact by reducing the environmental footprint of the Annual Meeting and the <italic>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</italic></p></list-item><list-item><p>Encouraging interdisciplinary research and partnerships to advance environmental sustainability within our global health efforts</p></list-item><list-item><p>Raising awareness within our society&#x02019;s reach</p></list-item></list></p></boxed-text></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene (ASTMH) Green Task Force is comprised of the following people (in alphabetical order): Shyam Prakash Dumre (Tribhuvan University, Central Department of Microbiology, Kathmandu, Nepal); A. Desiree LaBeaud (Stanford University, Department of Pediatrics, Division of Infectious Disease, Stanford, CA; ASTMH Green Task Force Chair); Hanna Ehrlich (Yale School of Public Health, New Haven, CT; ASTMH Green Task Force Co-Chair); Laia J. Vazquez Guillamet (ISGlobal Barcelona Institute for Global Health and Hospital Cl&#x000ed;nic&#x02014;Universitat de Barcelona, Spain); Bartholomew N. Ondigo (Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Egerton University, Nakuru, Kenya); Sapna P. Sadarangani (National Centre for Infectious Diseases, Singapore, Department of Infectious Diseases, Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore, and Lee Kong Chian School of Medicine, Nanyang Technological University, Singapore); Claire Njeri Wamae (M &#x00026; D Audubon Consultants, Nairobi, Kenya); and Kate Whitfield (ISGlobal Barcelona Institute for Global Health, Barcelona, Spain). We thank Rhonda Schultz and Lyn Maddox, ASTMH, Arlington, VA, for their valuable contributions to the ASTMH Green Task Force. The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene (ASTMH) assisted with publication expenses.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</collab>
, <year>2021</year>. <italic>Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</collab>
, <year>2022</year>. <italic>Climate Change 2022: Impacts, Adaptation and Vulnerability. Contribution of Working Group II to the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://report.ipcc.ch/ar6wg2/" ext-link-type="uri">https://report.ipcc.ch/ar6wg2/</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</collab>
, <year>2022</year>. <italic>Climate Change 2022: Mitigation of Climate Change. Contribution of Working Group III to the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italic>. 2021. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg3/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg3/</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atwoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2021</year>. 
<article-title>Call for emergency action to limit global temperature increases, restore biodiversity, and protect health</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>398</volume>: <fpage>939</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>941</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34496267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2021</year>. 
<article-title>Understanding the health needs of internally displaced persons: a scoping review</article-title>. <source>J Migr Health</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>100071</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ternova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Parasnis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovaleva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2022</year>. 
<article-title>Climate change and zoonoses: a review of concepts, definitions, and bibliometrics</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>893</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35055715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nosrat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2021</year>. 
<article-title>Impact of recent climate extremes on mosquito-borne disease transmission in Kenya</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>e0009182</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33735293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2008</year>. 
<article-title>Global trends in emerging infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>451</volume>: <fpage>990</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>993</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mordecai</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>LaBeaud</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>Climate change could shift disease burden from malaria to arboviruses in Africa</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e416</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e423</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32918887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2018</year>. 
<article-title>Pollution from fossil-fuel combustion is the leading environmental threat to global pediatric health and equity: solutions exist</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>
<volume>16</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2021</year>. 
<article-title>Climate anxiety in children and young people and their beliefs about government responses to climate change: a global survey</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e873</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34895496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2021</year>. 
<article-title>Intergenerational inequities in exposure to climate extremes</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>374</volume>: <fpage>158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>160</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34565177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pichler</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaccard</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2019</year>. 
<article-title>International comparison of health care carbon footprints</article-title>. <source>Environ Res Lett</source>
<volume>14</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bousema</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>Reducing the carbon footprint of academic conferences: the example of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>1758</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1761</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33069267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</collab>
, <year>2022</year>. <italic>Greenhouse Gas Equivalencies Calculator</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/energy/greenhouse-gas-equivalencies-calculator" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.epa.gov/energy/greenhouse-gas-equivalencies-calculator</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bousema</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2021</year>. <italic>Comparison of Carbon Emissions from the In-person and Virtual Conferences of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://zeroverse.org/uploads/1/3/8/7/138730731/astmh_carbon_comparison_in_person___virtual_meetings_2021[1751].pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://zeroverse.org/uploads/1/3/8/7/138730731/astmh_carbon_comparison_in_person___virtual_meetings_2021[1751].pdf</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabinowitz</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappaioanou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardosh</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2018</year>. 
<article-title>A planetary vision for one health</article-title>. <source>BMJ Glob Health</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e001137</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2021</year>. 
<article-title>Decarbonising healthcare in low and middle income countries: potential pathways to net zero emissions</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<volume>375</volume>: <fpage>1284</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change</collab>
, <year>2022</year>. <italic>Race to Zero</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/climate-action/race-to-zero-campaign#eq-2" ext-link-type="uri">https://unfccc.int/climate-action/race-to-zero-campaign#eq-2</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change</collab>
, <year>2021</year>. <italic>Get Net Zero Right</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://racetozero.unfccc.int/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Get-Net-Zero-right-2.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://racetozero.unfccc.int/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Get-Net-Zero-right-2.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>The Alliance for Sustainability Leadership in Education</collab>
, <year>2022</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eauc.org.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eauc.org.uk/</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>The Alliance for Sustainability Leadership in Education</collab>
, <year>2021</year>. <italic>Higher Education Climate Action Toolkit 2021</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eauc.org.uk/climate_action_toolkit" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eauc.org.uk/climate_action_toolkit</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Wellcome Trust</collab>
, <year>2021</year>. <italic>Carbon Offset Policy for Travel.</italic> Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://wellcome.org/grant-funding/carbon-offset-policy-travel" ext-link-type="uri">https://wellcome.org/grant-funding/carbon-offset-policy-travel</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>University College London</collab>
, <year>2022</year>. <italic>LEAF</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/sustainable/staff/labs/take-part-leaf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ucl.ac.uk/sustainable/staff/labs/take-part-leaf</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>My Green Lab</collab>
, <year>2022</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.mygreenlab.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.mygreenlab.org/</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>International Freezer Challenge</collab>
, <year>2022</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.freezerchallenge.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.freezerchallenge.org/</ext-link>. Assessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>University College London LEAF</collab>
, <year>2020</year>. <italic>How Much Carbon can you Save?</italic> Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/sustainable/staff/labs/how-much-carbon-can-you-save" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ucl.ac.uk/sustainable/staff/labs/how-much-carbon-can-you-save</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naomi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaylene</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2020</year>. 
<article-title>Climate change and the fossil fuel divestment movement in Canadian higher education: the mobilities of actions, actors, and tactics</article-title>. <source>J Clean Prod</source>
<volume>253</volume>: <fpage>119874</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reibstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>. The path to fossil fuel divestment for universities: climate responsible investment. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://ssrn.com/abstract=2565941" ext-link-type="uri">https://ssrn.com/abstract=2565941</ext-link>. Accessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitford</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2021</year>. <italic>Divestment Gap Emerges</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2021/04/28/divestment-gains-some-colleges-can-it-spread-where-oil-rules" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2021/04/28/divestment-gains-some-colleges-can-it-spread-where-oil-rules</ext-link>. Assessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cretu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bousema</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2022</year>. 
<article-title>Environmentally sustainable practices in global health research and higher education institutions: lessons from consultation with the TropEd Global Health institutions</article-title>. <source>Trop Med Int Health</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34932248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</collab>
, <year>2021</year>. <italic>ASTMH Green Statement</italic>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.astmh.org/about-astmh/who-we-are" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.astmh.org/about-astmh/who-we-are</ext-link>. Assessed April 21, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>