<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par58">These findings from the ethics discussion can shed light on the research question regarding the dominance of MBMs in shipping climate policy. The business ethics literature has charted an evolution of the role of business in setting regulation, from rule takers to rule makers, a move away from &#8220;state-centric&#8221; approaches (Andrade et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2014</xref>). In the governance of international shipping, the private sector is heavily involved at the IMO level, exerting a negative influence by obstructing climate policy. While various voluntary schemes are developing in the sector, they only target incremental gains that are easily overtaken by traffic growth. The key outcome from these schemes is in fact the way such voluntary governance is used to divert authority on environmental matters from regulatory organisations. The call for more environmental regulation from market leader Maersk has even been characterised as a way to strengthen existing market dominance because the hundreds of very small operators cannot do likewise, thus &#8220;further concentrating governance power within a few transnational corporations [and] potentially taking more ambitious regulation off the agenda&#8221; (Alger et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2021</xref>: 144). This outcome again ties the maritime case into Felli&#8217;s argument about the entrenchment of existing economic relations that avoid any radical system change. This entrenchment is further driven by the tension between nation states and the IMO, where some large nations refuse to consent to any international shipping regulation that may threaten their economic model. Analysing climate policy through the lens of ethics thus reveals an impasse at the heart of climate policy: climate change mitigation is a political problem requiring active intervention that cannot be achieved by leaving it to the market, but political actors do not want to change the market logic dominating their policies, which are underpinned by assumptions of growth and business-as-usual.</p>