<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">A handful of studies highlights the socio&#8208;cultural dimensions that remain absent in the dominating debates on institutional change and policy effectiveness in urban climate governance research. For example, Cid&#8208;Aguayo (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0098" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) explores social narratives of climate change in everyday life, as well as responses that arise from reconfigured assemblages between agricultural practices and relations with nature. This study demonstrates the process through which climate change becomes a force integrated into the daily structuring of objects and construction of meaning. Sou (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0270" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) argues that a rational interpretation of &#8220;risks&#8221; is not a critical factor shaping responses to climate change impacts. Instead, Sou (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0270" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0271" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) points to self&#8208;build housing process as &#8220;principally catalyzed and influenced by the transformation of broader social, cultural and economic processes,&#8221; shaped by sociocultural needs and responses to slow&#8208;onset, small&#8208;scale hazards. Waitt and Harada (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0287" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) explore the value&#8208;action gap between known climate effects of private vehicle transport and reliance on driving and conclude that policy studies downplay the role of emotions and identity related to car use. Adopting a theoretical perspective that emphasizes the embodiment of technologies and urban environments, they argue that, rather than reducing mobility choices to a question of rationality and attitudes, we need to understand how multisensorial experiences produce resistance against abandoning the use of the car. Acuto (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) argues that the search for global solutions often downplays the importance of mundane everyday spaces, which he identifies as the arena where politics are formed. Acuto (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>, p. 352) uses the analysis of waste flows as a means to examine &#8220;the &#8216;everyday&#8217; as a space for localized and routinized politics,&#8221; which are linked to individual habits and values that, at the same time, intersect with multiple strategies for waste management and recycling introduced by governmental and societal actors at different scales. Acuto (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) reminds us of the feminist observation that the personal is political and that the governance of the environment, even at a global level, is inseparable from the mundane.</p>