<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">This study has some limitations concerning (1) the design, (2) the instruments, and (3) the sample. First of all, we used a correlational design which is not suitable for conclusions on causal relations between variables. Further research may expand our study design and derive more suitable experimental designs. Additionally, we only gave one possible order of the questionnaires involved in this study. However, having previously presented a scale such as moral disengagement in high carbon behavior might have influenced the subsequent scales such as pro-environmental intention. Since moral disengagement is used as a justification for not behaving in a pro-environmental manner, responses on the pro-environmental intention scale might have been lower than if the moral disengagement scale had been administered subsequently. However, we wanted pro-environmental intention to be answered not directly after pro-environmental behavior as we hypothesized this would cause the participants to repeat their answers from pro-environmental behavior instead of actually elaborating on their pro-environmental intention. Furthermore, some other emotions that are associated with justice sensitivity (e.g., anger, or moral outrage) could be included in further investigations. Also, as mentioned before, qualitative approaches seem promising to get a broader insight into the emotional landscape in the context of climate justice. Second, questionnaires are based on self-reported behavior, which may introduce biased responses. To counteract this, we followed the recommendations of <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Satow (2012)</xref> and used a measure to exclude the data from socially desirable responding individuals. Due to the lack of an appropriate measure, we established a measure of the proneness to various emotions in the climate context for this study (see Methods). However, this measure was not validated. Also, the use of the carbon footprint calculator from Study 2 requires a lot of time and asks for very detailed information which may frustrate participants and lead them to not fill in the questionnaire conscientiously or even refrain from completing it at all. Additionally, standard answers are set in the carbon footprint calculator which may influence the answers of the participants. Third, our objective was to acquire a representative sample which is why we aimed to get a large sample size in Study 2. However, considering the high power of our calculations, we may have &#8220;oversampled&#8221; this second sample. A sample size that is that large may lead to an increased Type I error. At the same time, effect sizes, which we also used, are smaller in larger samples and account for this. Additionally, as we used the platform <italic>meinungsplatz.de</italic> to recruit panelists, the participants may be more affine toward digital media than other social groups as they created an account on that platform.</p>