<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">The use of machine vision in body condition scoring of dairy received extensive research attention in the last few decades. Fox et al. [<xref rid="B47-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] listed animal nutrition, insemination, and health as core reasons for body condition monitoring. When this process is carried out by the farmer or veterinary doctor (human monitoring), there is a possibility for biased data gathering, due to the individual&#8217;s mental state, level of experience, and residual knowledge [<xref rid="B48-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Furthermore, the process might also be time-consuming. Improvement in body condition scoring in the 1970s employed ultrasounds [<xref rid="B49-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], which was flawed on the ground that mastering the collection of reliable ultrasonic body condition scoring required more time in comparison to data gathering by humans [<xref rid="B50-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Additionally, the cost of purchasing the ultrasound device, and hiring an expert, made the process too expensive. This led to camera-recording of animals applied to body condition monitoring, based on the belief that this would yield better results [<xref rid="B48-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Fourier descriptor cameras [<xref rid="B51-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], thermal [<xref rid="B52-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], and RGB cameras [<xref rid="B53-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] were adopted. Nevertheless, images could not be processed automatically until seven years ago [<xref rid="B54-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. As a step in the right direction for body condition scoring, Spoliansky et al. [<xref rid="B55-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] used a 3D camera that was well-equipped to carry out automatic image processing, leading to the development of effective and unbiased collection of body condition scoring, in 2017 [<xref rid="B55-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The system provides real-time data, useful for commercial milking purposes, and genetic evaluation (based on lactation). In addition, automated image gathering of body condition scoring might provide ease of monitoring when there are more than one animal. This is pivotal to early warning signs for morphological changes in animal body size [<xref rid="B48-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</p>