<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par22">While the relationship to <italic>Janus</italic> is not direct, other developments in labor relations since 2016 may provide some signposts for the future. The use of the strike declined significantly beginning in the 1970s (Shierholz and Poydock <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2020</xref>). Many observers attribute the continued decline to President Reagan&#8217;s firing of the air traffic controllers in response to the PATCO strike in 1981, and the subsequent increase in employer use of replacements and lockouts (Dau-Schmidt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>, 776). The trend reversed in 2018 and 2019, however, led by massive unlawful teachers&#8217; strikes in states without collective bargaining laws (Dau-Schmidt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>, 776). These strikes followed years of decreases in state funding for education and they focused not only on teacher pay, but also on improved funding for classrooms, books, and other school staff (Dau-Schmidt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>, 1&#8211;2, 197). Union membership increased in states where walkouts occurred despite right to work laws (Semuels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2018</xref>). Thus far in 2020, scores of strikes have occurred in response to Covid-19 and in support of the Black Lives Matter movement, many of them wildcat strikes (Brecher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020b</xref>; Brecher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020c</xref>). In many cases, the workers are striking without the support of unions, either because they are not unionized or because their union does not support the strike (Elk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2020</xref>). In other strikes, the workers have continued to strike after the union has recommended a return to work (Dau-Schmidt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>, 197). Some recent strikes use unique tactics, such as getting small businesses to shut down to support the strike (Elk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2020</xref>).</p>