<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par24">Teachers in St. Paul, for example, have a long history of negotiating for the common good, including smaller class sizes, mental health teams for each school, more multilingual staff, more school nurses, and lighter loads for special education teachers (Verges <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2020</xref>). It is not only public sector unions that bargain for the common good, however. SEIU Local 26 in Minnesota, which represents cleaning workers, negotiated for green cleaning as well as a table of building owners and community groups to address environmental issues (Brecher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2020a</xref>). The union even engaged in a one-day strike, supported by community environmental organizations, in support of their demands (Brecher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2020a</xref>). Another recent example not directly tied to the Bargaining for the Common Good organization is the Milwaukee Bucks players&#8217; one game strike in response to the shooting of Jacob Blake and the protests in Kenosha, just down the road from Milwaukee (Jones and Danner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2020</xref>). The strike, which was joined by players in other professional sports, led to creation of a coalition by the NBA owners and players to address social justice issues, including &#8220;access to voting, promoting civic engagement and advocating for meaningful police and criminal justice reform&#8221; (Jones and Danner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2020</xref>). The move of traditional unions towards social movement unionism coincides with the development of alternative labor organizations which engage in worker advocacy without seeking exclusive representation rights (Hodges <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2016</xref>, 139). Funding remains a problem for these alternative groups without dues and fees to support their activities, however (Hodges <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2016</xref>, 139).</p>