<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Finally, and equally important, are the deafening silences in the IPCC report. A great number of working people in the world today need a range of access to a range of land and nature. The report is silent as to whether climate change mitigation and adaptation measures require prior or accompanying equitable distribution of control over land and other resources. Moreover, the report says nothing about how to equitably <italic toggle="yes">redistribute or restitute</italic> land to working people, and how to protect the threatened land access of working people. The term &#8216;redistribution&#8217; (of land) is mentioned occasionally in the report, but with no explanation or definition. The report also mentions &#8216;landscape&#8217; and &#8216;landscape governance&#8217;, which is a promising lead (Hunsberger et al., <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), but again says nothing of what these might mean. The concept of &#8216;landscape&#8217; is highly contested in the literature (see Mitchell, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>), and without clarifying what it means in the IPCC report, it is likely to be subsumed by the neoliberal &#8216;land tenure security&#8217; framework. We do not suggest that IPCC reports should get into prescriptive operational matters; but specifying fundamental principles that define categories and concepts could clarify perspectives and positions, especially amid competing narratives not only on land politics but on climate change (Borras et al., <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). While it is laudable that the report notes, albeit rather weakly, the issue of emissions by monoculture plantations, it is generally silent about what kind of agriculture contributes to and aggravates climate change, and &#8211; beyond enumeration of some technical and management-related issues in farming and soil management &#8211; on what type of agriculture can help mitigate climate change. This lacuna gives the impression that agriculture as a whole is the culprit. Our starting point in this paper is that it is capitalist industrial agriculture &#8211; which is not just an agroecological and technical farming system, but a socioeconomic and political system &#8211; that contributes significantly to climate change.</p>