<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par6">Rothstein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2017</xref>) details the effort by the federal government near the end of World War I to entice white Americans to build and own single-family homes as a stalwart against communism, but also to avoid racial strife, with entrenched policies assuring that only white people would likely end up owning those homes. Despite federal government encouragement, even very few white people owned homes before World War II. At that time, homeownership was the province only of the very rich, largely because it typically required large (50% or more) down payments to obtain a mortgage and very short repayment periods (Murray <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2008</xref>; Rothstein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2017</xref>). President Franklin D. Roosevelt signed both the National Housing Act in 1934 as part of the New Deal legislation,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1">1</xref> and the Servicemen&#8217;s Readjustment Act of 1944 (known as the &#8220;G.I. Bill of Rights&#8221;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref>); together, these laws radically changed access to homeownership in America. Eligible veterans could then borrow money with little or no down payment to purchase land (such as farms), houses, farming equipment, and more, with 30-year repayment periods. As Murray (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2008</xref>) observed, &#8220;[n]early five million veterans bought homes under the G.I. Bill, amounting to almost half of the new homes constructed in the United States in the decade following World War II.&#8221; The G.I. bill also provided these returning veterans free &#8220;education or training&#8221; which included up to 4 years of college or other types of vocational training (Blakemore <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2019</xref>), further increasing their ability to obtain wealth and stability that would then be passed down to future generations. The landscape of America was truly transformed by these laws, a middle class was firmly established, and the security of homeownership was felt my millions of Americans.</p>