<abstract xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="phn12866-abs-0001"><title>Abstract</title><p>The purpose of this integrative review is to examine recent literature on the intersection of SARS&#8208;CoV&#8208;2 (COVID&#8208;19 novel coronavirus) and climate change that will lead to a greater understanding of the complexities of the urgent pandemic linked with the emerging climate crisis. A literature search for peer&#8208;reviewed, English language, literature published since the pandemic emerged was conducted using Cumulated Index to Nursing and Allied Health Literature (CINAHL), PubMed, and the Cochrane Library. The final sample yielded a total of 22 commentaries, editorials, discussion papers, and a research study that explicitly addressed the intersection of COVID&#8208;19 and climate change. Sixty articles emerged in the initial review of the intersection of the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic and climate change with the final yield of 22 articles deemed valid for inclusion after full text review. With the emergence of COVID&#8208;19 and scholarly discourse that addresses the intersection of the pandemic with climate change, key issues emerged that intersect with policy /advocacy, social justice, and nursing's public health role in clinical practice, education, policy/advocacy, and research/scholarship. Five themes that emerged included the <italic toggle="yes">role of public health in COVID&#8208;19 and climate change efforts; global approach addressing human&#8208;environment issues; intersection of COVID&#8208;19 and climate change from a community and global perspective; impacts of COVID&#8208;19, climate change and the environment</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">professional associations and specialty organizations&#8217; views and responsibilities with a lens on COVID&#8208;19 and climate change</italic>. Despite the importance of addressing racial inequities as well as systemic and structural racism that impacts those most affected by climate change and pandemics such as COVID&#8208;19, no literature addressed this topic. Public health nursing has a critical role in addressing climate change and the pandemic response to COVID 19 in the 21st century.</p></abstract>