<contrib-group xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/"><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8254-4233</contrib-id><name><surname>Temudo</surname><given-names>Marina Padr&#227;o</given-names></name><address><email>marinatemudo@gmail.com</email><email>marinatemudo@isa.ulisboa.pt</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><bio><sec id="FPar1"><title>Marina Padr&#227;o Temudo</title><p id="Par1">is a senior research fellow at CEF, School of Agriculture, University of Lisbon, Portugal.&#160;She has conducted extensive ethnographic field research on development and conservation in Guinea-Bissau, Angola, Cape Verde, Mozambique, S. Tom&#233; and Pr&#237;ncipe, and in the Republic of Guinea. Some of her most recent articles have been published in Human Ecology, Applied Geography, and the Journal of Peasant Studies.</p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6417-450X</contrib-id><name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>Ana I. R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><bio><sec id="FPar2"><title>Ana I.R. Cabral</title><p id="Par2">is a senior research fellow at CEF, School of Agriculture, University of Lisbon, Portugal. She is a Geographic Information System and Remote Sensing expert, working in tropical regions, in the areas of deforestation, mapping and modeling of land cover/land use change scenarios and quantification of carbon emissions. Her most recent articles have been published in Human Ecology, Remote sensing and Journal of Peasant Studies.</p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0233-953X</contrib-id><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>Pedro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><bio><sec id="FPar3"><title>Pedro Reis</title><p id="Par3">is a senior research at National Institute of Agricultural and Veterinary Research, Portugal. He is an Agronomist, Agricultural Economy and Rural Sociology expert, working in the study of socioeconomic dynamics in the rural regions, analysis of the agricultural and forestry systems, agricultural and rural development policies, and study of the agricultural knowledge and innovation system.</p></sec></bio></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9983.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2181 4263</institution-id><institution>Forest Research Centre (CEF), School of Agriculture, </institution><institution>University of Lisbon, Tapada da Ajuda, </institution></institution-wrap>1349-017 Lisbon, Portugal </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>National Institute of Agricultural and Veterinary Research, Av. da Rep&#250;blica, Quinta Do Marqu&#234;s, 2780-157 Oeiras, Portugal </aff></contrib-group>