<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Building consensus at the centre may be worthwhile under certain conditions. But a major problem today lies in the tendency of such a strategy to incorporate contested concepts by emptying them of class analysis and definition (Arsel, <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Class &#8211; along with co-constitutive social identities, especially gender, race/ethnicity, generation and religion &#8211; intersect and influence the causes, conditions and consequences of climate change and political responses to the climate crisis we are now facing. Without class analysis, how can one understand how climate change shapes &#8211; and is shaped by &#8211; decisions about who should control land, how much, where and for what purposes, and who must lose, or be denied, access? If our assumption is that land-based inequalities must be addressed, then it is &#8216;redistributive land policy&#8217; &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">not</italic> &#8216;land tenure security&#8217; &#8211; that becomes urgent and necessary. In societies marked by land-based inequities, land tenure security in the form of formalization of land claims <italic toggle="yes">without</italic> redistributive and restitutive content is likely to legitimize and reinforce inequities. Land tenure security through formalization of land claims per se is not problematical because it can result to real benefits for working poor people, but where this occurred in the absence of accompanying redistributive and restitutive policies the outcomes tend to be ad hoc and limited, and sometimes essentially a counter-reform. Inherently a class-relational approach, social justice-oriented redistributive land policy requires an understanding of the underlying class character and direction of the flow of change in social relations. Gaining land access or suffering land dispossession are not random or neutral social processes, unmarked by purposive political action and theories of social change. <italic toggle="yes">In short, redistributive land policies necessarily include a component of land tenure security in the form of formalization of land claims and land titling, but stand-alone &#8216;land tenure security&#8217; through formalization of land claim or land titling on its own does not necessarily and always have redistributive and restitutive substance</italic>.</p>