<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par8">Hundreds of cases have been filed against unions which collected fair share fees under state laws that were invalidated by <italic>Janus.</italic> If successful, the claims would require unions to refund millions of dollars of fees collected when authorized by state laws and already spent representing members (Hodges <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2020</xref>, 4). The cases have been filed in many different jurisdictions based on a variety of legal theories, but primarily seek retroactive application of <italic>Janus</italic> (Hodges <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2020</xref>, 4&#8211;5). They have been singularly unsuccessful thus far, but impose substantial litigation costs on unions that could otherwise dedicate these resources to representing workers (Hodges <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2020</xref>, 6&#8211;9). Courts considering the issue have determined that unions have a good faith defense to such claims because they collected the fees in reliance on validly enacted state laws which had been declared constitutional by the Supreme Court in 1977 (Hodges <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2020</xref>, 6&#8211;9). Regardless of how one feels about unions and fair share fees, these cases have troubling implications. While thus far unions have prevailed, a contrary result would mean that a private party could be liable for millions of dollars for conduct that is not only explicitly authorized by state law but also state law that has previously been found constitutional by the highest court in the land. The plaintiff in <italic>Janus</italic> lost his case seeking to recoup his fees and has a petition for certiorari pending at the Supreme Court. Some have suggested that Justice Ginsburg&#8217;s death and likely replacement by a far more conservative justice might lead to another decision favoring union opponents in the fee repayment cases (Campbell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2020</xref>).</p>