<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0120">The second suggestion towards sustainable and resilient food systems is promoting alternative strategies to agriculture as a means of livelihood for women. Numerous research informs that owing to limited production resources, especially dwindling land and water access, agriculture may not be adequate to support livelihoods for everyone in rural communities (<xref rid="bb0385" ref-type="bibr">Lowder et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0345" ref-type="bibr">Jayne and Muyanga, 2012</xref>). Social protection programs such as direct cash transfer, food assistance and school meals programmes, have been increasingly promoted as alternative strategies to counter vulnerabilities among the most marginalized and poorest individuals (<xref rid="bb0485" ref-type="bibr">Slater, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Barrientos, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0490" ref-type="bibr">Soares et al., 2009</xref>). While such measures are critical in times of crisis, they may not be effective in maintaining sustainability and resilience of a food system. Indeed, as indicated by Guinn and Hamrick (<xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr">Guinn and Hamrick, 2015</xref>), drawing from a case of South Africa, with its history of Apartheid and inequality in land and other resources, social protection measures may serve in meeting urgent needs. However, these types of measures usually do not address the structural social issues that affect food accessibility. Against this backdrop, in certain circumstances, it is crucial to move beyond social protection measures to improve the local capacity to earn a livelihood outside agriculture and to address structural causes of inequality. Alternative interventions are off-farm activities that can be pursued. Women should be encouraged and supported to find alternative livelihoods to farming or providing labour in the agricultural sector, such as venture in in a business or promote access to wage labour in other sectors. This aspect is hardly emphasized in development policy and practice. Some people can get their livelihood in the agricultural sector, but what is beyond?</p>