<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par28">The IPCC did not, of course, create such countdown clocks by itself. However, it can be argued that the IPCC helped create&#8212;though, rather unintendedly&#8212;the <italic>political</italic> conditions for that its findings were used as rhetorical devices for setting an imaginary deadline to urge immediate climate action (Asayama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2019</xref>; Hulme <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2020a</xref>). As one of the main conclusions of the SR15, the IPCC estimated that the remaining time to reach 1.5&#176;C would be between 12 and 34 years from 2018 if the current rate of warming continues (IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2018</xref>; see Fig.<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). At the same time, the report also concluded that to limit global warming to 1.5&#176;C, global CO<sub>2</sub> emissions must decline by about 45% from 2010 levels by 2030, then reaching net zero around 2050. Soon after the release of SR15, this somewhat &#8216;dry&#8217; statement was reinterpreted as some kind of an &#8216;alarm bell&#8217; from scientists, warning us of how little time is left before it becomes too late to avert irreversible climate damage. The IPCC&#8217;s reference to the year 2030 made it appear as if a make-or-break deadline determining the fate of the climate.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The estimated date by which global temperature will reach 1.5&#176;C (Source: IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2018</xref>). The 2018 IPCC Special Report on 1.5&#176;C (SR15) estimated that human activities have caused approximately 1&#176;C of warming above pre-industrial levels and that if the current pace of warming continues, warming will reach 1.5&#176;C around 2040, within a likely range between 2030 and 2052.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10584_2021_3185_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>