<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Three themes of research have consolidated during the second wave: urban informality, nature&#8208;based solutions, and experimentation as a climate change governance approach. The emphasis on urban informality is most often associated with research on community&#8208;based action in the Global South, highlighting the inextricable links between climate&#8208;related risk, poverty, and marginalization. Empirical work demonstrates opportunities to work alongside communities most affected by climate disaster and collaboratively build their adaptive capacity, especially in the absence of government action (Ahammad, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0037" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Kumar, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0180" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Actions directed towards addressing contexts of urban informality need to combine climate adaptation action with poverty&#8208;alleviation agendas (Brown &amp; McGranahan, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0070" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), addressing livelihoods (Simatele, Binns, &amp; Simatele, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0266" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), tenure (Roy, Hulme, &amp; Jahan, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0247" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), local infrastructure (Kiunsi, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0171" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), sanitation (Heath, Parker, &amp; Weatherhead, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0145" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), and mobility (Milan &amp; Creutzig, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0205" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). This work is closely linked to studies that use participatory and coproduction approaches to deliver shared learning and communicating local needs (Archer et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; McEvoy et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0202" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), in actions that address marginalization (Dobson, Nyamweru, &amp; Dodman, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0110" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Roy et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0247" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Stein &amp; Moser, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0274" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), build recognition of local knowledge and skills (Haque, Dodman, &amp; Hossain, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0140" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Odemerho, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0217" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Wamsler &amp; Brink, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0288" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), and tackle technocratic impulses (Cast&#225;n Broto, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0083" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Some research gaps relate to the need to understand the unintended impacts of climate action on the ground, and the need to increase attention to social groups excluded from urban governance, such as migrants (Adri &amp; Simon, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0035" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Martin et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0199" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Santha et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0253" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p>