<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Third, a growing strand of research has examined urban climate governance through experimentation (Boyd &amp; Juhola, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0068" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Bulkeley &amp; Cast&#225;n Broto, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0074" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Cast&#225;n Broto &amp; Bulkeley, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0086" ref-type="bibr">2013b</xref>; Reed et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0233" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Experimentation may be an avenue through which civic groups and activists gain access to political processes and build legitimacy for alternative environmental narratives (Cloutier, Papin, &amp; Bizier, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0099" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). There is also an interest in the mechanisms through which social or technical experiments diffuse or institutionalize and translate into mechanisms of transformation. In particular, concerns about the possibilities of scaling&#8208;up or scaling&#8208;out, where horizontal replication through networks so far has been most common (Smeds &amp; Acuto, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0269" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The embedding of experiments requires the configuration of new actor relations and networks, contestation of hegemonic logics, and the parallel construction of new rationalities (Bulkeley, Cast&#225;n Broto, &amp; Maassen, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0075" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Bulkeley, Luque&#8208;Ayala, &amp; Silver, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0077" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). It has, however, been shown that experiments may reinforce current structures of power and function as non&#8208;inclusive mechanisms of knowledge production (Evans &amp; Karvonen, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0125" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) or support the creation of exclusive elite spaces (Marvin &amp; Rutherford, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0200" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In any case, a superficial evaluation of experiments is likely to lead to misunderstandings about what is a desirable outcome and how it is achieved. Cast&#225;n Broto and Bulkeley (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0085" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>) point to the importance of maintaining experiments through time, which highlights an understanding of climate change governance as a process and foster skepticism about the possibility to evaluate results at a single point of time.</p>