<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In recent years, this area of research has experienced a resurge through a growing interest in transformations. Recent work points towards an increased interest in the social learning required to transform urban systems (Wolfram, van der Heijden, Juhola, &amp; Patterson, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0295" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), which will require the interaction of multiple elements, such as local leadership, empowered communities, and trusted boundary&#8208;spanning organizations (Wolfram, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0294" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Intermediary organizations may play an essential role in building trust, creating networks, and contributing to facilitate shared construction of meaning in the process of institutionalization (Horne &amp; Moloney, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0155" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Yet, higher&#8208;order (e.g., triple loop) social learning in urban governance processes is so far modest (Fink, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0127" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Shefer, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0263" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), and it has proven difficult to overcome self&#8208;reinforcing mechanisms of existing logics and build legitimacy for new routines (Uittenbroek, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0283" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). De&#8208;institutionalization of incumbent regimes appears similarly challenging to attain (Parks, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0221" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and experiments may often fail to deliver institutional change (Madsen &amp; Hansen, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0196" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Nagorny&#8208;Koring (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0211" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) argues that the so&#8208;called &#8220;best practice&#8221; solutions are characterized by sticky and place&#8208;bound dimensions that prevent their diffusion. In terms of governance, this emphasis on &#8220;best practice,&#8221; she argues, overemphasizes generalizable rather than experiential knowledge, and thus removes attention from the contextual conditions that facilitate deep learning. In spite of the growing recognition that the governance of climate change requires multiple forms of learning&#8212;especially institutional learning&#8212;some analyses of current experiences suggest that learning&#8208;oriented organizations, such as the C40, continue to advocate measures that either lead to incremental change or reproduce the status quo (Heikkinen, Yla&#8208;Anttila, &amp; Juhola, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0146" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).</p>