<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In the lack of soundly validated <italic>and</italic> economic, i.e., brief, German scales to measure pride, guilt, and shame proneness, we designed four scenarios based on the Test of Self-Conscious Affect (TOSCA; <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">Tangney et al., 2000</xref>) &#8211; two in which an intended pro-environmental behavior was (a) accomplished or (b) not accomplished, respectively. An example of such a scenario is the following: &#8220;For ecological reasons, you have decided to travel less by car and more by bicycle. Accordingly, you have planned to ride your bike the short distance to visit someone in the evening. However, when the time comes, you feel exhausted and take the car again.&#8221; Participants rated statements such as: &#8220;You would regret taking the car&#8221; (guilt-proneness), on a 6-point scale (1 = not likely, 6 = very likely). Thus, guilt, shame, and authentic and hubristic pride were each assessed with 2 items in 2 different scenarios, resulting in 8 items; and each scenario measured two emotions (shame and guilt, or authentic and hubristic pride). The original questionnaire was developed on the basis of descriptions of personal experiences of guilt, shame, and pride, and was found to successfully measure characteristic guilt- and shame-proneness as well as authentic and hubristic pride. The internal consistency was questionable for guilt (&#945; = 0.66) and shame (&#945; = 0.67) and poor for both dimensions of pride (&#945;<sub>authentic&#8196; pride</sub> = 0.55, &#945;<sub>hubristic&#8196; pride</sub> = 0.54). However, as the scales comprise only two items and these items were presented in the context of different scenarios which might have introduced a context variance, the reliabilities were regarded as acceptable and, therefore, sufficient for the planned analyses; the scenarios and items can be found in <xref rid="S10.SS3" ref-type="sec">Appendix C</xref>.</p>