<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Soc Anthropol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Soc Anthropol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1469-8676</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SOCA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Social Anthropology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0964-0282</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-8676</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8013454</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1469-8676.13005</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SOCA13005</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Forum</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Forum</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>New climate change activism: before and after the Covid&#x02010;19 pandemic</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">New climate change activism: before and after the Covid&#x02010;19 pandemic</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">VON STORCH, SUN, LEY</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="soca13005-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Von Storch</surname><given-names>Lilian</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7994-7672</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="soca13005-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="soca13005-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>Lukas</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8423-0011</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="soca13005-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="soca13005-cr-0003" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0344-4697</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="soca13005-aff-0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><address><email>j.sun@stud.uni-heidelberg.de</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="soca13005-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Social and Cultural Anthropology</named-content>
<institution>University of Cologne</institution>
<named-content content-type="street">Albertus&#x02010;Magnus&#x02010;Platz</named-content>
<postal-code>50923</postal-code>
<city>Cologne</city>
<country country="DE">Germany</country>
</aff><aff id="soca13005-aff-0002">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Institute of Anthropology</named-content>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Center for Asian and Transcultural Studies</named-content>
<institution>Heidelberg University</institution>
<named-content content-type="street">Vo&#x000df;stra&#x000df;e 2</named-content>
<city>Heidelberg</city>
<postal-code>69115</postal-code>
<country country="DE">Germany</country>
</aff><aff id="soca13005-aff-0003">
<label><sup>3</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Institute of Anthropology</named-content>
<institution>Heidelberg University</institution>
<named-content content-type="street">Vo&#x000df;stra&#x000df;e 2</named-content>
<city>Heidelberg</city>
<postal-code>69115</postal-code>
<country country="DE">Germany</country>
</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/soca.v29.1</issue-id><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright">&#x000a9; 2021 European Association of Social Anthropologists<copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2021 The Authors. <italic>Social Anthropology</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of European Association of Social Anthropologists.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy-nc-nd"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non&#x02010;commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:SOCA-29-205.pdf"/><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>WOA Institution: RUPRECHT KARLS UNIVERSITAET HEIDELBERG</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-0002"><funding-source>Blended DEAL : ProjektDEAL</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="4"/><word-count count="1924"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>February 2021</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.0.1 mode:remove_FC converted:01.04.2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body id="soca13005-body-0001"><p>The global climatic and ecological crisis becomes more apparent with every passing year. Shocking images of the burning Congo Basin, of bushfires devastating aboriginal land in Australia, of thawing permafrost in Siberia and mass coral bleaching have gone viral. Countless studies from independent scientists have linked these events to climate change and revealed their serious effects on human wellbeing (Oreskes <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Watts <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). These catastrophes killed tens of thousands of people and destroyed the livelihoods of millions. Yet, so far, linking them to climate change has not generated meaningful political action (Swyngedouw <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Hornborg <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) to decrease consumption (Wilk <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), stop fossil fuel extraction, reduce pollution or halt ecological destruction. Faced with this inaction, a new type of climate activism recently emerged in Europe. Since the first student strikes dating back to August 2018, millions of mainly young people have participated in climate protests, with the Global Climate Strike in September 2019 counting a staggering number of 7.6 million participants. Spurred by public celebrities, such as Swedish Greta Thunberg, various &#x02018;for future&#x02019; movements organised peaceful mass protests and civil disobedient actions in the streets of cities all over the world, which have been regularly covered in media and noticed by politicians of all stripes. This new climate justice movement has accomplished exceptional things in a very short time: it created lasting international protest networks, managed to rally supporters through social media and public performances and, arguably, helped to raise the level of awareness of the climate crisis among youth and other generations.</p><p>The emergence of this new type of mass activism poses a number of anthropological questions. For many activists, especially young people, involvement with climate change&#x02010;related protest groups marks a sort of political coming&#x02010;of&#x02010;age. How do they learn political practice and citizenship? What examples and idols do they refer to? Studying novel climate action networks and their members and practices provides insights into contemporary forms of politicisation and the constitution of environmental subjectivities (Agrawal <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Callison <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Carefully weaving appealing graphic design and egalitarian language into their political messages, climate activists further constitute aesthetic systems (Sartwell <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Werbner <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Meyer <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>) whose public acts are intricately planned performances of disruption. What systems of meaning and subjectivities are created in the context of these performances and what are their affective scaffoldings (Dave <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>)? Since public actions are planned as non&#x02010;violent interventions, the movements challenge power structures by staging and publicly brandishing scientific knowledge. What is the role of science in acts of civil disobedience? Lastly, protests claim and intervene in urban spaces, making disruption and deceleration felt, and enacting an alternative way of life (Wetzel <xref rid="soca13005-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). How do urban publics respond to and shape these infrastructural disruptions?</p><p>Through this Forum, we hope to present some anthropological perspectives on the recent phenomenon of mass climate protests in Europe and beyond. Knowing that many anthropologists have been involved in the context of climate activism, we want to rekindle reflections on our discipline&#x02019;s stake in and influence on transitions to a different world in the aftermath of the Covid&#x02010;19 pandemic. We are interested in thinking about how we, as anthropologists, could work with and alongside the climate justice movement, both as individuals who advise and spread knowledge and as a well&#x02010;established and networked institution. In our opinion, during these times of multiple intersecting crises, anthropologists have the urgent task to ponder the role that the discipline has to play in fomenting social change and offering political alternatives. We know now for certain that the generations to come will have to deal with an unstable world <italic>and</italic> grapple with the lurking possibility of deadly pandemics. We hope that this Forum will help to show that anthropologists are poised to become interlocutors of environmental movements, but also that their knowledge can make a difference for humans and other beings as they face the impacts of climate change and for the generations of earthlings to come. Ultimately, we want to take stock of the stories that anthropology can tell to influence the outcome of the planetary crisis of climate change, because, as Jonathan Safran Foer cogently put it, &#x02018;History not only makes a good story in retrospect; good stories <italic>become</italic> history&#x02019; (<xref rid="soca13005-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>: 16).</p><p>In this Forum, 11 anthropologists talk about their experience with and offer interpretations of new climate activism. To allow readers to better navigate the Forum&#x02019;s diverse contributions, we grouped them into four topical categories: political implications, movements and the self, science, and specific forms of activism.</p><sec id="soca13005-sec-0002"><title>Political implications</title><p>Writing in the midst of a pandemic, Alf Hornborg argues that while climate activism raised general awareness of far&#x02010;reaching environmental problems, it proved unsuccessful at averting climate change. He wonders why the globally spreading Covid&#x02010;19 virus has been quicker in making inroads in reducing emissions and protecting ecosystems. Kevin M. DeLuca explores the role of image events in ecological activism in the age of globalisation and new media. He asks to what extent contemporary climate protest movements are able to challenge techno&#x02010;industrial capitalism, as their ways to act are based on the resources of this very system. Similarly, Sarah Vaughn sees in climate activism the potential to tell stories about connections between the local and planetary effects of climate change. Since these stories exist on the fringe of dominant discourses, ethnography can help highlighting these connections.</p></sec><sec id="soca13005-sec-0003"><title>Movements and the self</title><p>Thomas Hylland Eriksen thinks about the new climate protest movements from the perspective of generation. He describes young demonstrators as less entrenched in fixed social structures than older generations, which is why they can more easily question them. For him, this raises the question whether climate protest is just a phase in the life of a young person or whether we are witnessing a more lasting change in discourse. Arne Harms invites us to consider so&#x02010;called regenerative cultures as an invisible yet intimate form of activism. As a practice that requires turning inwards and practising self&#x02010;care, regenerative culture is about forming a resilient self in the face of political inaction and needs to be understood in the wider context of environmental decline. In her text, Paula Serafini argues that a joint global movement based on a decolonial, ecofeminist ethic of care is required to fight the multiple interconnected challenges of our times.</p></sec><sec id="soca13005-sec-0004"><title>Science</title><p>Looking at scientific understandings of climate change, Larry Lohmann examines the relationship between climate movements and the climate and energy sciences. He demonstrates that not only are the constituents of mainstream climate movements predominantly white, male and from privileged classes, but that climate science is also equally biased. In his piece, Franz Krause grapples with the fact that anthropological insights and expertise are not taken up by policy makers and institutions involved in the fight against climate change. Similarly, anthropological expertise has been largely absent in dealings with the Covid&#x02010;19 pandemic. Worried about this trend, he suggests that anthropologists highlight paths from their research insights to policy changes.</p></sec><sec id="soca13005-sec-0005"><title>Specific forms of activism</title><p>Alexander K&#x000f6;nsler urges the social sciences to attend to recent climate protests and their development, as they exhibit new forms of mobilisation. Drawing on his own research, he argues that doing research in rural areas is just as important as focusing on urban activism. Mario Kr&#x000e4;mer describes primarily leftist climate activism as a rather new phenomenon and deals with traditionalist origins of environmental conservation, as the former often causes scepticism among traditionalist groups. Due to the emergence of new narratives about environmental and climate protection, even among moderate ecological traditionalists as well as the far right, Kr&#x000e4;mer appeals for the anthropological exploration of those groups and their strategies. Despite growing commitment to renewable energy in Germany, Werner Krau&#x000df; highlights the importance of place&#x02010;based efforts to cope successfully with global climate change. In their everyday conversations and daily routines, some concerned citizens suggest departures from a carbon&#x02010;intensive way of life, making hidden climate costs visible. Based on observations in Bali, Indonesia, Annette Hornbacher talks about nascent environmental activism on the island, finding a local understanding of climate change that markedly differs from Western views. In Bali, representations of climate change include both meteorological shifts and societal change. Hornbacher thus points to a general &#x02018;mood of crisis&#x02019; in the wake of the island&#x02019;s turn to a modern, consumerist lifestyle. In Sophie Mahakam Anggawi&#x02019;s account of the Balinese punk collective &#x02018;Denkol&#x02019;, she shows how activists spring into action in the face of a careless and unreliable state response to the pandemic. The piece shows how civil efforts to protect the environment create an alternative support infrastructure that re&#x02010;enfranchises abandoned parts of society.</p><p>The convenors of this Forum are Jing Sun and Lilian von Storch, two anthropology students based in Heidelberg and Cologne, and Lukas Ley, a post&#x02010;doc at the Institute of Anthropology, Heidelberg University. All of us came into contact with contemporary climate protest movements in 2018 and have been involved as participants, action&#x02010;strategists as well as coordinators ever since.</p></sec><sec id="soca13005-sec-0006"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Funding Statement: Open Access funding enabled and organized by ProjektDEAL.</p><p>WOA Institution: RUPRECHT KARLS UNIVERSITAET HEIDELBERG</p><p>Blended DEAL: ProjektDEAL</p></sec></body><back><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="soca13005-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="soca13005-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="soca13005-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Agrawal</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2005</year>. &#x02018;<article-title>Community, intimate government, and the making of environmental subjects in Kumaon, India</article-title>&#x02019;, <source xml:lang="en">Current Anthropology</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13005-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Callison</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2014</year>. <source xml:lang="en">How climate change comes to matter: the communal life of facts</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13005-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Dave</surname>, <given-names>N. N.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2012</year>. <source xml:lang="en">Queer activism in India: a story in the anthropology of ethics</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13005-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Foer</surname>, <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2019</year>. <source xml:lang="en">We are the weather: saving the planet begins at breakfast</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin Books</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="soca13005-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Hornborg</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2017</year>. &#x02018;<article-title>Dithering while the planet burns: anthropologists&#x02019; approaches to the Anthropocene</article-title>&#x02019;, <source xml:lang="en">Reviews in Anthropology</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13005-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2009</year>. &#x02018;<chapter-title>From imagined communities to aesthetic formations: religious mediations, sensational forms, and styles of binding</chapter-title>&#x02019;, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
</string-name></person-group> (ed.), <source xml:lang="en">Aesthetic formations: media, religion, and the senses</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="soca13005-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Oreskes</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2004</year>. &#x02018;<article-title>The scientific consensus on climate change</article-title>&#x02019;, <source xml:lang="en">Science</source>
<volume>306</volume>: <fpage>1686</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15576594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13005-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Sartwell</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2010</year>. <source xml:lang="en">Political aesthetics</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="soca13005-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Swyngedouw</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2011</year>. &#x02018;<article-title>Depoliticized environments: the end of nature, climate change and the post&#x02010;political condition</article-title>&#x02019;, <source xml:lang="en">Royal Institute of Philosophy Supplement</source>
<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="soca13005-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Watts</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Amann</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Arnell</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Ayeb&#x02010;Karlsson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Belesova</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Berry</surname>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>. <year>2018</year>. &#x02018;<article-title>The 2018 report of the <italic>Lancet</italic> Countdown on health and climate change: shaping the health of nations for centuries to come</article-title>&#x02019;, <source xml:lang="en">The Lancet</source>
<volume>392</volume>: <fpage>2479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>514</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13005-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Werbner</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Webb</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Spellman&#x02010;Pots</surname>
</string-name>
<year>2014</year>. <chapter-title>The political aesthetics of global protest</chapter-title>, in <source xml:lang="en">The political aesthetics of global protest: the Arab Spring and beyond</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13005-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Wetzel</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2016</year>. <chapter-title>Two examples of recent aesthetico&#x02010;political forms of community: Occupy and Sharing Economy</chapter-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Claviez</surname>
</string-name></person-group> (ed.), <source xml:lang="en">The common growl: toward a poetics of precarious community</source>, <fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="soca13005-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="soca13005-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Wilk</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2009</year>. <chapter-title>Consuming ourselves to death</chapter-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Crate</surname>
</string-name></person-group> (ed.), <source xml:lang="en">Anthropology and climate change: from encounters to actions</source>, <fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>