<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par13">Research into <italic>policy packages</italic> relates to research regarding policymaking. Standard practice in policymaking is often called &#8220;policy patching&#8221; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Thus, empirical research on the design and content of national and/or international energy and climate policies often shows an ad hoc policy patching pattern. This pattern implies uncontrolled growth of local, regional, and federal state policies and interventions that are rarely consistent with one other [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The policy package approach tries to tackle this problem &#8220;by considering the interaction of the instruments in a bundle&#8221; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], considering one or more core policy measure(s) in combination with ancillary measures. The ancillary measures need to have one of three rationales. They should either increase the effectiveness of the primary measure, strengthen the acceptance of the primary measure, or facilitate political support for the primary measure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The result is a policy package that is, ideally, as effective, efficient, and accepted as possible in order to cope with a given problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The package mitigates possible unintended effects, increases legitimacy and acceptance of the measures, and/or facilitates their implementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The approach is usually applied to the design of theory-based policy packages in scientific and teaching environments outside the real-world policy arena [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Within this paper, we combined the policy package approach with sustainable pathway identification and policy impact assessment and evaluation.</p>