<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par14">Sustainability has become the keyword for future orientation to safeguarding societies worldwide in harmony with one another and the biosphere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. It is first and foremost a social construct that seeks to improve the quality of life for the world&#8217;s peoples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. A key issue of sustainability is to integrate the three dimensions of economic, environmental and social (including socio-political) wellbeing targets. <italic>Sustainability research</italic> serves these efforts in many ways across the three dimensions. Among others, sustainability research documents the status quo, extrapolates and forecasts future developments, develops coherent sustainability transformation pathways, provides problem-solving metrics, indicators and tool assessments, addresses ethics, conflicting goals and deliberation processes, and helps to develop branch and sector-oriented sustainability specifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. A special focus within sustainability research is on integrated impact assessment and evaluation, and sustainability target orientation. There is, for instance, a vast body of literature on sustainability impact assessment for the field energy transition and/or energy technologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Within the IPPA framework, we tackle several relevant issues of sustainability research, namely the field of sustainable pathway identification and interdisciplinary ex ante impact assessment. The concept of policy packaging should not focus only on the expected direct impact of the suggested measures, but has to foresee unexpected side-effects and unintended interrelationships with other sustainability goals. Interdisciplinary impact assessment from a variety of science disciplines therefore provides a multidimensional assessment picture in the areas of economic, environmental, and social dimensions.</p>