<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par15">The field of <italic>Responsible Innovation (RI) and Responsible Research and Innovation (RRI)</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] address the question of the responsible design and governance of research and innovation processes. The underlying idea is to steer the research and innovation process towards societally beneficial objectives. Science and research on RI/RRI were initially focused on technologies and processes with great societal transformation potential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>] as well as considerable scientific and ethical uncertainties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. A distinctive feature of RRI as understood in large parts of the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] is that steering innovation processes according to societal values and needs is interpreted as a collective responsibility. In this view, there is not only an obligation (for example for technology developers or policymakers) to organize inclusive and participatory processes. There is also an obligation for societal actors to engage in a collective debate that shapes the context for collective decision-making. It is in this regard that IPPA can be described as overlapping with RI/RRI approaches. The overlap is mainly in the dimensions of &#8216;anticipation&#8217; and &#8216;inclusion&#8217;. The &#8216;evaluation&#8217; component of the IPPA approach includes the different policy measures (or innovations in terms of new technology, infrastructure, policy, regulation) which compose the policy packages, and their interactions, in an ex ante impact analysis informed by the results of a preceding interdisciplinary analysis. This corresponds with RI/RRI&#8217;s dimension of &#8216;anticipation&#8217; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. As participative approaches, we used different methods such as stocktaking workshops, a Group Delphi workshop, and a Practice-Science Dialogue.</p>