<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par11">There are different visions and narratives of the EU bioeconomy (Bugge et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>; P&#252;lzl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">2014</xref>; Vivien et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2019</xref>). Importantly, however, they differ in terms of the lobbying and support they receive from stakeholders, which makes it possible to distinguish fewer dominant visions (L&#252;hmann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2020</xref>; Korhonen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2018</xref>; Vivien&#160;et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2019</xref>). The dominant EU bioeconomy visions and discourses are closely associated with industry, private sector, intensified biomass harvest, technological innovations, and production of novel bio-based materials. The EU dominant bioeconomy visions tend to overlook the ecological, social and cultural sustainability dimensions, which remain marginally covered (Ramcilovic-Suominen and P&#252;lzl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2018</xref>). Consequently, the bioeconomy policy as a whole has been framed as technology-driven and biomass-based green growth bioeconomy (Bugge et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>; Levidow et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2019</xref>), elite-driven neoliberalization of nature, which remains silent on the politics of bioeconomy (Birch et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2010</xref>; Levidow et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2019</xref>). Most recently, the policy has also been framed as a novel form of extractivism (Boyer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2019</xref>). These framings and critical analyses expose the gaps between the EU bioeconomy policies and the planetary boundaries and holistic sustainability (Gawel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2019</xref>; Ramcilovic-Suominen and P&#252;lzl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2018</xref>). I next shortly outline the evolution of EU bioeconomy policy and analyse the revised EU bioeconomy strategy (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>).</p>