<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par14">While the changes in the revised EU bioeconomy strategy are a step in the right direction, the revised strategy remains problematic in two major ways: first, the framing of challenges vis-&#224;-vis solutions; second, the ignorance of justice and inequalities. Concerning the former, all socioecological emergencies are approached as challenges or bottlenecks that need to be addressed so that the ultimate goals (green growth, jobs, the EU&#8217;s competitiveness) may be realized, rather than something that needs to be addressed and tackled in its own right. This is evident in the closer analyses of policy measures and actions, where policy actions concerning climate change, biodiversity loss, ecosystem degradation and deforestation are limited to the need for their better understanding, assessing, measuring, and in some cases their <italic>voluntary</italic> addressing. On the contrary, the proposed actions concerning all aspects related to growth and the EU&#8217;s competitiveness (e.g. bio-based industry, innovation, green jobs) are elaborated more concretely and include non-voluntary policy packages. Concerning justice and equality, the revised strategy is devoid of concerns and issues related to climate justice, carbon inequality, and different carbon footprints and resource use between different sectors of society in the EU, let alone EU ecological footprint and global extraction. This is despite the growing scientific and political debates on carbon inequality and climate injustice within the EU (Gore and Alestig <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2020</xref>). The reference to equality in the revised strategy is limited to &#8220;equal exploitation of bioeconomy opportunities across the EU coastal, rural and urban areas&#8221; and &#8220;equitable job creation to ensure European competitiveness&#8221; (EC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>, p.&#160;71). The idea of sufficiency rather than substitution alone and the need for and actions towards reducing production and consumption are also absent. The centrality of growth, the reliance on biomass and the framing of nature as a resource whose function is to serve humans and their economy remain unquestioned in the revised strategy (see also, Eversberg and Holz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2020</xref>; Kurki and Ahola-Launonen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2021</xref>).</p>