<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Cognitive linguistic studies, drawing on both psychology and narrative theory, provide supporting evidence for the benefits of a narrative-based approach, both to the communication of scientific research and to the creation and nurturing of movements for social change. Perhaps most notably in recent years, we have seen the rise of emotive, storytelling documentaries that have succeeded in motivating public and even policy discussions around environmental concerns (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_059" ref-type="bibr">Nolan et&#160;al. 2022</xref>), a phenomenon commonly dubbed the &#8220;Blue Planet effect&#8221; (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_020" ref-type="bibr">Gell 2019</xref>). The powerful role such storytelling can play in creating or encouraging mass social movements and systemic change is well attested in cognitive accounts of narrative persuasion (see <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_024" ref-type="bibr">Green et&#160;al. 2002</xref>). <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_034" ref-type="bibr">Jacobs (2002)</xref>, for instance, argues that narrative structures are instrumental in the forging of collective social identities and also allow members of those collectives to be furnished with a set of stories about a shared past, present, and future. Narratives, in essence, allow people to rationalise and order events in a conceptually manageable chronological sequence and to position themselves and others within that sequence in roles such as &#8220;hero&#8221; or &#8220;villain&#8221;. As Jacobs puts it, the creation of plot &#8220;encourages the public concentration of attention onto specific events, encouraging discussion about the meaning of those events&#8221;, while narrative features such as opposing characters &#8220;serve to dramatize a society&#8217;s deep cultural codes, increasing the likelihood of a continued emotional investment in public life&#8221; (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_034" ref-type="bibr">Jacobs 2002</xref>: 218).</p>