<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Ecolinguists, not to be confused with language ecologists (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_001" ref-type="bibr">Alexander and Stibbe 2014</xref>), contribute to our understanding of environmental discourses by critically analyzing instances of language for its pro- and anti-ecological sentiment. Stibbe, especially, has furthered the field of ecological discourse analysis by drawing on cognitive linguistic concepts of story, framing, and metaphor, as well as critical discourse analysis methods (e.g. <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_017" ref-type="bibr">Fairclough 2001</xref>; see <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_079" ref-type="bibr">Stibbe 2001</xref>), to develop a coherent approach to ecolinguistics: a positive, critical, ecological discourse analysis (see <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_082" ref-type="bibr">Stibbe 2021a</xref>, <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_083" ref-type="bibr">2021b</xref>). Doing ecolinguistics in this sense involves taking an explicit ecological and philosophical stance and then using a range of discourse analytic approaches to determine whether or not a discourse is aligned with that philosophy (see <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_s_003_s_001" ref-type="sec">Section 3.1</xref> for more on <italic toggle="yes">ecosophy</italic>). Ecolinguistics has been used to analyze the language of economics textbooks (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_081" ref-type="bibr">Stibbe 2020</xref>, <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_083" ref-type="bibr">2021b</xref>), haiku poetry (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_080" ref-type="bibr">Stibbe 2007</xref>, <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_083" ref-type="bibr">2021b</xref>), computer games (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_067" ref-type="bibr">Poole and Spangler 2020</xref>), road users (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_012" ref-type="bibr">Caimotto 2020</xref>), environmental debates (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_065" ref-type="bibr">Poole 2018</xref>), climate change news stories (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_060" ref-type="bibr">Norton and Hulme 2019</xref>), news reports (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_113" ref-type="bibr">Cheng and He 2021</xref>), and tourism texts (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_064" ref-type="bibr">Ponton 2022</xref>), to name a handful of recent examples. To our knowledge, it has not yet been used to analyze the language of plastics and plastic packaging, nor has it been used in industry-facing research, e.g. on consumer messaging strategies.</p>