<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Increasingly, ecolinguistics is also being employed in conjunction with corpus linguistic methods, a survey of which can be found in <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_066" ref-type="bibr">Poole (2022)</xref>, the first book-length treatment of corpus-assisted ecolinguistics. Doing linguistics with a <italic toggle="yes">corpus</italic>&#160;&#8211; literally, a &#8220;body&#8221; of text&#160;&#8211; simply means conducting linguistic analysis on a very large, computer-readable text or set of texts and, consequently, employing computational methods in processing and analyzing said text(s). The fact that a corpus can be constructed from any of a wide range of texts (or indeed other modalities), and that there is no prescribed method for doing corpus analysis, means that corpus methods can be applied to a wide range of language data and research questions. Corpus-assisted discourse analysis, for instance, is now commonplace and has been used to explore a host of societal and environmental issues, from media representations of mental health (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_032" ref-type="bibr">Hunt and Brookes 2020</xref>), Islam (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_008" ref-type="bibr">Baker et&#160;al. 2013</xref>), and feminism (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_035" ref-type="bibr">Jaworska and Krishnamurthy 2012</xref>), to discourses of nonhuman animals (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_075" ref-type="bibr">Sealey and Charles 2013</xref>), the environment (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_046" ref-type="bibr">Lischinsky 2015</xref>), and climate change (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_027" ref-type="bibr">Grundmann and Krishnamurthy 2010</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_037" ref-type="bibr">Koteyko et&#160;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_114" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Huang 2022</xref>), amongst many others. When it comes to corpus studies on plastic packaging and related themes, we are aware of just two: <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_056" ref-type="bibr">Napolitano (2018)</xref>, a corpus-assisted analysis of media discourse around the plastic bag ban in Australia; and <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_058" ref-type="bibr">Niceforo (2021)</xref>, a corpus-assisted ecolinguistic discourse analysis of two public-facing reports on plastic pollution.</p>