<p>This is a revolutionary moment whose archetypal parameters are prescribed in the <italic toggle="yes">I Ching</italic> in Hexagram 49, &#8216;Revolution (Molting)&#8217;; a time of &#8216;extremely grave matters&#8217;. A revolution &#8216;should be undertaken only under stress of direst necessity, when there is no other way out&#8217;. Real leadership is needed &#8216;by someone quite free of selfish aims&#8217; and then only when the time is ripe (Wilhelm&#160;<xref rid="joap12675-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">1967</xref>, pp. 189&#8208;90). Even the conservative British newspaper, the <italic toggle="yes">Financial Times</italic>, stated in an editorial about the pandemic on 4 April 2020:
<disp-quote content-type="quotation" id="joap12675-blkfxd-0002"><p>The great test all countries will soon face is whether current feelings of common purpose will shape society after the crisis &#8230;.</p><p>Radical reforms &#8211; reversing the prevailing policy direction of the last four decades &#8211; will need to be put on the table. Governments will have to accept a more active role in the economy. They must see public services as investments rather than liabilities, and look for ways to make labour markets less insecure. Redistribution will again be on the agenda; the privileges of the elderly and wealthy in question. Policies until recently considered eccentric, such as basic income and wealth taxes, will have to be in the mix.</p><attrib>(<italic toggle="yes">Financial Times</italic>&#160;<xref rid="joap12675-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>)</attrib></disp-quote>These sentiments were echoed on 5 April 2020 in a National Public Radio interview with historian Yuval Noah Harari, author of <italic toggle="yes">Sapiens &#8211; A Brief History of Humankind</italic>. Harari emphasized the rare opportunities for major change emerging from the extreme fluidity of the moment when old, solid forms could be quickly overturned. Experimentation is occurring with things that were previously considered to be crazy, like universal basic income and improved safety nets. Many choices are on the table with no predictable outcomes. Like any revolution, things could turn out badly in the form of authoritarianism and mass surveillance for example (Garcia&#8208;Navarro&#160;<xref rid="joap12675-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Things will solidify quickly once this is over in 2021, what in biology is called punctuated evolution &#8211; rapid major change followed by a plateau of indeterminate length of existence of the new form.</p>