<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par21">Many Nigerians depend on daily income, thus the sudden restriction of movement and grinding halt to economic activities created a shock to many. With a poorly coordinated social support system, it was difficult for many families during this period. This gap also extends to the educational system with many from the low-income bracket not able to send their children to private schools witnessing little or no learning for their wards. Many higher education institutions were ill-prepared and still trying to cope with the fallout of the pandemic&#8212;creating a knock-on effect on the welfare of the staff and students. This has a negative implication for achievement gaps and most importantly for social mobility. The lack of access or poor access to learning and education for some children and young people during this period will surely have implications beyond this COVID-19 pandemic. Whilst some states instituted radio and TV programmes to bridge the gap, the pandemic showcased the glaring disparities in education access. Some of those earning monthly incomes witnessed a reduction in salary, whilst some lost their jobs, due to employers&#8217; inability to pay as there were no economic activities to generate the necessary revenues to pay them. With the loss of jobs for many, the lack of employment insurance is worth considering as a measure to address the future downturn in labour market participation. Similar challenges are slowly emanating from climate change and global warming, which are inducing disasters, thus bringing up questions on.<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par22">How are we planning to ensure people losing their livelihoods to climate change and global warming are not left behind?</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par23">How do we mitigate the impact of climate change on education and prevent it from undermining education access?</p></list-item></list></p>