<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par26">Interpersonal violence is consistently seen to rise with temperature and, occasionally, low rainfall in a variety of circumstances (Hsiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2013</xref>; Miguel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2015</xref>). This response manifests in overt violence, such as retaliation in sports (Larrick et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>), violent crimes like rape, murder, robbery, and assault (Jacob et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2007</xref>; Ranson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2014</xref>), as well as low-level aggression like horn honking (Kenrick and MacFarlane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1986</xref>), antisocial behaviour towards service employees (Kolb et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2012</xref>), and the use of profanity on social media (Baylis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2015</xref>). The effect of temperature is remarkably linear with almost no delay, indicating that a physiological mechanism may be responsible for it (Morrison et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>; Ray et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2011</xref>; Seo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2008</xref>). Rainfall&#8217;s effects on interpersonal violence are predominantly observed in some underdeveloped agricultural environments, such as rural Tanzania (Miguel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2015</xref>) and India (Iyer and Topalova <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2014</xref>; Morrison et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>; Sekhri and Storeygard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2012</xref>) and Fulani-herdsman crisis in Nigeria 2020 (Folami and Folami <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2013</xref>) raising the possibility that harm to agricultural production may operate as a mediating factor. Furthermore, air pollution and cardiovascular illness and death, food and waterborne disease, food security, mental health, and stress-related impacts are some of the other challenges likely to be aggravated by climate change. Thus, we need to learn from the current pandemic and build back better in Nigeria. As climate change could lead to an increased in the level of socio-economic stress for everyone, we need to build resilience across the various facet of society.</p>