<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">A total of 581 students were enrolled in the first semester and a total of 588 students in the second semester. In our analysis, we only included responses from students who completed both the premodule and postmodule surveys and answered validation questions correctly. With these criteria, we had a 21% response rate (<italic>n</italic>&#160;=&#160;120) in the 2017 semester and a 45% response rate (<italic>n</italic>&#160;=&#160;263) in the 2018 semester. Participants were predominately white (72% in 2017, 59% in 2018), women (78% in both semesters), first or second year undergraduates (83% in 2017, 80% in 2018), and from a household with an annual income above $100,000 (50% in 2017, 47% in 2018). In 2017, students in the course had 1.0 previous Biology credit taken at the university, on average: 384 of the 581 students had not taken any previous Biology credits at the university; 96 had taken 4.0 previous Biology credits. In 2018, the average was 1.8 credits: 350 of the 588 students had not taken any previous Biology credits at the university; 203 students had taken 4.0 previous Biology credits. Additional participant demographic data from both semesters are given in Table <xref rid="ece35736-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>. For survey questions that were identical in both semesters, data from these semesters were combined for visualization and analyses. Because some questions were given in both semesters but others only in 2017, the figures indicate the number of respondents; questions with approximately 380 respondents were those given in both semesters. Data were analyzed using R v. 3.5.2. For many questions, we report only summary statistics (e.g., the percent of students who selected a particular response category); for some questions, we also used proportion tests to compare the change in the proportion of students choosing a particular response at the beginning of the semester versus the end of the semester. Data and code are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3334292">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3334292</ext-link>.</p>