<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0160">In this article, we argue that conflating CM and MR does not serve the variety of people affected by climate-induced risks and this plays into the lack of policy frameworks, governance mechanisms, and institutional pathways to address both issues. Individuals and communities trapped or on the move due to climate impacts face different challenges and require different solution-sets and resources. The biggest challenges with CM are the lack of recognition of CDPs and their associated rights under national and international law; the inadequate support for <italic>in situ</italic> adaptation; and the fragmentation of climate change policy regimes, development, migration, and humanitarian responses. With regards to MR, current challenges include inadequate consultation with affected communities; inequity in decision making; contestations over land and financing; elite capture and enclosure of land; and problems with cultural integration with receiving communities. A range of international documents such as The Peninsula Principles on Climate Displacements within States (<xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Displacement Solutions, 2013</xref>) and The UN Global Compact for Safe, Orderly and Regular Migration (<xref rid="b0620" ref-type="bibr">United Nations, 2018</xref>) offer recommendations on the roles, rights, and obligations of communities, aid agencies, and states with respect to relocation and migration, but these documents are not legally binding. A transformative approach encompassing radical shifts in discourse and practice is therefore required in how we address both issues. This shift must aim to create more options for justice and legal tools that acknowledge, enable, and support affected communities in <italic>realizing their goals</italic> for safety and access to livelihoods. It also means states have to create dedicated institutions, guidelines, trainings, pathways, and financing to address the needs of frontline communities while safeguarding their rights to self-determination.</p>