<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">There is no uniform definition of an extreme heat event. Diverse local climates make a single heat definition or threshold unfavorable because people who live in hotter climates have different health responses to equivalent levels of heat exposure as their counterparts in cooler climates [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0240841.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0240841.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Currently the National Weather Service alerts the public of a heat hazard when the heat index is greater than 105&#8457; for a minimum of two consecutive days [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The heat index is a measurement of the apparent temperature one would feel in the shade given the amplifying effects of humidity; it is an absolute metric that does not consider relative climatology and does not capture the fact that health impacts from different doses of heat vary among communities [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0240841.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0240841.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0240841.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The heat index is not to be confused with a vulnerability index, which is a metric that integrates indicators of vulnerability. To address the shortcomings of the heat index, many studies also measure extreme heat using a heat wave definition that spans multiple days and uses a relative, locally defined temperature threshold. However, many heat index and heat wave definitions employ extreme heat thresholds above temperatures where heat-related health impacts begin, potentially missing harmful events [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0240841.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0240841.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This study therefore includes metrics that measure absolute and relative extreme heat at thresholds shown to be relevant to heat-health risk.</p>