<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par9">Literature was selected based on an exploratory approach, combining the use of scholarly database searches (e.g. Scopus and Google Scholar) with a consultation process with different key stakeholders and informants.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref> The latter involved a total of five workshops and continuous communication with participants through the participatory development of a web-based communication platform and database in the field between 2017 and 2019.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn3">3</xref> This resulted in the identification of a total of 100 publications for analysis (cf. &#8220;<xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec">Relational Approaches to Ontology</xref>&#8221;, &#8220;<xref rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec">Relational Approaches to Epistemology</xref>&#8221; and &#8220;<xref rid="Sec5" ref-type="sec">Relational Approaches to Ethics</xref>&#8221;). The categorization of the identified papers to the three categories (ontology, epistemology and ethics) was based on the following definition of these terms and their relevance for sustainability:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(A)</label><p id="Par12"><italic>Ontologies</italic> describe the &#8220;assumptions (which may be implicit or explicit) about what kinds of things do or can exist in [reality], and what might be their conditions of existence, relations of dependency, and so on&#8221; (Scott and Marshall <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2009</xref>, p. 531).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(B)</label><p id="Par13"><italic>Epistemologies</italic> describe how we come to know the world. They define the criteria, standards, and methods for understanding reality (Steup <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2018</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(C)</label><p id="Par14"><italic>Ethics</italic> describes &#8220;what is morally good and bad and morally right and wrong&#8221; (Singer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2019</xref>, para. 1). It includes cultural values, morals, and norms shaped by social and political life.</p></list-item></list></p>