<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">When speaking about the influence of emotions on pro-environmental behavior, we can distinguish between (1) emotions that are currently experienced, (2) emotions that people believe their actions will elicit (anticipated emotions), and (3) emotions that are generalized due to multiple repetitions. <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Venhoeven et al. (2013)</xref> also address the emotions that pro-environmental behavior elicits, although their findings are not relevant to this study. The three aforementioned emotion groups cause different effects. First, experimentally induced current emotions, e.g., by confronting participants with environmental damages to elicit guilt (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Reese and Jacob, 2015</xref>), affected the pro-environmental intention or behavior of these individuals. However, these effects were found to be rather small, vary individually, and not remain stable over a period of time (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Landmann, 2020</xref>, p. 10). Second, anticipated emotions can motivate people to engage in pro-environmental behavior as they either believe it will make them experience pleasure (<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Rezvani et al., 2017</xref>) or prevent them from experiencing displeasure (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Onwezen et al., 2013</xref>). Third, according to the model of affect generalization (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Paolini et al., 2016</xref>), emotional episodes can generalize when experienced sufficiently often or with high intensity. In the context of pro-environmental behavior, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Landmann (2020)</xref> states that emotions only affect behavioral intentions if they are generalized. In line with the model of affect generalization, the emotions used in this work are not used as an emotional episode (currently experienced or anticipated), but rather as an affective attitude, that is, the proneness to feel these emotions.</p>