<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><italic>Guilt</italic> and <italic>shame</italic> due to environmental damage were consistently found to influence pro-environmental intention and behavior (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Carrus et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson and Branscombe, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Gausel and Brown, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Harth et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Rees et al., 2014</xref>). When individuals are highly perpetrator- or beneficiary sensitive, they are also prone to feel guilty (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Montada et al., 1986</xref>). Guilt results from regretting a specific behavior afterward but does not affect one&#8217;s self-identity. Shame, however, affects one&#8217;s self-identity as it goes along with a feeling of worthlessness and powerlessness (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Tangney, 1995</xref>). Therefore, guilt tends to be tied to a specific behavior (similar to authentic pride), whereas shame is linked to self-identity (similar to hubristic pride). <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Rees et al. (2014)</xref> found that both emotions predicted positive behavioral intentions, but it was shame and not guilt that transformed the intention into actual behavior. However, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Carrus et al. (2008)</xref> showed that anticipated guilt strongly affected an individual&#8217;s desire to use public transportation and engage in household recycling. The relationship between negative anticipated emotions and the pro-environmental intention was even stronger than that between attitudes and pro-environmental intention. Most research on emotions in pro-environmental behavior focused on guilt and pride. In direct comparison, pride and guilt were both significantly related to pro-environmental behavior and intention to engage in pro-environmental behavior. <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Shipley and van Riper (2022)</xref> found that anticipated pride and guilt had equal effects on pro-environmental behavior, but that experienced guilt had stronger effects on pro-environmental behavior than experienced pride. However, negative emotions must be dealt with consciously, as they result in aversive action tendencies. This is evident in the case of cognitive dissonance (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Festinger, 1957</xref>). According to the theory of cognitive dissonance, emotional stress occurs when actions and beliefs are inconsistent. This emotional stress is highly uncomfortable and needs to be resolved. Based on Festinger&#8217;s theory, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bandura (2007</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2016)</xref> developed the concept of <italic>moral disengagement</italic>. Moral disengagement can be seen as a cognitive restructuring of a situation to justify inaction or subjectively wrong action (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bandura et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bandura, 2007</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and does not only occur in individuals, but also in groups of individuals when harmful behavior is collectively morally justified (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Bandura, 2002</xref>). These justification mechanisms include denial and diffusion of responsibility. Euphemistic labeling, advantageous comparison, in addition to minimizing, ignoring, or misconstruing the consequences are also forms of moral disengagement. Engaging in these strategies can be prevented by a high degree of moral self-regulation, that allows individuals to remain consistent with their standards of justice. Such a higher moral self-regulation and, hence, less moral disengagement, was found in perpetrator and beneficiary sensitive individuals in a longitudinal study by <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Maltese and Baumert (2016)</xref>. <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bandura (2007)</xref> already theorized how moral disengagement selectively contributes to increasing environmental damage. These mechanisms prevent individuals from engaging in pro-environmental behavior, even if they have already recognized the injustice of their behavior. Some of the mechanisms were investigated in a qualitative study (<xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Stoll-Kleemann and O&#8217;Riordan, 2020</xref>) while the association of moral disengagement with high carbon behavior was found in a quantitative study (<xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Stoll-Kleemann et al., 2022b</xref>). It is assumed that moral disengagement in high carbon behavior correlates positively with victim sensitivity, as both tendencies are self-serving and prevent an individual from taking responsibility for the environment. Therefore, moral disengagement is also assumed to correlate negatively with pro-environmental intention and behavior.</p>