<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The latest report by the <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [IPCC] (2022)</xref> suggests that it is not only natural conditions that determine who is most affected by the climate crisis, but rather the living conditions of the individuals. Limited economic resources, suffering from inequality, enduring political instabilities and wars, or limited access to basic resources such as clean water are only a few examples of disadvantages faced by individuals due to climate change. Ultimately, human rights, such as the right to life, health, and subsistence are endangered by the consequences of climate-damaging behavior, i.e., behavior that emits a lot of greenhouse gases and, therefore, forces climate change. Due to unequally distributed resources (e.g., money, political power), climate change disproportionally affects the Global South, younger generations, women, and people with low income more intensely than the Global North, older generations, men, and people with high income (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [IPCC], 2022</xref>). In all of these cases, the same disproportion can be found, namely that the individuals who are least responsible for climate change are more affected by its consequences than those most responsible for it. For example, from 1990 to 2015, the global wealthiest 10% were responsible for 46% of emission growth whereas the global poorest 50% were responsible for only 6% of the total emission growth (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Kartha et al., 2020</xref>). As a consequence, discussions concerning climate change comprise ethical and moral issues regarding justice (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Caney, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Boom et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">De Smet et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alves and Mariano, 2018</xref>). Therefore, the term <italic>climate justice</italic> incorporates various justice principles in the domain of climate change. These include <italic>distributive justice</italic>, which considers the allocation of costs and benefits among people, <italic>procedural justice</italic>, which points out who can participate in decision-making processes, and <italic>recognition</italic>, which involves respectful and appropriate &#8220;consideration of diverse cultures and perspectives&#8221; (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [IPCC], 2022</xref>, p. 9).</p>