<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Individuals react with different intensity to injustices they have suffered themselves (as victims), to injustices they perceive in everyday situations (as observers), to injustices from which they passively benefit (as beneficiaries), and to injustices they have committed themselves (as perpetrators; <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Montada and Maes, 2016</xref>). Although justice sensitivity is inherent to all four perspectives, they differ in several ways. On the one hand, a high justice sensitivity as an observer, beneficiary, or perpetrator reflects the desire for justice for others and a feeling of social responsibility. On the other hand, a high score in justice sensitivity as a victim reflects a desire for justice for oneself (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Preiser and Beierlein, 2017</xref>). More precisely, individuals who score highly in perpetrator or beneficiary sensitivity rather experience prosocial concerns (e.g., existential guilt, social responsibility, or solidarity with the disadvantaged; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Gollwitzer et al., 2005</xref>). Observer sensitives were found to feel empathy and, as a result, take responsibility (<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Schmitt et al., 2005</xref>). Those who perceive injustice from the perspective of the beneficiary, observer, or perpetrator are more likely to feel responsible (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Ehrhardt-Madapathi et al., 2018</xref>). A greater sense of responsibility, in turn, is a promising predictor to engage in pro-environmental behavior (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Kollmuss and Agyeman, 2002</xref>). As already indicated, victim sensitivity relates differently and in part contrarily to the other three perspectives. In terms of behavioral outcomes, victim sensitivity was positively related to delinquent behavior (e.g., fare or tax evasion; <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Preiser and Beierlein, 2017</xref>). Victim sensitives are afraid of being disadvantaged and behave in anticipation of such an injustice. Therefore, they easily abandon their moral standards (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Gollwitzer et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Schmitt et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">M&#252;nscher, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Preiser and Beierlein, 2017</xref>), are rather jealous, neurotic, socially mistrusting, and paranoid (<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Schmitt et al., 2005</xref>) and fear the exploitation of their investments (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Rothmund et al., 2014</xref>). To summarize, we can distinguish three pro-social sensitivities (perpetrator, beneficiary, and observer) from one pro-self sensitivity (victim). We assume that the three pro-social sensitivities are positively associated whereas the pro-self sensitivity is negatively associated with pro-environmental intention and behavior.</p>