<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par25">Nevertheless, from the very beginning, China approached climate change through climate equity, constructed climate change as a North-South issue and connected to global historical inequality, regarded international climate negotiations as a North-South struggle, and discursively differentiated the South from the North in negotiations (Conrad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>; Harris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2013</xref>). Since the 1990s, China&#8217;s top leaders like the then Premier Li Peng (1992) and Wen Jiabao (2007) persistently represented China as a part of the developing world and stressed that the developing South was a &#8216;poor&#8217; and &#8216;innocent victim&#8217; of climate change and vulnerable to its adverse impacts while the North has the main historical responsibility to the climate change problem. Furthermore, besides stressing the equity principle through highlighting its own lower per capita emissions (Wen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2007</xref>), China framed the North&#8217;s emissions as &#8216;luxury emissions&#8217; while recognising the emissions of the South as &#8216;survival/development emissions&#8217; (ENB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1997</xref>: 9; Wen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2007</xref>). This argument is compatible with Henry Shue&#8217;s conceptions of climate justice regarding emissions (Shue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">1993</xref>). China repeatedly stressed that economic development and poverty eradication were &#8216;top priorities&#8217; of developing countries and the international efforts to fight climate change &#8216;should promote, not block, the economic development and poverty eradication&#8217; (Li <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1992</xref>; Wen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2007</xref>). Shouldering climate responsibility was actually seen by China and other developing countries as a heavy burden that would impact their economic development (Ong <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2012</xref>). China continued to keep and promote the CBDR principle at the forefront of international climate debates (Stalley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2013</xref>). China&#8217;s discursive constructions of climate change were widely shared by developing countries (Stalley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2013</xref>). In particular, the G77&#8212;a broad coalition of developing nations including many Asian countries&#8212;stood with China, supported those constructions and regarded China as the leader of the G77/China group (Kasa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2008</xref>). China defended the shared developing country identity of the developing world and maintained climate change as a marginal issue on its agenda.</p>