<notes xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><title>Notes on contributors</title><p><italic><bold>Cathy Rozel Farnworth</bold></italic> holds a PhD from the Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences and has extensive gender research and development experience in sub-Saharan Africa, Central/West/North Africa and South and South-East Asia. Her interests include climate change adaptation and mitigation, pro-poor gender-equitable value chain development, food and nutrition security, empowerment, participatory research methodologies, household methodologies, quality of life and agricultural innovation. She is co-author of <italic>Creating Food Futures: Ethics, Trade and the Environment</italic> (Ashgate 2012) and <italic>Participatory Plant Breeding and Gender Analysis</italic> (CIAT 2003).</p><p><italic><bold>Tahseen Jafry</bold></italic> is qualified as an engineer and a social scientist. She has research and development experience in sub-Saharan Africa, Asia and the Small Island States. An experienced lecturer in postgraduate and undergraduate courses on environmental management, sustainability and climate justice, she supervises theses to doctorate level. Jafry&#8217;s current research interests include the justice and equity aspects of climate change, gender and poverty targeting, the management of natural resources and the geo-politics of climate justice discourse.</p><p><italic><bold>Siddiqur Rahman</bold></italic> holds a PhD in Anthropology from the American University in Washington DC and has 22 years of research and teaching experience in the field of anthropology with a focus on contemporary development issues in Bangladesh. His research addresses the broader aspects of development &#8211; its global challenges and successes. Rahman holds a permanent teaching position as a professor of Anthropology at Jahangirnagar University (JU), Bangladesh.</p><p><italic><bold>Lone B. Badstue</bold></italic> is a rural development sociologist with focus on gender and social heterogeneity in relation to agriculture and natural resources management. As global Research Theme Leader for Gender and Social Inclusion at the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Centre (CIMMYT), she also leads the GENNOVATE research initiative on Gender Norms, Agency and Innovation in Agriculture in 26 countries. Her research interests include actor-oriented approaches, agricultural innovation processes, seed systems and farmer decision making.</p></notes>