<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Although this study focused on extreme heat, there are takeaways relevant to other hazards. First, across hazards, relying on a single quantitative vulnerability index without complementary analyses to guide adaptation decisions is likely insufficient. We demonstrated this finding for heat, but previous work has come to similar conclusions for sea level rise [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], flooding [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], and wildfires [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. A balance of data sources and methods for assessing vulnerability is needed to capture the richness and nuances across communities. Second, exploring the extent to which equity-oriented adaptations are needed for other hazards could be valuable. In this study, we found that increases in extreme heat under climate change will significantly impact vulnerable communities in California (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0240841.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Thus, there are clear opportunities with extreme heat for implementing solutions for those most in need and for thereby addressing environmental injustices. Recent work has shown that in inland communities, but not coastal communities, &#8220;economically disadvantaged&#8221; groups are more often found in flood zones than their wealthier counterparts [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Future research could explore whether such a relationship exists for other hazards such as wildfire. Third, addressing pollution justice concerns may not be equivalent to equitable adaptation to climate hazards. In this work we found that using CES, an index that was developed to consider cumulative pollution burden in addition to more traditional indicators of social vulnerability, did not result in equal prioritization of communities that will likely be at the front line of heat-related impacts in a changing climate (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0240841.g002">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0240841.g004">4</xref>). Nevertheless, the drivers of inequities in pollution exposure are likely linked to inequities in resource access. Previous work demonstrated that historic zoning practices such as redlining have been associated with increased urban heat island effect and pollution [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Understanding this link between pollution burden, elevated exposure, and equitable adaptation is critical across hazards.</p>