<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par2">The Mediterranean Basin constitutes a geographic and climatic unit that spans three continents and is especially sensitive to the adverse effects of climate change. The increase in the average surface temperature of this region is above the observed global increase, and it has already exceeded 1.4&#160;&#176;C with respect to the pre-industrial period temperature (1880&#8211;1899) (Medecc Network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2019</xref>). Likewise, heat waves are more frequent, severely affecting urban areas, and drought intensity and frequency are also increasing, causing water availability problems in some regions (Cramer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2018</xref>; Lange <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2019</xref>). The socioeconomic impacts of climate stress have been described in a wide variety of areas. Recent studies have shown severe impacts on crop production and a decreasing wheat yield (Danzi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2019</xref>). Rises in sea levels will alter the shape of coasts, seriously affecting coastal low-areas such as deltas and impacting strategic economic sectors (Ciscar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>; L&#243;pez-D&#243;riga and Jim&#233;nez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>). Predictions indicate that even achieving the temperature goals of the Paris Agreement, the risk of drought is likely to increase, and precipitations and surface runoffs are likely to decrease (IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2018a</xref>). These risks are significantly less in the 1.5&#160;&#176;C global scenario. This scenario would allow ecosystems to stay within the variability observed during the Holocene. In scenarios leading to 2&#160;&#176;C or more warming, Mediterranean terrestrial ecosystems would experience unprecedented changes never seen in the Holocene (Guiot and Cramer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2016</xref>).</p>