<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para350">The COVID-19 pandemic shows how zoonotic spillover events can quickly become a costly global problem and affect an immense breadth of health, social, economic, and environmental factors. Novel approaches to addressing drivers of zoonotic disease emergence through policy reform, regulation, fiscal measures, and more, will be enhanced by coordination, cooperation, and collaboration across international and regional borders, as well as disciplinary and sectoral boundaries.<xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>, <xref rid="bib126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref> To achieve this, there is a pressing need for more effective communication among all relevant actors across fields, including medical and public health scientists, practitioners and officials, Indigenous knowledge holders, conservation scientists and practitioners, veterinarians, zoologists, ecologists, social scientists, economists, policy makers, governmental authorities, non-governmental organisations, research bodies, and multiple other stakeholders and actors.<xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>, <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>, <xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>, <xref rid="bib127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>, <xref rid="bib128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref> Considering the inter-related nature of biodiversity, environmental health, and human health, it is appropriate that strategies to prevent the exacerbation of zoonosis drivers take a One Health approach.<xref rid="bib113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>, <xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref> This integrative approach, which has been called for by many in light of the COVID-19 pandemic,<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="bib129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref> acknowledges the tight relationship between the health of our planet and the health of humans. It works to address complex challenges faced in the environmental and global health spheres to achieve mutually beneficial, sustainable outcomes.<xref rid="bib113" ref-type="bibr"><sup>113</sup></xref> Through this approach, major issues such as land-use change, wildlife trade, intensive livestock production, and climate change are addressed as public health and economic challenges, including environmental issues. Strategies to comprehensively address these issues involve transdisciplinary collaboration and actions.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref>
</p>