<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">For each commune, we considered potential confounders, such as:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Temperature and humidity: The average annual air temperature and relative humidity from 1980&#8211;2010 were obtained from ARClim, which is an open-source meteorological dataset [<xref rid="B30-ijerph-18-07409" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. This dataset was chosen due to its official endorsement given by the Chilean Ministry of Environment, and because its spatial resolution (5 &#215; 5 km) provides data for all 188 communes.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Elderly index: Proportion of the elderly population (65 years old or more) for 2020 based on projections of the 2017 Census.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Self-report of health: Proportion of the population that have declared absence of chronic or acute diseases, based on the National Socioeconomic Characterization Survey [<xref rid="B31-ijerph-18-07409" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The reported illnesses include hypertension, diabetes, myocardial infarction, stroke, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, asthma, thyroid disease, cancer, and lupus.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Percentage of houses with moderate overcrowding: Number of houses with moderate overcrowding out of the total number of houses in each commune. The overcrowding corresponds to the ratio of the number of people to the number of bedrooms. Moderate overcrowding is defined as 2.5 to 4.9 people per bedroom [<xref rid="B32-ijerph-18-07409" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Percentage of houses built before 2000: Number of houses built before 2000 out of each commune&#8217;s total number of houses. Homes built before 2000 were not subject to the thermal standard considered in the first stage of regulations associated with thermal insulation of housing [<xref rid="B32-ijerph-18-07409" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Mobility index: Sum of the internal and external mobility indexes. The internal index is a measure of the number of trips that occur within a commune, whereas the latter corresponds to the number of trips made outside of the commune. Both indexes were summed and normalized by the population of the administrative unit [<xref rid="B33-ijerph-18-07409" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p></list-item></list></p>