<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In addition to their advocacy efforts, young people have also been applying a human rights and public health lens in their climate litigation efforts against national governments. South African youth have brought forth litigation to uphold their Constitutional rights to live in an environment that is not harmful to their health and one that protects future generations from pollution and ecological degradation, in light of heatwaves, droughts, poor sanitation, and water access, which have prevented adolescents to access and attend school [<xref rid="B57-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. In 2019, 16 children filed a claim against the governments of Argentina, Brazil, France, Germany, and Turkey for failing to rapidly reduce their greenhouse gas emissions, and therefore violating children&#8217;s rights to life, health, and the prioritization of the child&#8217;s best interest under the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child [<xref rid="B58-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In Colombia, the Supreme Court of Justice ruled in favor of 25 children and youth who argued that the deforestation of the Amazon rainforest is threatening their right to a healthy environment, life, and risking future generations [<xref rid="B59-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. With this historic ruling, the government was ordered to create an &#8220;intergenerational pact for the life of the Colombian Amazon&#8221; with the engagement of the plaintiffs, and municipalities were ordered to develop action plans to reduce deforestation [<xref rid="B59-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Six Portuguese youth have also filed a lawsuit against 33 European countries with the European Court of Human Rights (ECHR) [<xref rid="B60-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. With this first climate lawsuit filed with the ECHR, youth applicants contended that climate change is threatening their right to life, private and family lives, and right not to be discriminated against, among others. The lawsuit stressed the severe impact climate change is having on their physical and mental health, requiring European governments to implement more ambitious emission reductions and dramatically reduce fossil fuel exports [<xref rid="B60-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Youth-led lawsuits and the mobilization of grassroots climate activism have used arguments for the security of good health and rights to a healthy and sustainable life as the entry point for their action. These cases demonstrate how youth have vouched for the integration of public health and human rights interventions to climate change through legal and policy channels, to create policy pathways that are justice oriented and centered most around communities on the margins.</p>