<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par29">Degrowth builds on critiquing growth-oriented paradigms, including green growth, green economy and sustainable development (D&#8217;Alisa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>; Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>). Degrowth scholars argue that such frameworks and paradigms have been co-opted and reoriented from their original ideas, towards serving economic growth at the cost of nature or environment, society and cultures (D&#8217;Alisa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>). An important feature with direct implications for the policies such as the EU bioeconomy is the degrowth&#8217;s focus on sufficiency (rather than substitution, for example) and affinity for voluntarily limiting our consumption and accumulation (Kallis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2013</xref>). Degrowth&#8217;s focus on global environmental justice, care and reciprocity, which are increasingly articulated in the literature through the feminist and decolonial perspectives on degrowth (Dengler and Seebacher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2019</xref>; Mehta and Harcourt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2021</xref>; Nirmal and Roscheleau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR901">2019</xref>; Singh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2019</xref>), is also vital to EU bioeconomy. Kallis et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>) outline a number of strategies which they argue offer alternatives to the current capitalist extractivist economy. These strategies include carbon and wealth taxes, debt cancelation of the former colonies and GDP-poorer countries, redistribution of economic and political power across countries and regions of the world and scaling down environmentally polluting sectors and industries while promoting locally sourced production and consumption economies. While these measures are not exhaustive, especially when it comes to onto-epistemological aspects and decolonial justice, they hold tremendous potential for informing and inspiring EU bioeconomy policy to embrace socially and ecologically just approaches in building European bio-based societies.</p>