<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par22">In this study, a two-tier approach was adopted for lake level frequency analysis (FFA) under stationary and non-stationary conditions (SFA &amp; NFA). The first part was the identification of the best probability distribution functions (pdf). The AMS and PDS series fitted candidate pdfs of members from the extreme value distributions (EVD) family that are among those commonly applied in hydrological studies (Debele et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2017</xref>), namely Gumbel, generalized extreme value (GEV), generalized Pareto (GPA), exponential (Exp), and Pearson type 3 (PP3). There are many parameter fitting methods for probability distributions for hydrological assessments, as summarized by Singh (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">1998</xref>). In this study, the performances of maximum likelihood estimation (MLE), generalized maximum likelihood estimation (GMLE), Bayesian (through Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulations), and L-moments (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) on the candidate distributions were tested and compared with select the best. Each of these methods has their own merits and demerits and the reliability often depends on the length of the available record (Martins and Stedinger <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2000</xref>). A total of 15 different models based on the candidate distributions, series (AMS and POT), and parameter fitting methods were assessed under SFA, from which the best approach was selected.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>EVD and the parameter fitting methods for SFFA and NFFA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Series</th><th>EVD</th><th>Parameter fitting methods</th><th>Covariates</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>AMS</td><td>Gumbel, GEV</td><td>ML, GMLE, Bayesian, L-moments</td><td>None</td></tr><tr><td>PDS</td><td>GP</td><td>ML, GMLE, Bayesian, L-moments</td><td>None</td></tr><tr><td>PDS</td><td>PP</td><td>ML, GMLE, Bayesian</td><td>None</td></tr><tr><td>PDS</td><td>Exponential</td><td>ML, GMLE</td><td>None</td></tr><tr><td>AMS</td><td>Gumbel, GEV</td><td>ML, GMLE, Bayesian, L-moments</td><td>Rainfall, discharge, evaporation, SOI &amp; IOD</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>