<p>For starters, the killing occurred on 25 May 2020 in broad daylight on the streets of a major American city and was witnessed by several bystanders. This did not happen in the cover of darkness between police and a terrorized black man, nor filmed only by a policeman or police car dashcams. It was not a sudden and violent death from gunshot but a slow and deliberate killing of another human being as others pleaded for his life. It did not involve the struggle between a young black jogger and an armed white man, as in the Ahmaud Arbery murder on 23 February 2020 (USdayNEWS&#160;<xref rid="joap12675-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>); or the shoot&#8208;out in the murder of Breonna Taylor on 13 March 2020 (Duvall&#160;<xref rid="joap12675-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>); nor the murder of a crazed teen marching down a Chicago street threatening police with a knife as in the Laquan McDonald killing in 2014 (Chicago Police Department/<italic toggle="yes">The Guardian</italic> 2015). Floyd was handcuffed behind his back, lying face&#8208;down with a policeman&#8217;s knee on his neck while two other officers helped hold him down and a fourth officer kept bystanders at bay. We looked directly into the calm face of officer Derek Chauvin as he kept his knee on Floyd&#8217;s neck for eight minutes and forty&#8208;six seconds, aghast to see a human being so utterly unmoved by the cries of a helpless man gasping for breath, repeatedly saying &#8216;I can&#8217;t breathe&#8217; and finally crying out for his mother, who had died two years prior (YouTube&#160;<xref rid="joap12675-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The whole world was soon able to watch and bear witness. A policeman&#8217;s life was not being threatened nor was this an angry or panicky response by an officer or a trigger&#8208;happy racist. It was a statement about a whole system personified by four policemen unable to see or feel an African American man as a human being; unable to hear and feel the cries of a man dying under the weight of that system on his neck. To do this while hearing the shouts of anger and disbelief and knowing they were being filmed seemed to say this is not extraordinary; this is how it is &#8211; get used to it.</p>