<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par19">Stepping up to this moment requires first breaking with Extension&#8217;s historical role as a microcosm and mechanism of structural inequality. The Morrill Act of 1862 created land grant universities on Indigenous territory and raised additional funds through speculation on stolen land (Stein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2017</xref>; INFAS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2018</xref>; Ahtone and Lee <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2021</xref>). Agricultural programs in 1862 institutions served predominantly white farmers in the north and exclusively white farmers in former confederate states (Lee <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2013</xref>; Whayne <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">1988</xref>). The Morrill Act of 1890 banned racial preferences for federally funded colleges absent an alternative system, leading to the establishment of 19 &#8220;separate but equal&#8221; Black land-grant universities in southern states. In 1914, when the Smith-Lever Act formally created Extension in 1862 land grants, it rerouted funds for 1890 institutions through 1862 schools, which withheld aid from Black Extension programs that already faced egregious discrimination in the south (Whayne <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">1988</xref>; Harris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2008</xref>). Extension discrimination contributed to a &#8220;cavernous information gap between Black and white farmers&#8221; (Grant et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2012</xref>, p. 15), and was instrumental in the emergence of the conservative American Farm Bureau Association (AFBA) (Kile <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1948</xref>; Campbell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1962</xref>; Patel and Goodman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2019</xref>), the largest (US) farmer organization, which has a long history of racism, and is a powerful lobby for agribusiness monopolies, free trade, and subsidies which disproportionately benefit white farmers (Boyd and Faber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2020</xref>), while opposing farmworker rights, environmental regulations and independent farmer mobilization (Shearn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2012</xref>; Raderstorf <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2020</xref>).</p>