<table xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Environmental Factors and Supporting Scientific Data</th><th align="left" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Historical Evidence of Impacts</th><th align="left" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Future Impacts </th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Temperature</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Extremes</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Extreme Hot</italic>&#8212; <break/>Since 1970 there have been increasing numbers of days above 95 &#176;F and nights above 75 &#176;F, and decreasing numbers of extremely cold days [<xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major cities such as Atlanta, Miami, New Orleans, and Tampa have reported an increase in deaths from 1975 to 2004 relative to an increase in 95 <sup>o</sup>F and above days [<xref rid="B35-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heat stress can affect dairy and livestock production and reduce crop productivity with a coupling of drought conditions [<xref rid="B36-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Climate projections indicate that Georgia&#8217;s corn yields could decline by 15% and wheat yields by 20% by the end of 2020 [<xref rid="B37-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. <break/>Increased temperatures will cause a decline in dissolved oxygen in streams, lakes, and rivers, causing fish kills and loss of aquatic biodiversity [<xref rid="B38-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Extreme Cold</italic>&#8212; <break/>The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) indicates that in the last 50 years, daily minimum temperatures have increased faster than daily mean or maximum temperatures [<xref rid="B28-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Thus, the frequency of extreme cold temperatures has declined over the last half-century.</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">From records throughout the U.S. from 1895&#8211;2010, the trends show that in the most recent decades there has been an increase in the number of heat waves and a decrease in the number of cold waves [<xref rid="B39-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. This has direct impact on agricultural products with temperature threshold responses of agricultural pests [<xref rid="B40-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">While extreme events will increase overall, some extreme events, such as cold, will decrease [<xref rid="B41-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] (p. 495). <break/>The energy infrastructure in the Southeast U.S. can produce 32% of the nation's energy and is currently providing nearly 27%. Net energy demand will increase along with energy costs due to more extreme high relative to low temperatures and increased air conditioning usage [<xref rid="B42-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. </td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Seasonal Changes</italic></bold></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ENSO</italic>
<break/>ENSO (El Ni&#241;o Southern Oscillation), periodic changes in ocean surface temperature in the mid-latitude Pacific Ocean, may be correlated to increased precipitation in North America; whereas, La Ni&#241;a conditions in the tropical Pacific may be correlated to drought conditions in North America. These events are thought to be closely tied to global warming [<xref rid="B26-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The biggest cause of flooding and drought worldwide can be attributed to El Ni&#241;o and La Ni&#241;a climatic events [<xref rid="B43-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. <break/>The El Ni&#241;o/La Ni&#241;a event in 1997&#8211;1998 caused $35&#8211;45 million in damage and approximately 23,000 deaths worldwide as the Southeastern U.S. received record-setting rainfall [<xref rid="B44-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="B45-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atmospheric modelling programs project an increase of El Ni&#241;o events due to global warming, increasing occurrences of devastating weather effects [<xref rid="B44-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. <break/>Climate change may have a significant impact on the processes and feedbacks that are responsible for determining ENSO characteristics and thus, the frequency and strength of events [<xref rid="B46-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Changes in Seasons</italic>
<break/>Records from 1948 to 2007 have shown intensified fluctuations in summer rainfall in the Southeastern U.S. These anomalies are due to an increase in dry days occurring in already dry summers and an increase in wet days occurring in an already wet summers [<xref rid="B47-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The increased evapotranspiration occurring in extensive droughts increase sensible heat fluxes and surface temperatures, intensifying summer heat waves [<xref rid="B48-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the Southeast region, mortality rates due to seasonal heat sensitivity have remained consistent over recent time between 0.5 and 1.0 DSM (deaths per standardized million), and national regional variability in mortality has become less apparent across the U.S. [<xref rid="B35-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crops from trees and bushes requiring chilling periods may need to be replaced due to seasonal changes [<xref rid="B49-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. <break/>Warming in the Northern portion of the Southeast U.S. is projected to increase the length of the &#8220;freeze-free&#8221; season by as much as 30 days by approximately 2050 [<xref rid="B31-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Precipitation</bold></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Flooding</italic></bold>
<break/>The IPCC shows that incidences of flooding, as well as drought, have increased substantially in the last three decades [<xref rid="B28-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In Summer 2011, the Lower Mississippi Valley experienced areas of flooding and drought related to the La Ni&#241;a Conditions in the Pacific Ocean [<xref rid="B31-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. <break/>In Baton Rouge people were piling sandbags to protect from flooding, while people living in the upper landscape in Louisiana experienced extreme drought [<xref rid="B31-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration&#8216;s (NOAA) Climatic Data Center expects the Southeastern U.S. to remain on an increasing participation trend except in summer months [<xref rid="B31-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. <break/>Rural areas may be slightly better suited for flooding conditions due to pervious land cover by forested and agricultural land as compared to an impervious urban environment [<xref rid="B50-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Drought</italic></bold>
<break/>In the Southeastern U.S., the percentage of areas experiencing moderate to severe drought conditions has increased in the past 30 years [<xref rid="B38-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drought and intense thunderstorms have contributed to an increase in soil runoff and erosion and have affected crop yields as a result [<xref rid="B51-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Southeast is in a transition zone between conditions projected to be wetter in the north and drier in the southwest [<xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. <break/>The net water availability in the Southeast U.S. is projected to decrease in the decades to come, this is particularly in the western Southeast [<xref rid="B52-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. <break/>The North Atlantic Subtropical High (NASH) will intensify and move westward with the increasing CO<sub>2</sub> levels, increasing both extreme rainfall and drought in the Southeastern U.S. [<xref rid="B53-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Storm Surge</italic></bold>
<break/>Empirical evidence through modelling shows a heightened Atlantic hurricane surge in warmer conditions that is further exacerbated by sea level rise [<xref rid="B54-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The North Carolina Department of Transportation is already raising U.S. Hwy 64 from Albemarle-Pamlico by four feet to allow for anticipated sea level rise water levels and subsequent storm surges [<xref rid="B55-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Land loss may cause loss of plant and wildlife, food security, connectivity to the mainland, connections among family members and community cohesiveness [<xref rid="B2-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. <break/>Homes and infrastructures are susceptible to sea level rise, indirectly causing an increase in insurance cost or inability to receive coverage in certain areas such as along the Gulf Coast [<xref rid="B56-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Saltwater Intrusion</italic></bold>
<break/>This occurs when an aquifer is pumped faster than can be replaced and saltwater moves into the aquifer. The effects of groundwater extraction due to population growth along coastlines on coastal aquifers is more significant than the impact on sea-level rise due to climate change. Salt water inundation (landward movement of the coastline) will be more important than salt water intrusion due to sea-level-rise [<xref rid="B57-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rising sea levels put additional stress on energy and water utility companies to guard against contamination of saltwater into freshwater reserves along the Atlantic and Gulf coasts [<xref rid="B2-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. <break/>Leaders in Hallandale Beach, Florida, have already closed down 6 of the 8 drinking water wells due to salt water intrusion from seawater moving into porous aquifers [<xref rid="B58-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="B59-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crop production will be reduced due to the availability of freshwater underground for irrigation as saltwater intrudes aquifers in times of drought [<xref rid="B60-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. <break/>The development of lands due to increasing populations will exacerbate saltwater intrusion into freshwater aquifers, rendering the aquifer useless for irrigation and household use [<xref rid="B61-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Sea Level Rise</italic></bold>
<break/>Sea level has risen globally an average of 8 inches over the last century [<xref rid="B62-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Louisiana has lost 1880 sq mi of land in the last 80 years due to rising seas, sinking lands, and human development [<xref rid="B2-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sea level rise is expected to continue in this trend indefinitely [<xref rid="B62-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. <break/>Municipal infrastructures such as cities, railways, airports, and water supplies are at low elevation and subject to sea level rise. New Orleans, Miami, Tampa, Charleston, and Virginia Beach are particularly susceptible to sea level rise [<xref rid="B63-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. <break/>In the land areas bordering the Gulf of Mexico, almost all of the &#8220;most socially vulnerable people live in areas unlikely to be protected from inundation&#8220; due to sea level rise [<xref rid="B64-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Extreme Weather Events</bold></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hurricanes</bold>
<break/>Florida experienced four major hurricanes in one month in the summer of 2004, and the 2005 hurricane season brought four additional major hurricanes [<xref rid="B65-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. <break/>Between 1994 and 2008, rainfall from U.S. tropical cyclones that made landfall was higher than the historical average [<xref rid="B66-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hurricane-associated winds and flooding not only damaged property but caused drowning, injury, stress, illness, and death due to contaminated floodwater and CO poisoning (from generator use) [<xref rid="B65-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. <break/>&#8220;The Southeast has been affected by more billion-dollar disasters than any other region&#8220; [<xref rid="B2-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] (p. 397). </td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Projections suggest that warming will cause few tropical storms and hurricanes; however, the storms that do form will increase in intensity (<italic>i.e.</italic>, more Category 4 and 5 Storms). There may be even greater economic repercussions for those living within the paths of hurricanes [<xref rid="B67-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tornadoes</bold>
<break/>There has been an increase in number of tornadoes over the last 50 years but the increase is not statistically significant [<xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Southern U.S. experienced 753 tornadoes in April, 2011, breaking the previous monthly record of 542. In May 2011, 178 fatalities were reported in relation to tornadoes in the Southern U.S. [<xref rid="B68-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conditions leading to strong thunderstorms and subsequently, tornadoes, are expected to increase with warming; however, there are other factors to consider such as vertical and horizontal wind variations that are needed to produce tornadoes [<xref rid="B43-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Winter Storms</bold>
<break/>The number of severe snowstorms since 1960 is more than twice that of severe regional storms that occurred in the 60 years prior [<xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct relationships between human health and cold temperature are not as pronounced as compared to hot temperatures; thus, linking cold weather and death rates has been more difficult [<xref rid="B69-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Climate change will not only alter globally averaged surface temperature but also changes atmospheric circulation; occasionally stronger winds from polar regions will cause colder winters in the Southeastern U.S. [<xref rid="B43-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. <break/>Power outages associated with winter storms may lead to an increase in air quality problems from CO and particulates from wood and coal-burning stoves and fireplaces as well as gas or diesel generators [<xref rid="B70-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Thunderstorms</bold>
<break/>Severe thunderstorms with large values of wind shear and potential energy and moist enthalpy close to the Earth&#8216;s surface have been increasing over the last few decades [<xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wildfires are often begun by lightning strikes; the Southeast U.S. has the highest frequency of lightning strikes in the nation [<xref rid="B71-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Due to increasing temperatures and a change in weather patterns, lightning frequency may increase, which will, in turn, affect air quality and increase the occurrences of direct lightning strikes and wildfires [<xref rid="B2-ijerph-13-00189" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</td></tr></tbody></table>