<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para160">Land-use change, intensive livestock production, wildlife trade, and climate change are dynamic processes that vary in magnitude, extent, and attributes over space and time as they interact with and are altered by each other and external factors.<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref> These complex interactions have implications for the various drivers and their impacts on zoonotic disease emergence (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>
). <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>
illustrates the interconnectedness of the drivers with additional dimensions affected by the COVID-19 health crisis, all of which relate in some way to the state of biodiversity and ecosystems (<xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix pp 11&#8211;21</xref>). Crucially, adverse effects exacerbate drivers of zoonosis emergence, thus increasing the risks for future zoonotic disease events (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Zoonotic disease emergence feedback loop</p><p>Key anthropogenic drivers of zoonotic disease emergence (eg, including land-use change, wildlife trade, intensive livestock production, and climate change) increase the likelihood of zoonotic disease emergence, which could result in public health crises, such as the COVID-19 pandemic. Such crises could have negative effects on biodiversity and ecosystem health, as COVID-19 has had and could continue to have (<xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix pp 11&#8211;21</xref>). These effects can consequently exacerbate the drivers, leading to further emergence of zoonosis and potential future health crises with their own suite of effects. The continuation of this cycle would reinforce a feedback loop with substantial implications for human health, economies, society, and the environment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effects of the COVID-19 public health crisis related to biodiversity loss and ecosystem health</p><p>The figure shows multiple interconnected areas related to biodiversity loss and ecosystem health, which have been or are likely to be affected by the COVID-19 pandemic. The impact areas (outer circle) were assembled into seven categories (inner circle; connected via corresponding colours to relevant impact areas) for ease of visualisation and interpretation. Impacts areas could, in reality, correspond to multiple categories. The human-nature interactions category includes the key drivers of zoonotic disease emergence&#8212;land-use change, intensive livestock production, wildlife trade, and climate change, as shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>. Semi-transparent lines between categories show that effects are interlinked, with many effects directly or indirectly affecting others, including the drivers of zoonotic disease emergence. See <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix (pp 11&#8211;21)</xref> for a selection of effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on biodiversity and ecosystem health, organised by impact categories and impact areas.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>