<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par51">A project funded by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) and executed by the Institute for Biodiversity and Protected Areas (IBAP) of Guinea Bissau (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thegef.org/projects-operations/projects/9521">https://www.thegef.org/projects-operations/projects/9521</ext-link>, last accessed in 18.01.2022) provided new hope. However, the COVID 19 pandemic delayed field activities, and the actual support given for dike reconstruction has been minute, as the project is mostly focused on strengthening institutional and coordination capacities to scale-up and finance mangrove restoration. Djobel inhabitants want to be helped with a food-for-work aid intervention to rebuild the village protection dikes and create new rice fields. However, no external institution seems to believe that such a gigantic task can be achieved. In 2021, the new government (elected with Djobel political support) did finally help the villagers to take possession of the small fringe of their upland formerly demarcated as belonging to them by the legal advisor to the Minister of Territorial Administration of the previous government. However, the house foundations, hundreds of cement bricks (the area becomes flooded during the rainy season and the traditional mud bricks cannot be used), and the drinking water infrastructure built with the financial support of the state and the UN were all destroyed one night by Arame villagers (see Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>), some of whom were caught by soldiers and imprisoned. During the 2021 rainy season, more rice fields and a total of seven houses were destroyed by the rains and flooding, and a child drowned. The villagers' are beyond desperate, and have asked the state for authorization to make a traditional war against the village of Arame: "We do not want to violate the law, but if the state does not help us, we'll have no other choice (&#8230;) we may all die, but at least one 'seed' (someone) will survive."<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold>: Partial view of the destruction produced by Arame villagers in Djobel's new settlement (photos taken by Djobel villagers in July 2021 and sent to the first author through WhatsApp).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10745_2022_352_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p>