<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par44">In 1953, Djobel was characterized by a large and continuous area of rice cultivation. However, in 1966, the village's population was forced to take refuge in Casamance/Senegal. As mentioned, after Independence (1974), only around half of the former population returned to Guinea-Bissau. Many youngsters got jobs outside agriculture in Senegal, and others were studying and decided to stay. Consequently, the village had much less labor with which to rebuild and maintain the dike infrastructure constructed during colonial times. Additionally, some of the rice fields were covered by mangroves (as confirmed in Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> for the year 1976). As a result, many distant fields were abandoned, and the villagers' efforts became focused on the fields near their houses. Despite the destruction caused by seven years of refuge in Casamance, the inhabitants were able to rebuild the water management infrastructures needed to quickly achieve rice self-sufficiency. According to Djobel elders' public statements &#8211; which were never contested by Arame traditional authorities and urban elite representatives, who challenged other statements made by Djobel villagers, and were corroborated by Elia elders &#8211; although Djobel villagers helped the inhabitants of Arame in their post-war reconstruction work, their neighbors refused to help them in return. Instead, help was provided by those that had decided to stay in Casamance and by inhabitants of Elia. At that time, no water was visible inside the main polder, where both the houses and the nearer rice fields were located (as confirmed in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Nonetheless, according to farmers, the dike structure never again attained the previous level of robustness and regular maintenance.</p>