<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par3">Sustainable finance may often appear to be a topic of specialised interest for financial officials, regulators and market actors, but it is in fact inseparable from the moral imperative of climate justice. This connection is made directly in the Paris Agreement long-term goal of &#8216;[m]aking finance flows consistent with a pathway towards low greenhouse gas emissions and climate-resilient development&#8217; (Article 2.1(c)). This goal requires nothing less than that the &#8216;ultimate purpose of the global financial system&#8217; (which the system is still failing to meet) becomes &#8216;to ensure the cost-efficient and effective channeling of global savings to finance tomorrow&#8217;s inclusive, sustainable economy&#8217; (Zadek <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">2019</xref>, 19&#8211;20). This would amount to a normative reorientation of the financial system away from traditionally dominant (at least in the West) accounts of its purpose as a neutral and efficient allocator of resources (Andreotti <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2017</xref>, 25&#8211;27). Article 2.1c has been rightly described as a goal of &#8216;transformative potential&#8217; (Zamarioli et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2021</xref>, 578), which is different in kind from quantitative pledges of climate finance which, however significant to their recipients, nevertheless amount to a &#8216;small proportion&#8217; of overall global finance flows (SCF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2018</xref>, 12&#8211;13). It is no coincidence that &#8216;mission-oriented&#8217; approaches to finance (Mazzucato <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2021</xref>), such as the Article 2.1(c) goal, gained ground following the 2007&#8211;2008 financial crisis and its exposure of&#160;&#8216;blind faith&#8217; in efficient markets (Jordan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2014</xref>, 7).</p>