<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0065">The works of Bert van Wee and Karel Martens have constituted a turning point in their enshrining of research on questions of transport equity in deontological rather that consequentialist approaches to normative ethics in Euro-American liberal philosophy &#8211; be this the work of John Rawls (<xref rid="bb0350" ref-type="bibr">Van Wee and Geurs, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bb0355" ref-type="bibr">Van Wee and Roeser, 2013</xref>) and/or Michael Walzer (<xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Martens, 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Martens, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Martens et al., 2012</xref>). Consequentialist approaches foreground the centrality of the consequences of action &#8211; typically by the state when transport is concerned &#8211; to normative ethics and thinking about equity, and utilitarianism is one of their most well-known varieties. Deontological approaches, in contrast, emphasize rules and duties as the basis for ethics. They are exemplified by the maximax principle advocated by <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Martens et al. (2012)</xref> and the Rawlsian difference principle highlighted by <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al. (2017)</xref>. In the context of transport planning, the first holds that decision-making should maximise the &#8216;average&#8217; ease with which destinations can be reached from a given territory &#8211; a.k.a. accessibility and &#8220;widely accepted as the most important benefit of a transportation system&#8221; (<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Karner et al., 2020</xref>, page 2) &#8211; while ensuring an acceptable level of accessibility for the least well-off group(s) in that territory. In contrast, the difference principle suggests that inequalities in accessibility can only be considered fair if they work to the benefit of the least well-off; decision making should therefore maximise the minimum level of accessibility for the worst-off in a given territory and thus follow the maximin rule (<xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 2017</xref>).</p>