<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">This action plan identified short-term and long-term goals for both the medical school and wider university to work towards, and encompassed the key recommendations made by the PHRC (<bold><italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="f02" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></italic></bold>). For example, to address the recommendation entitled curricular thread, which aims to integrate planetary health and sustainable health education into learning as a cross-curricular theme, the school aims to create a toolkit to help learning facilitators explore and evaluate the importance of the &#8220;Global&#8221; theme within case studies, and many simple suggestions to incorporate planetary health topics into the current curricular content were made. Many resources exist at Queen&#8217;s highlighting the university&#8217;s dedication to climate action, although this information is difficult to find, and the development of a planetary health and sustainability website (currently in progress) will provide transparency to the university&#8217;s commitment to climate action and help develop further resources. Other proposed goals outlined in the action plan included the creation of a sustainability handbook or induction for all new students to help explain what planetary health is and why it is important to consider within healthcare; and to increase community outreach, the group hopes to collaborate with organisations such as the Northern Ireland Science Festival and the Northern Ireland Confederation for Health and Social Care (NICON). The creation of this report card has been a huge success within the SMDBS, with the findings discussed at the School Management Board Meeting and the Faculty Executive Board Meeting of the Faculty of Medicine, Health &amp; Life Sciences, and has encouraged other schools to share best practice goals and get involved in the initiative. The SMDBS has since signed &#8216;Health Declares: Climate and Ecological Emergency&#8217;, declaring a climate emergency and committing the school to advocate to protect planetary and human health(<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The student team has engaged with other key stakeholders within Queen&#8217;s, including the Faculty Engagement Manager, QUB Estates Manager for Environment, the Student&#8217;s Union and QUBSU Climate Action and Sustainability Group, beginning the process of building and strengthening interdepartmental groups dedicated to climate action, planetary health education and engagement. Going forward into the next academic year, 2021-22, the QUB student team is seeking to welcome more members to build upon the work done so far.</p>