<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par13">In sum, adaptation cannot be politically neutral, may imply a far-reaching overhaul of society, and involves questions of justice. Several authors interpret this conclusion as a clear imperative to democratize adaptation (Mikulewicz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2018</xref>; Burnell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2012</xref>). They echo advocates of the &#8216;enabling approach&#8217; to sustainability transformations (Scoones et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2020</xref>) who have argued that adaptation should involve communities who know best for themselves what they need to thrive in the face of climate change. Similarly, Schlosberg et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2017</xref>) advocate for a capabilities approach to just adaptation that starts from the needs of communities to inform interventions needed to support them. However, Mikulewicz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2018</xref>) emphasizes that democratization cannot be reduced to the &#8216;involvement&#8217; of communities through participatory processes or &#8216;community-based adaptation&#8217; (CBA) approaches. The former have often been found to be tokenistic processes to legitimize pre-determined outcomes, and while the latter may imply more meaningful engagement, they risk shifting responsibilities&#8212;not power&#8212;to communities (Few et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2007</xref>). Ultimately, democratization has to be mainly about identifying and redressing power imbalances that underlie adaptation-based injustices (Mikulewicz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2018</xref>): it is the disempowerment of certain communities that renders them vulnerable to maladaptation. Democratization is then understood as being about redressing maladaptation through empowerment that allows vulnerable communities to politicize and challenge mainstream adaptation.</p>