<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par20">Research on the Diola ethnolinguistic group (also known as Djola, Jola or J&#243;ola in Casamance, Senegal) living in around twenty villages of northern Guinea-Bissau started in 2015. Between 2017 and 2019, a survey exploring these villages' livelihoods was carried out with 342 Diola households in the villages of Bulol, Elalab, Edjaten, Edjin, Jufunco, Susana (the Ajaamat sub-group known as Felupe in Guinea-Bissau) and Arame, Elia, and Djobel (Baiote sub-group). Diola family units (<italic>fogon</italic> in Creole) overlap with production units, and, when present, both husband and wife were interviewed together. The Djobel livelihoods survey was applied during January and February 2017 to all households, but qualitative research has continued to date with short-term visits of one&#8211;two weeks every year during the early dry season. Research techniques were mainly based on oral history (nine interviews with elders of Djobel [3], Elia [3], Elalab [1], Edjaten [1], and Susana [2]), informal group discussions and key-informants interviews (about the extreme events of the previous rainy season, their consequences, the coping measures adopted, and the food security status of the inhabitants). Youths from Djobel and the other villages took part in five group discussions about their living conditions in the cities of Bissau, S. Domingos, Dakar, and Ziguintchor in comparison with rural livelihoods. Additionally, countless informal conversations about the inter-village conflict between Djobel and Arame were held through the years with people of all genres and ages from the villages under conflict and the neighbouring Diola villages mentioned above. These conversations took place in many informal contexts (e.g., over drinking palm wine, while walking, or travelling on public transport) to avoid the construction of stereotyped narratives. In 2021, the former state administrator of S. Domingos region, who had a major role in trying to solve the conflict, was interviewed by the first author and Lu&#237;sa Acabado. Two informal conversations took also place with the staff of the Cacheu Mangroves' National Park (in 2021), and another three (in 2021 and 2022) with the group of soldiers that has been recently settled in the Elia and Djobel upland to try to prevent further violence. We also had access to the reports made by the legal advisor (Dr Luciano Patron Matos) of the Minister of Territorial Administration, who tried to solve the conflict in 2019 and to help the villagers of Djobel to settle in a small fringe of their upland. All interviews were conducted by the first author either in Guinea-Bissau Creole or in Diola, with translations provided by a field assistant belonging to each village, when informants did not speak the local <italic>lingua franca</italic>. Unless otherwise stated, all empirical data were collected by the first author in Diola villages during a total of 12&#160;months of fieldwork (distributed in periods of 2&#8211;3&#160;months every year during the early dry season, when farmers are less occupied with farming activities).</p>