<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0220">My purpose here is not to prognosticate as to whether the Canadian Supreme Court will hear an appeal on &#8220;necessity to act&#8221; arguments, although given the vast scale of oil production increases linked to the TMX project and its incompatibility with the Paris Climate Accord, some political geographers might well focus here on the <italic>necessity</italic> arguments. More central to my point here is emphasizing the other of the two main defence arguments &#8211; that the injunction and how it was used constituted an abuse of process; it functioned as a judicial tool to deny rights and responsibilities. While legal geographers and political ecologists write about legal pluralism and multi-level jurisdiction (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">O'Donnell et al., 2019</xref>), and Indigenous law as a component of justice is (to an extent) acknowledged by the Canadian Supreme Court, proceedings in the BC courthouse showed an injunction being used to close down all such pluralistic principles, values and ethics, even before they could be articulated. As articulated by other scholars (<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Peel &amp; Osofsky, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Simpson, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">Wong &amp; Richards, 2020</xref>), Indigenous legal traditions are deeply rooted in place and in the ontologies of care that underlie responsibility for land protection. In this regard, <italic>intergenerational care</italic>, <italic>necessity to act</italic>, and <italic>Indigenous responsibilities for land protection</italic> weaved throughout the arguments of various defendants. John Borrows, a member of the Anishinabe Ojibwe Nation and leading scholar on Indigenous law, stressed that closer linkage between Canadian and Indigenous legal systems would be vital: &#8220;Indigenous legal principles form a system of &#8216;empirical observations and pragmatic knowledge&#8217; that has value both in itself and as a tool to demonstrate how people structure information. First Nations laws embrace ecological protection, and they could be woven into the very fabric of North American legal ideas&#8221; (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Borrows, 2002</xref>, p. 35). While &#8216;reconciliation&#8217; with Indigenous people is rhetorically promoted by Canadian politicians and often part of an acutely superficial &#8216;solidarity&#8217; discourse (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Boudreau Morris, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Daigle, 2019</xref>), the abuse of injunctions now arguably stands as among the most symbolically powerful illustrations of the triumph of a colonial system above other systems, and a blunt tool for fortifying oil interests. Injunctions in Canada are repeatedly being used to deny Indigenous law, values and necessity defences point blank.</p>