<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par22">Environmental and climate justice research implicitly takes the existence of a spatially homogenous community affected by climate impacts as a given. Despite a number of theoretical orientations, as Auyero and Swistun (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>) note, most accounts of environmental justice movements share a classical Marxist model of consciousness, where &#8220;physically proximate aggrieved people overcome false beliefs or persistent uncertainties through reflection and interaction&#8221; (pg. 358). The outcome is almost always, in environmental justice accounts, a single and determined consensus regarding the problem and its solution, where the main and singular actor is &#8220;the community&#8221; (Auyero &amp; Swistun, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>). Even in cases where communities paradoxically mobilize in favor of hazardous sites to be located nearby, such as community-supported fracking wells (Jerolmack &amp; Walker, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2018</xref>), or when communities are uncertain about where pollution comes from (Auyero &amp; Swistun, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>), the unit of analysis is an entire community thought to face a common risk and hold a common interest in planning for the future. Yet this theory fails to explain what happened in Manhattan, where we can observe a shared and clear recognition of flood projections and damage from Sandy, but two conflicting views on how to plan for the future. The Lower East Side, as we will see below, is wholly exposed and vulnerable to catastrophic flooding and was severely impacted by Sandy, but two opposing movements mobilized in the neighborhood and both used the language and framing of environmental justice advance their argument: One movement of people supported the climate infrastructure project and another movement rejected it.</p>