<author-notes xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> June 28, 2022.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> September 8, 2022. <?xpp bx;1?>doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.30282</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2022 Nagata JM et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi220857cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Jason M. Nagata, MD, MSc, Department of Pediatrics, University of California, San Francisco, 550 16th St, 4th Floor, Box 0110, San Francisco, CA 94158 (<email xlink:href="jason.nagata@ucsf.edu">jason.nagata@ucsf.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Nagata and Ms Lin had full access to all the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic>Concept and design:</italic> Nagata, Epstein, Nash, Weiser.</p><p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Nagata, Hampshire, Charlebois.</p><p><italic>Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Nagata, Epstein, Lin, Tsai, Nash.</p><p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Hampshire, Zakaras, Weiser.</p><p><italic>Supervision:</italic> Nagata, Weiser.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Nagata reported receiving grants from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and the American Heart Association during the conduct of the study. Ms Zakaras reported receiving fees from the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases K24 Award during the conduct of the study. Dr Murnane reported receiving grants from the NIH during the conduct of the study. Dr Charlebois reported receiving grants from the NIH during the conduct of the study. Dr Tsai reported receiving payments from Elsevier Inc for his work as coeditor-in-chief of <italic>SSM-Mental Health</italic> outside the submitted work. Dr Weiser reported receiving grants from the NIH during the conduct of the study and grants from the NIH and San Francisco General Hearts Foundation outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This project was funded by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (grant K24AI134326, PI: Weiser), the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (grant K08HL159350, PI: Nagata), and the American Heart Association (grant CDA34760281, PI: Nagata).</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funding organizations had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> Samuel Benabou, Levi Cervantez, and Natalia Smith Garcia de Leon, BS (University of California, San Francisco), provided editorial assistance. No financial compensation was provided.</p><p><bold>Additional Information:</bold> Survey data can be accessed through the following website by creating an account and filling out a brief form describing intended analyses: <ext-link xlink:href="https://dhsprogram.com/data/" ext-link-type="uri">https://dhsprogram.com/data/</ext-link>.</p></author-notes>