<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par26">This paper has sought to tap into a broad cross-section of climate activists from the global North to get a broad image of the role of adaption in CCMs today. Protest survey data were&#160;therefore used from demonstrations in 13 cities in the global North during the September 2019 Global Climate Strike, organized by FFF. The campaign was famously started by Swedish climate activist Greta Thunberg, who started her campaign in August 2018, when she decided to quit going to school and instead sat down in front of the Swedish parliament to demand appropriate climate action. Her actions drew widespread attention and support and soon escalated into a national and then global campaign of climate strikers. While initially targeted at fellow school students, the campaign over time grew substantially and increasingly attracted participants from all generations (de Moor et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020a</xref>). In particular, the September 2019 Global Climate Strike week of action between 20 and 27 September was explicitly targeted at getting adults involved as well, for instance by encouraging trade unions to mobilize their members to join. Moreover, the strikes explicitly refrained from making any particular official&#160;demands, apart from insisting that governments take stronger climate action. Hence, in principle, the demonstrations offered a platform for demands for mitigation as well as adaptation. The September strikes became the largest climate mobilization in history. Thus, while we do not know how the protesters related to the wider population of climate activists, the strikes&#8217; size, popularity and growing internal diversity made for a unique opportunity to analyze a broad cross-section of Northern climate activists&#8217; characteristics and views. Still, not all climate activists participated or even supported the events and demonstrations are but the most visible moments of social movement activity. Any generalization of the findings should therefore be made with appropriate caution.</p>