<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par27">To get a representative sample of participants in these demonstrations, an international team of researchers implemented the well-established protest survey method developed by Van Aelst and Walgrave (2001). As described in detail elsewhere (de Moor et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020a</xref>), the data collection followed the main principles outlined in this approach which makes sure that all protesters have an equal chance of being selected, thus yielding a random and therefore representative sample. In each surveyed demonstration, research teams handed out&#8201;~&#8201;1,000 personal invitations to an online survey that interviewees were asked to complete after the demonstration. Two principles were followed to randomly select protesters. First, interviewers would not select interviewees themselves, as this could lead to selection bias based on interviewers&#8217; perception of &#8216;approachable&#8217; looking individuals (Walgrave and Verhulst <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2011</xref>). Instead, interviewers would be sent to interview individuals who were selected by &#8216;pointers&#8217; who followed the second principle. That is, pointers would apply a systematic protocol to make sure every protester had an equal chance of being interviewed. For instance, in a demonstration of approximately 10,000 protesters, every 10th individual would be selected. Finally, it was made possible to assess whether no biases occurred in the responses ultimately received from those who were selected to participate. Specifically, every fifth interviewee also received a short face-to-face interview that recorded basic characteristics, such as gender, age, education, political interest and protest experience. Since the response rate on these interviews tends to be higher than 90%, it offers a baseline to assess and potentially correct response biases. Based on this survey, the current paper presents survey data from 2,344 protesters in 13 cities across Australia (Sydney), the USA (New York) and all regions of Europe (Brussels, Vienna, Bern, Berlin, Chemnitz, Malm&#246;, Gothenburg, Stockholm, Helsinki, Bucharest, Prague). Cities were selected based on the presence of a local research team that could carry out the survey. While thus presenting a convenience sample, our study includes several of the largest demonstrations from the September strike, thus contributing to the aim of obtaining a broad sample of climate activists. Each country team followed the ethical standards valid in their country or institution (including regarding informed consents and interviewing minors).</p>