<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Within the framework of the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR), several smart-village projects took off around the world. Many of which were funded through international research organizations with clear impacts in areas that were worse hit by climate change [<xref rid="B10-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. These projects mostly focus on training smallholder farmers on agricultural resilience, through the adoption of practices that support food security [<xref rid="B13-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], so that persons within these affected communities are able to maintain a livelihood through agricultural methods that help decrease GHG emissions. For instance, farmers in the Lower Nyando valleys of Kenya are benefitting from improved agroforestry systems that adopts knowledge of Information and Communication Technology (ICT) [<xref rid="B13-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Thanks to the CGAIR initiative, they are able to cultivate cash crops in-between rows of multi-purpose trees, thereby improving soil stability and enrichment. Given the increased demand for trees, several nurseries were developed, adding farmers&#8217; incomes, and with women as the highest beneficiaries. The state of Bihar in India also benefitted from the CGIAR&#8217;s smart village initiative. It previously had soils that were greatly affected by water-logging, but new drainage construction changed the channel of rapidly flowing flood waters, out of the farming areas [<xref rid="B14-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. This improved system also ensured that underground aquifers were steadily recharged. Improved technological ideas also saw better rainwater harvesting in areas benefitting from the Climate Change Agriculture and Food Security (CCAFS) program. Overall, weather and planting can now be monitored from smartphone applications by the farmers, in order to avoid unwanted losses [<xref rid="B15-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p>