<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par77">The findings here show that the city began with intentions to use democratic principles to guide the design and planning of the complex infrastructure project and attempted to reimagine the urban coastline as a blurred and sponge-like interstitial zone between city and ocean. For a time, this process succeeded as an experiment in participatory design and participants were able to iteratively recognize their own input in architectural sketches and diagrams &#8211; they felt they were meaningfully <italic>influencing</italic> the planning process. Importantly, in the first phase of the project, participants were not anti-expert, as they cooperated with highly specialized professional landscape architects and were willing to work with the funding expectations that the city set for the project. However, the city found it impossible to go through with this approach. As the project crunched through the bureaucratic city procedures to review its engineering feasibility and turn the plan into a built reality, the city found that it could not deliver the design promises it had made. To defend its new plan, the city then retreated into a technocratic decision-making style, repeatedly appealing to the authority of objectivity in public demonstrations. Residents no longer saw their input reflected in city plans even as they remained involved contributors in the process, and rejected the city&#8217;s plans as politically motivated and staff&#8217;s technical expertise as tarnished by political associations. The result was a legitimacy crisis and local resistance in opposition to the plan. Another result was a bitter conflict among neighborhood residents &#8211; between those who valued a flawed plan that would still provide flood protection, and those who rejected the city&#8217;s new decision-making style and the wholesale destruction of the park.</p>