<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Young people are also framing climate change as an issue of health, human rights, and equity and are using this framework to hold governments accountable for their constitutional duties to protect their citizens. Young plaintiffs, many of them children, have filed lawsuits against governments in Australia, Canada, Colombia, India, Mexico, Pakistan, and South Korea.<sup><xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup> Children have also filed complaints against Argentina, Brazil, France, Germany, and Turkey through the UN Committee on the Rights of the Child for their failure to reduce carbon emissions and their violation of children&#8217;s rights to life, health, and a healthy environment.<sup><xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> These efforts show the efficacy of arguing for a legally enforceable connection between climate change and governments&#8217; constitutional duties to protect citizens&#8217; health and safety. For instance, Colombia&#8217;s Supreme Court ruled that the deforestation of the Colombian Amazon contributed to climate change and that the Colombian government&#8217;s failure to limit it constituted a serious attack on the rights of current and future generations.<sup><xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup> Moreover, young people have also filed suits against other stakeholders, such as fossil fuel companies. Young Friends of the Earth (Netherlands) was a co-plaintiff in the recent successful suit <italic toggle="yes">Milieudefensie et al., v. Royal Dutch Shell PLC</italic>, in which the Hague District Court ruled in favor of young people and ordered the company to reduce its emissions by 45% by 2030, relative to 2019, to come into compliance with human rights obligations.<sup><xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup> Unlike other claimants, the organization was allowed to remain a plaintiff in this case, as it had sufficient grounds to represent Dutch citizens and because its members&#8217; interests were directly affected.<sup><xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> This example indicates that young people can play a critical role in leveraging judicial systems to support climate change efforts.</p>