<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0180">Importantly, until November 2018 all the cases were tried under &#8220;criminal contempt&#8221; &#8211; not &#8220;civil contempt&#8221;; the judge was adamant that pleading &#8220;civil contempt&#8221; was <italic>not</italic> an option &#8211; he reiterated this frequently. The <italic>public and symbolic</italic> nature of resistance acts, he stressed, made it a criminal contempt issue, despite efforts by some defendants to plead otherwise. On November 23rd, it thus took me some time to appreciate that the judge had turned his logic entirely around. &#8220;The judge is having it both ways,&#8221; one courtroom observer whispered to me, explaining that the change regarding civil versus criminal contempt that day was intended to facilitate new intimidation. The day before, an Indigenous woman had tried to argue that she should be heard in Indigenous courts, not in <italic>this</italic> court, and the judge stressed that it was only in this court and only under the criminal contempt charge that these cases could be considered. Yet on that day, Trans Mountain Corporation lawyers argued for &#8220;<italic>civil contempt</italic>&#8221; charges for the two new defendants, an Anglican Priest and her parishioner, who, the lawyers argued &#8220;have not apologized and purged their contempt&#8221; and referenced &#8220;exhibition a&#8221; and &#8220;exhibition b&#8221; &#8211; local newspaper articles, where one defendant was quoted as expressing <italic>&#8220;the absurdity of a Texas company on unceded territory&#8221;</italic>; the lawyer read it aloud as if it was incriminating. These defendants had chained themselves to a tree because, as they explained, they were respecting pre-existing Coast Salish law. The Trans Mountain Corporation lawyers were using this as a testing ground for new mechanisms of inflicting fear, threatening a prohibitively exorbitant &#8220;special cost&#8221; component which defendants could be forced to pay.</p>