<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0025">According to the Asian Development Bank, the coronavirus pandemic could cost the global economy as much as $8.8 trillion (&#163;7 trillion) in losses or 9.7% of global gross domestic product.<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> COVID-19 may have had positive, indirect effects on our environment.<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Global warming is driven by the concentrations of CO<sub>2</sub> and other greenhouse gases in the atmosphere, which is a consequence of anthropogenic emissions of these chemicals. Human activity has accelerated global warming and has led to changing climates around the world. The reduction of air pollution is a good thing, and reducing greenhouse gas emissions can help mitigate warming and slow climate change. Although the epidemic has helped to reduce greenhouse gas emissions, for the time being, the consequent death of hundreds of thousands of people was a steep and unacceptable cost for achieving the desired goal. Climate researchers and activists see no success in reducing environmental impacts at the expense of human lives and health; it is an anathema to their destinations. The threat of this disease may be only temporary, but global warming, climate change, and extreme weather events will challenge societies for years to come. Human health cannot be separated from the health of global natural systems and the environment.<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Although the consequences of the coronavirus crisis are enormous, the climate change crisis cannot be ignored.<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> There have been many studies on the impact of the coronavirus crisis on the environment, global warming, and climate change. Helm<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> studied the environmental effects of the coronavirus crisis, and Lidskog et al.<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> showed the Corona as an opportunity to re-implement climate change policies, and Ching and Kajino<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> led the battle against COVID-19 to bring short-lived, long-lasting, and positive and negative impacts on the warming climate. Fischedick and Schneidewind<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> simultaneously examined the coronavirus crisis and climate protection.</p>