<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par12">The study of the tension between participatory democracy and expert knowledge &#8211; a tension that has troubled sociologists for nearly a century &#8211; may shed light on this paradox of &#8220;rising participation and declining democracy&#8221; (Walker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2015</xref>). The debate over democracy and expertise began with Walter Lippmann&#8217;s <italic>Public Opinion</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">1922</xref>),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1">1</xref> where he denied the &#8220;omnicompetence&#8221; of the public. In everyday decision-making, Lippmann argued, public officials should consider the views of experts rather than solely listen to voters, since the world is complex and people&#8217;s ability to engage with issues is limited by their lack of expertise. John Dewey agreed that the public had little understanding of the political world. But for Dewey, experts, like all elite authorities, ultimately speak for their own interests rather than for the public interest, and they risk becoming an oligarchy if the public &#8220;do not have the chance to inform the experts as to their needs&#8221; (Dewey, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1927</xref> quoted in Schudson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2006</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref> In present day, Eyal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>) argues, we find ourselves amidst a crisis of expertise, which doubles as a crisis of democracy: Technical experts have largely lost the trust of the public to be the sole decision-makers after several high-profile incidents wherein experts miscalculated risk with dire consequences (e.g. Chernobyl or Fukushima). Yet at the same time, the modern world is fraught with potentially catastrophic risks that require specialized knowledge to address, or at least, to reach a decision within the time-frame demanded by the problem (Beck, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1992</xref>).</p>