<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par13">Development and urban studies scholars have also long documented tensions between experts and democracy in various empirical settings, often in the Global South. Easterly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2014</xref>), studying the World Bank&#8217;s history in Africa, found that development experts routinely subvert rights and democracy in favor of technical solutions to poverty. The experts&#8217; solutions often involve advising authoritarian governments to implement top-down development schemes that do not alleviate poverty with the same effectiveness as bolstering rights and self-determination. Li and Zhong (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2020</xref>), in an account of the remaking of Shanghai&#8217;s waterfront, found that the local state claimed their plan was democratic because it was &#8220;for the people,&#8221; but the plan was drawn up entirely by local leaders and planners, and sidelined the everyday users of the area. A number of other case studies ranging from participatory forestry in Guatemala (Millner et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2020</xref>) and Tanzania (Green &amp; Lund, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2015</xref>), to water supply management in Taiwan (Fan, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2016</xref>) and neighborhood planning in Philadelphia (Maskovsky, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>), have similarly meditated on the complicated relationship between specialized knowledge and democracy. The conclusion of this research is that participation holds promise to promote&#160;procedural justice, but the government&#8217;s tendency to wield authority based on expert advice rather than public input is a significant barrier towards achieving democratic decision-making for complex sociotechnical environmental issues (Ottinger, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2013</xref>; Pickering et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2020</xref>).</p>