<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Extreme events devastate almost all the societal sectors, for instance, destroying housing and critical infrastructural systems [<xref rid="B11-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], suspending healthcare and social services [<xref rid="B12-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and disrupting economic growth [<xref rid="B13-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. These negative impacts not only cause compounded impacts on global citizens&#8217; health and well-being, but also reversely reinforce the frequency, scope, and magnitude of extreme events and further increase inhabitants&#8217; exposure to related hazards, weakening resilience and threatening sustainability at the individual, family, community, and societal levels [<xref rid="B14-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. GSW interventions require social workers to respond to these disaster-specific, multi-dimensional influences and compounded impacts [<xref rid="B17-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. More importantly, green social workers must identify and address the root causes of these influences and impacts, namely structural inequalities, such as poverty, health disparities, and food and natural resources security, and fundamentally advocate for environmental justice and social justice [<xref rid="B18-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Historically, social workers have stood on the frontline, fighting these systemic injustices in our societal systems, and have advocated for human health and well-being in non-disaster scenarios [<xref rid="B19-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Extreme events add an extra layer and increase the contextualized complexity of social work practice. Applying the knowledge, skills, and interventions obtained from the non-disaster settings to their service in disaster surroundings would enable social workers to continue supporting vulnerable and marginalized groups. A paucity of literature, however, addresses this knowledge mobilization in social work education and professional training. Social work professionals have a long history of engagement in supporting individuals, families, and communities (particularly those of the vulnerable and marginalized) affected by extreme events worldwide through the entire disaster cycle [<xref rid="B21-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and in non-disaster settings [<xref rid="B22-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B23-healthcare-10-01245" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p>