<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Although relatively few professional associations and specialty organizations have addressed the intersection of climate change and COVID&#8208;19, Coates and colleagues (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) examined the critical role of advancing public health and climate action from the perspective of the International Society of Dermatology's Climate Action Committee. They urged a wake&#8208;up call for the convergence of climate change and COVID&#8208;19 and meaningful action for both of these global health crises. The American Thoracic Society (ATS) discussed the importance of shared responsibility in engaging in action to confront COVID&#8208;19 and climate change (Shankar et al., <xref rid="phn12866-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The primary focus was on air travel and its impact on the environment and as a reservoir of COVID&#8208;19 infection. Their position statement was aimed at urging individuals to fly less, fly more efficiently, purchase carbon offsets, and address other sources of waste at conference attendance. As a society aimed at addressing lung health, the ATS&#8217;s commentary was a critical viewpoint on opportunities to address our current pandemic and an urgent climate change agenda. Furthermore, Morrison (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) also urged that general practitioners examine the importance of COVID&#8208;19 in our climate&#8208;changing world. Morrison's lens was based on an understanding of health and social inequalities during the current pandemic; the author also suggested that there is a need for progressive and comprehensive actions to assure health equity in pandemics and amidst climate change. The findings of Morrison (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) fit within this theme of the role of professional organizations, but also overlap with Theme 2 Global Approach Addressing Human&#8208;Environmental Issues. Finally, Patruno and colleagues (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) offered a commentary regarding the intersection of climate change, COVID&#8208;19 and dermatology. They suggested that telehealth has emerged as a key way to provided health care to reduce contacts and discussed the influence climate change has on dermatological conditions such as cancer in our climate&#8208;changing world.</p>