<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0545">The often predominant emphasis on global transformations needs to be complemented by elevating applied research for context-specific solutions. There is the need to establish sustainable farm business models as a source of development for smallholders by reforming land tenure systems, increasing investment in locally relevant research and development, selective technology transfer, efficient extension services, and modern information systems, including extending the use of mobile phones more widely in rural areas. Building more sustainable farm systems, refocusing and improving rural livelihoods will require greater attention being paid to innovations in technology and practice targeting smallholders. Based on the findings of Ceres2030, an international research consortium assessing ways end hunger, agricultural research has neglected the needs of smallholders. Despite over 475 million of the 579 million or so farms in the world being estimated to be under two hectares in size, they are not at the core focus of research initiatives intended to improve agricultural practices. Recent estimates suggest that smallholders working on less than 2&#8239;ha of farmland produce 30&#8211;34% of the world's food while small to medium size farms (&lt; 50&#8239;ha) contribute 62&#8211;66% (<xref rid="bb0455" ref-type="bibr">Ricciardi et al., 2018</xref>). <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Herrero et al. (2017)</xref> report similar numbers and highlight the relevance of small and medium size farms for diverse agricultural production. The diversification of agricultural practices has shown to be important in enhancing the food security of farming households, among other factors (<xref rid="bb0615" ref-type="bibr">Waha et al., 2018</xref>). Improving access to more sustainable and resilient livelihoods and practices suited to smallholder farmers through targeted technical and financial assistance and strengthened institutional support structures should become a greater focus of both research and governance agendas, while also facilitating the transition to alternative, more secure livelihoods, where shifting economic and environmental conditions make this necessary.</p>