<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par40">Commercial agriculture drains aquifers (Basso et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2013</xref>) while extreme weather caused by global warming threatens multiple breadbasket failure (Gaupp et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2019</xref>). Commercial monocultures rely heavily on herbicides and chemical fertilizers that deplete soils (Armundson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2015</xref>), drive adaptive evolution in plants and weeds (Gould, Brown and Kuzma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2018</xref>), kill beneficial insects and pollinators (Woodcock et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2016</xref>), and contaminate water systems (Parris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2011</xref>). Petroleum-based fertilizers, alongside deforestation, soil depletion, industrial meat production, and global supply chains, make agriculture a major contributor to global warming (Tubiello et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2013</xref>; Amundson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2015</xref>). High-volume, high-speed industrial meat processing disproportionately pollutes poor and nonwhite communities (Wendee <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2013</xref>), causes unfathomable animal suffering, cultivates super bacteria, and facilitates animal to human contagion, making it a likely source of the next pandemic (Davis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2006</xref>; Croft et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2007</xref>; FAO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2013</xref>, Wallace et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2020</xref>). The first affected will be a hyper-exploited, primarily non-white, non-unionized workforce (Striffler <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2005</xref>; Stuesse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2016</xref>), including an overwhelming number of Indigenous Central American immigrants, who, like many farmers in the Global South, are displaced by political violence, transnational land grabs, the dumping of subsidized agricultural overproduction that undercuts subsistence agriculture, and by global warming (Copeland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2020</xref>). Meanwhile, US farmers face intense pressure from retail and agribusiness monopolies to cut prices, decreasing their profits and driving consolidation through the supply chain (Howard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2006</xref>; Moss and Taylor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2014</xref>; Hendrickson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2017</xref>).</p>