<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par7">Using online searches, our own personal networks of colleagues and snowballing (i.e. asking colleagues to recommend others working in this area), we developed a list of 360 potential stakeholders working on climate change and disaster risk reduction in the region (adaptation, mitigation, loss and damage, humanitarian responses). All 360 potential stakeholders were emailed to participate in this study, followed by two reminder emails to help garner a high response rate. Overall, we yielded 42 responses (13% response rate) across five target stakeholder groups in the sample (see Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Quantitative data were analysed using the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) (v27) and qualitative data were, using the NVivo software program, analysed through content analysis to capture key themes and storylines.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sample size of stakeholder groups and countries represented in the questionnaire</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Key informant stakeholder group</th><th align="left">Sample size (n-value)</th><th align="left">Respondent country of residence and work</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Government (local, national and regional)*</td><td char="." align="char">15</td><td align="left"><p>American Samoa, Cook Islands, Federated States of Micronesia, Fiji, New Zealand, Papua New Guinea,</p><p>Republic of Marshall Islands, Samoa, Solomon Islands</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Civil society (non-governmental organisations, faith-based organisations, community-based organisations, youth groups)</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left">Australia, Fiji, New Zealand, Samoa, Vanuatu</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Intergovernmental organisations inclusive of regional agencies</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td align="left">Fiji, Samoa, New Caledonia</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Donors and development partners</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left">Federated States of Micronesia, Fiji</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Relevant others (universities, student associations, research-based organisations, private sector)</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left">Australia, Cook Islands</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Three participants chose not to disclose their country of residence and work</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>