<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par55">For all-inclusive resilience to be achieved, it is pertinent to develop and implement long-term people-oriented plans. The following needs to be established to insulate economies and communities from future outbreaks:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par56">Supply chain resilience and circularity: Supporting local production closer to point of consumption can create new job opportunities, but efforts should be made to support industries and enterprises that would not increase environmental impacts, e.g. climate-smart agriculture, peri-urban vegetable production and animal rearing. Production systems that showed clear opportunity and innovation towards circularity could be supported. This could limit disruption and enhance resilience.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par57">Furthest behind first: National health insurance programmes should be restructured and reinforced to capture and cater to the health needs of different classes of society. State insurance schemes should be made to complement the national scheme. The social safety net needs to be overhauled considering challenges encountered during the pandemic to make it effective and efficient&#8212;data driven. A move away from just empowerment slogans to a robust innovation-driven entrepreneurial support framework is a must. The problem of housing needs to be addressed as the overcrowding, slums and informal settlements create viable contagion hotspots.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par58">Diversified growth and innovation hubs: The identification of potential opportunity zones across States and LGAs away from the traditional urban centres is necessary. Thus, creating new centres for innovations and economic development. As government revenue is under significant pressure such opportunity zones can improve IGR and support job creation. However, these would have to be supported by adequate infrastructures to connect them to established centres and create redundancies.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par59">Reorientate priorities: People-centred and socially responsible policies should drive the next stage of national development. The drive towards collective responsibility be reiterated, as we face climate change impacts, and the risk of another pandemic is imminent in the future. The need for movement away from business as usual is pertinent to building resilience, as various inadequacies of the current system were laid bare.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par60">Agile and responsive institution: Poor response and agility of many of Nigeria&#8217;s institutions imply that there are poorly prepared to handle unexpected situations. This was exemplified by the failure to prevent imported cases from entering the country. Responsive institutions would have anticipated points of failure and set up redundancies to mitigate such failures or address the point of failure as they were identified.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par61">Preparedness investment: The fatalistic attitude of Nigerian society often dissuades the prioritisation of prevention and preparedness. Thus, exacerbating losses and damages. This needs to change and to do that we need to invest more in preparedness and public education. Emergency management agencies should not be looked at as relief agencies, they must be actively working on risk reduction and preparedness planning. Most States and LGAs across the country do not have existing infrastructure to support preparedness planning. Whilst the national agency has provided various capacity-building exercises across these levels of government, the poor attitude is a major challenge to disaster risk reduction in Nigeria. There are inadequacies in ambulance and fire services across the nation. This can be attributed to the attitude towards prevention and preparedness. This attitude also dovetails into other areas where prevention and preparedness could save lives and properties.</p></list-item></list></p>