<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par59">The concepts and processes of decoloniality, degrowth and transformations are crucial for the radical changes, as argued above. Yet, each of these concepts and political agendas is highly susceptible to co-optation that leads to dilution of their radical ideas, followed by their absorption into the &#8216;ordinary&#8217;. This co-optation can, and usually happens from the outside&#8212;by actors who favour status quo (Coy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2013</xref>; Katz-Rosene and Paterson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2018</xref>; Stephens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">2020</xref>). Co-optation can also happen from the inside, and by the proponents themselves, when faced with a temptation for proliferating and mainstreaming their concepts and political agendas. While co-optation from the outside is the most dominant across all three concepts and political agendas, it currently appears to be the most extreme in the case of transformations, where the term is used to describe and therefore legitimize sociotechnical and eco-modernist solutions as &#8216;transformative&#8217; (Kruus and Hakala <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2017</xref>; Tome Valencia Hamilton and Ramcilovic-Suominen forthcoming; UNECE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">2012</xref>). Decoloniality, inter alia, appears to be prone to co-optation by often well-intended group of actors, including scholars, who may use the term without properly engaging the theory and previously published literature, and may end up reducing the term to a buzzword or a metaphor (Deschner and Hust <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Tuck and Yang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2012</xref>). Internal co-optation is highlighted as a potential risk to degrowth. As degrowth ideas start to gain wider popularity, including among policymakers, they tend to reduce degrowth to a toolbox for &#8220;broadening the sustainability debate (and for meeting EU&#8217;s) sustainability ambitions&#8221; (EEA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2021</xref>; p.&#160;2), largely omitting the sociocultural and justice dimensions of degrowth. Some scholars have noted that degrowth proponents in some cases flirt with policy approaches that can be considered rather reformist, statist, and non-heterodox, risking internal co-optation (Deschner and Hust <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Dunlap <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2021b</xref>; Garcia-Arias and Sch&#246;neberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2021</xref>).</p>