<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par60">As Tome Valencia Hamilton and Ramcilovic-Suominen (forthcoming in this Special Feature) argue, whether a certain political process or agenda is to result in radical transformations or not will depend not only on their foci and even outcomes but also on the nature of the process of change. Concerning the focus and outcomes, in this paper I have argued for a need of an all-encompassing change and reinvention across all dimensions&#8212;from onto-epistemological, to material, to political. The focus should be firmly on justice, race, colonial histories, inequalities, gender, class, and it should ensure that marginalized and colonised voices and concerns are not only attended to but are at the centre of the processes where problems are defined, and solutions designed and implemented. Such focus is a prerequisite not only for co-creating just alternatives and solutions, knowledge, and technologies but also a precondition for safeguarding against co-option by elite interests and actors. Concerning the process of change, as decoloniality, transformations and degrowth imply reshuffling and redistribution of power, wealth and privilege, the process ought to be messy, flexible, deeply democratic and locally owned. Direct democracy, local ownership, local autonomy, collective action and solidarity should be fiercely defended. As the protests for climate justice associated with the COP26 climate change conference in Glasgow bear witness to, it is becoming clear to an increasing number of people that, in the words of the COP26 Coalition for Climate Justice: &#8220;The transformative solutions that we need in order to survive and build a more just and fairer world can only be brought about through collective action, solidarity and coordination, from our local communities to international levels&#8221; (@COP26_Coalition twitter account, tweet 6.11.2021).</p>