<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par37">Indicators of HDI are life expectancy at birth, expected and mean years of schooling, and gross national income (GNI) per capita (UNDP, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2020</xref>). Life expectancy quite neatly translates to the capability &#8216;Life&#8217;, defined as &#8216;being able to live to the end of a human life of normal length&#8217; or &#8216;not dying prematurely&#8217; (Nussbaum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2006</xref>: 76). While not equivalent to expected and mean years of schooling, education is included in the capability &#8216;Senses, imagination, and thought&#8217;, which stresses the ability to use these faculties in &#8216;a way informed and cultivated by an adequate education, including, but by no means limited to, literacy and basic mathematical and scientific training&#8217; (Nussbaum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2006</xref>: 76). The category &#8216;a decent standard of living&#8217; is reduced to a single economic measure. Such a measure has no obvious correlation with the capabilities but may refer to the agency and capacity to choose that permeates and motivates the capabilities. However, this means that there are many of the capabilities that Nussbaum mentions that are not included in the HDI, which may speak to the limitation of the HDI rather than be a limitation of the CA. Despite the above, the HDI could be helpful for understanding the relationship between per capita energy consumption and at least some of the dimensions of human well-being that are necessary for living a life worthy of human dignity. Strengthening the relation between HDI and capabilities is how HDI primarily was originated by Sen (Gasper, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2002</xref>: 444). Sen focus on the CA as prerequisites for functionings, the choices that people make, and HDI is meant as an indicator for a good life (Gasper, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2002</xref>: 444).</p>