<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par38">Both HDI and CA have the strengths of avoiding many of the problems associated with other theories concerning the currency of justice, such as welfarist accounts that was described above. Being based on preference satisfaction, welfarist accounts need not give precedence to those that are below a certain level, for several reasons. First, it may theoretically be the case that the preferences of those below the threshold are satisfied, due to those preferences being adapted to what is realistically achievable in harsh conditions (see Page, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2007</xref>: 455). Second, those above the threshold may be less well-off than they could be, which would justify increasing their already substantial consumption of energy. This is a variation of the &#8216;expensive tastes&#8217; problem (Crisp, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2003</xref>) and of &#8216;luxury emissions&#8217; (Shue, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2014</xref> [1993]). Given that the relation between energy consumption and HDI has the shape of a diminishing marginal utility, it is likely that this would require substantial increases in energy consumption to increase preference satisfaction. This is similar to satisfying the preferences of someone who has cultivated expensive tastes in food and wine. In contrast, which adds to its reasonableness as a theory of justice, the CA would restrict its focus to those that are below the threshold, and when supplemented with ceilings would exclude the moral relevance of &#8216;luxury&#8217; preferences and when satisfaction would be at the expense of those below the threshold. In contrast, preferences are adaptive to poor conditions, and focusing too narrowly on preference satisfaction may be inconsistent with the demands of justice (Nussbaum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2006</xref>; Sen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1999</xref>). The CA is more consistent with fulfilling the demands of justice in this regard, as it avoids the problem of adaptive and aggregative preferences.</p>