<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0340">Livestock farming systems use approximately 40% of the agricultural land (<xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Mottet et al., 2017</xref>). Their transformation into integrated crop-livestock systems can play an essential role in the farming system's circularity since animals are fed with grass (biomass), which cannot be utilized in alternative ways, and improve soil fertility via manure (<xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr">Van Zanten et al., 2019</xref>). The reform of the agricultural supply chains should promote &#8220;One Health&#8221; principles to eliminate the risks related to antibiotic resistance, control diseases that spread between animals and humans like (COVID-19 or flu), secure food safety, and reduce greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions (<xref rid="bb0300" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2017</xref>). Besides, start-ups and existing businesses developing innovative products that redefine our consumption norms (e.g., plant-based proteins and other meat alternatives) are expected to grow their market shares over the next years (<xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Galanakis et al., 2021</xref>). The fortification of foods with bioactive ingredients to consumers' immune system could also be a great opportunity (<xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Galanakis, 2020</xref>), and the recovery of these compounds is nowadays conducted in the context of bioeconomy, valorizing sources like food processing by-products, fungi, and yeasts<sup>1</sup>. The &#8220;blue bioeconomy&#8221; could comprise a vital alternative to land-based animal feed and food. As the possibility of expanding the current fish supply remains limited, a sustainable &#8220;intensification&#8221; could come from aquaculture, e.g., microalgae cultivation and the development of multitrophic systems (<xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Rowan and Galanakis, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Fritsche et al., 2020</xref>).</p>