<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">These policy assumptions and implications are broad; they are made somewhat more specific in the tabulated format (IPCC, <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, pp. 751&#8211;752: Table 7.7), the highlights of which are as follows:
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p><italic toggle="yes">Assumption:</italic> Insecure land rights are one factor deterring adaptation and accentuating vulnerability. Specific dimensions of inequity in customary systems may act as constraints on adaptation in different contexts. LSLAs may be associated with monoculture and other unsustainable land use practices, have negative consequences for soil degradation and disincentivize more sustainable forms of agriculture.</p></disp-quote>
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p><italic toggle="yes">Implications:</italic> Secure land rights, including through customary systems, can incentivize farmers to adopt long-term climate-smart practices, e.g. planting trees in mixed cropland/forest systems. Landscape governance and resource tenure reforms at farm and community levels can facilitate and incentivize planning for landscape management and enable the integration of adaptation and mitigation strategies.</p></disp-quote>
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p><italic toggle="yes">Assumption</italic>: Land tenure security can lead to improved adaptation outcomes, but land tenure policy for forests that focuses narrowly on cultivation has limited ability to reduce ecological vulnerability or enhance adaptation. Secure rights to land and forest resources can facilitate efforts to stabilize shifting cultivation and promote more sustainable resource use if appropriate technical and market support are available.</p></disp-quote>
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p><italic toggle="yes">Implications</italic>: Land tenure insecurity has been identified as a key driver of deforestation and land degradation leading to loss of sinks and creating sources of greenhouse gases. While land tenure systems interact with land-based mitigation actions in complex ways, forest decentralization and community co-management have shown considerable success in slowing forest loss and contributing to carbon mitigation. Communal tenure systems may lower transaction costs for REDD+ schemes, though with risk of elite capture of payments.</p></disp-quote>
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p><italic toggle="yes">Assumption</italic>: Many pastoralists in lands at risk from desertification do not have secure land tenure, and erosion of traditional communal rangeland tenure has been identified as a determinant of increasing vulnerability to drought and climate change and as a driver of dryland degradation.</p></disp-quote>
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p><italic toggle="yes">Implications</italic>: Where pastoralists&#8217; traditional land use does not have legal recognition, or where pastoralists are unable to exclude others from land use, this presents significant challenges for carbon sequestration initiatives. Carbon sequestration initiatives on rangelands may require clarification and maintenance of land rights.</p></disp-quote></p>