<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">To further complicate matters, plastic is not a straightforward material to dispose of responsibly. A range of different polymers are used and often combined, along with chemical additives, to make different kinds of plastics with specific material properties, and not all of these plastics can effectively be recycled (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_011" ref-type="bibr">Bucknall 2020</xref>). Even those which theoretically could be recycled are often not, due to local logistical and economical constraints (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_011" ref-type="bibr">Bucknall 2020</xref>). Citizens commonly report difficulty in knowing which items are recyclable&#160;&#8211; in the UK, this can vary even from one city to the next&#160;&#8211; and indeed cannot know for certain whether their efforts will ensure that the waste is eventually recycled (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_033" ref-type="bibr">INCPEN 2021</xref>). Even when plastics are successfully recycled, the quality of the plastic is reduced with each iteration. This depends crucially on the type of plastic; for example, 100% recycled polyethylene terephthalate (PET) can be used in a closed loop if the plastic is upgraded at each stage, whereas polyolefins (polyethylene and polypropylene) need the addition of virgin polymer at every recycling event so that properties are maintained (see <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_015" ref-type="bibr">Eriksen et&#160;al. 2019</xref>). A life-cycle assessment, the calculation of all of the environmental impacts associated with a product, from its manufacturing to its disposal, may also rule out recycling as the most ecological option for a particular kind of plastic waste product (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_091" ref-type="bibr">Walker and Rothman 2020</xref>). Beyond all of these material limitations, the story that recycling promotes&#160;&#8211; that single-use products are largely redeemable, and that disposing of them is unproblematic&#160;&#8211; does not serve to challenge our over-production and over-consumption of single-use plastics and plastic packaging. In short, recycling is not enough.</p>