<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par2">With respect to young children, the UNSDG 4 <italic>Ensure inclusive and equitable quality education and promote lifelong learning opportunities for all</italic> is in a very direct way linked to the provision of early childhood education and care for all children as well as to the right for all children to have equal access to quality education. Further, UNSDG 4 does also include the right to sustainable education i.e., education that contributes to a more just and sustainable world. A recent initiative to strengthen the work on UNSDG 4 in the realm of education for young children, is the <italic>Global Partnership Strategy for Early Childhood (GPS) 2021&#8211;2030</italic> (UNESCO, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2021a</xref>). The GPS was launched after close collaboration with researchers, NGOs, UNICEF, WHO and the World Bank. Its overall aim is for countries and partners to make it their highest priority to invest in early childhood education and care (ECEC) services by 2030. Further, the GPS encourages them to recommit on their earlier promise and to ensure that ECEC is fully inclusive, accessible, affordable, gender-responsive, equitable and developmentally appropriate for each child. This promise mainly relates specifically to UNSDG Target 4.2 and includes 5 key strategies: (1) evidence for action and rights; (2) data, monitoring and evaluation for accountability; (3) scaling-up access, inclusion, equity and quality; (4) strengthened policy, governance, financing and advocacy; (5) international and national coordination and cooperation. There is also a proposal to lobby for a United Nations&#8217; decade for ECEC. With respect to the magnitude of the sustainability challenges we are now facing, it could be argued that the GPS should address children&#8217;s rights to early childhood education for sustainability (ECEfS). ECEC should be permeated by efforts that provide opportunities for all children to develop values, attitudes, understandings, and skills that contribute to their resilience, for instance their capacity to handle the changes and challenges in terms of climate change, loss of biodiversity, depletion of natural resources as well as the multiple economic, social, and cultural injustices that need to be addressed in order for a more sustainable world to actually come into realisation and for the intentions of <italic>Agenda 2030</italic> to be met. &#196;rlemalm-Hags&#233;r and Pramling Samuelsson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2021</xref>) show in a case study with an experienced ECEC teacher how the ECEC teacher&#8217;s knowledge and skills about sustainability and the SDGs, as well about how to implement the knowledge as part of the pedagogical practices with children, is crucial.</p>