<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0050">Women all over the world face major barriers to adequately meet their livelihoods. But nowhere is this problem more pronounced than in rural agricultural areas of developing countries. Besides land ownership and user rights constraints, women are likely to struggle more with accessing input, technology and innovation, markets and services (<xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2011</xref>). Hence, widespread ongoing development interventions in an attempt to tackle these issues. Notwithstanding the current efforts, significant work in these areas remains. The Millennium Development Goal (MDG) 3: <italic>Promote Gender Equality and Empower Women</italic>, which defined efforts to tackle gender inequality in the 2000s and early part of the last decade are considered to have made little progress. Furthermore, literature indicates that this MDG agenda narrowly focused on access to education, in numerical terms, leaving out critical issues such as economic discrimination, gender-based violence, reproductive health, and access to essential resources, such as affordable water (<xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Fehling et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0395" ref-type="bibr">Mohindra and Niki&#233;ma, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0375" ref-type="bibr">Langford, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Eyben, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bb0505" ref-type="bibr">Subrahmanian, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Kabeer, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Attaran, 2005</xref>). Presently, notable progress has been made through the fifth goal of the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs). Nevertheless, gender inequality challenges persist even in the advanced economies (<xref rid="bb0535" ref-type="bibr">UN, 2021c</xref>; <xref rid="bb0515" ref-type="bibr">UN, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bb0335" ref-type="bibr">IISD, 2019</xref>). Among others, discriminatory laws and social norms, political underrepresentation, gender-based physical and sexual violence remain visible. Specific barriers that women continue to face with respect to local food systems and food security needs are discussed below.</p>