<p>We are aware of a geopolitical turn in social work education and the need for urgent
responses to a changing climate and the adverse and ongoing devastating impacts of climate
change on human well-being and livelihoods in countries throughout the world. These approaches
recognize the interconnections between social work and the natural environment in definitions
and agendas (see <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">IFSW, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Truell and Jones, 2015</xref>) and integrate critical awareness, knowledge and
impetus to pursue social and environmental action into social work education. As educators, we
are interested in current theoretical developments in social work that seek shifts at the
ontological level and are beginning to re-shape fundamental practice understandings. These
approaches include Heather <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Boetto&#8217;s transformative
ecosocial work model (2017)</xref> and Indigenist ontologies (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Martin, 2008</xref>) that are characterized by understandings of the
interdependence of humans and the natural world, and community sustainability. We define
sustainability in a community development context as working with people at local, regional and
global levels to reconnect, restore, repair and regenerate life-sustaining global ecosystems
which are vital to support health, well-being, empowerment and the livelihoods of communities
(<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Lynch, 2020</xref>). Ecosocial approaches are beginning to
influence social work interventions, driven by practitioner awareness and connection to the
environment at personal and political levels (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Boetto
<italic toggle="yes">et&#160;al</italic>., 2020</xref>). While actions remain at individual level, this
movement foreshadows collective responses to tackle environmental injustices at group,
community, structural and policy levels. Aligned with this new emphasis on ecosocial work
models and the role of social workers in environmental practices with communities, we
incorporate practice scenarios in the classroom. For example, we discuss a scenario where a
rural social worker engages with members of the community to explore their deep concerns about
changes in the environment. The social worker provides support to a community group formed to
research how the biodiversity of their region could be restored (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Ramsay and Boddy, 2017</xref>). Another contemporary example for use in the
classroom is the Australian &#8216;Buy from the Bush&#8217; campaign which connects people
living in urban and rural communities to support economic sustainability (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Buy from the Bush Queensland, 2018</xref>). In this way, we aim to pursue a
critical pedagogy which draws on contemporary themes and instils collaborative thinking and
deep critical inquiry as well as reflective praxis enriched by contemporary research, practice
and theory into the social work curriculum.</p>