<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">While IoT-based sensing techniques are available for improving precision agriculture, optimizing these ideas with blockchain technologies might offer even more robust results. Patil et al. [<xref rid="B45-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] noted that IoT-based sensing technologies might sometimes be flawed on the grounds of; extremely large scale, a lack of homogeneity of different IoT-based sensing operations, as well as standardization. This meant that the data gathered using IoT-based sensing technologies comes with privacy concerns for the farmer [<xref rid="B45-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Hence, the researchers developed a blockchain greenhouse farming tool to cater to security and privacy. The model is made up of a smart greenhouse (a covered piece of farmland protected from environmental conditions) that comprises a series of sensors and actuators, smart hub (a local blockchain which manages the connectivity of all sensors and equipment in the smart greenhouse); an overlay network connection that manages the nodes; a cloud storage platform and an end-user platform. A system of this nature addresses security challenges across all fronts within the farm [<xref rid="B45-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In another Blockchain-based smart agricultural study [<xref rid="B46-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], a traceability platform for food safety was designed. In collaboration with the Internet of Things, the system involved &#8220;Enterprise Resource Planning&#8221; where farmers, processing plants, and organizations involved in the logistics of agricultural and food products, and the consumers, can assess on their mobile phones, a blockchain node that gives detailed description of how the products were cultivated, harvested, stored, processed, and sold [<xref rid="B46-sensors-20-05977" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The essence of this technique was to build virtual trust in food processing, using the so-called <italic>Trusted Trade Blockchain Network Cloud Platform (TTBNCP)</italic></p>