<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par67">The following conclusions are gathered from the NDC analysis:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par68">High-income countries (countries from the EU27 and Israel) should review their first NDC by considerably increasing their ambition in order to align it with the 1.5&#160;&#176;C goal. These countries have GDPs per capita that are higher than the region&#8217;s average and can support their capacity for ambitious mitigation. The revision of the EU27 NDC presented in December 2020 is an important step in order to regain leadership on climate change mitigation and to set an example for the international community. However, to assess the impact that the updated NDC will have at the Mediterranean level, we will have to wait until the EU27 carries out a new distribution of emissions reduction among its member countries.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par69">At a Mediterranean level, cooperation strategies should be launched in order to achieve conditional commitments that figure in the NDCs of countries such as Algeria, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Lebanon, Morocco, and Tunisia. This would enable those that are not aligned with the 1.5&#160;&#176;C goal to achieve this target and will also help the whole regional group to move towards this direction.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par70">Turkey, which has a future emissions budget similar to the historical one, has a not very ambitious NDC that consumes almost the entirety of it. The country should rethink its development model in order to reach the peak of emissions as soon as possible and then start a transition to a low emission model.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par71">Albania, Egypt, Morocco, and Syria are countries that in 2030 will not have consumed the 40% of the emissions budget assigned to them by the MCJ, and therefore they are in line with the 1.5&#160;&#176;C goal. It is important that they manage this budget properly in order to make it available to their development agenda and, in this way, achieve a coordinated implementation of their climate change and adaptation policies together with their sustainable development agenda.</p></list-item></list></p>