<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0030">Climate change, sea level rise (SLR), and increasing extreme events have brought climate-migration and managed retreat to the epicenter of global adaptation debates and disaster risk reduction policies. An extensive literature review shows these two concepts are used interchangeably with variations ranging from planned retreat, planned relocation, climate migration, climate resettlement, managed relocation, managed migration, assisted migration, climate relocation, and climate-displacement (<xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Farbotko and Lazrus, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Ferris, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Bukvic et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Collins et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Ajibade, 2019</xref>). Of these different concepts, the two dominant ones that emerged from academic databases and an evaluation of existing literature are climate migration (CM) and managed retreat (MR). To date, there is no consensus on the meaning of CM or MR. According to <xref rid="b0640" ref-type="bibr">Wilkinson et al. (2016)</xref> climate-induced migration implies four different patterns of mobilities: (i) people displaced by climate-related disasters who move temporarily; (ii) people forced to migrate more permanently due to recurrent events; (iii) people forced to migrate due to greater environmental degradation and (iv) people who &#8220;choose&#8221; to move as an adaptation strategy in response to environmental or others pressures. This definition encompasses a myriad of environmentally-motivated mobilities yet the lived experiences of those that migrate and those resettled through managed retreat programs are radically different. While both CM and MR suggest displacements caused by climate-related risks, this paper aims to untangle the relationship between them. Based on a critical review of 150 journal articles and grey materials published between 2000 and 2020, we identify six key differences between CM and MR. We do this not only for the sake of conceptual clarity and planning purposes, but to inspire researchers, practitioners, journalists, and advocates working on these issues to better serve their constituencies through building stronger alliances, mobilizing resources from appropriate agencies, and campaigning for social, environmental and climate justice using the right language targeted at the right audience.</p>