<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para200">Lockdowns and restrictions to human movement have had diverse effects, with consequences for biodiversity and ecosystems. On the one hand, they have reduced tourism pressure in many areas, but on the other hand, they have simultaneously disrupted important environmental conservation programmes.<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr"><sup>68</sup></xref> For example, the Australian Antarctic Division experienced COVID-19-related project delays, reduced capacity to train and deploy expedition teams,<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr"><sup>69</sup></xref> and scaled back their 2020&#8211;21 summer expedition, potentially undermining the realisation of research goals.<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr"><sup>70</sup></xref> These changes came as Antarctica's 2019&#8211;20 summer temperatures were substantially above average,<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr"><sup>71</sup></xref> concluding the Earth's hottest decade ever recorded.<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref> This disruption and similar other interferences could compromise the accuracy and continuity of climate research that is required to both guide and measure progress on reducing greenhouse emissions, and impede mitigation of climate change's effects on disease emergence.<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref> Although economic shutdowns initially led to some significant reductions in air pollution and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions around the world,<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref> emissions declined less than expected by climate researchers and rose substantially again as 2020 progressed.<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr"><sup>76</sup></xref> A continued surge of activity aimed at economic recovery as social lockdowns and economic shutdowns are relaxed could probably negate the benefits of a short pause in human activity unless managed correctly.<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref>
</p>