<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In response to the requirements of climate change mitigation and adaptation that have relevance to land, and partly in recognition of global land grabs as a key context, the IPCC report summarizes its essential points on land tenure, pointing out the way forward, as follows:
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p>Land tenure systems have implications for both adaptation and mitigation, which need to be understood within specific socio-economic and legal contexts, and may themselves be impacted by climate change and climate action (<italic toggle="yes">limited evidence, high agreement</italic>). Land policy (in a diversity of forms beyond focus on freehold title) can provide routes to land security and facilitate or constrain climate action, across cropping, rangeland, forest, fresh-water ecosystems and other systems. Large-scale land acquisitions are an important context for the relations between tenure security and climate change, but their scale, nature and implications are imperfectly understood. (IPCC, <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, p. 677)</p></disp-quote>
<disp-quote specific-use="block"><p>Insecure land tenure affects the ability of people, communities and organisations to make changes to land that can advance adaptation and mitigation (<italic toggle="yes">medium confidence</italic>). Limited recognition of customary access to land and ownership of land can result in increased vulnerability and decreased adaptive capacity (<italic toggle="yes">medium confidence</italic>). Land policies (including recognition of customary tenure, community mapping, redistribution, decentralisation, co-management, regulation of rental markets) can provide both security and flexibility response [<italic toggle="yes">sic</italic>] to climate change (<italic toggle="yes">medium confidence</italic>). (IPCC, <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, p. 29)</p></disp-quote></p>