<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> is a Venn diagram which visually pulls together the key findings in relation to the first research question &#8211; the strategies women develop to participate in innovation processes as individuals and through organisations. It depicts the key actors and their interrelationships with each other. The points at which boundaries overlap show where information-sharing on wheat&#8211;maize innovations is occurring. This is shown to be a strongly gendered process. The woman-dominated Kalipara Union Federation lies at the centre of the diagram. Its presence is decisive to the ability of women to develop and realise their strategies. The Kalipara Union Federation is an effective mechanism for RDRS with its male extension officers to train women in women-only groups in wheat&#8211;maize innovations. Santal women have been the primary beneficiaries. They have profited because they are strongly involved in all aspects of field crop agriculture, are physically mobile and because they have demanded inclusion. The success of Santal women has in turn inspired some low-income Muslim women to become members of the Kalipara Union Federation and to be trained in wheat&#8211;maize innovations themselves. That is to say, women who have been ethnically marginalised and those who have been marginalised due to their poverty have interests in common. Joytee, the Santal woman president, is an inspirational role model for such women. The least successful would-be participants in innovation processes are middle-income Muslim women. Their desire for training in wheat&#8211;maize innovations has yet to be met due to lack of support from male family members &#8211; though a few of such women receive training on vegetable production and other forms of income generation at the Kalipara Union Federation. This suggests that cultural norms rather than ethnic identity shape their opportunities. <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> further shows that RDRS interacts directly with middle-income Muslim and Santal men, and only very marginally with low-income Santal and Muslim men. Potential information-sharing relationships between low- and middle-income women and men were not explored in this study and are thus not depicted.
<fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Key actors and institutional relationships, partly shaped by strategies women develop to access and participate in wheat&#8211;maize innovation processes.</p><p>Source: The authors. Note: RDRS: Rangpur Dinajpur Rural Service.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="RCJD_A_1650332_F0001_OC"/></fig></p>