<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par56">There is growing emphasis on the role of SBTs to decarbonize the private sector as part of global effort to achieve the temperature goal of the Paris Agreement. The emerging body of literature related to existing company engagement with SBTs (lens 1) shows a relationship between company engagement with SBTs and prior experience reporting emissions, setting internal targets and achieving emission reductions; SBT-setting companies on average are setting higher percentage emission reduction targets than internal target-setting companies (but perhaps over a longer timeframe), reporting increased investment towards emission reductions and making progress towards achieving scope 1 and 2 SBTs; evidence of both symbolic and substantive action; and lacking engagement from the largest emitting companies. Definitive conclusions are hindered by current incomplete and inconsistent corporate disclosures. Additional research is needed to understand the mechanisms linking emission reporting and internal target-setting and achievement to SBT setting, distinguish between symbolic and substantive SBT adoption, identify investments and actions that lead to SBT progress, assess companies&#8217; ability to achieve SBTs in the long-term, understand the extent to which companies can influence and monitor scope 3 SBT achievement, and perhaps most importantly, understand the specific barriers to SBT adoption by high-emitting companies and companies in underrepresented regions. This will require access to standardized, transparent corporate disclosure on targets, investments, and progress as well as rigorous hypothesis formulation and testing to understand the specific drivers, barriers, and outcomes of SBT engagement. Moreover, there is a lot to gain from more diversity in methodological approaches including both qualitative (e.g., interview-based or ethnographic approaches) and mixed methods research.</p>