<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par21">Many of these mobilisation case examples are embedded in established social movement industries and, importantly, are not outside the scale of mobilisations seen in pre-internet youthled movements during the Cold War. In similar &#8220;existential&#8221; issues of concern for young people (such as anti-conscription in the 1970s or anti-nuclear movements of the 1980s), mobilisation of youth movements was significant, pre-internet. An alternative hypothesis is that we can see this as part of the routine, periodical &#8220;cycle of contention&#8221; of post-war youth mobilisations in which &#8220;good, decent, little people&#8221; with an apparent distrust towards establishment rally against the &#8220;corrupt and evil forces from above whose policies are responsible for their pain and suffering&#8221; (Kazin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1998</xref>). Equally, we could argue that established collective action theory might be hierarchically higher than social media-specific theorising in explaining case examples, as it provides a better-substantiated explanation of a greater number of recurrent phenomena. Further, the basic premises of the existence of a &#8220;deficit&#8221; have been challenged. Collin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2015</xref>), for example, argues that claims about youth disengagement are exaggerated. She points to volunteering and social movement participation rates as correctives to reliance on &#8220;formal&#8221; institutional measures of (dis)engagement. While longitudinal data on social media and volunteering in Australia is scarce and unreliable (Walsh and Black <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>), internationally, there is evidence that increased volunteering rates pre-date widespread internet adoption and may be associated with motivations like experience-gathering to enhance employability or college entry (Jones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2000</xref>). Again, membership and volunteering may now be afforded via online channels, but this does not demonstrate a causal connection between the means and social practice. Lastly, flexible definitions of participation serve as a correction of the institutionally oriented &#8220;democratic decline&#8221; literature by expanding what political participation looks like. They do so by recognising a shift towards informality in terms of participation in the public sphere (&#8220;everyday making&#8221;; Bang and S&#248;rensen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1999</xref>).</p>