<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par8">The existing scholarly work has identified a number of domestic and international factors that impact China&#8217;s climate practices, including economic growth (Ong <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2012</xref>), energy security (Conrad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>), severe air pollution and environmental problems (Schreurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2016</xref>), international reputation and image (Belis and Schunz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2013</xref>), the &#8216;New Normal&#8217; of economic development (Dong <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2017</xref>; Hilton and Kerr <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2017</xref>), technological innovation and development in renewable energy (Heggelund <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2021</xref>) and the changing international negotiating context (Tiberghien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2018</xref>). All these factors and their interplay have indeed contributed to China&#8217;s changing climate practices. This article does not negate the importance of these factors in understanding China&#8217;s presence in global climate governance. But this article will show that the qualitative change in China&#8217;s international role as transpires from the case of global climate governance is also related to China&#8217;s changing construction of its international identity. In international studies, constructivists stress that one cannot comprehensively understand a state&#8217;s foreign policy behaviours without taking identity into account, and argue that identity can mediate and shape a state&#8217;s understanding about international issues (such as global climate governance) and can shape, enable and constrain the state&#8217;s policy behaviours (Wendt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1999</xref>). A state&#8217;s foreign policy can be seen as its identity constructing performance (Messari <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2001</xref>: 235&#8211;237). Many existing studies that focus on material circumstances treat China&#8217;s changing climate practices as a mechanical act of rational adaptation to its domestic and external material circumstances, thus missing the meaning and implication of how China communicates itself to the world. In addition, the importance of China&#8217;s presence in promoting justice in the climate governance regime is also neglected (Stalley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2013</xref>).</p>