<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par38">Following previous research on political attitudes among protesters and in the climate movement more specifically (e.g. Emilsson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2020</xref>; Wahlstr&#246;m et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2013</xref>; Wahlstr&#246;m et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2019</xref>), the analyses control for basic personal characteristics including age, gender, education and left&#8211;right placement. Age is particularly important considering the youthfulness of FFF and was accordingly recoded to distinguish those below the age of 20 from those above. Education was firstly coded following the international ISCED categorization and then recoded to &#8216;low&#8217;, &#8216;middle&#8217; and &#8216;high&#8217;. Left&#8211;right self-placement was measured on a scale ranging from 0 (left) to 10 (right). Unsurprisingly, the participants overwhelmingly placed themselves to the left. To capture meaningful differences, the variable was therefore recoded into &#8216;far left&#8217; (0&#8211;2), &#8216;centre left&#8217; (3&#8211;5), &#8216;right&#8217; (6&#8211;10), and a category for those who indicated that they did not know or found the distinction meaningless. Furthermore, previous experience with environmental or climate protest was included, as experienced activists may over time develop different beliefs regarding for instance the likely successfulness of mitigation. Political efficacy, or the belief that one can make a difference in politics, is also included to control for the possibility that a more general sense of fatalism (the opposite of efficacy) leads to a preference for adaptation. This item was measured with a rescaled sum-variable of the following three statements that respondents rated from &#8216;strongly disagree&#8217; (1) to &#8216;strongly agree&#8217; (5): &#8216;My participation can have an impact on public policy in this country&#8217;; &#8216;Organized groups of citizens can have a lot of impact on public policies in this country&#8217;; &#8216;If citizens from different countries join forces, they can have a lot of impact on international politics&#8217;. All items load more than 0.59 on the same factor in an exploratory factor analysis, and the resulting factor has high reliability (Cronbach&#8217;s alpha&#8201;=&#8201;0.76). Finally, a dummy variable was added to distinguish European and non-European demonstrations. While the European cities in our study have only been exposed to relatively mild climate impacts, inhabitants of New York and Sydney have been exposed to more serious climate-related impacts like hurricanes (e.g. Hurricane Sandy, 2012) and forest fires (e.g. the widespread bushfires in 2019&#8211;2020). Such immediacy may have affected attitudes towards adaptation.</p>