<p>Scientists who study companion animal&#8211;human interactions are also well-suited to contribute to conversations regarding climate change. Working toward sustainable climate mitigation and adaptation strategies requires us to engage in whole-systems thinking rather than focus on individual components (<xref rid="icab025-B138" ref-type="bibr">Stephen 2021</xref>). Strengthening the ability for researchers to be &#8220;specialized generalists&#8221; that are capable of bringing both specialized knowledge of their field as well as a significant capacity to collaborate with other fields is necessary for climate resiliency research (<xref rid="icab025-B112" ref-type="bibr">Parkes 2021</xref>). Companion animal scientists are already &#8220;specialized generalists,&#8221; with most studying both biological sciences as well as the social aspects of the human&#8211;animal relationship. Researchers who study companion animals have backgrounds in many different kinds of disciplines, ranging from animal and veterinary science (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B151" ref-type="bibr">Van Haaften et al. 2017</xref>), psychology (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B160" ref-type="bibr">Wynne 2016</xref>), biology (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B91" ref-type="bibr">Lindblad-Toh et al. 2005</xref>), anthropology (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B96" ref-type="bibr">MacLean et al. 2017</xref>), public health (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B13" ref-type="bibr">Bauman et al. 2001</xref>), nursing (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B11" ref-type="bibr">Banks et al. 2008</xref>), and even archeology and biogeography (e.g., <xref rid="icab025-B86" ref-type="bibr">Larson et al. 2012</xref>), among many others. And many companion animal focused conferences bring together differing disciplines. In fact, companion animal scientists are embracing the One Health and/or One Welfare framework, which recognizes the connection between humans, animals, and the environment (<xref rid="icab025-B142" ref-type="bibr">Sykes et al. 2020</xref>). This interdisciplinary and holistic framework identifies that multiple systems are intrinsically linked and interventions must be understood as part of a whole&#8212;wherein improving the health/well-being of one of the three facets ultimately improves the others (<xref rid="icab025-B116" ref-type="bibr">Pinillos et al. 2016</xref>). As such, companion animal scientists may already be experienced in systems thinking and collaborations across disciplines in their work, positioning them well for incorporating climate change complexities into their research.</p>