<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Young people also play a fundamental role in scrutinizing and pushing for transparency in government and private sector climate change governance, including fossil fuel subsidies and investments. For example, many young people are voicing their concerns over the rise of &#8220;greenwashing&#8221;: marketing something as environmentally friendly, with no certification, while continuing to engage in polluting activities, such as investing in fossil fuels. In January 2021, using Tik Tok and Instagram, more than 300,000 youth activists denounced Procter and Gamble&#8217;s Charmin toilet paper brand for its &#8220;greenwashing&#8221; sustainability claims while the company continues to contribute to deforestation and the violation of Canadian indigenous peoples&#8217; rights.<sup><xref rid="r65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup> Similarly, young Norwegians have been vocal about their government&#8217;s double standards: on the one hand, the Norwegian government praises itself for its climate change pledges (such as to become carbon neutral by 2030 and its role as a major donor of the Green Climate Fund, which supports climate-related efforts in LMICs), while on the other hand it continues to subsidize oil and gas extraction in Norwegian waters and sell fossil fuels abroad.<sup><xref rid="r66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup> Young leaders of the Nature and Youth group have called for an end to the Norwegian government&#8217;s support to the fossil fuel industry and for divestment in its sovereign wealth fund.<sup><xref rid="r67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup> The UN Secretary-General&#8217;s Youth Advisory Group on Climate Change has also warned against the risk of &#8220;greenwashing&#8221; in the use of COVID-19 financial recovery funds destined for green transition plans, given that there is &#8220;no internationally agreed taxonomy of green jobs.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="r68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup></p>