<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0100">Today, the world is struggling with a sudden crisis: the COVID-19 pandemic, whose effects have been felt in every country - developed and developing. The pandemic is known to have &#8216;[...] resulted in immediate, serious, and worldwide human health issues&#8217; (<xref rid="bb0500" ref-type="bibr">Stephens et al., 2020</xref>). In addition, it is widely reported to be having major implications on agriculture, food systems and global food security (<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Carducci et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Barrett, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0500" ref-type="bibr">Stephens et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Galanakis, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Bakalis et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Aday and Aday, 2020</xref>). The World <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Bank (2021)</xref> informs that the pandemic has led to a dramatic rise in the number of those that are acutely food insecure in 2020&#8211;2021. An estimated 272 million people are already or are at risk of becoming acute food-insecure (<xref rid="bb5000" ref-type="bibr">WFP, 2021b</xref>). Based on the State of the World Food and Nutrition Security Report 2021, &#8216;the prevalence of undernourishment increased from 8.4 to around 9.9 percent in just one year&#8217; (<xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2021</xref>). Among the COVID-19 pandemic's effects that may have led to these challenges are &#8216;[...] movement restrictions of workers, changes in demand of consumers, closure of food production facilities, restricted food trade policies, and financial pressures in the food supply chain&#8217; (<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Aday and Aday, 2020</xref>). In the low- and middle-income countries, the pandemic has caused major disruption in the domestic supply chains (<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Carducci et al., 2021</xref>). Consequently, this has had a profound impact on food security of individuals, especially women, who largely depend on agri-food supply chains for their livelihoods (<xref rid="bb0400" ref-type="bibr">Montalvao and van de Velde, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr">Headey and Ruel, 2020</xref>). Based on <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">CARE (2020c)</xref>, the pandemic induced global food crisis has disproportionately affected women and girls. Among others, they have experienced many challenges, including increased unpaid labour, incidences of gender-based restrictions i.e. reduced mobility, higher rates of gender-based violence, and unintended pregnancies. In certain instances, it has been warned that economic shocks and related food insecurity will result in girls being pulled out of schools to help at home or married off early to relieve the family of another child to feed (<xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2020</xref>). Some research have called for a feminist response to COVID-19 impact (food insecurity therein) on women, given the obvious effects of the existing gendered inequalities during a crisis (<xref rid="bb0350" ref-type="bibr">Jessica and Priscilla, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0435" ref-type="bibr">Oxfam, 2021</xref>).</p>