<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para40">Here, we examined 48 new or updated NDCs (as of Dec 31, 2020) for their inclusion of COVID-19, representing 75 (40%) of the 191 parties to the Paris Agreement and accounting for about 30% of global greenhouse gas emissions.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> COVID-19 was referenced in 42% NDCs. Based on content analysis, various recurring themes and entry points were discussed in relation to COVID-19 recovery and climate commitments, including altered ambitions, gendered impacts, and human wellbeing (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">table</xref>). However, most governments did not meaningfully reflect the impacts of the pandemic and worsening climate crisis on their level of commitment.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table</label><caption><p>Recurring themes in new or updated NDC, relating COVID-19 response and recovery to climate change commitments<xref rid="tbl1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><bold>COVID-19 theme in NDC</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>UNFCCC parties</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Relevant text example</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Barrier to ambitious climate action, through factors such as the economic impacts of COVID-19</td><td align="left">Argentina, Brunei, Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica, Fiji, Grenada, Jamaica, Maldives, Marshall Islands, Nepal, Panama, Tonga, VietNam</td><td align="left"><bold>Fiji</bold>: &#8220;...this NDC update recognises that the cost of implementing this target currently stands at US$ 2&#183;97 billion between 2017&#8211;20305. This is an exorbitant financial challenge compounded by competing adaptation and disaster risk challenges the country faces, all of which are exacerbated by the COVID19 economic crisis.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Driving force for ambitious climate action by factors such as committing to a green recovery from COVID-19</td><td align="left">Andorra, Argentina, Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica, EU, Fiji, Maldives, Marshall Islands, Mexico, Panama, Peru, South Korea, Thailand, UK</td><td align="left"><bold>South Korea</bold>: &#8220;The Green New Deal is underpinned by 3 key pillars; green transition in cities/spatial planning/living infrastructure, diffusion of low-carbon and distributed energy, and establishment of innovative green industry ecosystems. A total of KRW 73&#183;4 trillion will be invested by 2025 and the Green New Deal will facilitate GHG emissions reduction and help sustaining climate-resilient recovery.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Just transition from fossil fuels</td><td align="left">Chile, Colombia, Panama, South Korea, UK</td><td align="left"><bold>Chile</bold>: &#8220;...our priority is overcoming that crisis and moving towards sustainable development with a pragmatic and crosscutting focus, holding human and territorial wellbeing at its core. The actions we take today, together with a just transition towards sustainable development, will define the type of society that we will build in the coming decades. Special attention has been paid to the afore-mentioned issue, which led to the incorporation of a specific social pillar focused on a just transition and sustainable development goals.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Need for science-based targets and decision making</td><td align="left">Andorra, Argentina</td><td align="left"><bold>Andorra</bold>: &#8220;For all these reasons the National Energy and Climate Change Strategy incorporates a program of innovation, research and systematic observation &#8230; as well as fostering interaction between economic actors and the scientific sector (Article 8). A key piece in the improvement of management in the face of climate change and other sectors, such as health, as has been demonstrated in the recent health crisis produced by COVID-19. The transition to a low GHG emissions economy should not only be a technological transition, and for this reason it is also working on a social transition that goes through education and capacity building.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Impeding broad stakeholder engagement in NDC processes</td><td align="left">Grenada, Nicaragua</td><td align="left"><bold>Grenada</bold>: &#8220;Inclusiveness and Engagement: The process was characterized by its inclusiveness and consultative nature albeit in mostly virtual sessions due to Covid-19 and the need to adhere to the attendant protocols.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gendered impacts and risks</td><td align="left">Panama</td><td align="left"><bold>Panama</bold>: &#8220;It should be noted that these diseases have a direct impact on responsibilities and burdens of care, especially for women and girls, as evidenced by the COVID-19 pandemic. &#8230; Designing sustainable infrastructure that takes into account the differentiated needs and preferences of men and women leads to more inclusive, resilient and sustainable development in the long run and may represent a novel opportunity for employment and economic empowerment for men and women if gender-responsive actions are implemented. &#8220;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Need for nature-based solutions</td><td align="left">EU, UK</td><td align="left"><bold>UK and Northern Ireland</bold>: &#8220;The Scottish Government is committed to delivering a green recovery after the impact of Covid-19, and plans outlined in the Programme for Government 2020/2118 are among a range of measures to protect biodiversity, create green jobs and accelerate a just transition to net zero.&#8221;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Health and equity as cross-cutting priorities</td><td align="left">Andorra, Argentina, Chile, Costa Rica, Mexico, Panama</td><td align="left"><bold>Argentina</bold>: &#8220;The pandemic has forced us to reflect on the importance of human health and its interrelation with the health of the planet. Climate change is a reality that is affecting humanity as a whole, which requires immediate and coordinated action from leaders around the world.&#8221;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>NDC=nationally determined contributions. UNFCCC=UN Framework Convention on Climate Change.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fn1"><label>*</label><p id="cenpara10">NDC text excerpts are for illustrative purposes only. They do not provide a comprehensive representation of the content or level of ambition of respective NDCs. Translations of text excerpts were conducted by the authors. An overview of all references to COVID-19 in the 48 NDCs is available in the <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>