<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par5">Bill Gates&#8217;s book, <italic>How to Avoid a Climate Disaster</italic>, clearly follows the zeitgeist and is based on the fundamental principle that the world must get to net zero carbon emission by 2050 or earlier if possible. In fact, there is a whole chapter call &#8220;Why Zero&#8221;. This principle needs some unpacking. Net zero carbon emissions means that there will be no increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide by 2050&#8212;and if there are any emissions, these must be balanced by carbon dioxide being sucked out of the atmosphere either by technology or by planting vast forests, hence the term &#8216;net&#8217;. What Bill Gates glosses over is that even if we reach net zero carbon by 2050, the science clearly shows we must have negative emissions for the rest of the century if we are to have any hope of keeping global temperatures below the 2&#160;&#176;C limit set by world leaders in Paris in 2015. To try to make the net zero carbon target understandable, Bill Gates refers to the current 51 billion tons of carbon emitted per year as a way of illustrating all the things we need to do to reduce this huge number and eventually hit zero. Chapter 4 addresses 27% of the 51 billion tons and is about our production and use of electricity: it examines how we can decarbonise electricity production and accelerate the uptake of renewables. Chapter 5 covers 31% and mainly focuses on the production of concrete which if it were a country it would the 6th largest emitter in the world. Chapter 6 represents 19% and concerns itself with agriculture and deforestation: it explores how we can produce food more efficiently, with less environmental destruction and greenhouse gas emissions. Chapter 7 analyses how we transport ourselves and our goods around the world which makes up 16% of the total tons of carbon emitted: it looks at ways of removing fossil fuels from vehicles, ships and aircraft&#8212;though the latter two only get two pages in the book because they are so difficult. Finally, chapter 8 analyses the remaining 7%, looking at how we heat and cool our buildings&#8212;for example, how we will need to shift from natural gas to electricity for heating our homes. He acknowledges that the effort to make all of these changes will be hard and in each chapter the book presents some of the available technological solutions&#8212;with an occasional suggestion that we should do less of those things which create the most carbon emissions.</p>