<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para110">Land-use change often involves the encroachment of human activity into wildlife habitat resulting from urban expansion and infrastructure development, agriculture and livestock farming, hydrological alteration, natural resource extraction, and other practices. Land-use change can often result in environmental alterations, such as deforestation and habitat fragmentation.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Such anthropogenic disturbances can affect pathogen transmission dynamics by changing ecological community composition, population structure, vector ecology, host abundance, host behaviour, and immunity. This effect can alter host exposure, susceptibility, and transmission rates of pathogens.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> Through these alterations, destruction and degradation of habitats often lead to an increased interface for wild host, vector, and human interactions, potentially facilitating zoonotic pathogen spillover to new hosts, including humans.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Land-use change can forge new pathways for direct human&#8211;wildlife interactions, for example, by facilitating access of poachers engaged in the wildlife trade to previously less accessible natural environments.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> When land is converted for agriculture and other uses, boundary and edge areas between natural ecosystems and human-modified areas often increase.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> This change provides additional opportunity for pathogen spillover and adaptation to new hosts,<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and has been involved in the emergence pathway of several zoonotic diseases, such as rabies, yellow fever, and the Ebola virus.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> A 2020 study in Uganda's Kibale National Park found that landscape fragmentation, including higher densities of edges and forest core loss due to deforestation, is associated with increased interactions between humans and non-human primates, enhancing opportunity for spillover of zoonotic pathogens.<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref>
</p>