<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par12">Consequently, there are many initiatives at different levels for actions towards sustainability. However, a common result when asking ECE teachers and student teachers about ECEfS, is a weak understanding of the involved concepts (Engdahl et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2021</xref>; Wolff &amp; Furu, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2018</xref>). There is also a growing body of research on ECEfS within the ECE Teacher Programmes, which shows that ECEfS is weakly or not implemented in Early Teacher Education and that further studies are needed (&#196;rlemalm-Hags&#233;r &amp; Elliott, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2020</xref>; Davis &amp; Davis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). Altogether, there is a risk that teachers, if they read original UN related documents, feel estranged by the policy language, and cannot relate the goals and indicators to their own ECE practice. Contemporary research shows, on the other hand, that many ECEC teachers include sustainability in their projects and themes in preschool education (Davis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2014</xref>; Engdahl, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2015</xref>; Espinosa &amp; Triverio, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2021</xref>; Furu &amp; Heilala, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2021</xref>; Furu &amp; Valkonen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2021</xref>). Children and their teachers are increasingly involved in &#8216;practises of collaborative exploration&#8217; (&#216;degaard, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2021</xref>), for instance in monitoring and saving animals, cleaning up the environment, as well as by themselves in building relationships with new friends with multiple backgrounds. This approach to ECEfS respects children&#8217;s needs to play, explore, move and is based on entanglement with both the human and the more-than-human world (Hackett &amp; Rautio, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2019</xref>; Myrstad et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2020</xref>). Further, it is characterised by playful learning, meaning-making and authentic problem solving and is an expression of a genuine care for Human and planetary wellbeing.</p>