<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par45">Canada is warming at twice the global rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], resulting in a wide range of health effects and changing patterns of migration. One particularly affected group are the Indigenous peoples of Canada that include Inuit, M&#233;tis, First Nations, and all First Peoples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Indigenous communities face unique challenges as their livelihoods depend on their spiritual, cultural and environmental ties to the land [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. This is also exacerbated by marginalization, living in remote, inaccessible areas, often with poor surrounding infrastructure, and an ageing population, which can be among the drivers of relocation to other communities or urban areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The warming climate has also affected the migratory patterns of animal species and led to changes in harvesting patterns, fueling food insecurity among the Indigenous populations who may rely on subsistence hunting and traditional foods. Another important group to consider in terms of climate-change related health impacts in Canada are immigrants, a significant proportion of whom originate from LMICs. Many contextual factors, such as the nature of the migration process, the capacity of the receiving community, and other push-pull factors, influence the health outcomes of immigrant populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Research in this area is heterogenous and lacking. While demographic studies have highlighted &#8220;the healthy immigrant-effect&#8221;, due to the positive selection of healthier people to migrate, this converges to host country levels over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Research has shown that immigrants, especially those migrating from rural to urban areas, have higher rates of chronic illness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Immigrants, a heterogenous group, often face numerous challenges such as cultural and language barriers, discrimination, socioeconomic differences, lifestyle changes, changes in their living arrangements, occupational exposures as well as barriers to accessing healthcare, which can result in poor health. While migration can pose significant health risks, it is an important adaptation response to the effects of a changing climate. The health needs of migrant and Indigenous populations should be at the forefront of climate adaptation strategies in Canada.</p>