<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par4">In Chapter 2, Bessant astutely explores the contested histories of apprehending and classifying the boundaries of <italic>politics</italic> and <italic>the political</italic>&#8212;in particular, how social and political scientists have represented children and young people as political beings (p. 45). Bessant traces the connections between the received &#8216;common sense&#8217; idea that children and young people are &#8216;semi or partial citizens&#8217; (p. 46), &#8216;immature and incapable of the rational deliberation and decision-making&#8217; required for participation in democratic political life (p. 47), and a &#8216;narrow conceptualisation of politics&#8217; (p. 51) that understands politics as a demarcated sphere from the &#8216;private&#8217; and the &#8216;social&#8217;&#160;(cf. Nakata&#160;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>). Political philosoper Hannah Arendt&#8217;s thought becomes a case in point to track the potential pitfalls in interpreting and representing young people&#8217;s political lives. Bessant notes the potential for Arendt&#8217;s concept of &#8216;natality&#8217;&#8211; the bringing forth of renewal and novelty into &#8216;democratic orders&#8217; from those &#8216;<italic>on their borders</italic>&#8217; (p. 61)&#8212;to invite reconsideration of &#8216;the role children and young people can play in politics on the border of the political order&#8217; (p. 62, Bessant&#8217;s emphasis). Yet, according to Bessant, Arendt failed to recognise when these dynamics were at work in her own time. At the beginning of&#160;Chapter 2, Bessant recounts the story of Elizabeth Eckford, the 15-year-old African-American student who was photographed by press photographers on September 4, 1957, outside the all-white Little Rock Central High School, Arkansas, USA, surrounded by a jeering white mob, during the national campaign for desegregation led by the National Association for the Advancement of Coloured Peoples (NAACP). Arendt published an essay after the photograph, criticising Eckford&#8217;s parents and the NAACP for asking her to be &#8216;be a hero&#8217; (1959, p. 45, cited by Bessant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2021</xref>, p. 43). Arendt, according to Bessant, thought that Elizabeth Eckford and the other African-American students in the Little Rock Nine had been &#8216;manipulated by their elders who should have known better&#8217; (p. 43). Bessant narrates how Arendt&#8217;s critique was countered by African-American writer Ralph Ellison, who &#8216;said that Arendt failed to see what was actually happening&#8217; (Bessant&#8217;s summary, p. 43)&#8212;that is, how African-American parents &#8216;were obligated to teach their children that America was for many, if not all African-Americans, a dangerous society&#8217; and where &#8216;children and young people had a legitimate role in being political&#8217; (p. 64). For Bessant, Arendt and Ellison interpreted Eckford&#8217;s actions differently because of their &#8216;different conceptions of the status as children&#8217; and &#8216;of politics&#8217; (p. 44). Arendt&#8217;s strong distinction between the &#8216;private&#8217; and &#8216;public&#8217; and &#8216;the social&#8217; and &#8216;the political&#8217; shaped her critique of Eckford&#8217;s parents and the NAACP (p. 63). According to Bessant, the gap between Arendt&#8217;s theorising of natality and her misrecognition of the politics of Elizabeth Eckford and other African-American young people of her time highlights &#8216;the effect of interpretive frames that inhibit our [that is, any adult expert&#8217;s] capacity to see what children and young people are actually doing and experiencing&#8217; (p. 51).</p>