<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par5">Chapter 3 begins Bessant&#8217;s historical sociological analysis of young people in the eighteenth century. Bessant draws attention to the relative youth (compared to contemporary times) of political leaders and military commanders of figures like William Pitt, who became Prime Minister of Britan at 24, and Napoleon Bonaparte, who was a general in the French army by 24. Bessant considers the central role of young people in the French Revolution, and how the French Revolution &#8216;linked an idea about being young with the idea of change&#8217; (p. 86). The French Revolution is argued to have &#8216;created an association&#8217; between &#8216;the idea of democracy and equality, dangerous disorder and the destructive role played by young people&#8217; that would &#8216;lead to representations of young people as part of the &#8220;dangerous classes&#8221;&#8217; (p. 87). Chapter 4 tracks the emergence, following the French Revolution, of the category of the &#8216;dangerous classes&#8217;, and the simultaneous &#8216;civilising offensive&#8217; on working-class children and young people in Europe and colonised subjects of European empires. For Bessant, there are &#8216;significant affinities&#8217; between late nineteenth-century representations of adolescents as &#8216;savages&#8217; and &#8216;barbarians&#8217; and &#8216;the popular white-racist view of colonialism as the necessary imposition of civilisation on &#8220;savages&#8221; and &#8220;natives&#8221;&#8217; (p. 109). These affinities are exemplified in the development of the &#8216;&#8220;scientific&#8221; model of adolescence&#8217; (p. 115) by North American psychologist G. Stanley Hall. Hall&#8217;s recapitulation theory&#8212;that is, the theory that &#8216;the biological development of each individual recapitulates the history of the whole species&#8217; from &#8216;barbaric&#8217; to &#8216;civilised&#8217;&#8212;created a &#8216;new common sense&#8217; of adolescence as &#8216;a transitional agonistic and rebellious stage in the life-cycle&#8217; (p. 119). Bessant demonstrates how Hall&#8217;s work, which informs contemporary concerns about young people&#8217;s hormones and peer-orientation, was profoundly influenced by eugenic theories of &#8216;race, racial hygiene and evolution&#8217; that naturalised white supremacy (p. 115).</p>