<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par8">Where the previous chapters had worked with the emergence and flourishing of modernist narratives of &#8216;an unrelenting historical process of socio-economic, technological and intellectual progress&#8217; (p. 184), Chapter 7 maps how representations of young people changed (and stayed the same) following the impacts of economic and climate changes from the late 1970s onwards&#8212;consequences of the unrelenting extractivist logics of colonialism and capitalism. Bessant tracks how the &#8216;problem of unemployment&#8217; became translated &#8216;into a problem of the unemployed and of [the] young unemployed in particular&#8217; (p. 207), and the ascendance of two representative tropes: the young precariat and the young entrepreneur. Economist Guy Standing&#8217;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2011</xref>) account of &#8216;the precariat&#8217; is argued to have &#8216;many historical resonances with the &#8220;dangerous classes&#8221; of the 1840s and 1850s&#8217; (p. 193). Standing&#8217;s representation of the &#8216;precariat&#8217; constructs young people as &#8216;victims of &#8220;structural forces&#8221;&#8217; (Bessant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2021</xref>, p. 203) &#8211; vulnerable but simultaneously to be feared as potentially sparking &#8216;&#8220;a politics of inferno&#8221;&#8217; (Standing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2011</xref>, p. vi, cited by Bessant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2021</xref>, p. 203). The alternate representation of young people&#8217;s entrepreneurialism, created by neoliberal governments, financial agencies and think-tanks, offers &#8216;a more upbeat and reassuring story&#8217; (p. 203), but fails to acknowledge or account for &#8216;the decline of full-time employment or long term stagnant productivity or halting wage growth&#8217; (p. 206). Both representations&#8212;the young precariat and the young entrepreneur&#8212;are &#8216;shaped by political worldviews and specific political-economic interests&#8217; (p. 205) and divert attention from the &#8216;&#8220;everyday reality of precarious labour markets, political upheaval lead by conservative and&#160;reactionary forces, and global risks such as climate change&#8221;&#8217; (Threadgold 2019, p. 5, cited by Bessant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2021</xref>, p. 206). </p>