<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par9">Chapters 8 and 9 explore young people&#8217;s political responses to these altered conditions&#8212;in particular&#8212;children and young people&#8217;s political activism in the face of persistent government inaction on anthropogenic climate change. Chapter 8 summarises historical examples of school student activism and their representation&#8212;from anti-Iraq war protests involving school students across Europe, the USA and Australia (pp. 221&#8211;222) to more recent digital political satire including the creation and distributions of memes on platforms like TikTok (pp. 224&#8211;227, 229&#8211;231). Bessant analyses the political tactics of global youth climate justice activism: from physical strikes (2018&#8211;2019) to digital strikes (with the emergence of COVID-19), to legal challenges where young people are taking their governments to court&#8212;&#8216;playing them at their own game&#8217; (p. 234). Drawing on Arendt, Bessant suggests that these collective actions, in online and offline spaces, are suggestive of the &#8216;emergence of a new kind of politics&#8217; (p. 234)&#8212;an &#8216;&#8220;impulse&#8221; that &#8220;springs&#8221; from the beginning [of] &#8220;something new on our own initiative&#8221;&#8217; (Arendt, 1958, cited by Bessant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2021</xref>, p. 232). In Chapter 9, Bessant presents an overview of how &#8216;political elites (e.g. politicians, policy-makers and mainstream media workers)&#8217; have represented children and young people &#8216;when they demonstrated their capacity to be political&#8217; in recent years (p. 239). Like other recent media analyses of the school strikers and other young activists (e.g. Bergmann and Ossewaarde <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2020</xref>; Taft <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2020</xref>), Bessant notes the prevalence of tropes of young people as, variously, &#8216;privileged brats&#8217;, &#8216;vulnerable dupes&#8217; (p. 245) and &#8216;naughty truants&#8217; (p. 247). Bessant draws on Canadian philosopher Charles Taylor&#8217;s politics of recognition and misrecognition to account for how &#8216;many young people are rejecting how they are being represented&#8217; and engaging in &#8216;debates to contest how there are named&#8217;, affirming &#8216;their political status&#8217; and directly questioning &#8216;the authority of those offering those accounts of them&#8217; (p. 250).</p>