<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par10">This compelling and important book will appeal to sociologists of childhood and youth, historians and political scientists keen to attend to the representation of young people in contemporary political life. The book opens a pathway for further work on contemporary representations of young people&#8217;s politics, not only for persistent negative representations but also in analysing historical resonances in apparently positive representations. Greta Thunberg is often credited for sparking the student climate justice movement and is the ubiquitous &#8216;face&#8217; of contemporary youth climate activism. However, collective youth networks like Seed Indigenous Youth Climate Network in Australia and Pacific Climate Warriors, young Indigenous activists in other settler colonial nations, and young activists from the Global South have been campaigning for climate justice for at least the past ten years (Unigwe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2019</xref>). Why are these organisations and individual activists less visible in mainstream media representations of climate activism? Which organisations and individuals get platformed and gain traction in positive mainstream media/political representations, and how do representations of certain &#8216;extraordinary&#8217; individuals (like Greta Thunberg) reinscribe historical discourses of white savourism (Bergmann and Ossewaarde <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2020</xref>; Taft <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2020</xref>)? While some young people may be &#8216;answering back&#8217; (p. 237) to dominant deficit representations of state institutions, understanding what is &#8216;actually happening&#8217; necessitates also attending to decolonial and Indigenist politics of <italic>refusal</italic> of the colonial state as the primary recognising agent (Coulthard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2014</xref>; L&#243;pez L&#243;pez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2019</xref>). Further work might consider the political potency of young people&#8217;s refusals of &#8216;common sense&#8217; politics-as-usual and the colonial extractivist state as they, collectively, seek to &#8216;make up&#8217; another possible world.</p>