<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par51">What can we learn from the management of the Covid-19 pandemic for the management of the climate crisis, which will be the most important task ahead of us for the rest of the century? As we have argued in this paper, the Covid crisis exemplifies how the demand not only for political, but also for epistemic authority soars in face of a major threat, and how the threat comes to be seen as at least temporarily legitimizing the use of emergency powers. However, using emergency powers&#8212;that is, suspending individual liberties and, more importantly, bypassing processes of democratic will-formation&#8212;comes at a high price to democracy. This is because the very idea that the point of democracy lies in the quest for &#8216;correct&#8217;, welfare-maximising solutions is a misunderstanding of the very conditions of politics: in our societies, social groups compete for resources and conflicting understandings of the good and the right that are never entirely reducible. Under these conditions, <italic>politics is not about finding, but about constructing solutions to societal problems and challenges</italic>. We have argued that denying the contingency and political quality that collectively binding decisions retain even in situations of emergency leads to serious legitimacy problems. Moreover, it will not be sustainable in the long run, as it is likely to lead to reactance and non-compliance among citizens. However, scientific expertise is indispensable if democracy is to deal with major challenges like climate change, and citizens expect decisions to be based on evidence and good reasons. Against this backdrop, the last section of our paper has pointed out three necessary, but not sufficient requirements for legitimate expert involvement in political decision-making: politically mandating and controlling expert bodies, making uncertainty and expert disagreement transparent and enhancing inclusive and effective citizen deliberation.</p>