<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par22">Regarding just transition, the Commission proposed a Just Transition Mechanism (JTM) to &#8216;focus on the regions and sectors that are most affected by the transition because they depend on fossil fuels or carbon-intensive processes&#8217;, and under which &#8216;[s]upport will be linked to promoting a transition towards low-carbon and climate-resilient activities&#8217; (European Commission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2019</xref>, 16). The JTM consists of three &#8216;pillars&#8217;: a Just Transition Fund (JTF), a just transition scheme under InvestEU and a European Investment Bank public sector loan facility. The JTF, financed by &#8364;7.5 billion from the 2021&#8211;2027 Multiannual Financial Framework (MFF) and &#8364;10 billion from the NextGenerationEU (NGEU) pandemic recovery facility (on which see below, &#8220;Climate justice at the COVID crossroads&#8221; section), will provide mostly grants, with matching financing from other EU funds and Member State co-financing, and would assist &#8216;territories with high employment in coal, lignite, oil shale and peat production, as well as territories with greenhouse gas-intensive industries, which will be either discontinued or severely impacted by the transition&#8217; (Ibid, 19). The InvestEU scheme would &#8216;crowd in&#8217; private and public investment in &#8216;new economic activities&#8217; in affected regions through the provision of guarantees (Ibid, 20&#8211;21). The EIB facility would provide concessional loans for public sector investment in the regions (Ibid, 21&#8211;22). The Regulation establishing the InvestEU programme was adopted in March 2021 (European Parliament/Council <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2021a</xref>), while in July 2021, the Council approved the Parliament&#8217;s position on the public sector loan facility regulation, paving the way for its adoption (Council of the EU <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2021</xref>).</p>