<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par33">With the transformation of China&#8217;s overall identity construction towards a new Yinling Leading Power, this part will show that climate change governance has been recognized and framed as an important platform where China can play as a leading state and China&#8217;s self-representation of a &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; has accordingly dominated China&#8217;s national narratives on its presence in global climate governance in the pre- and post-Paris period. Before the Paris Summit, China&#8217;s former Vice-Foreign Minister and ambassador to France&#8212;Jun Zhai (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2015</xref>)&#8212;formally framed the Paris Summit as &#8216;a platform in which China can play an international leadership role in global governance&#8217;. China&#8217;s climate negotiators such as Qimin Chai (Interview 2017), Qingchen Chao (Interview 2017) and an expert member (Interview 2017) stressed that global climate governance is the &#8216;world stage&#8217; of which China has been gradually at the &#8216;centre&#8217; since Xi Jinping&#8217;s rise to power in 2013. China official narratives framed itself as a &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; in promoting international climate cooperation. For instance, China&#8217;s state-owned newspaper People&#8217;s Daily (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2015</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2016</xref>) repeatedly stressed that &#8216;China&#8217;s actions &#8220;<italic>yinling</italic>&#8221; global climate governance&#8217; and the world expects China to be &#8216;a pioneer and an example for global efforts in combating climate challenge&#8217;. Chinese President Xi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2017b</xref>) concluded at the 19th Party&#8217;s Congress: &#8216;taking a driving seat in international cooperation to respond to climate change, China has become an important participant, contributor, and &#8220;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8221; in the global endeavour for ecological civilization&#8217;. Xi particularly linked the concept &#8216;ecological civilization&#8217;, which is rooted in China&#8217;s past ecological philosophy, with his vision for China&#8217;s international leadership and aimed to distinguish Chinese leadership from the traditional Western paradigms (Hansen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>). China&#8217;s top climate negotiator Xie Zhenhua also emphasized that China has become an important &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; in the global construction of ecological civilization (Chinanews <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2017</xref>). Moreover, China&#8217;s climate negotiator Qimin Chai stressed that:<disp-quote><p id="Par34">China&#8217;s self-positioning is transforming from a participant to a &#8216;<italic>yinlingzhe</italic>&#8217; in global climate governance. Since Xi Jinping became the President, China has become increasingly more proactive in global climate governance (Interview 2017). </p></disp-quote></p>