<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par38">China&#8217;s identity reconstruction in climate governance is also discursively done through reconstructing issues of climate justice. Undertaking climate responsibility has been reconstructed from a heavy burden to China to its own positive duty and an important way to show its leadership. China&#8217;s Xie Zhenhua (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2015</xref>) has repeatedly stressed that &#8216;addressing climate change is what China needs to fulfil its due international obligation as a responsible power&#8217;. Furthermore, China accepted, reconstructed and promoted a more flexible, balanced differentiation mechanism. For example, China and the USA together redefined the CBDR principle by adding a new qualifier&#8212;&#8216;in light of different national circumstances&#8217; (Foreign Ministry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2014</xref>) and this new formulation was directly reiterated in the Paris Agreement. This new construction of the CBDR actually &#8216;reduces the weight of the historical responsibility of developed countries&#8217;, and its &#8216;novel operationalization&#8217;&#8212;the Nationally Determined Contributions as a key mechanism in the Paris Agreement may ultimately result in &#8216;the smallest common denominator in terms of climate justice&#8217; (von Lucke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2021</xref>: 50&#8211;51). In addition to the reconstruction of those specific justice-related norms and principles, China&#8217;s construction of distributive climate justice in terms of a fair climate deal also transformed from strictly embedding fairness into the established top-down model for developed countries to linking fairness with all Parties&#8217; voluntary contributions and highlighting inclusiveness. Moreover, by accepting and promoting the ideas of peaking emissions and carbon neutrality (see below), China&#8217;s construction of climate justice regarding the right to emit and the exemption of developing countries from caps on emissions have also exhibited changes and flexibility.</p>