<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/"><italic>Comitato No Grandi Navi</italic> started out as a&#160;neighborhood information platform about big ships. It was turned into a&#160;civic protest group after the Costa Concordia accident in January 2012, at the Isola del Giglio in Tuscany, where 32&#160;people died. The fear of similar accidents in Venice due to ever larger ships, as well as concerns over the management of big infrastructure projects in this delicate urban environment, brought several activist groups together. In 2012, they started their joint initiative against cruise ships in the lagoon and the city. The <italic>Comitato</italic> is organized as a&#160;collective actor (Buechler <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2000</xref>: 149), with individual actors connected on a&#160;local level. This open structure is a&#160;typical feature of recent social movements: &#8220;[&#8230;] independent of specific milieus, subcultures and social affiliations, the most recent forms of protest are characterized by network-like coordination and non-identitarian forms of participation within the framework of little formalized, temporarily limited structures&#8221; (Balint et&#160;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2014</xref>: 10). Characterized by a&#160;collective approach, the <italic>Comitato</italic> brings together individuals, associations, and groups (Della Porta &amp; Diani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>) that had already been established at the local level. Several members and friends of the committee have been involved in local politics, have work experience in the industrial sector, or have expertise in dealing with government authorities. Members of the committee empower themselves by acquiring knowledge and establishing counter-expertise. When the construction of the flood barrier project <italic>MOSE</italic>&#8212;short for experimental electromechanical module (<italic>modulo sperimentale elettromeccanico</italic>)&#8212;began in 2002, the Committee Save Venice with the Lagoon (<italic>Comitato Salvare Venezia con la Laguna</italic>) was founded. Since then, it has organized protests, produced informational documents, and appealed to local and national authorities. Since 2005, the Permanent Assembly NOMOSE (<italic>Assemblea Permanente NOMOSE</italic>) has followed and commented on the structure&#8217;s implementation. The association EnvironmentVenice (<italic>AmbienteVenezia</italic>) was created in 2007 to advocate for the protection of the lagoon, the coastal system, and the rights of the local population.</p>