<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">The <italic>Comitato No Grandi Navi</italic> is characterized by a&#160;strongly transversal character in its organization, its communication strategies, and its actions. Combining different approaches, materials, and modes of action, the network has established a&#160;&#8220;strategic cooperation around an objective beyond the scope of which, each associated member maintains its specificity&#8221; (Vianello <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2013</xref>: 9). The heterogeneous composition of the committee reflects the variety of fields it engages in, and it visibly affects its production of counter- and extra-expertise. Since the committee has no official spokesperson, several persons held leadership positions over the years. Activists from the antifascist social center Occupied Laboratory Morion (<italic>Laboratorio Occupato Morion</italic>) play a&#160;crucial role, with Tommaso Cacciari being an important representative of the committee. Aside from assemblies, talks, and informational meetings, the activists organize and coordinate direct actions connected to the protests in the city. <italic>Laboratorio Occupato Morion</italic> stands in the tradition of the social movements of the 1970s, with &#8220;strategies of struggle, discourses and actions of the radical approach to contestation through protest&#8221; (Vianello <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2013</xref>: 9). However, its high visibility has not necessarily gained it the support of the wider public (Kurik <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2016</xref>), as some interviewees, including members and non-members of the committee, have pointed out.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn7">7</xref> Yet despite divergent political orientations or disagreements over appropriate protest tactics, all interviewees shared the group&#8217;s general critique of local politics. <italic>AmbienteVenezia</italic> plays another important role in the committee. Its spokesman, Luciano Mazzolin, a&#160;former petro-chemical worker and councilor of the Province of Venice, is another of the committee&#8217;s spokespersons. Through the collection and circulation of documents, <italic>AmbienteVenezia</italic> provides a&#160;record of incidents in the lagoon and on mainland Venice. It also runs a&#160;continuous information campaign on industrial, ecological, and political developments, and makes this information public through different channels. Aside from these central actors, there are experts from technical and academic fields who participate in the <italic>Comitato, </italic>such as Giuseppe Tattara, former professor of economics at the Universit&#224; Ca&#8217; Foscari, and the architect and writer Gianni Fabbri, who contribute in-depth analyses and reports on the ecological and social effects of the cruise industry on urban development (e.g. Fabbri &amp; Tattara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2014</xref>). Other members and supporters commit by producing or collecting and spreading a&#160;large variety of documents, ranging from reports to letters. A&#160;central platform for the distribution of information and the coordination of action is a&#160;mailing list, where synopses of press coverage are regularly circulated. In addition, the occupied S.a.L.E. Docks, a&#160;space for critical artistic expression, has become an important site for the movement and regarding the debate. Another initiative which cooperates with the committee is the non-profit association <italic>We are here Venice</italic>, which has strong transnational connections and specifically addresses ecological challenges as well as questions of policymaking in Mediterranean ports.</p>