<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">Running right through the Giudecca Canal, one of the main canals passing the historic center and the Piazza San Marco, the waves created by ever more and increasingly larger ships damaged the foundation of the city since years. The emission of sulphur oxides from cruisers contributes to air pollution. Moreover, the ability of ships to enter the lagoon necessitates expansion of waterways and further deepening of existing channels, which in turn could cause additional damage. Such infrastructural adjustments harm the natural environment. The committee aims to convince both local and national policymakers that personal, social, and environmental wellbeing should not be subordinated to economic logic (No Grandi Navi 2021). Through the actions of activists and ordinary citizens, a&#160;reappropriation of urban infrastructures and spaces has begun. The newsletters of <italic>AmbienteVenezia</italic> make this clear: &#8220;Misguided models of development have produced the environmental and social devastation that everyone can see! Only the awareness and mobilization of citizens can change and improve this situation&#8221; (2020).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn8">8</xref><italic>AmbienteVenezia</italic> regularly accuses policymakers of disregard for social concerns as well as a&#160;blindness for objectives other than profit maximization. At the same time, its newsletter reads like a&#160;general call to a&#160;&#8220;protest attitude, commitment and (moral) change of values&#8221; (Balint et&#160;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2014</xref>: 10). The heterogeneity of the group members, their networks, their long history of activism on ecological issues, and their utilization of academic and journalistic publications have brought the topic to international public attention&#8212;which in turn has increased opportunities for forging transnational connections. Most importantly, their struggles have led to a&#160;partial victory. In August 2021, the national government announced that large cruise ships will no longer pass the Giudecca Canal in Venice&#8217;s historic center&#8212;a&#160;ban that applies to ships weighing more than 25,000 tons or measuring more than 35&#160;meters in height or 180 meters in length.</p>