<contrib-group xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>Annie Hyokyong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff13"/><bio><sec id="FPar1"><title>Annie Hyokyong&#160;Nam</title><p id="Par1">is a graduate of the Technology, Innovation, Education Masters program at the Harvard Graduate School of Education (HGSE). She co-founded and led the first student environmental group at HGSE in addition to facilitating the first inter-school climate conference at Harvard University celebrating the 50th anniversary of Earth Day. She is&#160;currently working for the MIT Sloan School of Management and the Berkeley Haas School of Business, helping to digitize the program at both schools.&#160;Prior to Harvard, she worked for a private education firm, managing teachers and scaling core services by digitizing the curriculum. She has written a best-selling book on early English education for South Korean mothers.</p></sec></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sueyoon</given-names></name><address><email>yoon314sue@daum.net</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff13"/><bio><sec id="FPar2"><title>Sueyoon Lee</title><p id="Par2">is a graduate of the Human Development and Psychology Masters program&#160;(Child Advocacy Strand) at the Harvard Graduate School of Education. She was a leader of the &#8220;Education and Communication&#8221; panel in the programming committee for the first inter-school climate conference at Harvard University. Her background centers around child rights advocacy. She volunteered for UNICEF Korea, planning and carrying out various campaign activities regarding child rights. She is certified as a Professional Instructor of Child Rights by the International Child Rights Center and has a certificate in Child Protection offered by the Harvard FXB Center for Health and Human Rights.</p></sec></bio></contrib><aff id="Aff13"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.38142.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000041936754X</institution-id><institution>Harvard Graduate School of Education (HGSE), </institution></institution-wrap>Cambridge, MA USA </aff></contrib-group>