<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">A commentary by Herrero and Thornton (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) inquired: &#8220;What can COVID&#8208;19 teach us about responding to climate change?&#8221; (p. e174). Their most important lesson is that investment in behavioral responses such as social distancing and engagement of governments, businesses, and resource mobilization can be achieved and may limit the spread of the pandemic. They noted that &#8220;governments have found $8 trillion to help combat the spread and effects of COVID&#8208;19 in just 10&#160;weeks&#8221; (p. e174) and that these same aggressive measures should be applied with the same urgency to climate change. O&#8217;Reilly et al. (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) examined the transmission across the globe and the role of climate in mitigation of the current pandemic. They discussed the importance of future studies on climate variability, air pollution, heat and humidity in the incidence, susceptibility, and surveillance of COVID&#8208;19 related disease. Further Amuasi and colleagues (2020) examined the interconnection of <italic toggle="yes">The Lancet One Health Commission</italic> with climate change and COVID&#8208;19. They also suggested a linkage with the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals and the approach of the One Lancet Health Commission which includes the animal&#8212;environment&#8212;human interface. Their goal is to enhance health within an environment shared by humans and animals in our climate&#8208;changing world. Schwartz (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0035" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) urged greater preparedness and consciousness about climate change and COVID&#8208;19 and the need for understanding of what climate change migration will bring to the landscape of current and future pandemics. Rosenbloom and Markard (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) offered a lens on COVID&#8208;19 recovery for our struggling climate and planet. One outcome may be that there are opportunities to catalyze change on climate change for communities, nations, and globally as we address the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic.</p>