<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par49">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> lists the fairness and corruption objections to MBMs if they were introduced to maritime transport. The fairness objections show how MBMs would not lead to fair outcomes due to problems built into the system design, which, despite continued claims that they can be fixed, never are. MBMs are not even being discussed at any serious level of impact. The only MBMs being considered (regional ETS, very low carbon tax of 2 USD) are too weak to have any significant effect. The major negative outcome is that these arguments serve to disincentivise the necessary structural transition away from fossil fuels. Moreover, they serve as a placeholder that avoids national responsibility because keeping maritime emissions in the international sphere makes it very difficult to reach agreement. The case showed how lobby groups prevent maritime emissions going back to the UNFCCC, knowing that in the IMO they can continue to delay, thus evading action.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>List of fairness and corruption objections to MBMs in maritime transport</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Problem</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Description</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Objection</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">How it is relevant to maritime transport</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><bold>F</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>C</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Bad system design</td><td align="left">Problems include too many free permits, not enough auctioning, financialisation of the instruments, difficulty in setting price, allowing offsets, administrative complexity. Defenders argue that these can be fixed, even though there is no evidence that they can or will be</td><td align="left">X</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Cannot agree on a global policy. Only options considered are a very low carbon price of 2 USD or bringing maritime emissions into EU ETS, both unlikely to make significant difference</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Disincentivises the structural transition</td><td align="left">Thereby locking in the future emissions and worse outcomes. It does depend where and how the cuts are made but the current market ignores that</td><td align="left">X</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">As long as fossil fuels remain abundant and cheap, MBMs will not incentivise transition away. Strong evidence that the price would just be absorbed</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Avoids national responsibility</td><td align="left">The national level is the best level to take action yet leaving shipping emissions to the international market and using MBMs to get consumers to pay lets countries off the hook to take responsibility themselves</td><td align="left">X</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Shipping lobby groups prevent maritime emissions going back to UNFCCC because in the IMO they can continue to delay, thus evading national scrutiny</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Climate justice</td><td align="left">Ignoring historical emissions leads to unfair outcomes, expecting developing countries to pay the same, even though most of them a) did not emit and b) will face the worst outcomes</td><td align="left">X</td><td align="left"/><td align="left" rowspan="2">IMO wants NMFT rather than CBDR, conflicts with UNFCCC and climate justice</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MBMs attempt to remove the moral element of polluting and in particular the role of historic pollution and industrial development and state that there is nothing morally wrong with emissions or who emitted them&#8212;it&#8217;s just a market issue to resolve</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">X</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Commodifies nature</td><td align="left">Proposed solutions do not aim to solve the problem but to create opportunities for companies to make money, which influences the kinds of solutions adopted</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">X</td><td align="left">MBMs &amp; efficiency approaches rather than regulations or bans</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Crowds out non-market norm that pollution is not acceptable</td><td align="left">Combatting pollution with a fee makes pollution acceptable. No discussion of how it is wrong&#8212;just endless technical debate about finding the best technique. The urgency is lost and action is disincentivised by allowing pollution to be acceptable rather than something that companies want to get away from</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">X</td><td align="left">Only argue about the price but no urgency to transition</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>