<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0130">There is an increasing emphasis on integrative participatory processes in adaptation to generate or achieve sustainable development. Evaluations of such processes should evolve in parallel with those developments. The methodological process of this review revealed many knowledge gaps in how SDGs are addressed through co-production. We have outlined three major aspects of the problematics associated with the nexus of SDGs, co-production, and adaptation. We have opened the door for further fruitful investigations and research for integrating the SDGs in other processes. We found that there is a plethora of approaches to processes of co-production of knowledge that are being carried out to further adaptation. Most of these are derived from studies of adaptation in an SDG context. We grouped them into seven distinct methods, of which different variants of workshops were the most common. Both in the literature on the sustainability science agenda in general (<xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Sen, 2013</xref>) and the SDG agenda (<xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Shrivastava et al., 2020</xref>), and on adaptation (e.g., <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">Wamsler et al., 2020</xref>), there are calls for more interventionist approaches. We assessed the application of interventionist approaches in the corpus we reviewed using the scale of degrees of interventionism illustrated in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, from &#8220;applied research&#8221; to &#8220;transformative co-production intervention.&#8221; We only found five articles presenting interventionist co-production approaches for adaptation, indicating that such approaches are not yet commonplace when doing participatory research on adaptation in the context of the SDGs or as part of SDG localizing. There are also related calls for a transformative research agenda to implement the SDGs (<xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Fazey et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Shrivastava et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">Wamsler et al., 2020</xref>), but the review revealed little evidence that this has taken hold in the literature. This suggests that the SDG agenda is not yet contributing to more transformative approaches in the field of climate change adaptation.</p>