<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0150">In a juridical context where historical erasures and ongoing systemic violence shaped a judge's (and several prosecutors') embracing of narrow visions of justice, the courtroom here was an &#8220;affective theatre of power&#8221; (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bens, 2018</xref>, p. 12) in several senses. The judge who created the injunction claimed at one point that his courtroom was &#8220;<italic>not theatre.</italic>&#8221; He said this to chide people in the gallery after one defendant's words conveying values of respect for nature and Indigenous rights led to quiet but audible sounds of support from observers; on that day, proceedings were in a regular courtroom instead of the special basement room with the glass barrier (the usual place for the hearings). Yet, <italic>theatre</italic> is an inescapably relevant notion. As communicated to me by the artist of <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
, the motivation for this drawing &#8211; created right after one of the trials &#8211; is partly to render that theatre of power visible, showing the judge <italic>performing coloniality</italic>. For <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bens (2018)</xref>, the very purpose of <italic>courtroom ethnography</italic> is to <italic>recognise</italic> theatres of power and to &#8220;keep both the linguistic and the non-linguistic in mind when analysing the law and the state&#8221; (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bens, 2018</xref>, p. 14). Courts perform as &#8216;theatre&#8217; overtly when their function is primarily <italic>showing</italic> powers of control. This was the case unambiguously here; this judge's decisions to pursue new trials let alone raise prison sentences &#8211; even after the Federal Court of Appeals ruled the government's approval of the pipeline expansion as illegitimate &#8211; was an illustration of <italic>his subjective power to perform</italic>. He made other subjective and aggressive choices in expanding his injunction orders as well, as discussed below, and turned his court into a theatre for investigating emotions; defendants were repeatedly asked if they would &#8216;purge&#8217; their &#8216;guilt&#8217; when brought before the judge, and those accused of contempt would have to admit whether they knew about his injunction when standing on the road (some did not know about it) and express remorse in either case. The prison sentence he rendered would hinge in large part on how he felt the defendant <italic>performed</italic>, how their subservience in his theatre of power played out.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>&#8220;My Lord&#8221; - Artistic depiction of judge presiding in Trans Mountain Pipeline Hearings at the British Columbia Supreme Court - Artist: George Rammell, reproduced with permission.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>