<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0160">Some of the people in the BC court gallery had been attending each case since the <italic>very</italic> start of these contempt trials to show solidarity. I was told that I missed one occasion where this judge responded to an Indigenous defendant who tried to explain that his people had been on the land since time immemorial. &#8220;What is <italic>time immemorial</italic>?&#8221; the judge was said to have queried. Beyond diverse cultural and generational differences among those on trial (reflecting diverse peaceful efforts in defending land, water and earth<xref rid="fn8" ref-type="fn">8</xref>
), various positionalities in the courtroom observation gallery also were playing themselves out. Before I arrived on August 16th, one of the people who swooped briefly into the public gallery reportedly came because he used to oppose the same judge when that judge was a lawyer for the asbestos and tobacco industry. One person expressed that this judge's injunction was creating a huge embarrassment for the BC judicial system. After the conclusion of the day's sentencing hearing, we talked about how trials for serious offences are being dismissed because of time/resource pressures on the criminal justice system. &#8220;But all the time in the world is being made for prosecuting big criminals like grandmothers,&#8221; a courtroom friend relayed to me. We also discussed developments on Burnaby mountain by the pipeline construction site; the &#8220;Camp Cloud&#8221; protest camp (a make-shift camp) was closed by police at dawn that very morning. Newspapers were not allowed to cover details up close; land and water defenders wished that drones were there to better capture the situation. People charged at Camp Cloud later saw their charges dismissed as they were under a different judge, underscoring that the performativity of power includes its own subjective and arbitrary logic.</p>