<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurpub</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The European Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1101-1262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-360X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8574567</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckab164.189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ckab164.189</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Parallel Programme</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>3.E. Workshop: The Role of Digital Public Health in the European Climate Pact and Green deal</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC01210</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02610</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>3.E. Workshop: The Role of Digital Public Health in the European Climate Pact and Green deal</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>Organised by: EUPH-DH, EUPHA-ENV, WHO/Europe, Climate Reality Leaders</collab></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><collab>Chair persons: Luis Lapao (Portugal), Marija Jevtic (EUPHA-ENV)</collab><!--luis.lapao@ihmt.unl.pt--></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ckab164.189-cor1">Contact: <email>luis.lapao@ihmt.unl.pt</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-10-20"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>31</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><issue-title>Supplement 14th European Public Health Conference Public health futures in a changing world</issue-title><elocation-id>ckab164.189</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Public Health Association. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is published and distributed under the terms of the Oxford University Press, Standard Journals Publication Model (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model">https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model</ext-link>)</license-p></license><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the COVID-19 pandemic or until permissions are revoked in writing. Upon expiration of these permissions, PMC is granted a perpetual license to make this article available via PMC and Europe PMC, consistent with existing copyright protections.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ckab164.189.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s555"><title>&#x02002;</title><p>Europe is facing two major structural changes: the climate crisis, having a significant impact on public health, and digitalization of the economy, that could play a role in mitigating climate change and its impacts on public health. The COVID-19 pandemic has affected our lives in many ways including how we see public health, the climate change and has created the conditions for the almost exponential growth for telemedicine and digitalization in healthcare. Underlining that the world is facing an increasing innovation and integration of digital tools to address public health and environmental problems, as the UN Secretary-General and the Director-General of the World Health Organization both declared that we are currently fighting a climate &#x0201c;pandemic&#x0201d; in the same way as we are fighting COVID-19. Digital solutions have been implemented to address COVID-19 and impacted by reducing CO2 emissions and improving quality of life. Digital systems, including Artificial Intelligence, robots and drones, are now changing the paradigm of public health and environment management. Due to the complex nature of the information ecosystem our societies and communities live in, a digital public health approach can be managed to reduce harm to individual, community and population health, support social cohesion and trust in emergency response and interventions to deal with climate change. Digital health could, within 10 years establish a new paradigm in public and environmental health. Public health professionals need urgently to tackle digital health to bridge the gap with others areas of healthcare. During the COVID-19 crisis, national public health authorities have been challenged in the way they communicate with the public, engage with communities in collecting data to improve response, providing the scientific evidence, the day-to-day facts and figures. Likewise, The European Climate Pact provides a space for collectively develop and implement climate solutions. The Climate Pact is an open, inclusive and evolving initiative for climate action through an online platform and citizen dialogues and exchanges, it will foster the link between the digital and green transition. This workshop aims to share the experiences of digital public health interventions with significant impact on climate change mitigation during the pandemic. It will be organised as a round table, starting by setting the scene with an introduction to key digital health concepts and challenges. Each speaker will give a short pitch on how they have experienced the challenge of using digital systems in public health and how they approached its management during the crisis. This will be followed by a panel discussion. Participants will have ample time to ask questions to the panellists. The workshop will end with a summary of a selection of tools participants can use in their own environmental management activities and key take home messages from the panellist will be provided as a conclusion.</p></sec><sec id="s556"><title>Key messages</title><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Digital Public Health has been establishing evidence on interventions with significant effects on reducing the impact of climate crisis.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A Partnership is needed across the health system and society to manage this crisis. European Green Deal and Climate Pact could be used as a roadmap in digital public health.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>