<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Urban</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ Urban</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EAU</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">speau</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environment and Urbanization</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0956-2478</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1746-0301</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9557810</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/09562478221115334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_09562478221115334</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Addressing Urban Inequalities I: Co-creating Pathways Through Research and Practice &#x02013; Reframing Trajectories, Politicizing Knowledge and Transforming Pedagogies</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Crafting urban equality through grassroots critical pedagogies:
weave, <italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic>, mobilize, reverberate,
emancipate</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>Adriana</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1691-9620</contrib-id><name><surname>Wesely</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blanes</surname><given-names>Paola</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brandolini</surname><given-names>Florencia</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Enet</surname><given-names>Mariana</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iacovini</surname><given-names>Rodrigo Faria G</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fassina</surname><given-names>Rosario</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Flores Pacheco</surname><given-names>Bahi&#x000e1;</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>Graciela</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muniz</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>Soledad</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>Silsa</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reina</surname><given-names>Marilyn</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amparo S&#x000e1;nchez Medina</surname><given-names>Luz</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Adriana Allen (corresponding author) is a Latin American activist and
academic based at The Bartlett Development Unit, University College
London and the current President of Habitat International
Coalition.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Address: The Bartlett Development Planning Unit, University College
London, 34 Tavistock Square, London WC1H 9EZ, UK; email:
<email>a.allen@ucl.ac.uk</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Julia Wesely is a Postdoctoral Research Fellow at The Bartlett
Development Planning Unit, University College London.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>julia.wesely@ucl.ac.uk</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio3-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Paola Blanes is a member of CISCSA Ciudades Feministas, Centro de
Intercambio y Servicios para el Cono Sur, Argentina, where she leads
CISCSA Feminist Schools.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>paola@ciscsa.org.ar</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio4-09562478221115334"><p><bold>Florencia Brandolini is a member of the Communication team of CISCSA
Ciudades Feministas, Centro de Intercambio y Servicios para el Cono Sur,
Argentina</bold>.</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>florjbrando@gmail.com</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio5-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Mariana Enet is a pedagogue and independent advisor, based at the
National University of C&#x000f3;rdoba, Argentina.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>marianaenet@yahoo.com.ar</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio6-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Rodrigo Faria G Iacovini is Coordinator of the Citizenship School at
Instituto P&#x000f3;lis, Brazil.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>rodrigo@polis.org.br</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio7-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Rosario Fassina is Coordinator of the Right to the City Programme at
Asociaci&#x000f3;n Civil por la Igualdad y la Justicia (ACIJ), Argentina.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>rfassina@acij.org.ar</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio8-09562478221115334"><p><bold>Bah&#x000ed;a Flores Pacheco coordinates the Communication team at CISCSA
Ciudades Feministas, Centro de Intercambio y Servicios para el Cono Sur,
Argentina</bold>.</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>bahiasinflores@gmail.com</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio9-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Graciela Medina is a member of the Citizenship School team at
Instituto P&#x000f3;lis, Brazil.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>graciela@polis.org.br</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio10-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Alejandro Muniz is a member of the Communication team of the
Federaci&#x000f3;n Uruguaya de Cooperativas de Vivienda por Ayuda Mutua
(FUCVAM), Uruguay.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>alejandromuniz@fucvam.org.uy</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio11-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Soledad P&#x000e9;rez is a member of CISCSA Ciudades Feministas, Centro de
Intercambio y Servicios para el Cono Sur, Argentina.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>soledad@ciscsa.org.ar</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio12-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Silsa Pineda is a member of the Communication team of FUNDASAL, El
Salvador.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>spineda@fundasal.org.sv</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio13-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Marilyn Reina is a member of the Communication team of the Federaci&#x000f3;n
Uruguaya de Cooperativas de Vivienda por Ayuda Mutua (FUCVAM),
Uruguay.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>mar.reina@fucvam.org.uy</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio14-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Luz Amparo S&#x000e1;nchez Medina is Project Coordinator at Corporaci&#x000f3;n
Region, Colombia.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>amparo.sanchez@region.org.co</email></bold>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="bio15-09562478221115334"><p>
<bold>Juan Xavier is a member of the Communication team of the Federaci&#x000f3;n
Uruguaya de Cooperativas de Vivienda por Ayuda Mutua (FUCVAM),
Uruguay.</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Email: <email>juan.xavier@fucvam.org.uy</email></bold>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2022 International Institute for Environment and Development
(IIED)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="society">International Institute for Environment and
Development</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits
any use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further
permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE
and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>How do ordinary citizens, activists and urban practitioners learn to become
agents of change for a socially just habitat? The paper explores this question
through the experiences of eight grassroots schools of popular urbanism working
under the umbrella of the Habitat International Coalition (HIC) in Latin
America. Building on a process of self-documentation and collective pedagogic
reflection driven by the protagonists of these schools, the analysis explores
the core pedagogic practices identified across the schools to enact popular
urbanism as a collective and intentional praxis: to weave,
<italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic>, mobilize, reverberate and emancipate. We argue
that, put in motion, these pedagogic practices transgress the rules and
boundaries of the formal classroom, taking participants to and through other
sites and modes of learning that host significant potential to stimulate
collectivizing and alternative ways of seeking change towards urban
equality.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>critical pedagogy</kwd><kwd>Latin America</kwd><kwd>pedagogic practices</kwd><kwd>popular urbanism</kwd><kwd>urban equality</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="award1-09562478221115334"><funding-source id="funding1-09562478221115334">
<institution-wrap><institution>UK Research and Innovation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100014013</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id rid="funding1-09562478221115334">ES/ P011225/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><fig position="float" id="fig6-09562478221115334"><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_09562478221115334-img1" position="float"/></fig><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-09562478221115334"><title>I. Introduction</title><p>
<disp-quote><p><italic toggle="yes">The academy is not paradise. But learning is a place where paradise
can be created. &#x02026; This is education as the practice of
freedom</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn1-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">1</xref>)</sup></p></disp-quote>
</p><p>In this quote, bell hooks invites us to discover the practice of freedom through
learning; not as a practice of individual freedom but as a collective way to
transform the world we live in. In this paper, we look at sites of learning other
than the academy, where paradise can be created. We reflect collectively on the
pedagogic practices of eight schools of popular urbanism working under the umbrella
of the Habitat International Coalition (HIC) across Latin America, and on their
capacity to activate critical agency to confront urban inequalities and advance
habitat-related human rights.</p><p>HIC is a global alliance currently constituted by over 350 member organizations (of
which about a third are based in Latin America), which struggle collectively for
greater social justice, gender equality and environmental sustainability. For over
45 years, the Coalition has brought together social movements, non-governmental
organizations, community-based organizations and activist and research institutions
with a common political purpose: mobilizing their collective muscle from local to
global scales to make visible, defend and produce habitat rights.<sup>(<xref rid="fn2-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">2</xref>)</sup> In keeping with
its collective orientation, the Coalition&#x02019;s structures (its Board, General
Secretariat and Regional Coordination Offices) follow the mandate of HIC&#x02019;s Members,
who are their governing body.</p><p>The schools analysed here are not one institution, but rather an assemblage of
diverse pedagogic experiences. They are run by HIC members, friends and allies in
Latin America, and each school has a high degree of autonomy. Their pedagogic
practices are encapsulated in formative processes: in the building of cooperative
housing movements in Uruguay, and the capacity-building of Colombian taxi driver
associations to become inclusive in their work with people with disabilities; in the
learning encounters between Indigenous populations and low-income communities in San
Mart&#x000ed;n de los Andes in Argentina, and the reclaiming of bodies and public spaces
from a feminist perspective in C&#x000f3;rdoba, Argentina, to name a few. Despite their
diversity, the schools have in common the political parity of learners and
pedagogues (who include community leaders, cooperative members, youth, women&#x02019;s
groups and local government officials, among others), as well as a commitment to
horizontal, counter-hegemonic learning to act in advancing struggles through popular
urbanism.<sup>(<xref rid="fn3-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">3</xref>)</sup></p><p>Most of the schools analysed here are part of the HIC Latin America (HIC-AL) working
group on the social production of habitat. This group encompasses a great diversity
of theoretical approaches, from those rooted in a Marxist perspective that
ultimately seek to restore the social function of land and housing, to feminist and
decolonial perspectives rooted in the assumption that theory, knowledge and practice
are constantly re-made through activism and resistance. In this sense, the Coalition
has acted over the years as a resonance chamber, enabling member organizations to
exchange and mature their practices in critical dialogue with others.<sup>(<xref rid="fn4-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">4</xref>)</sup> In a similar vein,
HIC-AL&#x02019;s involvement with the schools is expressed in several ways, from providing
inputs into their pedagogies, concepts and content, to nurturing and expanding their
regional networking capacity. Since 2003, HIC-AL has also hosted a working group on
capacity-strengthening which has spearheaded the consolidation of various pedagogic
experiences from its members and articulated some of them into formal education
programmes (including the Diploma Course in Participatory Design, one of the
experiences analysed in this paper).</p><p>How do these diverse pedagogic practices contribute to achieving their transformative
and transgressive vocation? Or, in other words: How do participants learn to become
agents of change for a socially just habitat? To respond to these questions, in June
2019, the two first-named authors of this paper (one of whom became president of HIC
in 2020), embarked on an in-depth pedagogic exploration of the schools under the
HIC-AL umbrella as part of the capacity-building and action research programme,
Knowledge in Action for Urban Equality (KNOW). The research initially involved 21
extensive conversations with 14 HIC-AL members and affiliates, online and in person
in Argentina, Colombia, Chile, Cuba and Mexico.<sup>(<xref rid="fn5-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">5</xref>)</sup> As the COVID-19 pandemic brought
the possibility of further face-to-face encounters to a halt, we shifted to a
multimodal way of working, which included a process of self-documentation and
analysis by schools interested in this reflexive<sup>(<xref rid="fn6-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">6</xref>)</sup> exercise and collective online
workshops devoted to identifying the core &#x0201c;pedagogic narrative&#x0201d; underpinning each
school, as well as their common practices (see <xref rid="fig1-09562478221115334" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-09562478221115334"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Location of HIC-AL members (orange dots) and the eight schools (violet dots)
analysed in this paper</p><p>SOURCE: Authors.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_09562478221115334-fig1" position="float"/></fig><p>The remote phase of engagement evolved around the production of short films by each
school and a collective documentary, as entry points to distil the core and common
pedagogic practices that have coalesced under the umbrella of HIC-AL. In this
context, the short films and documentary acted as catalysts for horizontal
conversations on the role of popular urbanism pedagogies in nurturing struggles for
habitat rights; that is, articulating critical and political learning processes as
pathways towards strategic change to address inequalities. Supported by La Sand&#x000ed;a
Digital &#x02013; a feminist collective of filmmakers based in Mexico &#x02013; this horizontal
process involved four online workshops with around 15 participants each, between
August and November 2021, in which pedagogues and communication teams from each
school developed their story from a pedagogic viewpoint. These exchanges evolved
from oral accounts to audiovisual narratives and culminated in a fifth comparative
analysis workshop through which all participants identified the practices that make
their pedagogic approaches critical and counter-hegemonic. Between the workshops,
the pedagogic reflexion involved a larger number of participants, as each school
engaged in searches through their own archives, focus group discussions, one-to-one
interviews, storyboarding and filming.</p><p>The following section outlines key contributions and principles of critical pedagogy
within the field of popular urbanism in Latin America. We then analyse the five core
pedagogic practices collectively identified by the eight schools: to weave,
<italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic> (feel-think), mobilize, reverberate and
emancipate.</p></sec><sec id="section2-09562478221115334"><title>II. The Role of Critical Pedagogy in Popular Struggles for Habitat Rights</title><p>Building on historical experiences, such as the <italic toggle="yes">Hacedores de Ciudad</italic>
in Venezuela and large-scale movements of <italic toggle="yes">autogesti&#x000f3;n</italic> in Peru in
the 1960s, numerous authors have highlighted the impactful scale and scope of
popular urbanization in the context of Latin America. The strategy is recognized as
a set of practices and processes through which the hegemonic logics of the market,
political regulation and fiscalization in issues of land, housing and territory are
contested through bottom-up, citizen-led actions.<sup>(<xref rid="fn7-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">7</xref>)</sup></p><p>While this body of research often refers to &#x0201c;popular urbanization&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;popular
urbanism&#x0201d; as interchangeable notions, we argue for recognizing their difference.
Popular urbanization pertains to the processes by which low-income and marginalized
women and men typically produce and appropriate the urban territory. In contrast,
popular urbanism &#x02013; the arena in which the schools thrive and the focus of the
present paper &#x02013; refers to a domain of practice that contests the institutional power
of urbanism as a discipline, and the legitimacy it enjoys in producing knowledge and
practices. Thus, popular urbanism encapsulates a collective intentionality to
reclaim the authority and legitimacy of other ways of producing and using the city
as a commons; the ability to craft a different relationship with state institutions
across periods of dictatorship and (re)democratization<sup>(<xref rid="fn8-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">8</xref>)</sup> and conscious and explicit
efforts to valorize the experiences, pedagogies and principles that have redressed
social and environmental inequalities and injustices over time, and that continue to
do so.</p><p>Within Latin America, historiographic work has highlighted the political and
socio-spatial complexity of popular urbanism throughout the 20th and 21st
centuries.<sup>(<xref rid="fn9-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">9</xref>)</sup> Tracing the genealogy of popular urbanism across Latin America
has been a central project for many regional activists and academics over the years,
with a notable example being the work of the architect Enrique Ort&#x000ed;z Flores, a
member of the non-governmental organization COPEVI since 1965, and one of the
co-founders of HIC in 1976.<sup>(<xref rid="fn10-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">10</xref>)</sup></p><p>To talk about popular urbanism is thus to recognize other ways of making the city,
parallel to the rules established by the institutions of government and academia,
and to the logics of capital.<sup>(<xref rid="fn11-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">11</xref>)</sup> In this conception, popular urbanism hosts substantial
potential to redress prevalent urban inequalities in four key dimensions: first, by
working towards the fair redistribution and commoning of the goods, services and
opportunities that are integral to the realization of habitat-related rights;
second, by amplifying the voices and claiming recognition for differentiated
identities and knowledges, particularly of those engaged in pushing the boundaries
for urban equality on an everyday basis; third, by advocating for their parity in
political participation, not just in invited spaces, but through claimed spaces of
city-making; and last, but not least, by fostering urban practices built on mutual
care and solidarity, as well as on state responsibility.<sup>(<xref rid="fn12-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">12</xref>)</sup></p><p>Thus, popular urbanism is a conscious political practice; a practice identified with
by social movements, NGOs, research institutions and other supporting organizations
from the eight schools participating in this collective reflexion, as well as many
others across the region. Although not all these pedagogic experiences call
themselves &#x0201c;schools&#x0201d;, many self-identify as such in recognition of their alignment
with the foundational work of Paulo Freire.<sup>(<xref rid="fn13-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">13</xref>)</sup> It is the practice of critical
pedagogy, with its ethical and political intentions, that is key to re-signifying
where popular urbanism learning happens and how it works. As critiqued by
Giroux,<sup>(<xref rid="fn14-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">14</xref>)</sup> the school, as the main social instrument and space devoted to
education, has become over time an instrument of students&#x02019; social assimilation
rather than a space to engage critically with society and strengthen capacities to
change it. Adhering to this critique, the work of the schools discussed in this
paper encapsulate a conscious effort towards reclaiming the emancipatory power of
popular education.</p><p>Although Freirean critical pedagogy has its roots in rural peasant movements in
Brazil, it has long been embraced by, and expanded into, urban realities as well as
more intersectional and feminist perspectives on popular struggles. Black,
Indigenous and feminist scholars, in this context, have brought forward notions of
the oppressed in relation to structural racism and patriarchal
domination.<sup>(<xref rid="fn15-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">15</xref>)</sup> Freire&#x02019;s foundational work<sup>(<xref rid="fn16-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">16</xref>)</sup> in critical pedagogy
emphasized the dialogical relation between theory and praxis, as well as the
importance of giving this praxis a direction towards change for social justice,
nurtured by iterative and deep processes of reflexion. His conceptualization of
critical pedagogy as freedom through learning benefited over the years from
contributions from postmodern, feminist, postcolonial and queer theories and,
perhaps most importantly, has continued to be a central practice of social movements
and organized civil society.</p><p>According to Sara Motta, the critical pedagogies underpinning popular urbanism do not
aim to create an <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;alternative monological practice of life&#x0201d;</italic>, but
rather aim for the <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;pedagogical [to] become an essential part of creating
the openings, possibilities and relationships to enable communities that are
often silenced and violently invisibilised to appear as embodied political
subjects&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn17-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">17</xref>)</sup> To achieve this end, learning through, with and in
struggle, requires a pedagogy that transgresses the rules and boundaries of the
classroom as a site of learning and <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;instead embed[s] educational practice
in multiple spaces: the community, the workplace, the co-operative, the home,
the self&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn18-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">18</xref>)</sup> Moreover, the content of learning is co-constructed rather
than being based on predefined curricula, which is responsive to context-specific
urban knowledges of learner-pedagogues as well as to the inequalities and injustices
the learning process seeks to confront. As argued by Motta, for learning to become
emancipatory, pedagogical practice needs to be the <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;product of praxis at the
collective level of lived experience&#x0201d;</italic>,<sup>(<xref rid="fn19-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">19</xref>)</sup> in which counter-hegemonic
knowledges and (hi)stories of resistance and hope are cultivated.</p><p>While these counter-hegemonic knowledges and ways of knowing
(<italic toggle="yes">saberes</italic>) have received attention in discussions on critical
pedagogy and popular urbanism,<sup>(<xref rid="fn20-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">20</xref>)</sup> relatively little attention has been given to the
pedagogic practices (<italic toggle="yes">haceres</italic>) that nurture and sustain them. Thus,
this paper centres on <italic toggle="yes">how</italic> learning activates collective agency for
a socially just habitat, aiming to elicit pedagogic practices that stimulate
alternative ways of seeing, listening, being and seeking change.</p></sec><sec id="section3-09562478221115334"><title>III. The Schools at Work: <italic toggle="yes">Haceres</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Saberes</italic>
as Pedagogic Practices</title><p><xref rid="table1-09562478221115334" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> provides an
overview of the eight schools participating in this pedagogic reflexion, and their
convenors, learners, purpose and pedagogic approach.<sup>(<xref rid="fn21-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">21</xref>)</sup></p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-09562478221115334"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Description of the eight pedagogic experiences documented and analysed in
this paper</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_09562478221115334-table1" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name and location</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Convenors</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Learners</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aims</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedagogic approach</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Diplomado Territorio y H&#x000e1;bitat &#x02013;</italic> Diploma on
Territory and Habitat; Mexico City</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma de la Ciudad de M&#x000e9;xico, Movimiento Urbano
Popular, Centro Operacional de Vivienda y Poblamiento, AC
(COPEVI)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Members of collective and neighbourhood organizations,
Indigenous inhabitants of the city and university students</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To develop critical, reflexive and propositional thinking; based
on popular urban movements&#x02019; perspective on <italic toggle="yes">buen
vivir</italic>, participatory democracy and territory and
habitat rights.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focusing on dialogic methods, inter-learning and the
co-production of knowledge among participants, the Diploma is
structured across 4 online modules over a period of almost 8
months. Before the pandemic, the course also included field
visits.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cooperativism and women-led housing construction and habitat
processes; Potrerillos and La Palma, San Salvador</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fundaci&#x000f3;n Salvadore&#x000f1;a de Desarrollo y Vivienda M&#x000ed;nima
(FUNDASAL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Female) community and cooperative members.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To strengthen women&#x02019;s knowledge and capacities to claim and
enact their habitat rights.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">From self-recognizing one&#x02019;s rights to constructing them
collectively through women-led housing, FUNDASAL&#x02019;s pedagogy
works through a mix of workshops aimed at developing a new
consciousness and hands-on sessions on self-construction
techniques.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Medell&#x000ed;n Ciudad Accesible</italic> &#x02013; Medell&#x000ed;n Accessible
City; Medell&#x000ed;n, Colombia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corporaci&#x000f3;n Regi&#x000f3;n + Fuerza Incluyente</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neighbourhood organizations, collectives of disabled people, and
advocacy target audiences (such as taxi drivers, local
government officials and the general public).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To strengthen participants&#x02019; consciousness and capacities to
advocate an intersectional perspective in building mobility as
part of the Right to the City.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Largely experiential pedagogies, which engage with and through
the realities of differently-abled people, for example, through
discussions, events in public squares, shared walks and transits
through the city.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cooperativism schools, with a particular focus on
intergenerational and gendered learning and relationships with
the state; across Uruguay</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Federaci&#x000f3;n Uruguaya de Cooperativas de Vivienda por Ayuda
Mutua<break/>(FUCVAM)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current and future members of cooperatives, with some learning
processes particularly focused on youth and women.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To nurture, sustain and mobilize the housing cooperative
movement as a key strategy to reclaim the social function of
housing and land.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capacity-building is integral to the working of cooperatives and
operates through different modes of learning, including
learning-by-living/doing, decentralized workshops, and peer
learning across cooperatives.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feminism schools &#x02013; <italic toggle="yes">Voces de Mujeres Diversas por
Ciudades Seguras, Inclusivas y Sostenibles</italic> &#x02013; Voices
of Diverse Women for Safe, Inclusive and Sustainable Cities;
C&#x000f3;rdoba, Argentina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CISCSA Ciudades Feministas</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community leaders and members of women and feminist
organizations, as well as women working in urbanism and urban
planning.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To strengthen debates on the rights of women and diversities to
the city; to build social force around the experiences and
demands of those identifying as women, trans and lesbians; to
develop concrete proposals that advocate for a feminist
city.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capacity-building and participatory workshops developed through
feminist methodologies, such as
<italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;cuerpo-territorio&#x0201d;</italic>, visioning exercises,
manifestos, public manifestations and celebrations.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Diplomado Iberoamericano Dise&#x000f1;o Participativo
Sustentable del Habitat &#x02013;</italic> Ibero-American Diploma in
Participatory Sustainable Habitat Design; LA Regional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Universidad Nacional Aut&#x000f3;noma de M&#x000e9;xico in collaboration with
HIC-AL and Taller 36 of the National University of Cordoba</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anyone interested in the social production of habitat, including
leaders of grassroots organizations, university students and
professionals of different disciplines.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To learn and apply concepts, methodologies and tools for the
social production and management of habitat, which are not
taught in regular design courses.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inter-learning spaces as well as group and individual work
across 210 hours, 2 x 2 hours of live sessions per week
(workshops) and 8 hours of independent learning.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escola da Cidadania</italic> &#x02013; Citizenship School, with
a cycle of 16 different thematic courses (such as culture and
cities, climate justice and urban infrastructures, etc); S&#x000e3;o
Paulo, with online participants across Brazil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instituto P&#x000f3;lis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400&#x02013;500 online learners with diverse identities and backgrounds
(in terms of professional experience, gender, age, geography and
others). Core target groups are social movements and public
officials.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To be a space for reflection and formation of critical thinking
in the different dimensions of constructing citizenship: human
rights, right to the city, activism and public policies.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polis Institute applies creative pedagogic practices, such as
the collective development of thematic playlists, and the use of
social media as a means to extend the learning beyond the
boundaries of the school.<break/>Practically, each thematic
course consists of six online 2-hour weekly sessions, with
voluntary discussion groups in between sessions.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Programa de Formaci&#x000f3;n en Derechos para Referentes
Barriales</italic> &#x02013; Formative Programme in Rights for
Community Leaders; Buenos Aires 2019, now online and with reach
across Argentina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asociaci&#x000f3;n Civil por la Igualdad y la Justicia (ACIJ)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In 2019 ACIJ&#x02019;s school brought together 60 community leaders,
including representatives of social and political organisations
in informal settlements, and independent leaders, who seek to
incorporate or reinforce within their repertoire of public
actions, the use of legal tools and the language of rights as a
way to strengthen their interaction with public
authorities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To promote communities&#x02019; understanding of their rights as
guaranteed by the legal system.<break/>To strengthen grassroots
organizations&#x02019; capacities to claim their right to the city and
to claim parity of political participation in their
neighbourhood improvement and redevelopment processes.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACIJ&#x02019;s approach is learner-centred and works through horizontal
exchanges that valorize the knowledges and practices of
community leaders as pedagogues. The curriculum is therefore
open and flexible to respond to specific needs, contexts and
challenges and typically works through 13 sessions/4 modules/40
hours of classes over three months.<break/>Sessions are
facilitated as interactive workshops &#x02013; with space for debates
and role plays.</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-09562478221115334"><p>SOURCE: Authors.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We now turn to the five verbs that encapsulate the core pedagogic practices
identified by the participating schools as crucial means to foster the articulation
of <italic toggle="yes">saberes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">haceres</italic> underpinning popular
urbanism. While not all these verbs are present equally across all schools, they
resonated strongly with every participant, as critical practices with profound
potential for activating and sustaining change. We explore each verb starting with a
vignette from a sequence of the films produced by the schools, followed by a
discussion of what each critical pedagogic practice involves in developing key
capacities to tackle urban inequality.</p><sec id="section4-09562478221115334"><title>a. Weave</title><p>
<disp-quote><p>On a sunny day, an architect and an Indigenous inhabitant of
<italic toggle="yes">Barrio Intercultural</italic> stand on an empty lot, holding
in their hands a model of one of the planned buildings in the
neighbourhood. As their hands move around the model, the light creates
shadows that get them to imagine together how the building might be used
at different times of the day and what that would mean for different
collective uses and members of the community.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>In the <italic toggle="yes">Barrio Intercultural</italic> (Intercultural Neighbourhood) in the
south of Argentina, inter-learning spaces bring together diverse professions,
social identities, knowledges and practices in dialogue with each other.
Inter-learning, in this context, refers to a process whereby the intentional
juxtaposition of different, contrasting and complementary knowledges and
practices generates new forms of living and working together. This school
emerged from an alliance between <italic toggle="yes">Vecinos Sin Techo</italic> (Neighbours
without a Roof) and the Curruhuinca <italic toggle="yes">lof</italic> (community) of the
original Mapuche people in San Mart&#x000ed;n de los Andes.<sup>(<xref rid="fn22-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">22</xref>)</sup> Initially unified by their
common need for housing, over time the development of their Intercultural
Neighbourhood became a means to coexist in a common place rooted in the
cosmovision (or worldview) of <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;buen vivir&#x0201d;</italic>. As argued by
Eduardo Gudynas, this cosmovision embodies community-centric, ecologically
balanced and culturally sensitive conviviality.<sup>(<xref rid="fn23-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">23</xref>)</sup> It encapsulates
perspectives that are a far cry from market-led approaches to housing, land and
services and seeks to build new forms of public coexistence, in diversity and in
harmony with nature. In this experience and across those of other schools,
weaving is the key pedagogic practice that crafts a new material and social
fabric by interlacing threads of collective dreams, rights and aspirations.</p><p>Weaving is not just about connecting different knowledges and actors, but a
process of rooting contemporary struggles in a rich historic trajectory of
learning from, for and in political struggle. In the case of the school of
<italic toggle="yes">Barrio Intercultural</italic>, contemporary collective dwelling
practices were reimagined with the Mapuche people &#x02013; and thus re-embedded in
their ancestral forms of being part of the territory. Here, the school has been
the open space that connected historical and contemporary demands and ways of
being in dialogue with Western critiques of capitalism, particularly from the
field of feminist thought and environmentalism. This dialogue not only wove
together narratives and experiences of oppression but also alternative ways to
dwell in the territory as an intercultural community, which over time opened new
institutional possibilities for the recognition of social production of habitat
processes.</p><p>The practice of weaving together historically rooted and contemporary habitat
struggles is also present in the pedagogic practices of the Ibero-American
Diploma in Participatory Sustainable Habitat Design, a regional experience with
22 organizations that actively engages with the <italic toggle="yes">Barrio
Intercultural</italic> in its content and pedagogy. The diploma also draws
from the pedagogical practices of the so-called <italic toggle="yes">Taller Total</italic> in
the early 1970s, a model in which architecture was understood as a social
practice, and in which &#x0201c;users&#x0201d; or dwellers play the same role as trained
professionals.<sup>(<xref rid="fn24-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">24</xref>)</sup></p><p><italic toggle="yes">Taller Total</italic> set a radical precedent across the region, aiming
to open up the university and transform the education of urban practitioners
through a collective transdisciplinary pedagogical experience. Originally
implemented at the National University of C&#x000f3;rdoba (Argentina), over time the
pedagogic principles and practices of <italic toggle="yes">Taller Total</italic> were adopted
in other locations and disciplines. While this wave of radical pedagogies was
brought to a halt in 1975 by the repressive dictatorship of 1976&#x02013;1983, its
legacy continues to be re-lived by contemporary experiences such as the
<italic toggle="yes">Barrio Intercultural</italic> and the diploma course. In these
experiences, the key tenets of <italic toggle="yes">Taller Total</italic> are reactivated
under contemporary circumstances, prompting a dissolution of disciplinary
boundaries converging in the &#x0201c;habitat&#x0201d; problematic by building a critical
history of the habitat and its social production, while weaving in new
capacities and possibilities for social transformation.</p><p>Hence, weaving as a historical and relational pedagogy generates an
inter-learning space that enables the interaction between different
<italic toggle="yes">saberes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">haceres</italic>, rooting them,
problematizing them, questioning their assumptions and generating new ways to
frame a given problematic. Unlike conventional pedagogies, the capacity to act
does not rest on having full knowledge and control of the problem and the
solution, but rather on the capacity to engage with uncertainty, singularity and
conflict, and to recognize and deploy the social production of habitat as long
and open-ended processes of dwelling that will continue to change over time.</p></sec><sec id="section5-09562478221115334"><title>b. <italic toggle="yes">Sentipensar</italic></title><p>
<disp-quote><p>In a community centre in C&#x000f3;rdoba, Fada lies on the floor, the outline of
her body being drawn on a big sheet of paper. <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;Now, let&#x02019;s think
where we locate our emotions, which form they have, and where we
want to put them on our drawing of the body&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn25-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">25</xref>)</sup>
Paola guides the group through an exercise of
<italic toggle="yes">cuerpo-territorio</italic>, a feminist methodology often
used in the context of violence and inequalities to reflect on the body
as <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;means to diagnose territorial conflicts and to initiate
healing of bodies and territory&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn26-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">26</xref>)</sup></p></disp-quote>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Sentipensar</italic> can be roughly translated in English as the capacity
to &#x0201c;feel-think&#x0201d;. <italic toggle="yes">Sentipensar</italic> refers to pedagogies that
cultivate sensibilities and affections that see the human and non-human world as
interdependent and in constant flow. It invites us to engage with the energy
that flows and interacts between situated minds-bodies and action in their full
diversity and highlights the role of the medium and the media in the
construction of <italic toggle="yes">haceres</italic> and
<italic toggle="yes">saberes</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn27-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">27</xref>)</sup></p><p><italic toggle="yes">Sentipensar</italic> offers a transformative pedagogic practice that
emphasizes the complementary relationship <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;between the</italic>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">sentir</italic></bold>
<italic toggle="yes">of intuition and the inner life and the</italic>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">pensar</italic></bold>
<italic toggle="yes">of intellectualism, between tacit knowledge and wisdom; between Western
and non-Western ways of knowing and doing.&#x0201d;</italic><sup>(<xref rid="fn28-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">28</xref>)</sup> Practised
across several of the schools as a way to learn and as a learnt capacity, it
departs from our language and affections as sites that actively build the world
in which we are immersed in its full complexity. It challenges the Cartesian
separation between us humans and nature, as well as the separation between us
and others. From this perspective, to co-learn is to develop simultaneous
capacities to be, to know, to do and to care.</p><p>The potential of <italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic> to confront urban inequalities is
multiple and most deeply realized through the way it advances epistemic justice
&#x02013; not just by including typically marginalized <italic toggle="yes">saberes</italic> but,
more deeply, by awakening new ways of making sense of the world from our senses,
affections and positionalities. This critical pedagogy practice adopts feminist
and decolonial thought, insisting on the plurality of knowledges, to acknowledge
the diverse points of departure and inequalities that, as argued by De Jong and
colleagues: <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;emerge from the intersections of race/ethnicity, class,
gender, sexual orientation, age, body ableness and so
on&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn29-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">29</xref>)</sup> This pedagogic practice further emphasizes the
importance of situating the present in historical perspective in order to unveil
the roots of different forms of oppression.</p><p>In the above vignette, CISCSA&#x02019;s feminist school works from the scale of the body
to understand the household, the neighbourhood, the city and the wider territory
(see <xref rid="fig2-09562478221115334" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). This
engagement with felt and sensed areas of pain and joy, of repression and
freedom, allows learners to connect with their own maps of
<italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic> and those of others, and to trace patriarchal
and racist genealogies, active in the present way in which women&#x02019;s bodies can
and cannot inhabit the city; aiming, in short, to counteract their disembodiment
from the city.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2-09562478221115334"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>&#x0201c;Our body, our territory&#x0201d;</p><p>SOURCE: <xref rid="bibr7-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">CISCSA et al.
(2021)</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_09562478221115334-fig2" position="float"/></fig><p>Like weaving, this approach resonates with Ivan Illich&#x02019;s work on learning
webs,<sup>(<xref rid="fn30-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">30</xref>)</sup> through which he argues that learning requires unlearning
the ways in which our bodies and minds have been schooled and tamed. The
un-taming of the schools under the HIC umbrella in Latin America through
<italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic> practices should not be confused with the
development of empathy, but rather with radical ways to see the world, to break
with deeply learnt forms of oppression and control that inadvertently travel
from our bodies into our homes, neighbourhoods, public spaces and cities. Here,
<italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic> practices activate new forms of caring and
conviviality. This approach is also clearly expressed in the <italic toggle="yes">Barrio
Intercultural</italic>, where the neighbourhood is conceived, built and
lived as a place for mutuality and conviviality.</p></sec><sec id="section6-09562478221115334"><title>c. Mobilize</title><p>
<disp-quote><p>In the hillsides of Medell&#x000ed;n, members of <italic toggle="yes">Fuerza
Incluyente</italic>, a collective of people with disabilities, wait
for a taxi to get to the city centre. As a taxi driver stops, the group
engages in a conversation with him, first showing him how to dismantle
and store a wheelchair in the taxi boot. Then, Nancy &#x02013; who has short
upper limbs &#x02013; takes a seat and instructs the taxi driver to put her
seatbelt on. On their way, the conversation covers a range of topics &#x02013;
from Nancy sharing her experience with verbal abuse, to the ways in
which people with disabilities can be addressed in a dignified manner.
At the end of their ride, she hands the taxi driver a sticker to put
behind his windshield (see <xref rid="fig3-09562478221115334" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). It declares him an
&#x0201c;inclusive taxi driver&#x0201d;, that is, one of many transport providers across
the city who have taken part in a pedagogic experience of learning from
people with disabilities and who commit to practising inclusive
transport services.<sup>(<xref rid="fn31-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">31</xref>)</sup></p></disp-quote>
</p><fig position="float" id="fig3-09562478221115334"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>&#x0201c;I am an inclusive taxi driver&#x0201d;</p><p>SOURCE: <xref rid="bibr8-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Corporaci&#x000f3;n
Regi&#x000f3;n et al. (2021)</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_09562478221115334-fig3" position="float"/></fig><p>In this vignette, the taxi becomes the classroom, the co-learning space where
women and men with different disabilities share their experience of the city
with taxi drivers and, in the process, build new ways of understanding how their
bodies interact in a common territory. The pedagogic practice of &#x0201c;mobilizing&#x0201d;,
in a literal sense, fosters the inclusion of marginalized groups in the city,
not merely by adapting the city to their particular needs through retrofitted
urban design, but by advocating for more pluralistic and intersectional
perspectives on urban mobilities. In this school, <italic toggle="yes">Corporaci&#x000f3;n
Regi&#x000f3;n</italic>, working together with <italic toggle="yes">Fuerza Incluyente</italic>,
co-developed an experiential pedagogy which opens spaces to encounter
diversities, enhancing possibilities for people with disabilities to move around
the city, while simultaneously generating a new consciousness among key actors
and institutions responsible for enhancing mobility for all.</p><p>Another way in which these mobilizing pedagogies address inequalities is through
the strategic role that education assumes in social movements for facilitating
the transfer and expansion of knowledges over generations, as well as across
territories. In the Uruguayan Federation of Mutual Aid Housing Cooperatives
(FUCVAM), intergenerational learning has been a strong pillar of its work as a
movement. This, on the one hand, concerns the everyday learning through which
young people living in cooperatives acquire values of mutual care and
solidarity, as well as consciousness of the wider political project within which
they are growing up. As Ignacio Lostorto, a young adult in FUCVAM&#x02019;s cooperative
school states: <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;[mutual care] is the most natural, beautiful, and
productive way to advance, and it is the way that promotes values such as
conviviality and which gives you tranquillity with yourself and with
others&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn32-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">32</xref>)</sup></p><p>On the other hand, FUCVAM has evolved and systematized the promotion of
intergenerational learning through modular pedagogic systems that can be adapted
to specific needs and challenges among cooperative members. For instance,
confronted with the challenge that young adults often left the cooperatives
after moving out of their parents&#x02019; house, the Federation started the so-called
<italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;nucleo de promoci&#x000f3;n juvenil&#x0201d;</italic> (youth educators programme).
Javier Vidal, the former coordinator of formative activities at FUCVAM,
highlights that this initiative: <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;did not intend to fill the physical
premises of the Federation with hundreds of young people, but rather aimed
to work in a decentralized manner across the territory, so that young people
can build their own spaces in the cooperatives and, in turn, create new
cooperatives when they move out, when they socialize, when they start their
families. That worked pretty well, we had many cooperatives originating from
this&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn33-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">33</xref>)</sup></p><p>Thus, mobilizing pedagogies operate both as a means to enhance everyday mobility
from an intersectional perspective and to promote intergenerational learning and
mobilization within social movements. To mobilize involves seeking change
through moving literally across the city as well as by mobilizing collective
agency. Through these practices, mobilizing becomes a means to common the city,
and to restore its social function and production, opening the space for
sustained and expanded action.</p></sec><sec id="section7-09562478221115334"><title>d. Reverberate</title><p>
<disp-quote><p>Flavia has not missed a single session of Polis&#x02019;s Citizenship School.
Since the start of the pandemic, she felt isolated in her struggles for
the right to the city, and overwhelmed by the political neglect with
which they are ignored. Fighting isolation, she has become active on
social media platforms, where she engages in discussions initiated by
the school that resonate with her. In the process and inadvertently, she
is expanding the learning process beyond the school, allowing her &#x0201c;aha&#x0201d;
moments and reflections to reverberate with a far wider community.</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Following its relaunch at the beginning of the pandemic, Polis Institute&#x02019;s
Citizenship School in Brazil provoked unanticipated pathways and practices of
learning, as its pedagogies started to reverberate from curated online sessions
to social media channels like Instagram (see <xref rid="fig4-09562478221115334" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). There, stories and
observations from the virtual classroom were shared and further debated, while
new conversations led to thousands of new followers. Engagement with the
activating effects of social media and their political power, for example,
through proactive engagement with &#x0201c;influencers&#x0201d;, has since become a strategic
leveraging practice for the pedagogues running the school.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4-09562478221115334"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Snapshots of reverberations of the School of Citizenship on Instagram</p><p>SOURCE: Authors&#x02019; personal communication with Polis Institute based on raw
footage shared by them.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_09562478221115334-fig4" position="float"/></fig><p>The notion of &#x0201c;reverberation&#x0201d; is widely applied in sound studies,<sup>(<xref rid="fn34-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">34</xref>)</sup> not only
with a physical but also a political meaning. In this context, to reverberate
means the putting-in-motion of resonance, to amplify diversity perspectives, to
grant them a dignity of attention and recognize their value and importance. As a
pedagogic practice, reverberating is led by learners as they synthesize their
own sense-making of how, for example, a transgender person experiences their
right to the city, while provoking further reflections that together build new
collective understandings, creating social proximity even in a context of
physical distance. As such, to reverberate sets off new possibilities to act
across spaces, temporalities and struggles that go beyond those curated by the
schools.</p><p>Moreover, reverberation provokes, in Gershon&#x02019;s words, <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;a collapsing of
distance across spacetimes so that the reverberations of resonances come
crashing down on individuals, groups&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn35-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">35</xref>)</sup> Hence, reverberating
pedagogies also give rise to the travelling of ideas and practices across the
region through relational and translocal learning. For instance, in the online
Citizenship School of Polis, one participant from northern Brazil managed to
successfully fight an imminent eviction with the tools and capacities acquired
from a participant from another region, which resonated with him. In a similar
way, the participatory design process undertaken in the <italic toggle="yes">Barrio
Intercultural</italic> in Argentina generated reverberations through a
shared framing of the right to housing as a collective practice embedded in
conviviality with one another and with the territory. Moreover, the process of
&#x0201c;weaving&#x0201d; pedagogies described before, here reverberates to a large number of
learners and organizations, leading to the formation of new collectives working
on participatory design in the social production and management of habitat.</p></sec><sec id="section8-09562478221115334"><title>e. Emancipate</title><p>
<disp-quote><p>Amidst laughter and the creation of an unfolding collective manifesto
towards a feminist city, Paola reflects on CISCSA&#x02019;s feminist school:
<italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;Something that we seek all the time in this work process is
to encourage ourselves to imagine other possible realities that we
always had on the horizon. We conduct several exercises to be able
to make room to imagine a feminist city in which we would like to
live [<xref rid="fig5-09562478221115334" ref-type="fig">Figure
5</xref>]. This means to give rise to the power of the feminist
imagination, to the possibility of imagining and dwelling cities
from other more beautiful, fairer, more habitable, more loving
places.&#x0201d;</italic><sup>(<xref rid="fn36-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">36</xref>)</sup></p></disp-quote>
</p><fig position="float" id="fig5-09562478221115334"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>&#x0201c;We want access to dignified housing: The land is for those who inhabit
it!&#x0201d;</p><p>SOURCE: <xref rid="bibr7-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">CISCSA et al.
(2021)</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_09562478221115334-fig5" position="float"/></fig><p>Across all the schools, pedagogy is critical to the project of emancipation, and
emancipation critical to urban equality. As a pedagogy, to emancipate does not
just evoke a destination but a journey; a journey through which the capacities
to dare and to imagine a different city are activated. This intention
counteracts the pursuit of liberal and andragogical theories of learning and
brings to the fore the development of a critical consciousness that exposes and
confronts the oppressive structures which confine and limit our experience of
the urban and of the right to the city.</p><p>Drawing on Thompson&#x02019;s work,<sup>(<xref rid="fn37-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">37</xref>)</sup> while raising the case for critical pedagogy in
nursing education, Jane Harden argues that <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;everyday living as
experienced by the majority is characterised by a naive, pre-reflective
adherence to &#x02018;established&#x02019; versions of the life world. The consequence of
this is that &#x02018;factual&#x02019; or doxic patterns of living are never challenged, and
the question of legitimacy is never raised, because the social world is
presented and accepted as a natural phenomenon&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn38-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">38</xref>)</sup> In this
sense, a critical parallel can be established between nursing and urban planning
education. For a long time, professional education, in this and other fields,
has hampered critical awareness and responses from learners, inadvertently
turning professions of care into professions of oppression. In the case of
nursing education, the dismissal of emancipatory capacities has indeed turned it
into a site of oppression for those practising the profession, typically women,
who are subordinated to a subservient role.</p><p>Critical pedagogy is fundamentally about hope, liberation and
equality;<sup>(<xref rid="fn39-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">39</xref>)</sup> it is about <italic toggle="yes">conscientisation</italic> &#x02013; that
is, the process of developing a critical awareness of one&#x02019;s social reality
through reflexion and action &#x02013; and about counter-hegemonic practices, which are
the backbone of emancipatory pedagogies in the full sense of Freire&#x02019;s
educational practice theory. To emancipate thus implies to transform the
internal conflict experienced by subordinated or colonized groups in an
oppressive society, a conflict defined as <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;double
consciousness&#x0201d;</italic> by W E B Du Bois.<sup>(<xref rid="fn40-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">40</xref>)</sup> This calls for activating
a shift from seeing ourselves simultaneously through our own eyes and from the
perspective of oppressive systems such as racism, patriarchy, colonialism or
neoliberalism to rediscovering and asserting our social identities as crucial
sites to imagine more socially just visions for the future of the city.</p><p>Activating a new consciousness &#x02013; one that leads to the very possibility of
enacting counter-hegemonic and transgressive visions and practices of inhabiting
a more equal city &#x02013; is at the core of the schools working under the umbrella of
HIC-AL. In the school driven by <italic toggle="yes">Corporaci&#x000f3;n Regi&#x000f3;n</italic> and
<italic toggle="yes">Fuerza Incluyente</italic> in Medell&#x000ed;n, this translates into the
ways in which an inclusive city is approached: not as one that accommodates the
needs and experiences of people with disabilities through marginal artefacts and
ad hoc interventions such as ramps, but rather by turning accessibility and
mobility for all as a default position from which the city is planned and
managed. In a similar vein, FUCVAM&#x02019;s schools of cooperativism do not build
houses to be traded as assets in the real estate market, but as homes to be
inhabited, as concrete political practices that reclaim the social function of
housing and land in cities &#x02013; where, as expressed in the title of their short
film, <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;the dwelling is not the end, it is the beginning&#x0201d;</italic>.</p><p>CISCSA&#x02019;s feminist school explicitly employs emancipatory pedagogies that valorize
situated experiences as opportunities to reclaim the city, and align with Sara
Motta&#x02019;s call to <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;deconstruct subordinated and naturalised social and
spatial relations, while looking at gender, race, age, class, sexual
orientation and mental and physical ability as one&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn41-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">41</xref>)</sup> These
emancipatory pedagogic practices work through power and consciousness-raising,
acknowledging the existence of oppression, as well as the possibility of ending
it, and foregrounding the desire and capacity for social transformation. These
practices manifest through the use of open &#x02013; non-predetermined &#x02013; learning
strategies that encourage participants to share in a safe space their own
intersectional positionalities and experiences with those of others through
written, spoken and visual reflections.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section9-09562478221115334"><title>V. Creating Paradise Beyond the Classroom</title><p>To weave, to <italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic>, to mobilize, to reverberate and to
emancipate &#x02013; these verbs together articulate the grammar of the schools coalescing
under HIC in Latin America. The power of these actions should not be underestimated,
as together they convey the ways by which critical grassroots pedagogies can
activate collective agency and capacities to carve pathways towards urban
equality.</p><p>Teresa Caldeira<sup>(<xref rid="fn42-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">42</xref>)</sup> contends that as ordinary citizens engage in making the urban,
they often become fluent in claiming their right to the city. Working through the
critical pedagogies examined in this paper, we see that such fluency is not acquired
spontaneously or individually, but as the outcome of collective learning processes
that turn habitat struggles into sites of transformative change by linking learning
with mobilization, advocacy and action.</p><p>As argued by Paulo Freire,<sup>(<xref rid="fn43-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">43</xref>)</sup> the main method of critical pedagogy is dialogue, a
dialogue adapted to each context, in which everyone can actively participate through
the following process: (a) by encouraging women and men to develop their own
critical consciousness in order to effect change in their world through social
critique and political action; (b) by critically understanding one&#x02019;s own practice;
and (c) by changing our practices in order to tackle common struggles and act upon
reality. By collectivizing consciousness, resistance and contestation, as well as
possibilities, sensibilities and hope, we are witnessing a contemporary reinvention
of popular urbanism, driven by social movements, as a simultaneous practice of what
Motta and Esteves call <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;pedagogising the political and politicising the
pedagogical&#x0201d;</italic>.<sup>(<xref rid="fn44-09562478221115334" ref-type="fn">44</xref>)</sup> This double practice challenges the logics of neoliberal
capitalism, of patriarchy and of racism and their hegemonic translation into
systemic urban inequalities. It does so by subverting the marginalization of
ordinary citizens, by embodying learning in their practices and in the everyday life
experiences of the urban, by generating spaces to unlearn the oppressor&#x02019;s logic, by
re-signifying the social and the public, and by pluralizing the
<italic toggle="yes">saberes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">haceres</italic> that make a just city a
concrete field of imagination and action.</p><p>The five pedagogic practices shape the four dimensions of urban inequality as well as
the links between them. Emancipatory pedagogies, for example, have been fundamental
in making visible, revalorizing and seeking a social redistribution of the roles of
women as carers, particularly pertinent in pandemic times. The experiential
pedagogies in Medell&#x000ed;n were critical for people with physical disabilities to break
away from their isolation in the hillsides of the city, towards actualizing their
rights and opportunities in the city. In terms of reciprocal recognition, the
practices of <italic toggle="yes">sentipensar</italic> in particular provoke profound reflections
not only on the question of what and whose knowledge counts in habitat struggles,
but how relations between different knowledges, feelings and practices &#x02013;
professional, embodied, experiential and others &#x02013; are constructed and enacted.
Importantly, the pedagogic practices of mobilization and reverberation remind us of
the strategic trajectory and political weight of HIC schools in Latin America to
advance towards a socially just habitat. For example, FUCVAM&#x02019;s intergenerational
pedagogies are not static practices, but have responded to the Federation&#x02019;s changing
relations to the state over time &#x02013; building capacities to act in the absence of,
against, or with government institutions depending on their (legal) support for
cooperative housing models. Finally, the schools have been fertile grounds for
learning and acting in solidarity, as witnessed through their provoking of
alternative economic, cultural and environmental models and imaginaries of
<italic toggle="yes">buen vivir</italic>, as in the case of the <italic toggle="yes">Barrio
Intercultural.</italic></p><p>This paper is ultimately a call for humility to those of us engaged in academia and
professional practice, and for acknowledgement and recognition of and deep
engagement with the actual grounded pedagogies that activate transformative change
towards urban equality across time and geographies. In simple terms, it is about
activating the practice of collective freedom and, in doing so, creating paradise
not just in the classrooms of higher education institutions, but through the
multiple sites in which urban inequalities are experienced and effectively contested
and counteracted.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank the pedagogues, learners and communication teams from all
eight schools who contributed to the videos and reflections, as well as Maria Silvia
Emanuelli &#x02013; HIC-AL Regional Coordinator &#x02013; and Lorena Z&#x000e1;rate &#x02013; HIC President until
the end of 2019 &#x02013; for their insights and willingness to embark on this reflexive
journey. Finally, our thanks to the team from La Sand&#x000ed;a Digital &#x02013; especially Suleica
Pineda, Ana Salgado and Yetlanezi Garc&#x000ed;a &#x02013; for their support throughout the process
to help us find a better way to narrate the stories of the schools beyond words.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This article draws from the work conducted by the authors as part of the research
programme Knowledge in Action for Urban Equality (KNOW), supported by UKRI
through the Global Challenges Research Fund GROW Call. Grant Ref: ES/
P011225/1.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Julia Wesely <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_09562478221115334-img2.jpg"/>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1691-9620" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1691-9620</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-09562478221115334"><label>1.</label><p><xref rid="bibr24-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">hooks (1994)</xref>, page
207.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-09562478221115334"><label>2.</label><p><xref rid="bibr3-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al.
(2020)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-09562478221115334"><label>3.</label><p><xref rid="bibr40-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Wesely et al.
(2021)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-09562478221115334"><label>4.</label><p><xref rid="bibr22-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Habitat International
Coalition (2016)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-09562478221115334"><label>5.</label><p>See reference 3.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-09562478221115334"><label>6.</label><p>By &#x0201c;reflexive&#x0201d;, we mean a process of reflection that is intrinsically linked to
action, that is opened to question its values, assumptions and practices, as
well as participants&#x02019; roles in relation to others.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-09562478221115334"><label>7.</label><p>See <xref rid="bibr34-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">P&#x000ed;rez (2016)</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr36-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Schmid et al.
(2018)</xref>; <xref rid="bibr37-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Streule
et al. (2020)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-09562478221115334"><label>8.</label><p>See <xref rid="bibr2-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Allen (2021)</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr5-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Castells (2016)</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr33-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Ortiz Flores
(2017)</xref>; <xref rid="bibr39-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Turner
(1976)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-09562478221115334"><label>9.</label><p><xref rid="bibr6-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Castillo-&#x000c1;lvarez
(2021)</xref>; <xref rid="bibr17-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Garc&#x000ed;a
Alc&#x000e1;ntar and Quiroz Rothe (2017)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-09562478221115334"><label>10.</label><p>Enrique Ort&#x000ed;z Flores was HIC&#x02019;s Secretary General and President during 1988&#x02013;1999
and 2003&#x02013;2007 respectively. He was also advisor and civil servant to the Mexican
government in 1982&#x02013;1988, specifically in the National Fund for Popular Housing
(Fonhapo in its Spanish acronym), and co-author of the first national housing
programme in Mexico. He is an internationally recognized activist for the right
to housing and the defence of the social production of habitat.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-09562478221115334"><label>11.</label><p><xref rid="bibr1-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Abramo (2011)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-09562478221115334"><label>12.</label><p>See <xref rid="bibr41-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Yap et al.
(2021)</xref>. The four dimensions explained in this paper are equal
distribution, reciprocal recognition, parity political participation and
solidarity and mutual care.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-09562478221115334"><label>13.</label><p><xref rid="bibr15-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Freire (2001)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-09562478221115334"><label>14.</label><p><xref rid="bibr19-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Giroux (2019)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-09562478221115334"><label>15.</label><p><xref rid="bibr20-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Gore (1993)</xref>; <xref rid="bibr25-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">hooks (2003)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-09562478221115334"><label>16.</label><p>See reference 13.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-09562478221115334"><label>17.</label><p><xref rid="bibr31-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Motta (2017)</xref>, page
5.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-09562478221115334"><label>18.</label><p>See reference 17, page 14.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-09562478221115334"><label>19.</label><p>See reference 17, page 2.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-09562478221115334"><label>20.</label><p><xref rid="bibr10-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">de Sousa Santos
(2018)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-09562478221115334"><label>21.</label><p>The pedagogic reflexion with the eight schools in Latin America is part of a
wider process open to other member organizations within HIC that seeks to
elucidate how learning, mobilization, advocacy and action are simultaneously
practised within the Coalition. Since 2021, this process has informed the
development of cross-regional co-learning spaces driven by HIC&#x02019;s members. For
more information on this initiative and HIC&#x02019;s first co-learning space on
feminist approaches to habitat rights see: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.hic-net.org/how-do-hic-members-and-allies-learn-cross-regionally-to-strengthen-our-collective-advocacy-muscles-on-feminist-approaches-to-habitat/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.hic-net.org/how-do-hic-members-and-allies-learn-cross-regionally-to-strengthen-our-collective-advocacy-muscles-on-feminist-approaches-to-habitat/</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-09562478221115334"><label>22.</label><p><xref rid="bibr13-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Enet et al. (2021)</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr12-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Enet and Romero
(2019)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-09562478221115334"><label>23.</label><p><xref rid="bibr21-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Gudynas (2011)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-09562478221115334"><label>24.</label><p><xref rid="bibr30-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Malecki (2016)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-09562478221115334"><label>25.</label><p><xref rid="bibr7-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">CISCSA et al.
(2021)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-09562478221115334"><label>26.</label><p><xref rid="bibr42-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Zaragocin and Caretta
(2021)</xref>, page 1508.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-09562478221115334"><label>27.</label><p><xref rid="bibr14-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Escobar (2020)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-09562478221115334"><label>28.</label><p><xref rid="bibr35-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Rend&#x000f3;n (2009)</xref>,
n.p.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn29-09562478221115334"><label>29.</label><p><xref rid="bibr9-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">De Jong et al. (2019)</xref>,
page xv.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn30-09562478221115334"><label>30.</label><p><xref rid="bibr26-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Illich (1973</xref>, <xref rid="bibr27-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">1977</xref>, <xref rid="bibr28-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn31-09562478221115334"><label>31.</label><p><xref rid="bibr8-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Corporaci&#x000f3;n Regi&#x000f3;n, Fuerza
Incluyente, HIC and KNOW (2021)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn32-09562478221115334"><label>32.</label><p><xref rid="bibr16-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">FUCVAM et al.
(2021)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn33-09562478221115334"><label>33.</label><p>See reference 32.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn34-09562478221115334"><label>34.</label><p>As a diverse field, sound and sonic studies are amongst many things interested in
the ways sound and acts of listening make differences in society and culture.
See for example <xref rid="bibr18-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Gershon
(2020)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn35-09562478221115334"><label>35.</label><p>See reference 34, page 1164.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn36-09562478221115334"><label>36.</label><p>Paola Blanes speaking in reference 25.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn37-09562478221115334"><label>37.</label><p><xref rid="bibr38-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Thompson (1987)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn38-09562478221115334"><label>38.</label><p><xref rid="bibr23-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Harden (1996)</xref>, page
32.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn39-09562478221115334"><label>39.</label><p><xref rid="bibr29-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Luke and Gore
(1992)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn40-09562478221115334"><label>40.</label><p><xref rid="bibr11-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Du Bois (1994)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn41-09562478221115334"><label>41.</label><p>See reference 17, pages 5&#x02013;6.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn42-09562478221115334"><label>42.</label><p><xref rid="bibr4-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Caldeira (2017)</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn43-09562478221115334"><label>43.</label><p>See reference 13.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn44-09562478221115334"><label>44.</label><p><xref rid="bibr32-09562478221115334" ref-type="bibr">Motta and Esteves
(2014)</xref>, page 21.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abramo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <source>La producci&#x000f3;n de las ciudades
latinoamericanas: mercado inmobiliario y estructura urbana</source>,
<publisher-name>Organizaci&#x000f3;n Latinoamericana y del Caribe de Centros
Hist&#x000f3;ricos</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Quito</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2021</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Navigating stigma through
everyday city-making: gendered trajectories, politics and outcomes in the
periphery of Lima</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Urban Studies</source>
<volume>Vol 59</volume>, <issue>No 3</issue>, pages
<fpage>490</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>508</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coci&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wesely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2020</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Habitat International
Coalition: networked practices, knowledges and pedagogies for translocal
housing activism</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Radical Housing</source>
<volume>Vol 2</volume>, <issue>No 2</issue>, pages
<fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caldeira</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2017</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Peripheral urbanization:
autoconstruction, transversal logics, and politics in cities of the global
south</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Environment and Planning D: Society and
Space</source>
<volume>Vol 35</volume>, <issue>No 1</issue>, pages
<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Castells</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2016</year>), <source>De la crisis econ&#x000f3;mica a la crisis
pol&#x000ed;tica. Una mirada cr&#x000ed;tica</source>, <publisher-name>Libros de
Vanguardia</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Castillo-&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>R
M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2021</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Procesos de urbanizaci&#x000f3;n
popular y derecho a la ciudad en el oriente de la zona metropolitana del
Valle de M&#x000e9;xico</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Procesos Urbanos</source>
<volume>Vol 8</volume>, <issue>No 2</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>CISCSA, HIC and KNOW</collab> (<year>2021</year>),
&#x0201c;<article-title>&#x000a1;Queremos cambiarlo todo! Formaci&#x000f3;n feminista por los
derechos a la ciudad</article-title>&#x0201d;, video, <publisher-name>Escuelas de
HIC-AL</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Corporaci&#x000f3;n Regi&#x000f3;n, Fuerza Incluyente, HIC and KNOW</collab>
(<year>2021</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Por una ciudad
accesible</article-title>&#x0201d;, video, <publisher-name>Escuelas de
HIC-AL</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Icaza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutazibwa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2019</year>), <source>Decolonization and Feminisms in
Global Teaching and Learning</source>,
<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Sousa Santos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2018</year>), <source>The End of the Cognitive Empire:
The Coming of Age of Epistemologies of the South</source>,
<publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Du Bois</surname><given-names>W E B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>), <source>The Souls of Black Folk</source>,
<publisher-name>Gramercy Books</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Enet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2019</year>), <source>Dise&#x000f1;o participativo sustentable
del h&#x000e1;bitat como herramienta de la producci&#x000f3;n y gesti&#x000f3;n social del h&#x000e1;bitat y
para el ejercicio de derechos</source>, <publisher-name>UNAM,
HIC-AL</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Mexico
City</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Enet, M, HIC and KNOW</collab> (<year>2021</year>),
&#x0201c;<article-title>Fortalecimiento de capacidades para la producci&#x000f3;n social del
h&#x000e1;bitat</article-title>&#x0201d;, video, <publisher-name>Escuelas de
HIC-AL</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2020</year>), <source>Pluriversal Politics</source>,
<publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>), <source>Pedagogy of the Oppressed</source>,
<publisher-name>Continuum</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>FUCVAM, HIC and KNOW</collab> (<year>2021</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>La
vivienda es el principio y no el final</article-title>&#x0201d;, video,
<publisher-name>Escuelas de HIC-AL</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a Alc&#x000e1;ntar</surname><given-names>E
A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quiroz Rothe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2017</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>El urbanismo popular en
M&#x000e9;xico. elementos para una hist&#x000f3;ria pendiente</article-title>&#x0201d;,
<source>URBANA: Revista Eletr&#x000f4;nica do Centro Interdisciplinar de Estudos
Sobre a Cidade</source>
<volume>Vol 9</volume>, <issue>No 1</issue>, pages
<fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gershon</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2020</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Reverberations and reverb:
sound possibilities for narrative, creativity, and
critique</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Qualitative Inquiry</source>
<volume>Vol 26</volume>, <issue>No 10</issue>, pages
<fpage>1163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Giroux</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2019</year>), &#x0201c;<part-title>Utopian thinking in
dangerous times: critical pedagogy and the project of educated
hope</part-title>&#x0201d;, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cot&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>R J F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Peuter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (editors), <source>Utopian Pedagogy: Radical Experiments Against
Neoliberal Globalization</source>, <publisher-name>University of Toronto
Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>, pages
<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>), <source>The Struggle for Pedagogies:
Critical and Feminist Discourses as Regimes of Truth</source>,
<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gudynas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Buen vivir: germinando
alternativas al desarrollo</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Am&#x000e9;rica Latina en
movimiento</source>
<volume>Vol 462</volume>, pages
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Habitat International Coalition</collab> (<year>2016</year>),
<source>Habitat International Coalition and the Habitat Conferences
1976&#x02013;2016</source>, <publisher-name>HIC</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Enlightenment, empowerment
and emancipation: the case for critical pedagogy in nurse
education</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Nurse Education Today</source>
<volume>Vol 16</volume>, <issue>No 1</issue>, pages
<fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>hooks</surname><given-names>b</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>), <source>Teaching to Transgress: Education
as the Practice of Freedom</source>,
<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>hooks</surname><given-names>b</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>), <source>Teaching Community: A Pedagogy of
Hope</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>New York and London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Illich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>), <source>Deschooling Society</source>,
<publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Harmondsworth</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Illich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Disabling professions:
notes for a lecture</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Crime, Law and Social
Change</source>
<volume>Vol 1</volume>, <issue>No 4</issue>, pages
<fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Illich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), &#x0201c;<part-title>Eco-paedagogics and the
commons</part-title>&#x0201d;, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (editor), <source>Education and Development</source>,
<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Abingdon</publisher-loc>, pages
<fpage>4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Luke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (editors) (<year>1992</year>), <source>Feminisms and Critical
Pedagogy</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge, Chapman &#x00026;
Hall</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Malecki</surname><given-names>J S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2016</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Crisis, radicalizaci&#x000f3;n y
pol&#x000ed;tica en el Taller Total de C&#x000f3;rdoba, 1970&#x02013;1975</article-title>&#x0201d;,
<source>Prohistoria</source>
<volume>Vol 25</volume>, pages
<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2017</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Emancipation in Latin
America: on the pedagogical turn</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Bulletin of Latin
American Research</source>
<volume>Vol 36</volume>, <issue>No 1</issue>, pages
<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Esteves</surname><given-names>A M</given-names></name>
</person-group>, (<year>2014</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Reinventing emancipation
in the 21st century: the pedagogical practices of social
movements</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Interface: A Journal for and about
Social Movements</source>
<volume>Vol 6</volume>, <issue>No 1</issue>, pages
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ort&#x000ed;z Flores</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2017</year>), <source>Hacia un h&#x000e1;bitat para el Buen
Vivir. Andanzas compartidas de un caracol peregrino</source>,
<publisher-name>Rosa Luxemburg Stiftung</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Mexico City</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>P&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2016</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Las heterogeneidades en la
producci&#x000f3;n de la urbanizaci&#x000f3;n y los servicios urbanos en Am&#x000e9;rica
Latina</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>territorios</source>
<volume>Vol 34</volume>, pages
<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rend&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>L I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <source>Sentipensante (Sensing/thinking)
Pedagogy: Educating for Wholeness, Social Justice and Liberation</source>.
<publisher-name>Stylus Publications</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Sterling VA</publisher-loc></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karaman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanakata</surname><given-names>N C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kallenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kockelkorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Streule</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2018</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Towards a new vocabulary of
urbanisation processes: a comparative approach</article-title>&#x0201d;,
<source>Urban Studies</source>
<volume>Vol 55</volume>, <issue>No 1</issue>, pages
<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Streule</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karaman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2020</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Popular urbanization:
conceptualizing urbanization processes beyond informality</article-title>&#x0201d;,
<source>International Journal of Urban and Regional Research</source>
<volume>Vol 44</volume>, <issue>No 4</issue>, pages
<fpage>652</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>672</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Critical scholarship: tile
critique of domination in nursing</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Advances in
Nursing Science</source>
<volume>Vol 5</volume>, <issue>No 2</issue>, pages
<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>), <source>Housing by People: Towards Autonomy
in Building Environments</source>, <publisher-name>Pantheon
Books</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wesely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Z&#x000e1;rate</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Emanuelli</surname><given-names>M S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2021</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Generative pedagogies from
and for the social production of habitat: learning from HIC-AL School of
grassroots urbanism</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>plaNext&#x02013;Next Generation
Planning</source>
<volume>Vol 11</volume>, pages
<fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coci&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2021</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>The Urban Dimensions of
Inequality and Equality</article-title>&#x0201d;, GOLD VI Working Paper Series,
Working Paper 1 (<month>November</month>
<year>2021</year>), <publisher-name>United Cities and Local
Governments</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc>,
<fpage>40</fpage> pages.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-09562478221115334"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zaragocin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caretta</surname><given-names>M A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2021</year>), &#x0201c;<article-title>Cuerpo-territorio: a
decolonial feminist geographical method for the study of
embodiment</article-title>&#x0201d;, <source>Annals of the American Association of
Geographers</source>
<volume>Vol 111</volume>, <issue>No 5</issue>, pages
<fpage>1503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1518</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>