<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par10">For Avi Brisman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2021</xref>), a major reason to read is to affirm/confirm things that we already know, or think we know. We read to have our own views validated or reassured. No matter how much we seek to inquire about something we do not fully understand, perhaps this is also a major reason for <italic>writing</italic>. Or, citing Ray Michalowski&#8217;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1996</xref>) invocation to reach a useful truth through hearing <italic>and</italic> telling multiple versions of the same story, Brisman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2021</xref>) argues we need to hear tragedies told again and again from different perspectives. I am not sure I am comfortable with this. At COP26, repetitions of the same story&#8212;climate change and its remedies&#8212;are told and retold, and there is common ground between the stories told by the government and corporate leaders inside the cordon sanitaire at Glasgow and the protestors outside. They all tell variations of the story that we need system change and not climate change. We all know that unless our economic system changes radically, it will overheat the planet and probably lead to extinction of our species and countless other species. Capitalism&#8217;s historical dependence on fossil fuels needs to be broken (Malm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2016</xref>). This is something that is universally agreed. The phrase, &#8220;system change, not climate change,&#8221; becomes rather empty phrase, however, if we cannot specify what needs to be done. The first aim of the book is to bring us to a more concrete understanding of what system change might actually mean. And so, the book argues that &#8220;the corporation&#8212;the mechanism that capital uses to reproduce itself&#8212;was designed in a way that virtually guarantees ecocide. Understanding the capitalist corporation and then doing something about it must therefore be at the centre of the struggle to control climate change and the ecological crisis&#8221; (Whyte <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>: 4).</p>