<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par3">In this paper, I make an attempt to make progress in analyzing the status of procreation in the question of the fair distribution of resources, in particular environmental resources. If we aim to reduce our impact on ecosystems in order to reach an ecologically sustainable equilibrium, should we consider procreation to be morally equivalent to overconsumption (whereby overconsumption is understood as the consumption of goods and services beyond those needed to meet one&#8217;s basic needs)? The answer to this question has implications for the debates on fair emissions quotas or permits, because whether the emissions caused by procreation should be taken from the parents&#8217; emissions quota or not depends in part on the question of whether emissions are seen as morally on a par with consumption and other forms of emitting acts.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref> If procreation and overconsumption are morally equivalent, then one&#8217;s fair emissions share would not increase if one wanted to procreate. Instead, the emissions needed to procreate and parent would come from the same individual emissions budget. If two persons have the same individual emissions budget before either of them has children, the person who procreates will not be given additional emissions rights. A nonparent could claim that it is morally permissible for him to consume more than a person who procreates, since he is opting to not take those ecological resources that procreation would require. The nonparent could claim that as long as his total appropriation of ecological resources does not exceed that of the parents and the offspring those parents choose to have, and as long as he is not exceeding his personal quota, there is no case of unfairness. After all, if a parent&#8217;s procreating acts require additional natural resources, why shouldn&#8217;t a nonparent be morally permitted to expend the same amount of natural resources in a different way, for example via traveling extensively or building a private swimming pool?</p>