<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par8">In the next section, the case of Ann and Pearl is described. Ann is happy to forfeit her right to procreation so she can stick to a life of greater affluence, including overconsumption, whereas Pearl has children. Can Ann expend more ecosystem resources on consumption than Pearl? As was just mentioned, an influential way to answer this question is to adopt the liberal equality of resources view, which is analyzed and criticized in section&#160;<xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec">3</xref>. An alternative way of answering this question is developed next that draws on an account of human flourishing that is based on the capabilities approach (section&#160;<xref rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref>). A capabilitarian view allows us to reject Ann&#8217;s claim to more ecosystem resources, but at the same time limits the procreative freedom of Pearl (section&#160;<xref rid="Sec5" ref-type="sec">5</xref>). This brings us to the first critique of the view that procreation and consumption are morally equivalent, namely that it is based on an implicit acceptance of resources as the metric of distributive justice. If, instead, we endorse capabilities as the metric of distributive justice, we do not necessarily have to accept that claim. In section&#160;<xref rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec">6</xref>, how one could develop a second and independent argument is sketched out&#8212;this is the argument from human self-understanding. This argument moves beyond the terrain of liberal theories of distributive justice. Instead, it draws on the claim that we should conceptualize procreative parenting as part of our self-understanding. If the argument from human self-understanding is correct, then it leads to a rejection of the view that procreation and consumption are morally equivalent. In the final section, an objection is briefly addressed, and some conclusions are drawn.</p>