<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0640">The paper is an outcome of a Consultative Science Platform, established by the International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA) and the International Science Council (ISC) to explore perspectives on the implications of COVID-19 for sustainable development. Focused on the implications for the resilience of food systems, the paper builds on an initial background report and briefs and benefitted from virtual discussion rounds, which were prepared by the IIASA-ISC team. The author team is most grateful to Ismail Serageldin for chairing the consultation rounds and the feed-back and comments given by the following experts, which helped shape the scope of the paper: Sasha Alexander, David Beckmann, James Birch, Nadereh Chamlou, Fernando Chaparro, Ruben Echeverria, Ismahane A. Elouafi, Shenggen Fan, Nina Fedoroff, Nighisty Ghezae, Oliver Greenfield, Ameenah Gurib-Fakim, Mario Herrero, Saleemul Huq, Daniel Kurdys, Sidney Leclercq, Martin Lees, Uma Lele, Mauricio Lopes, Michal Nachmany, Eva Ohlsson, Sheela Patel, Guy Pe&#233;r, Richard Roberts, Pedro Sanchez, Pauline Scheelbeek, Ben Simmons, Elena Smirnova, Barbara Stinson, Stefan Uhlenbrook, Kevin Urama, Joachim von Braun, Chris Walzer, Koko Warner, and additional input from Marcelo In&#225;cio da Cunha. The authors are thankful for the overall guidance on the IIASA-ISC Initiative provided by Leena Srivastava, Flavia Schlegel and Luis Gomez Echeverri, additional comments from Dilek Fraisl, Steffen Fritz, Tamas Krisztin, Michaela Rossini and Shonali Pachauri at various stages of the process, and helpful support by Philippa Baumgartner, Ansa Heyl, Anastasia Lijadi, David Soto Martinez, and Amela Ploskic. The paper presents a snapshot of the evolving situation of the pandemic and impacts on the food system. The viewpoints and perspectives presented by the authors do not necessarily reflect the opinions of their institutions and affiliated partners.</p>