<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par40">Relevant dimensions worth considering for resilience building in Nigeria include<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par41">Build integrated data infrastructure: Currently, most of the ministries, departments, and agencies (MDAs) of government operate in silos, with each fighting one another for budgetary allocation. Synergy and cooperation would have to be developed to ensure data collection and sharing and open data policies are adopted to support research and development. Two types of data gaps were identified during the pandemic (1) &#8220;data poverty&#8221;&#8212;lack of data jeopardising response and (2) &#8220;poor data&#8221;&#8212;lack of adequate data about vulnerable people, perpetuating various forms of inequality (Milan and Trer&#233; 2020). Filling this gap also enhances the nation&#8217;s ability to address climate change and its impact.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par43">Improving supply chain resilience and circularity: The pandemic raised the question about the resilience of global and local value and supply chains as well as production systems. Thus, triggering the need for a more diversified and localised production and most importantly short supply chains. Therefore, policy and stimulus could be targeted at ensuring that local supply chains improve their resilience, resource use efficiency and circularity (designs out waste and keeps products in use). Addressing this not all reduces wastage it also reduces the national carbon footprint which is a critical factor in ongoing discussions of reducing risks associated with climate change.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par45">Focus on the furthest behind first: As the pandemic exacerbates inequalities within the countries and pushes some further into poverty, resources must be allocated and used in ways that effectively reach and support the furthest behind. Such might include strengthening and overhauling social protection and health systems. There is a need for an efficient and effective method of identifying and supporting the furthest behind and their care needs to be prioritised (we are as strong as the weakest amongst us). The slums and informal settlements created contagion hotspots across the country thus there is a need to change the narratives. Climate change impact may affect the poorer amongst us more, but it will also put the well-off at risk, thus inclusive development is a must for us to ensure climate justice.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par47">Sponsored growth and innovation: There is currently a dichotomous growth across the country, with some places growing economically, whilst others just get drained of human and natural capital to support the growth of the major urban centres. Thus, to ensure an inclusive economy there is a need for growth to be sponsored across other places which are not currently major hubs of economic activities across the country. Such will provide redundancies for the economy and ensure that innovations can be derived from the peculiarities of such places outside the traditional economic hubs. Urban areas currently house most of the population of Nigeria, thus there is a heightened risk from climate change. Efforts at improving land-use efficiency of urban areas ensure that we achieve sustainable development and minimise the carbon footprint of urban existence. Rural&#8211;urban migration is putting pressure on infrastructure in city centres, driving people further into slums and making them more vulnerable to climate-induced disasters, like flooding. New agricultural methods are required to resolve issues of the farmers&#8211;herders crisis stemming from outdated pastoral practices of migrating with herds in search of pasture and water, which lack thereof, is exacerbated by climate change.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par49">Reorientate priorities: The national discourse needs a clear purpose to reorientate priorities. The current purpose is economic development with GDP growth being the target. With the challenges of climate change, we need to reorientate national priorities towards inclusive and sustainable development. The welfare of organised labour, protection of the environment, elimination of discrimination, and emphasis on social goals are central to ensuring well-being and inclusivity. The lack of such priorities has resulted in greater inequality leading to political instability and the risk of disruptions due to climate change. If the nation&#8217;s priorities do not change, then we have not learnt anything from the current pandemic. Consequently, we are not going to be better prepared for the uncertain future we face.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par51">Build agile and responsive institution: The development of agile and responsive institutions is necessary to address risk and reduce vulnerabilities. Institutional capacities would need to be enhanced at all levels of government to both prevent and manage crises. The value of institutional capacities in achieving national sustainable development priorities cannot be overemphasised. Good plans cannot be implemented without adequate and capable institutions. By integrating national, state, and local plans via (agile and responsive) institutions, strategies and resources could be collectively aligned in achieving set out priorities.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par53">Invest in preparedness: COVID-19 underscores the importance of preparedness, especially investing in crisis prevention, risk reduction and planning. Therefore, financing industries and institutions that are efficient and effective in enhancing risk reduction should be promoted as part of climate change adaptation planning.</p></list-item></list></p>