<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para190">In a Wildlife and Countryside Link survey from March, 2020,<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr"><sup>62</sup></xref> estimated losses due to COVID-19 for 23 responding organisations were already greater than US$100 million, not inclusive of future losses from decreased grant opportunities. Reduced funding for conservation has been substantial in many locations,<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref> impeding effective global biodiversity conservation, including achieving UN Aichi biodiversity targets, and issues such as deforestation, wildlife poaching, and greenhouse gas emissions.<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64</sup></xref> The $343 billion global wildlife tourism industry<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref> has been substantially affected by the COVID-19 pandemic<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref> with income shock affecting households throughout a range of countries and regions with high biodiversity,<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref> and wildlife-related tourism activity entirely vanishing in some locations.<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref> For example, in Kenya, tourism to Tsavo National Park generates a mainstream revenue for the Kenya Wildlife Service, whose operations are crucial to wildlife protection, protected area establishment, and anti-poaching enforcement.<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr"><sup>67</sup></xref> Tsavo Trust reported a 50% reduction in their capacity to operate in March, 2020,<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr"><sup>67</sup></xref> which could substantially disrupt conservation work for years to come. Such disruptions can lead to increased illegal resource extraction and wildlife poaching that feeds into the illegal trade, both as a result of diminished capacity to patrol protected areas, and severe reductions in income that wildlife tourism provides to millions worldwide.<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> Although data on the effects is still being collected for some of these cases, there have already been increased instances of poaching and illegal resource harvesting, although, these trends might not be universal.<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref>
</p>