<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par61">Moreover, RA presidents never invoked &#8220;the community&#8221; as the unit they were representing. Instead they frequently highlighted that their constituency specifically comprises residents of public housing. At an early 2019 meeting, Camille Napoleon, a resident association vice-president, explained what she viewed as the priorities of residents in her development, not the community at large. She highlighted that avoiding a future disaster similar to Sandy was the foremost priority for her residents, and the rest of the issues regarding the plan could be negotiated:<disp-quote><p id="Par62">&#8220;I represent Baruch Houses and we are the largest development citywide. I have a population of 5,096 residents right now. Listen, we are concerned with safety, with what we went through with Sandy. As long as this park considers its number one priority as safety, we can work the rest out. Right now we are in agreeance with this plan. The Tenants Association agrees with the current plan. As long as safety for my development and all those along the river is the number one priority.&#8221;</p></disp-quote>Camille went on to use her experience with Hurricane Sandy to urgently prioritize the need for future flood security above other concerns, referencing potential events that could reprise Sandy&#8217;s devastation. In her account, she only claimed to represent residents of her own public housing development. She also is more modest about her experience and what she knows, in sharp contrast to the activists:<disp-quote><p id="Par63">&#8220;I don&#8217;t know about any other development, but my own. I had to climb 24 stories to my apartment after Sandy. Every single day with flashlights. So as long as you protect my development and we don&#8217;t have to go through that again, the rest can be worked out. Protect us from the water, please.&#8221;</p></disp-quote>Both RA presidents mentioned that flood protection from future storms is their priority, and that the &#8220;rest can be worked out.&#8221; Contrast the language of representation used by RA presidents to language used by activists who oppose the plan. At a public meeting&#160;in early summer of 2019, a leader of East River Alliance, a newly formed group to protest the city&#8217;s change of plans, occupied a dedicated slot to speak in front of a crowd after a presentation by city officials. The leader, a white woman, said: &#8220;[After the plan change] we stepped into the role of engaging a community that the city sold short - addressing concerns about the new plan&#8230; we&#8217;ve talked to a lot of people in the community and we&#8217;re trying to understand different needs, different concerns.&#8221; The language of &#8220;the community&#8221; is also ubiquitous in pamphlets and on the websites of groups opposing the plan. The East River Alliance, for example, calls itself a coalition of &#8220;community members&#8221; with the goal of engaging in collaborative processes between city agencies and the &#8220;community.&#8221; Whom the community comprises remains undefined and the language obscures disagreements among neighborhood residents about preferences for flood protection.</p>