<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par66">In the summer of 2019 I went to a meeting of a neighborhood group focused on emergency preparedness. As I sat at a table of five people during a breakout exercise, the conversation veered off topic and landed on the ESCR, as it often did. Two activists began discussing a recent local news article about the project, which quoted two people living in public housing who supported the city&#8217;s plan. Val, an older black activist, and Danny, an older white activist, discussed the news article:<disp-quote><p id="Par67">&#8220;Val: The problem with it, is that it somewhat divides the community. You have Baruch, Lillian Wald, Jacob Riis [public housing developments], mainly black and Puerto Rican, poor, who need flood protection.</p><p id="Par68">Danny: Now they&#8217;re telling us that if you oppose the plan you are racist, and if you are for it, you&#8217;re not racist. How does that make sense?</p><p id="Par69">Val: [Sarcastically] Yeah, the people that don&#8217;t want it, are racist, that&#8217;s how it is. The two people they quoted were Puerto Rican folks that live in Baruch and Jacob Riis, they said, &#8216;I wanna be protected,&#8217; and that&#8217;s why they quoted them.</p><p id="Par70">Danny: That was on purpose by the proponents by this plan. They want to create division.&#8221;</p></disp-quote>Val and Danny&#8217;s exchange tells us that from the point of view of some activists, city officials and the news media cynically deployed the issue of race to garner support for the plan. When asked about the sources of disagreements between people who supported the plan and those who oppose it, few activists acknowledged that disagreements revealed a genuine diversity of opinions. Rather, activists pointed at city agencies for sowing discord, racially or otherwise: &#8220;The city&#8217;s doing very little building of the social fabric here,&#8221; Nancy, a white older activist told me, &#8220;really the city has, I think done a really good job of separating us, creating mistrust&#8230;&#8221; After the city embarked on its four-year process of collaboration with residents, Nancy felt that city agencies did not build up the &#8220;social fabric&#8221; &#8211; highlighting how the late move to change plans undermined all of the previous efforts to generate solidarity and consensus in the neighborhood. Similarly, Greg, a high-profile white activist who runs a local youth engagement organization, told me: &#8220;Yeah, nobody wants to be flooded again, but people are like mislead. People have been misled to believe that this is really the only plan to save them.&#8221; Greg went on to state that the city tries to &#8220;mush up people&#8217;s thinking&#8221; about the issue.</p>