<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">In our path to implement universal educational standards for planetary health in medical curricula Canada-wide, we have encountered two significant barriers: 1) the limited space for new curricular content, and 2) the lack of faculty expertise to provide effective teaching. Our experiences align with the literature; a minority of health educators from a large Australian university reported confidence to explain (36.9%) and inspire (44.2%) students to incorporate planetary health principles into their practice.<sup><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> The CFMS HEART has developed a series of evidence-based <italic toggle="yes">Climate Wise</italic> slides to address these observed barriers and enable prompt curricular change.<sup><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> This open-access repository of slides are an approach to integrate our planetary health medical educational competencies into pre-existing medical curricula. Each slide teaches future physicians about the impact of climate change on patient health as well as how healthcare practice and systems can be transformed to advance climate change adaptation and mitigation. For example, a respirology faculty lecturer could integrate the air pollution and respiratory diseases slides in their lecture on asthma to teach students about the negative impacts of air pollution on respiratory health and how to counsel patients to reduce their exposure to air pollution. They are organized by system (e.g. cardiology) and specialty (e.g. pediatrics), which is concordant to the design of most preclinical and clinical curricula worldwide, respectively. These slides work within the limited space for curricular content through their ease of integration into existing lectures. Further, these slides provide a well-researched pedagogical tool for planetary health that can be taught by instructors regardless of their expertise in planetary health topics.</p>