<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par3">The international mood for supporting the climate change policy has been seeking the solutions including the energy consumption (Davenport, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2020b</xref>; Eilperin et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020</xref>; Guven et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2021</xref>; McGrath, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2020</xref>; Oztig, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2017</xref>; Templearchive, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>; Thompson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2020</xref>). So, it is needed to consider the non-carbon emission energy society with renewable and nuclear energies. As is seen in the case of Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, the disease is one of the critical factors for the energy outlook in the future. Due to the pandemic situation, carbon neutrality has been reached to reduce the carbon emission fuels, which means the activities of the summations of carbon consumption and production using planting trees or installing the alternative facilities compensating the fossil fuels. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the society by climate energy-mix incorporated with the pandemic in which pandemic, climate, and energy-mix create the future society. For the characteristics of climate change, the carbon emissions are controlled by the balancing of the interesting elements in which the leverage is conceptualized as neutrality. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> is the configuration of balancing for carbon neutrality where the reducing factors are tree planting, non-carbon emission energy, electric cars, and money payments, and the producing factors are fossil fuels, classic cars, and conventional plants (AT&amp;T, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2020</xref>). Hence, the right side of the leverage could be regarded as the feedback or resilience from the state of the global warming situation.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Society by climate energy-mix incorporated with pandemic</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10668_2022_2551_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Configuration of balancing for carbon neutrality</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10668_2022_2551_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>