<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par7">From a global climate justice perspective (Gardiner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2004</xref>, Harlan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2015</xref>, Vanderheiden <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2013</xref>), we aim to analyze recent power dynamics that operate at two levels: first, economic-commercial relations and negotiations between Brazil and China, as well as between Brazil and the EU, considering their impacts on the Brazilian territory, with emphasis on the scenario of socio-environmental injustice and climate insecurity; second, policy practices of both China and the EU in climate governance, bearing in mind the notions of climate justice and development as conceptual guides to observe these contradictions. Unlike other studies that analyze climate justice issues in state behaviour by focusing on negotiations and institutions, we demonstrate that the interdependence between domestic and international levels is often more decisive for the understanding of the contradictions that prevail in prescribing policy goals and criteria, conceptions of justice and the legitimacy of the climate change multilateral regime itself. For the climate agenda, the domestic-international nexus encompasses understandings, arrangements and bridge-building, as well as disagreements, disputes and conflicts of interest at different and complex political levels (Inoue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2016</xref>). Our approach allows us to contribute both to the climate justice literature on the social, political and economic dimensions of structural inequalities and system asymmetries and to the broader literature on climate politics and international political economy, recalling a classical dilemma in international relations: although countries have a common goal in protecting collective goods from all sorts of risks, they seek to preserve their own interests.</p>