<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par2">At the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic, democracy&#8217;s promise to enable well-informed, responsible decisions gained almost unprecedented appeal. In the face of shock and extreme uncertainty, the criteria for success&#8212;limiting infections and fatalities while keeping economic damages low&#8212;seemed uncontroversial, und the challenge merely one of selecting the right strategies to achieve these ends. Struggling to demonstrate liberal democracy&#8217;s superiority over authoritarian regimes like China and populist governments like Donald Trump&#8217;s in the US, many European leaders vouched to defer to expert judgment in their decision-making. For example, the Swedish government followed Anders Tegnell&#8217;s advice to pursue a strategy of herd immunity, whereas the German government in the first phase of the pandemic preferred to seek advice from virologists and epidemiologists advocating a restrictive &#8216;No-Covid&#8217;-strategy. However, in asking citizens to follow their lead in deferring more or less blindly to expert judgments, governments have taken what Cristina Lafont (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>) calls an &#8216;expertocratic shortcut&#8217;. That is, they have tried to avoid the long and arduous road of inclusive will-formation and justification by asking citizens to just accept decisions by those who supposedly know better. Expertocratic shortcuts to decision-making can be very much in demand in emergency situations. However, they are harmful to democratic systems in two main respects: First, by undermining democratic self-government, they tend to reinforce existing power relations. Second, expertocratic justifications and shortcuts to decision-making can validate reliance on individual opinion leaders and the purely instrumental use of evidence, thereby creating a resonance base for reactant, populist mobilization. The relevance of this problem becomes even clearer when we consider a second crisis that is also characterized by the perception of a major threat and the need for informed decision-making: the climate crisis. Particularly in view of the fact that our societies will have to grapple with this crisis for much longer than with the Covid-19 crisis, we should not give in to the tendency toward expertocratic governance that has become visible in the pandemic.</p>