<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par3">Our paper starts out by delineating the perceptions of threat and high uncertainty that characterize the situations that are perceived as states of emergency in the cases of both the Covid-19 and the climate crisis. It is apparent that the perception of climate change as a rather gradually unfolding process is becoming increasingly unfounded (&#8220;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Covid-19 and the climate crisis: perceptions of threat</xref>&#8221; section). Consequently, the framing of a &#8216;climate emergency&#8217; is gaining ground. This is reasonable, but can also form a basis for justifying expertocratic shortcuts. We go on to describe respective temptations for the two cases (&#8220;<xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec">Expertocratic temptations in the Covid-19 pandemic and the climate crisis</xref>&#8221; section) and point out why shortcuts to democratic decisions ultimately constitute dead ends (&#8220;<xref rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec">Why shortcuts to democratic decisions are dead ends</xref>&#8221; section). Drawing primarily on the German experience, we illustrate the societal consequences of expertocratic government and show how expertocratic justifications and shortcuts to decision-making can validate reliance on individual opinion leaders and the purely instrumental use of evidence, thereby creating a resonance base for reactant, populist mobilization (&#8220;<xref rid="Sec5" ref-type="sec">Societal consequences of expertocratic government</xref>&#8221; section). We thus conclude that eventually, expertocratic practices not only undermine democratic self-government, but also risk compliance with laws and regulations. In &#8220;<xref rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec">Three requirements for a democratic use of expertise</xref>&#8221; section, we thus finally identify three requirements for legitimate expert involvement in political decision-making, arguing that while there is room and need for experts and expertise in a deliberative system, their authority and mandate must result from inclusive meta-deliberative processes and must be contestable and transparent.</p>