<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">The shipping industry shapes the connection between island and mainland in important ways. Its dominance, together with the influence of external interests in local politics (Benevolo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1979</xref>), has been subject of debate for years. This imbalance is depicted in the cartoon film &#8220;Mr. Rossi in Venice&#8221; (1974).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn11">11</xref> The illustrator, Bruno Bozzetto, comments on societal transformations and points to the complex processes that lie behind seemingly simple actions. The film also hints at the historical dimensions of current debates. It critically portrays clich&#233;s about Venice and visualizes the decline of the city, an issue that several historical destinations started to face at the time of its creation. By showing traffic, smog, pollution, frustrated inhabitants, and large-scale infrastructural projects, the short film depicts ecological and political issues that affect the city, its environment, and the people who live and work there. In addition, it addresses the immense influence of consumerism, raising questions about staging, authenticity, power, and the subordination of ecological interests to economic motivations. It is especially noteworthy that the film highlights the tight connection of the island to the mainland part of the city, Mestre, the &#8220;unloved child&#8221; (Petri <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1988</xref>: 112) of Venice next to the industrial port of Marghera. Both play a&#160;crucial role for the city&#8217;s economy and its everyday life. Island and mainland are part of the metropolitan city of Venice that rarely appears in popular representations. This constellation has led to several conflicts concerning the governance of the area as a&#160;whole. The division between island and mainland is expressed not only in spatial terms but also in the &#8220;island and mainland identity&#8221; (Casagrande <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2016</xref>: 121), which is the subject of heated debate.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn12">12</xref> The cartoon illustrates the entanglement between island, lagoon, and industrial area through the tentacles of huge passenger and transport ships, reaching out in every direction.</p>