<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0030">The state of food and nutrition security of any group is determined by the condition (i.e., the sustainability and resiliency) of the food system linked to the group (<xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Ericksen, 2008</xref>). Given that millions of people are food insecure today, it is evident that numerous food systems are in poor condition (<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Branca et al., 2020</xref>). While much of the systems bottlenecks are localized &#8211; with respect to a lack of or limited resources and support available, research suggests that some of the causes of the local food systems insufficiencies emerge from the nature of the global agri-food systems. Indeed, as indicated by <xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr">Guinn and Hamrick (2015)</xref> presently, &#8216;[...] national food systems are deeply interlinked through patterns of trade and investment that are often referred to as global value chains (GVCs).&#8217; In the value chain arrangements, they add, the key players are &#8216;[...] powerful lead firms &#8211; large food processing firms, trading companies, and national and multinational retail and restaurant chains &#8211; setting the terms by which farmers may participate in the food system&#8217;. This leads to agri-food practices, policies and interventions that promote the corporate profit-led interests, which rarely align with local needs for inclusive food systems i.e., those that ensure everyone has secure access to preferred, safe and nutritious food. For example, due to unequal food systems, it is maintained that although there is enough food being produced in the world, not everyone has access to this food (<xref rid="bb0470" ref-type="bibr">Schipanski et al., 2016</xref>). Among the primary reasons for this critical disparity is growing (global and local) social and economic inequality (<xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Dixon et al., 2007</xref>). Elsewhere, recent studies on inclusive agribusiness, the currently popular and dominant approach for improving smallholder livelihoods, food and nutrition security therein, show that not every farmer gets to participate, while those that do and manage to obtain better income it does not necessarily lead to improved food and nutrition security (<xref rid="bb0560" ref-type="bibr">Wangu et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0565" ref-type="bibr">Wangu et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">Gebru et al., 2019</xref>). On a different note, agriculture is associated with adverse environmental implications that undermine food production (<xref rid="bb0495" ref-type="bibr">Steffen et al., 2015</xref>). This has a negative impact on the food systems. Conversely, a poorly functioning food system can equally have a negative impact on agriculture and the environment. Overall, a food system that is not equitable and that has a negative impact on the environment cannot be considered sustainable.</p>