<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0035">The need for resilient food systems cannot be overemphasized. Because of growing population, increased competition for agricultural resources from non-food production, such as in the case of biofuel crops, impacts of agricultural production, socio-economic inequalities, changing human diets, among others, food systems have become increasingly vulnerable and are under immense pressure to ensure people everywhere are able to meet their food needs. As <xref rid="bb0470" ref-type="bibr">Schipanski et al. (2016)</xref> point out, individuals and communities can simultaneously experience multiple shocks and stressors operating at different scales. Resilience research has argued for increased capacity for all actors to self-organize and adapt to disturbances, as well as promoting equity and social justice (<xref rid="bb0470" ref-type="bibr">Schipanski et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Ensor et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Chappell and LaValle, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Carpenter et al., 2001</xref>). In their argument for improving food systems and food and nutrition security accordingly, <xref rid="bb0470" ref-type="bibr">Schipanski et al. (2016)</xref> emphasize on the need to target the vulnerable and marginalized population in terms of enhancing their capital and productive resources. This necessitates having a deep understanding of the key constraints they face as well as the individuals' role in ensuring their food and nutrition security. Hence, our case for a stronger gender lens, as specifically women are vulnerable and marginalized in both delivering and acquiring adequate and healthy food. Therefore, in the next section women's duality aspect in food systems and related barriers are being explored. This includes emphasizing the need to acknowledge women's role in food availability and access, as well as in consumption.</p>