<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">As illustrated in <xref rid="sec2-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="sec">Section 2</xref> and <xref rid="sec3-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref>, more data is needed to better encapsulate and capture the interconnected health and human rights facets of the climate crisis in order to design integrated human rights and public health-based approaches to climate policy and implementation. Data collection should include and account for disparities and marginalizing factors that lead to vulnerability, such as age, gender, race, class, income, disability, and geography, in order to assure that policies are not blind or even harmful to these groups but on the contrary promote equity and justice [<xref rid="B66-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Having such cross-cutting data at the national level will also guide nation states to include these co-benefits in their NDCs and to develop climate adaptation policies, which take into account the multisectoral impacts of the climate crisis [<xref rid="B67-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. For instance, such national-level analyses would enable national policymakers to understand what is needed to ensure their healthcare system is prepared and resilient to future climate-induced public health crises, what training is needed for health professionals, and what type of civil society awareness campaigns are required [<xref rid="B67-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Frameworks such as the Health in All Policies approach, where the health considerations of communities and people are collaboratively integrated into policymaking across sectors, can ensure that co-benefits in other policy areas, including environmental health and human rights, are realized [<xref rid="B68-ijerph-19-04840" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Such approaches can be undertaken at all levels and multisectoral synergies can be optimized and inequities avoided. In these processes, engaging youth in data collection can ensure their lived experiences are reflected. Finally, through such integrated data collection, public health, human rights, and climate researchers and practitioners can better inform their advocacy efforts and have more impact as agents for climate action.</p>