<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par15">The CA has many benefits. A common starting-point when discussing the currency of justice (Page, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2007</xref>) that can serve as a contrast to CA is welfarism, being a view that &#8216;restricts the judgments of state of affairs to the utilities in the respective states (paying no direct attention to such things as the fulfillment or violation of rights, duties, and so on)&#8217; (Sen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1999</xref>: 59). That is, the aggregate level of utility is given precedence in welfarist theories of distributive justice, and &#8216;injustice&#8217; is restricted to &#8216;aggregate loss of utility compared with what could have been achieved&#8217; (Sen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1999</xref>: 59). An unjust society is one which consists of less level of utility, measured by for instance happiness or preference satisfaction, than it could have consisted of. The aggregative nature of welfarism suffers from distributional indifference and a neglect of rights, freedoms and concerns that cannot be translated to utilities (Sen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1999</xref>: 62). Moreover, welfarism risks ignoring preferences that are adapted to detrimental conditions, thus fulfilled already under relatively harsh circumstances (Sen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1999</xref>: 62). In contrast, CA focus on &#8216;people&#8217;s substantive freedom to achieve the life that they have reasons to value&#8217;, being &#8216;human &#8216;functionings&#8217; and the &#8216;capabilities&#8217; to achieve them&#8217; (Page, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2007</xref>: 461; Sen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1999</xref>). CA is less vulnerable to the accusations to welfarist accounts, since CA is not as restricted to aggregate preference satisfaction. Rather, some CA theorists, such as Martha Nussbaum, identifies a list of ten capabilities as prerequisites of leading a decent life (Nussbaum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2006</xref>). Others, such as Amartya Sen, does not provide a set list, but rather focus on the relation between capabilities as freedom, health, and life (Sen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1999</xref>). Sen argues for a contextual version of CA, according to which the capabilities should be determined through public reasoning and open debates (Sen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1999</xref>).</p>