<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Progressive public communications in the UK have been championed perhaps most notably by the Public Interest Research Centre (PIRC),<fn id="j_jwl-2022-0017_fn_001"><label>1</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://publicinterest.org.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://publicinterest.org.uk/</ext-link> (accessed 6 May 2021).</p></fn> whose framing and communication toolkits have spanned topics such as nature, equality, climate justice, and the economy. PIRC work with community interest groups as well as other framing specialists such as the FrameWorks Institute<fn id="j_jwl-2022-0017_fn_002"><label>2</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frameworksinstitute.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frameworksinstitute.org/</ext-link> (accessed 6 May 2021).</p></fn> to evaluate how complex issues such as the environment and the economy are understood by members of the British public, and then to produce co-created booklets of framing and narrative recommendations for a range of communicators. They also disseminate their findings in the form of posters, card decks, and postcards; their &#8216;The Narratives We Need&#8217; postcard, for example, distils the findings of 15 research projects and ten years of work into five key questions for public-issue communicators: (i) &#8220;Are you talking to people&#8217;s best selves?&#8221;; (ii) &#8220;Are you showcasing a big, diverse &#8216;us&#8217;?&#8221;; (iii) &#8220;Are you showing we can all play a role in change?&#8221;; (iv) Are you highlighting how the system is unfairly designed?&#8221;; and (v) &#8220;Are you demonstrating that change is possible?&#8221; (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_063" ref-type="bibr">PIRC 2020</xref>). Along with the FrameWorks Institute and the US-based Center for Story-Based Strategy,<fn id="j_jwl-2022-0017_fn_003"><label>3</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.storybasedstrategy.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.storybasedstrategy.org/</ext-link> (accessed 6 May 2021).</p></fn> PIRC represents a leading example of politically sensitive, narrative-driven, public-issue communications, or knowledge brokering. Similar approaches are gradually being adopted, based on more rigorous methodological foundations, by academics working with metaphor and narrative: an output of <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_077" ref-type="bibr">Semino et&#160;al.&#8217;s (2017)</xref> work on cancer discourses was an illustrated &#8220;metaphor menu&#8221;<fn id="j_jwl-2022-0017_fn_004"><label>4</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="http://wp.lancs.ac.uk/melc/the-metaphor-menu/" ext-link-type="uri">http://wp.lancs.ac.uk/melc/the-metaphor-menu/</ext-link> (accessed 6 May 2021).</p></fn> for cancer patients and healthcare practitioners to use in cancer-related communications; and <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_047" ref-type="bibr">Lockton et&#160;al. (2019)</xref> have translated their design research into a toolkit and a deck of cards that can be used in metaphor-generating workshops, for example.</p>