<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Where pro-environmental communication is concerned, a growing amount of research is being carried out by marketing and business scholars, in particular, on optimal ways of promoting environmentally beneficial products and practices (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_085" ref-type="bibr">Taylor 2015</xref>). Despite often having a somewhat capitalistic undercurrent, industry-oriented research on &#8220;green&#8221; marketing and advertising has produced many useful, experimental findings around effective use of language, particularly with regard to promoting pro-environmental behavior change. Studies on the appropriate level of assertiveness, for example, have found that gentler and less assertive phrasing is typically found to yield more compliance on a range of issues, including environmental practices <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_097" ref-type="bibr">(Baek et al. 2015)</xref>, and that employing a greater number of &#8220;green&#8221; messages can in fact backfire, leading to reactance (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_053" ref-type="bibr">Moyer-Gus&#233; et&#160;al. 2019</xref>) and negative brand perception (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_061" ref-type="bibr">Olsen et&#160;al. 2014</xref>). There are a few instances in which more forceful messaging may be more effective, however: when&#160;the recipient already invests some effort in the promoted behavior <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_097" ref-type="bibr">(Baek et al. 2015)</xref>; when the issue is accepted to be of extreme importance <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_101" ref-type="bibr">(Kronrod et al. 2012b)</xref>; or when the message encourages &#8220;hedonic consumption&#8221; rather than virtuous behaviors <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_100" ref-type="bibr">(Kronrod et al. 2012a)</xref>. Interestingly, and perhaps unsurprisingly, an experimental study on the language of returnable packaging labels found that &#8220;ease of use&#8221; messages, as opposed to messages that justify why returning packaging is important, were more effective at raising consumers&#8217; intentions to actively participate in return schemes (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_069" ref-type="bibr">Ratnichkina et al. 2021</xref>). A key finding of <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_095" ref-type="bibr">WRAP (2021a)</xref>, however, is that consumers typically spend very little time reading such labels&#160;&#8211; around ten seconds or less&#160;&#8211; and as such they must be clear, simple, direct, and easy to find if they are to have any benefit.</p>