<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par42">Despite the seemingly progressive claims to replace shareholder capitalism with stakeholder capitalism, the WEF solution of marginalizing the most inclusive UN agency (the CFS) and its research arm, the HLPE, is a clear example of selective stakeholderism to strengthen corporate governance. While traditionally a multilateral forum, with member government representation and voting power, the CFS reformed a decade ago to include civil society (agrarian movements and progressive NGOs) and private sector representation, with voice but no vote. As noted earlier, the IPC was tireless in negotiating this global policy space through which to represent frontline producers, farmworkers and Indigenous Peoples (McKeon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2015</xref>; Duncan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2015</xref>; Claeys <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2015</xref>; Edelman and Borras <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2016</xref>; Gaarde <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2017</xref>; Mann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2019</xref>). And CSM input has shaped such landmark reports as <italic>Voluntary Guidelines on Responsible Governance of Tenure of Land, Fisheries and Forests in the Context of National Food Security</italic> (FAO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2012</xref>) and <italic>Connecting Smallholders to Markets: An Analytical Guide</italic> (Kay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2016</xref>). Meanwhile, the CFS commissions research from its High-Level Panel of Experts (HLPE), who produce annual scientific and field research reports on significant food security-related topics. These include Agroecology, Smallholder Agriculture Investment, Nutrition, Water, Sustainable Livestock, Youth Engagement and Employment, Food Waste, Biofuels, Fisheries, Climate Change, Land Tenure, Gender, and more. Sidelining of these voices and reports by the UNFSS in the name of a vacuous &#8216;stakeholderism&#8217; is testament to corporate takeover of such critical spaces.</p>