<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">We studied how California has allocated CCI-funded interventions across vulnerable groups to date. Data about CCI projects were obtained from the CCI website and included projects through November 30<sup>th</sup>, 2019 [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Many projects spanned multiple years and census tracts. Here, each unique combination of project identification number and tract was considered a tract intervention. Multi-year projects within a tract that had the same project identification number were considered one intervention, yielding 56,125 unique tract interventions from 2,929 unique project identification numbers. Data were further narrowed down to include heat-relevant investments, which were classified into four categories: heat, outdoor workers, greening and surfaces, and weatherization. Selection of interventions for each of these categories built from existing guidelines for systematic review searching and screening and for topic coding through qualitative content analysis [<xref rid="pone.0240841.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0240841.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The search strategy included two iterations of inclusion and exclusion of projects based on keyword search terms. For the first iteration, a list of heat-specific adaptation words was created for each of the categories drawing from keyword phrases familiar to the authors and within the literature considered throughout this study. The keyword searches were done in the following CCI project data columns: &#8220;ProjectDescription,&#8221; &#8220;DisadvantagedCommunityBenefitsDescription,&#8221; and &#8220;OtherProjectBenefitsDescription.&#8221; From this first search, we developed a table of the number of tract interventions associated with each phrase (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0240841.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). This table was reviewed and keyword phrases that returned zero results were removed from the keyword list. Phrases that returned tract interventions with subprograms that were not obviously relevant, such as the &#8220;Alternative Manure Management Program&#8221; or the &#8220;Fire Prevention Grant Program,&#8221; were further scrutinized. From this analysis, a second round of inclusion and exclusion keyword phrases was developed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0240841.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). This second iteration was used to identify CCI-funded tract adaptations for each of the heat-focused categories.</p>