<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par2">The bleak findings from global assessments and literature showing the rapidly degrading state of socioecological systems continue to fill our newsfeeds. Figures and scenarios related to climate change and biodiversity loss are alarming and are among the most highlighted in policy discourses and public debates. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) report of 2018 estimated that to have a 50&#8211;66% chance to stay within 1.5&#160;&#176;C of the pre-industrial level, global carbon emissions need to be reduced to around 50% from the current levels by 2030, and eliminated by 2050 (Masson-Delmotte et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2018</xref>). The IPCC report of 2019 shows an accelerating rate of species extinction and suggests that we are approaching a tipping point of global biodiversity beyond which a more dramatic and faster biodiversity decline is inevitable (Tucker et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">2018</xref>). The IPCC report of 2021 echoed these messages, with higher clarity and precision than before, removing any doubts of the alarming state of the global climate, suggesting that nothing short of an immediate and complete cessation of CO<sub>2</sub> and other greenhouse gas emissions can stabilise the climate (IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2021</xref>). Each year is warmer than the preceding one, with the last 7&#160;years being the hottest years ever recorded in the last 140&#160;years (NASA Global Climate Change&#160;database). The year 2020, the hottest ever recorded, also became the turning point in history when human-made materials outweigh the living biomass (Elhacham et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR900">2020</xref>). The Earth Overshoot Day, the point of time when human resource extraction exceeds the capacity for regeneration of those resources, indicates that collectively we humans require the equivalent of 1.75 planets to sustain our lifestyles (Gills and Morgan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2020</xref>). This figure is much larger in GDP-rich countries (Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2020b</xref>).</p>