<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par5">This increased focus relates to the concepts and initiatives for transitions and transformations, the literature on which has flourished over the last decade (Feola <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2015</xref>; Feola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2021</xref>; H&#246;lscher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2018</xref>). Discussions range from a need to shift our economic model towards one that prioritizes people and wellbeing over economic growth and profit (Raworth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">2012</xref>) to the need for a civilizational shift and the rise of a new era (Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>; Kothari&#160;et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>). Taking into account the distinction between transitions and transformations elaborated in the next section, I join the scholars who argue that transformations and transformative approaches rather than transitions and reformist approaches are needed to tackle the concurrent global socioecological and inequality crises (Gills et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2021</xref>; Temper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2018</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>; Martin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2020</xref>). Social movements have a key role to play in transformations by providing alternative ways of relating to one another and to more-than-human worlds, and by outlining alternative modes of economic and governing systems (Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>; Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2019</xref>; Temper et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2018</xref>). Degrowth and environmental justice are prominent fields of study and constitute the agenda of many social movements that call for a shift in our imaginaries, mentalities and economies, with justice at the heart of transformation processes (Akbulut et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2019</xref>; Gerber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2020</xref>; Martin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2020</xref>, Martinez-Alier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2012</xref>).</p>