<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par18">The unsustainability and inherent inequality of current carbon-intensive lifestyles and consumption patterns are obvious. The drivers of the climate crisis have a direct relationship with economic inequality, whereby the greenhouse gas emissions of the &#8216;haves&#8217; are largely driving a crisis which will impact on the &#8216;have-nots&#8217; the hardest (Gore <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015</xref>). The G20 group of nations account for 78% of all emissions (UNEP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2019a</xref>). The average carbon footprint of the 1% most wealthy globally may be as much as 175 times that of the poorest 10% (Gore <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015</xref>). While countries in sub-Saharan Africa contribute the lowest levels of per capita CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent emissions, these countries are ranked as the most vulnerable to climate change impacts (Eckstein et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>). By 2030, an additional 100&#160;million people may be pushed into poverty in the absence of urgent action (Eckstein et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2019</xref>). Developing countries will be disproportionally impacted due to low latitudes locations, the amount and variability of rainfall and current levels of development (Stern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2007</xref>). For vulnerable countries in the global south, both the cost of borrowing and the risk of debt crises are increased by environmental hazards; many such vulnerable countries are already highly indebted to begin with (Fresnillo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>). Countries facing highest levels of temperature variability also have the least economic potential to cope with the impacts (Bassetti <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2019</xref>).&#160;Fleurbaey et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2014</xref>) outline four key equity principles: responsibility, capacity, equality, and the right to sustainable development. Given international poverty alleviation goals, redistribution of carbon shares from wealthy elites to the global poor would seem to be appropriate (Hubacek et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2017</xref>), from both distributional justice and operational policy perspectives. Fair burden sharing between countries implies that countries benefiting from greater climate stability should also help to shoulder a higher burden of the effort and costs of climate change mitigation and adaptation (Puaschunder <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2020</xref>).</p>