<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0230">Political geographies of <italic>care</italic> were, however, reconfigured and dramatically remade in responding to injunction violence. People attending trials as participants and observers found, in the courthouse corridor and gallery, spaces for building anti-colonial solidarities and linking concerns about TMX to other struggles internationally, other Indigenous rights struggles near and far, and for fortifying intergenerational support in a context of multiple overlapping global crises. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>
provide an illustration of some of these &#8211; depicting, respectively, the extensive attendance in the courtroom gallery there to support defendants on trial, with words of defendants captured by the artist in the drawing itself (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>); the pain at seeing the settler-colonial court's contempt for Indigenous truths (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>); and the moment of collective revulsion at a judicial system's exclusion of scientific evidence that was readily available for presentation (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Solidarity-building also took on other creative forms. &#8220;Irreparable Harm?&#8220;, a play created after some of the trials, was performed by the &#8220;Sinister Sisters Ensemble&#8221;, a group composed of activists and theatre folk, young and old, Indigenous and settlers, including people who were arrested for breaching the TMX injunction. The play re-performed court scenes and testimony, revisiting emotions, solidarities and judgments, as well as the twists and turns in the courtroom sagas. A project of public educating became pivotal in this process, seeking to both recontextualise what &#8220;rule of law&#8221; means in real terms and re-frame who is doing &#8220;irreparable harm&#8221; to whom and to the planet, challenging settler-colonial court's mantras.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Depiction of the courtroom gallery and witnessing words by one defendant telling the judge &#8220;my time on the mountain with the people was healing&#8221;, defiantly but gently, as well as about the anxiety linked to the oil pipeline and arrests. Artist Joe Pepper, reproduced with permission.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The Truth is Not a Defence &#8211; &#8220;I get pain in my bones thinking of the charge: that a corporate &#8230; entity which has no life except on paper, can hold a human being of blood and bones in contempt for being Indigenous and Human and representative of the living &#8230;. The black sludge, bitumen &#8230; will obliterate knowledge of our life blood connection to the flow of blood and water. The injunction disavows the truth for Indigenous People who have lived experience long forgotten &#8230; Who are &#8220;they&#8221; to hold the living in contempt? (June 13, 2018). Artist and writer -Joe Pepper, reproduced with permission.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>(Not) Discussing Toxins as Reckless Endangerment: &#8220;&#8230; The reckless endangerment of neighbourhoods make the mountain particularly vulnerable &#8230; An expert witness, directly affected who is also a university professor, bio-chemist and cancer research specialist was not allowed to give her expert testimony due to Court interference.&#8221; Artist-witness-writer: Joe Pepper &#8211; reproduced here with permission.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>