<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0235">By February 2020, TMX injunction trials were still going on for arrests from as early as August 2018 &#8211; and in some cases, repeat arrestees. Very little news media attention had been dedicated to TMX court proceedings in this period, which involved moves by RCMP to contravene official injunction protocol by arresting people based just on their review of video surveillance several days after the alleged infractions, with no face-to-face warnings. Subtle forms of resistance were now increasingly playing out. An Indigenous elder who had been watching over the land in Burnaby &#8211; and witnessing illegal company construction activities &#8211; on January 29<sup>tth</sup> defied the judge's instructions to plea, instead expressing concerns about what happened as a result of the crimes of the Crown kidnapping Indigenous children. Although these encounters were relatively hidden from public view, public discourse about BC court injunctions would suddenly be remade, thrust into national and global spotlights the very next week. On February 6th, militarised police began intensifying raids and arrests in Indigenous communities elsewhere in BC, in Wet'suwet'en territory, to remove Wet'suwet'en people from obstructing the construction of long-resisted gas pipelines on their (also never ceded) land (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bliss &amp; Temper, 2018</xref>). Aggressive injunction &#8220;enforcement&#8221; was caught on video, capturing police pointing guns and belligerently manhandling women. RCMP violence on Wet'suwet'en territory catapulted public consciousness about injunctions; solidarity movements linking Indigenous and non-Indigenous people together sprouted across the country. Trains throughout the land were cancelled by Indigenous-led blockades thousands of miles away, with slogans such as &#8220;<italic>when justice fails, block the rails</italic>&#8221;; ports, bridges and roads were also shut down, for some representing a &#8220;watershed moment&#8221; (<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">The Star, 2020</xref>) and a recognition that &#8220;<italic>reconciliation is dead</italic>&#8221; unless there are major state changes on Indigenous rights.</p>