<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0245">To this I add that critically studying what transpires in courtrooms helps dispel any residual assumptions that the legal system in Canada proceeds with neutral objective processes, illuminating asymmetrical power relations and cultural imperialism at play &#8211; as well as how these are experienced viscerally. Both the TMX and Wet'suwet'en injunctions illustrate how judges routinely exude bias in favour of the fossil fuel industry's narratives when defining &#8220;irreparable harm&#8221; and in rigidly enforcing forms of legal territorialisation that &#8220;invert traditional expectations of justice&#8221; (<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Sylvestre et al., 2020</xref>). Even within confined visions of an economic-profits-above-all-else philosophy, industry narratives that blocking pipeline construction constitute &#8220;harm&#8221; to the taxpaying public have themselves been shown to be untenable.<xref rid="fn14" ref-type="fn">14</xref>
A judge's moves during injunction proceedings not only routinely side-stepped evidence on financial matters, including financial harms of climate change itself,<xref rid="fn15" ref-type="fn">15</xref>
but also countless other more-than-merely-financial harms that are unequally distributed by race, gender and class, with more than human ecosystems at stake. For settler-colonial courts, care for corporate interests routinely trumps forms of caring that are central to Indigenous laws &#8211; care for land, water, people and other inhabitants of the planet; and for many people who came to the BC courthouse, each day in the court seemed to make it increasingly clear that far too sparse attention was being paid to every one of the critical concerns. As one fellow courtroom observer and supporter of land and water protection remarked in a letter to the Office of the B.C. Attorney General, amid the systemic racism on display:<disp-quote><p><italic>&#8220;The blatant bias and privileging of the Crown throughout the proceedings has been offensive and disturbing to witness. The power differentials that exist between the well-moneyed Crown working in tandem with the Trans Mountain Pipeline Expansion against the Indigenous land defender on Legal Aid are clear to the members of the public watching the trial &#8230; We can see that no justice will be served in these courts, and that the Crown is a well-oiled tool in the ongoing systemic discrimination against Indigenous peoples and all who hold values that respect the land.&#8221;</italic><xref rid="fn16" ref-type="fn">16</xref></p></disp-quote>
</p>