<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0255">In this vein, Indigenous laws of the People of the Inlet, the Tsleil-Waututh Nation, <italic>command</italic> engagement with &#8220;<italic>a sacred obligation to protect, defend, and steward the water, land, air, and resources of the territory</italic>&#8221; (Tsleil-Waututh Nation legal principles as cited in: <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Curran et al., 2020</xref>). In one court appearance, the Defence counsel for three Indigenous defendants pointed to Section 13 of the Trans Mountain injunction order, which excludes &#8220;<italic>persons acting in the course of or in the exercise of a statutory duty, power or authority</italic>.&#8221; The defence argued for recognizing the co-existence of multiple systems of law, and cited the foundational belief in Indigenous law held by the defendants that they carried the duty and authority to act as they did to protect the land, water, and all living things.<xref rid="fn17" ref-type="fn">17</xref>
The argument was immediately rejected by the judge. Notably, at sentencing hearings in September 2020, Indigenous elders from the Tsleil-Waututh Nation and Chief Judy Wilson of the Union of BC Indian Chiefs again re-confirmed that these defendants had been given the responsibility to act exactly as they did, and that their action was in keeping with Indigenous laws and sacred obligations with which they were explicitly entrusted. Despite the BC provincial government passing UNDRIP legislation, the Crown and judge's vocabularies, epistemic starting points, jurisdictional assumptions and relational practices in the court all remained rigidly aligned &#8211; through the TMX injunction &#8211; as anathematic to sacred obligations. While talk of &#8216;decolonial&#8217; approaches widely circulate in political discourses outside of courts, settler-colonial violence in the courtroom continues to flourish in the most blatant of ways, denying truths and rigidly embracing fossil fuel-friendly conceptualisations of &#8216;care&#8217; and &#8216;harm&#8217; to drive the punishing of those peacefully resisting.</p>