<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0590">As the pandemic rages on through 2021 and access to vaccines is uneven, international solidarity continues to be tested. It is thus important that alternative platforms and mechanisms within and across countries continue to be developed, tested, and strengthened to maintain dialogue and foster understanding, knowledge exchange, and momentum for change. This includes city alliances, which have already proven powerful in the international climate debate, partnerships for change between civil society, public and/or private sectors, and international collaboration between regional governments. Alongside traditional actors in the food system and environmental space, a number of action-oriented knowledge and funding platforms for the transformation of the food systems are emerging, for example EAT, the Climate Land Use Alliance (CLUA), the Food Agriculture Biodiversity and Energy Consortium (FABLE), and the Food and Land Use Coalition (FOLU), which seek to bring together multiple stakeholders operating across different scales and sectors. The discussions in the context of the IIASA&#8211;ISC Consultative Science platform suggest that in addition to moving forward with the global agenda, further attention must be focused on identifying context-specific solutions and implementation capacities, which are informed by the larger strategic and programmatic rationale for food system transformations. The often-predominant emphasis on global transformations needs to be complemented by elevating applied research for context-specific solutions. Here, public&#8211;private partnerships and research networks should be strengthened with a focus on improving targeted research and implementation capacities in developing countries, to facilitate the adoption of technologies and practices that are suitable for the prevailing socioeconomic and environmental conditions, but also take into account global trends and sustainability demands.</p>