<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par32">Bigger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>) identified three technical challenges that could prevent the successful operation of an ETS: lack of participants in the market (generally not a problem for large markets like carbon markets), limitations in making the natural object fungible and substitutable and the regulatory nature of the market. The latter includes political uncertainty and the overlap with non-market regulations, as well as regulatory limits on the market such as maximum permit holding or price controls that limit market functionality and liquidity. Part of the challenge in making the natural object fungible is the huge measurement issues. Cooper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2015</xref>: 1795) points out the role of assumptions in establishing trading schemes, which include: &#8220;(1) that the activities that produce emissions are equivalent in kind; (2) that a unified measure of emissions is available; and (3) that the volume of emissions generated by each firm is known. However, none of these assumptions holds true in the absence of a coordinated metrological system&#8221;. The over-allocation of free permits leading to huge wealth transfers to large emitters was noted above as a problem in early phases of the EU ETS (Moore &amp; Jordan, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2020</xref>). Not all markets allow offsets, but those that do allow use of the CDM involve major risks of errors in accounting practices, periodic revaluations and many documented instances of fraud (B&#246;hm et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>; Lohmann, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2010</xref>). Market proponents argue that these technical challenges can be resolved, yet even if such resolutions were possible, there remain some fundamental challenges relating to measurement assumptions, postponing the structural transition and inequality between developed countries and the Global South (Bryant et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2015</xref>; McAfee, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2012</xref>; Pearse &amp; B&#246;hm, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2014</xref>).</p>