<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par33">Possibly the most fundamental objection to MBMs is that they postpone the structural transition away from fossil fuels. Treating all emissions as equal ignores the importance of lock in and path dependence, because it does not incentivise the best technology for emissions reduction but rather the best financial practices to keep costs low. This may involve simply purchasing permits or switching to a more profitable fossil fuel technology rather than transitioning from fossil fuels (Aldred, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2012</xref>; Bryant, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2017</xref>; Lohmann, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2010</xref>). This lack of transition is a particular issue given that industrialised Global North countries are the major historical emitters. It has been argued that carbon markets, particularly the use of the CDM and Payments for Ecosystem Services (PES), serve to entrench disparities of development with regard to the Global South (McAfee, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2012</xref>; B&#246;hm e al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>). Some of the seminal work on this topic has been done by Lohmann (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2010</xref>: 240) who points out that cutting the emissions via &#8220;routine, cheap efficiency improvements that leave a fossil-fuelled infrastructure as it is&#8221; will be far more damaging and even expensive in the longer term than cutting the same amount by &#8220;investment in renewable technologies with a high potential for wide adoption, or through initiating approaches to food production, energy generation, or transport that are fundamentally more conducive to climatic stability&#8221;. Emissions in different locations cannot therefore be treated equally, because we must consider their role in the structural transition away from fossil fuels. In this process of deterritorialisation, MBMs further ignore the role of climate justice. Hickel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2020</xref>) considers historical emissions as &#8220;a process of atmospheric colonisation&#8221; whereby Global North countries have emitted the majority of historical emissions but Global South countries will face the majority of climate impacts and associated costs.</p>