<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par1">&#8220;Conference of the Parties&#8221; or COPs is a global climate summit which was started by United Nations (UN) to bring all the countries of the world together in order to escalate goals of Paris Agreement (2015) and the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) (a treaty that came into force in 1994) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ukcop26.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/COP26-Explained.pdf">https://ukcop26.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/COP26-Explained.pdf</ext-link>). This year (2021)&#160;was the 26th annual summit of COPs, hence given the name COP26 and was held at Glasgow, United Kingdom (UK) in partnership with Italy. COP26 is one of the biggest and most significant summits on climate change since the&#160;Paris Agreement in&#160;2015) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nationalgrid.com/responsibility/environment/cop26">https://www.nationalgrid.com/responsibility/environment/cop26</ext-link>). Paris Agreement was an international treaty on climate change and was taken up by 196 Parties at COP21where countries were determined to put forward the plans on how to reduce their emissions, known as Nationally Determined Contributions, or NDCs. The main target was to restrict global warming to below 2 &#176;C, preferably 1.5 &#176;C when compared to pre-industrial era (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-paris-agreement/the-paris-agreement">https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-paris-agreement/the-paris-agreement</ext-link>). In COP26 nearly 200 countries participated to adopt the &#8216;Climate Pact&#8217;, which is directly related to Paris Agreement rulebook and is a way forward to keep the aims of the treaty alive in order to spike the decarbonisation of the global economy (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_21_6021">https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_21_6021</ext-link>). The Glasgow meeting made few progresses, such as cutting down on emissions, declaration on zero-emission vehicles to promote greener transport and acknowledging deforestation, but looking at the outcome of the conference, the evaluation reveals that the targets have not been achieved and overall the roadmap is not very clear. The signatories do not seem to be unified against the environmental menace, just like the nations have failed to show united front to COVID-19.</p>