<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par2">There are four major goals that have been set up to achieve at COP26. First is to secure global net zero carbon by mid-century, keeping 1.5 &#176;C within reach (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ukcop26.org/cop26-goals/">https://ukcop26.org/cop26-goals/</ext-link>). To keep the first target within reach global emissions must be reduced by 45% by 2030 in comparison to levels of 2010 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-03431-4">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-03431-4</ext-link>). Climate change is no more a low-level issue but has become a life threatening global emergency. According to a study by Climate Action Tracker, even if the pledges announced at the COP26 meeting are enforced, still temperatures are predicted to rise by 2.4 &#176;C up to 2100. This is much above the target of 1.5 &#176;C accepted at the Paris Agreement and the effects of this are likely to be catastrophic in future (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-03433-2">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-03433-2</ext-link>). In fact, in the latest report of Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), it has been revealed that the planet is going to witness the limit of 1.5 &#176;C in early 2030s itself, triggering irreversible changes in our environment (such as flooding, drought, bushfires, and destruction of species) and called it &#8216;code red for humanity&#8217; (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/sr15/">https://www.ipcc.ch/sr15/</ext-link>). According to a global climate report published by World Meteorological Organisation (WMO) (2021), despite the fact that the world was stalled due to pandemic caused by novel corona virus (COVID-19) for last 2 years, yet the global mean temperature in 2021 i.e. between January and September was 1.08&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.13&#160;&#176;C more than the 1850&#8211;1900 (pre-industrial era). The report also suggests that as a result of rising temperatures, global sea levels have also risen by 4.4&#160;mm/year between 2013 and 2021 (State of the Global Climate 2021 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://library.wmo.int/doc_num.php?explnum_id=10859">https://library.wmo.int/doc_num.php?explnum_id=10859</ext-link>). Oceans are known to produce 50% of atmospheric oxygen, absorb 25% of anthropogenic carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) emissions and trap 90% of excess heat in the climate system. To highlight the important connect between oceans and climate change, European Union (EU) called for &#8216;EU Ocean Day&#8217; at COP26. However, acidification of oceans due to unprecedented rate of global warming and overexploitation of its resources remains to be marginalised at climate change negotiations thus hampering its sustainability (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://theconversation.com/cop26-failed-to-address-ocean-acidification-but-the-law-of-the-seas-means-states-must-protect-the-worlds-oceans-171949">https://theconversation.com/cop26-failed-to-address-ocean-acidification-but-the-law-of-the-seas-means-states-must-protect-the-worlds-oceans-171949</ext-link>). Data reveals that 14% of coral species have already vanished; Arctic has lost ice sheets about six times the size of Germany in last 40&#160;years and marine species are disappearing at double the rate than on land (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/oceans-and-fisheries/news/cop-26-eu-ocean-day-highlights-role-oceans-tackling-climate-change-2021-10-29_en">https://ec.europa.eu/oceans-and-fisheries/news/cop-26-eu-ocean-day-highlights-role-oceans-tackling-climate-change-2021-10-29_en</ext-link>).</p>