<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par4">Similarly, deforestation is among the major drivers of climate change and past forest protections acts and agreements have failed to mitigate the loss of forest cover (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dw.com/en/zero-deforestation-commitment-empty-promises-or-a-workable-plan/a-59700862">https://www.dw.com/en/zero-deforestation-commitment-empty-promises-or-a-workable-plan/a-59700862</ext-link>). Forests cover about 31% of global land and one-third of the area is of primary origin (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fao.org/state-of-forests/en/">https://www.fao.org/state-of-forests/en/</ext-link>). Protecting forest loss and reversing unprecedented rate of deforestation is critical for climate change and biodiversity loss. Global Forest Watch report states that forests act as sinks and absorb a net of 7.6 billion metric tonnes CO<sub>2</sub> per year, i.e. more than 1.5 times carbon emitted by US annually (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.globalforestwatch.org/blog/climate/forests-carbon-emissions-sink-flux/">https://www.globalforestwatch.org/blog/climate/forests-carbon-emissions-sink-flux/</ext-link>). Although more than 130 countries at COP26 have pledged to reverse deforestation by 2030, some of them backed out during the final proposal despite having a large proportion of forest covers that need immediate conservation measures. Situation is already grave and past record reveals that we have lost huge chunks of forest areas. State of World&#8217;s Forest Report by Food and Agricultural Organization FAO (2020) suggests that since 1990, forest loss has been estimated to be 420 million hectare, mainly due to land conversion by humans. According to a data of World Resource Institute, about 12.2 million hectares of forest cover was lost in 2020 only. Of this area, around 4.2 million hectares (an area equal to the size of Netherlands) was lost in humid tropical primary forests, which are extremely important zones of carbon sequestration and biodiversity. The loss resulted in carbon emissions of 2.64 Gt which is equivalent to emissions of 570 million cars (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://research.wri.org/gfr/forest-pulse">https://research.wri.org/gfr/forest-pulse</ext-link>). Another report by World Wildlife Fund for Nature&#160;(WWF) suggests that in the last 50&#160;years, we have lost approximately 17% of the Amazon rainforests mainly due to conversion of forest for cattle ranching. Other drivers include agriculture, poorly planned infrastructure and illegal logging (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldwildlife.org/threats/deforestation-and-forest-degradation">https://www.worldwildlife.org/threats/deforestation-and-forest-degradation</ext-link>). In addition, forest fires are another major cause of forest loss. In this regard, a series of satellite images by Monitoring of the Andean Amazon Project (MAAP) estimate that around 2.2 million&#160;hectares of the Brazilian Amazon&#8217;s rainforest was burned in 2020. In fact, the report also reveals that there is a strong link between deforestation and forest fires and all of the major fires of 2021 broke out on land deforested in 2020, which was mainly due to anthropogenic reasons (such as agribusiness and cattle pastures) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://news.mongabay.com/2021/06/the-brazilian-amazon-is-burning-again/">https://news.mongabay.com/2021/06/the-brazilian-amazon-is-burning-again/</ext-link>). Land use change is one of the biggest issues which requires to be taken up seriously.</p>