<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par6">Another goal was at protecting communities and natural habitats. This calls for conservation and restoration of ecosystems and also developing defences, warning systems and resilient infrastructure (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ukpublichealthnetwork.org.uk/cop26-goal-two-adapt-to-protect-communities-and-natural-habitats/">https://ukpublichealthnetwork.org.uk/cop26-goal-two-adapt-to-protect-communities-and-natural-habitats/</ext-link>). It is high time to take into account the preservation of lands and livelihoods of indigenous people and forest communities as they are the ones who are least responsible for causing damage to the environment but most affected due to climate change and global warming. Natural disasters like storms, floods and wildfires are escalating at a sharp speed around the world, mainly due to increased anthropogenic activities. A report by WMO suggests that rapid pace of climate change has increased the frequency of natural disasters by five-fold in last 50 years, affecting poorer and developing countries in particular (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://news.un.org/en/story/2021/09/1098662">https://news.un.org/en/story/2021/09/1098662</ext-link>). The analysis is based on Centre for Research on the Epidemiology of Disasters&#8217; (CRED) Emergency Events Database (EM-DAT). The report reveals that between 1970 and 2019, 22,326 disasters were recorded, of which 11,072 were caused due to weather, climate and water hazards, resulting in 2.06 million deaths and US$ 3.64 trillion of economic losses (Atlas Of Mortality And Economic Losses From Weather, Climate And Water Extremes (1970&#8211;2019) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://library.wmo.int/doc_num.php?explnum_id=10769">https://library.wmo.int/doc_num.php?explnum_id=10769</ext-link>). This calls for development of proactive measures and integrated policies to reduce disaster related risks to vulnerable communities.</p>