<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par9">If aspirations of COP26 are to be met, we need to immediately take action to implement the targets both at micro and macro levels. It is also important to mention that progress towards combating climate change, which is the core of COP26 summit, is also a roadmap to Sustainable Development Goals 2030 (SDGs 2030). Therefore, any blowout to the aims of COPs also intersects with the SDGs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.the-ies.org/sites/default/files/documents/cop26_the_sdgs.pdf">https://www.the-ies.org/sites/default/files/documents/cop26_the_sdgs.pdf</ext-link>). Climate resilient development demands an integrated approach for sustainability, economic growth and equitable human environment. To stabilize climate and move towards sustainability, climate smart agriculture, sustainable forest management, early warning and sharing systems, resilient infrastructure, soil and water conservation and diversification of livelihood must be adopted. Realising the importance of ocean&#8217;s contribution towards climate change and scaling up of ocean-based strategies is also needed to accelerate net-zero carbon world as they are the natural sinks to CO<sub>2</sub>. Strict laws must be formulated to conserve natural resources and biodiversity. Remote sensing and geographical information system (GIS)&#160;can be helpful tools for monitoring and investigating any kind of over-exploitation (Arora and Mishra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2020</xref>). Moreover, it has become urgent to accelerate the efforts to phase-down coal power and stop fossil fuel subsidies without any further dilutions. Labelling of carbon footprint on packaged products must be done to increase the understanding of carbon emission and its control among the consumers. Gross Domestic Product (GDP) should be replaced with Gross Carbon Footprint (GCF) and Gross Sustainable Production (GSP) for assessment of sustainable development and measuring the impact of production on the environment (Arora and Mishra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2019</xref>). To increase awareness of the current climate crisis, educational and media programs should also be encouraged, especially the participation of young generation to make it a public movement. This will put pressure on policymakers to deliver a positive outcome. Hundreds of natives and local communities along with activists marching outside the Glasgow conference is already a proof that people are not ready to be in this existential crisis that demands losing their health, infrastructure, jobs and above all, their lives. Climate justice for poor, marginalised communities like those from vulnerable habitats and Small Island Developing States (SIDS), most vulnerable to climate change and unable to bear the hardships, food insecurity and displacements must be addressed at a very urgent basis. This is a matter of human rights and also right of living for every species on earth and hence unified laws and negotiations must be implemented. It is imperative that we as a society must urge and take a step in the direction of protecting those who are weakest and least responsible for any climate emergency by allotting monetary or other systems of help to them. Financial support from businesses, non-profit organizations, societies and developing nations could be vital in fulfilling this agenda. Also, developed countries must deliver on the USD 100 billion funding as early as possible, to give it a momentum. Moreover, restriction and sanctions should be levied on those that do not follow the guidelines. This kind of socio-economic justice will engage more people who were not earlier involved in this course and will make this climate emergency more relatable to these individuals. Nature-based solutions are integral and must be adapted at global, national and local levels. Ecosystem-based Adaptation (EbA), is one such solution and could be useful in meeting the challenges of climate change, which involves conservation, sustainable management and restoration of ecosystems. It will reduce climate-related vulnerabilities and build resilience to human communities by harnessing ecosystem services and biodiversity conservation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.iucn.org/resources/issues-briefs/ecosystem-based-adaptation">https://www.iucn.org/resources/issues-briefs/ecosystem-based-adaptation</ext-link>). It is also necessary to realise the importance of cumulative progress as each goal is interlinked with the other.</p>