<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0220">A total of six SDGs is reviewed below and eventually listed in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref> and plotted in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;2</xref>.<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015"><list-item id="u0035"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0225">Objective 1.4 aims to ensure equal rights for economic resources and basic services and financial services &#8211; above all microfinance to everyone &#8211; stressing on the poor and the vulnerable.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0040"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0230">Objective 2.3 is focused on agricultural productivity and income of small farmers, underlying the importance of the vulnerable; for such a scope, the goal proposes to improve financial services, markets, and opportunities for farmers.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0045"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0235">Objective 5.1 has the sake to boost reforms in favour of gender equality concerning economic resources; the objective attempts to foster women's access to financial services, natural resources, land and other property ownership.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0050"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0240">Another paramount objective is 8.3: it spots the cruciality of promoting access to financial services and further strategies to facilitate development-oriented policies as policies to boost the private sector.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0055"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0245">Objective 8.10 claims that granting access to banking, insurance and financial services to all is vital to reinforce financial institutions.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0060"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0250">Lastly, objective 9.3 recognises access to financial services and affordable credit as a major strategy for small businesses as a priority (<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">UN, 2015</xref>).</p></list-item></list><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Categorisation of SDGs dedicated to access to finance.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Table&#160;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>SDG</th><th>SD Dimensions</th><th>SD sub-dimensions</th><th>Domain</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1.4</td><td>Economic; Social</td><td>Financial</td><td>Equal rights; Economic resources; Financial services; Vulnerable</td></tr><tr><td>2.3</td><td>Economic; Social</td><td>Agricultural; Financial</td><td>Agricultural productivity; Small farmers income; Vulnerable; Financial services</td></tr><tr><td>5.1</td><td>Economic; Social; Governance</td><td>Legal; Agricultural</td><td>Gender equality; Reforms; Access to finance; Access to resources</td></tr><tr><td>8.3</td><td>Economic; Social</td><td>Financial; Economic; Entrepreneurial</td><td>Access to finance; Private sector boosting</td></tr><tr><td>8.10</td><td>Economic; Social</td><td>Financial</td><td>Access to finance; Universal access; Financial institutions</td></tr><tr><td>9.3</td><td>Economic</td><td>Financial; Economic; Entrepreneurial</td><td>Access to finance; Affordable credit; SMEs enhancement</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#160;2</label><caption><p>Content analysis on microfinance and resilience within SDGs.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#160;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>