<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">In addition to these visual campaigns, the <italic>Comitato No Grandi Navi</italic> has also engaged in confrontational initiatives over the years. The area around Piazza San Marco, the political center of the former Venetian Republic, is arguably the most symbolically resonant space in the city (Araya L&#243;pez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2021</xref>). Despite being Venice&#8217;s primary tourist attraction, Piazza San Marco continues to hold symbolic meaning and value for the city&#8217;s residents. For them, it represents their former independence. Because of the increase in tourism, as well as the laws that prohibit protests at Piazza San Marco, everyday use of the space by locals has declined. Dominated by tourists and for years framed by passing cruise ships, the piazza has become a&#160;symbol of spatial expropriation, an issue that activists address through creative forms of protest. By performing a&#160;collective jump into the basin in front of the smaller Piazzetta San Marco, they allude to the issue while also circumventing the ban on protests. The use of their bodies shows their performative and playful approach to this matter, as well as their aim of communicating their right to the space. Their emphasis on embodied and tacit knowledge conveys what it means to live in the city. Like other recent protest movements, such initiatives show a&#160;&#8220;strong aestheticization [&#8230;], characterized by symbolic action, such as the symbolic visualization of grievances and the reappropriation of public space&#8221; (Balint et&#160;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2014</xref>: 11). The committee has developed creative strategies for appropriating space, which they skillfully use in different locales. They express their spatial knowledge through the use of their bodies and emphasize the cultural significance of symbolic places which otherwise tend to remain unrepresented in the popular imagination. In doing so, they show that both public and political space are constantly renegotiated and produced anew (Fischer-Lichte <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2004</xref>: 199).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn18">18</xref></p>