<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">To assess the associations between heavy rainfall and HIV prevalence and risk of transmission, a multivariable regression model was fitted for each outcome and pooled across all countries and within each country. We fitted the pooled models with survey-level fixed effects and the heavy rainfall variable, as well as sex, marital status, age, educational level, wealth index, urban residence, and survey month. Fixed effects allow for the models to be run within country and accounts for key differences between countries and the timing of surveys. Standard errors account for clustering at the enumeration area level. For binary outcomes (HIV prevalence and STIs), a logistic distribution was assumed. Given that the binary outcomes were relatively uncommon (&lt;10%), the odds ratio (OR) approximates the risk ratio.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> For the regression model specifying the number of sexual partners (count variable) as the outcome, we assumed a negative binomial distribution. The exponentiated coefficients from these models therefore represent the incidence rate ratio. To assess for interactions between heavy rainfall and potential modifiers (male vs female sex, rural vs urban residence, and adolescent vs younger adult vs adult age), we included product terms in the regression models and considered a 2-sided &#945; significance level of .05 for the interaction term. Given that the evaluation of interactions was exploratory, we applied the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure to adjust for a false discovery rate.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Subgroup analyses were conducted for ages 15 to 19 years given that HIV among this younger age group could be a proxy for HIV incidence because it captures a more recent pattern.<sup><xref rid="zoi220857r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> All analyses were conducted in SAS, version 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc).</p>