<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">It is well known that animals including bats are reservoirs for several viruses and were a conduit for the Ebola epidemic as well as severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) Coronavirus 1, Middle Eastern Respiratory Syndrome (MERS), and the emergence of COVID&#8208;19 (Hemida &amp; Ba Abduallah,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Habitat disruption is the main driver of loss of biodiversity, and climate change may play a role by forcing species to shift habitat and changing geographical range of species (Bale,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Xiao et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). As species shift habitats, this brings animals in closer range to humans and livestock which then serve as a vehicle for launching a global pandemic. Even more extreme conditions existed in Wuhan, China, the epicenter of the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic, where bats and pangolins&#8212;with pangolins recently emerging as vectors for transmission of viruses&#8212;are suggested as vectors for coronaviruses since they are housed in crowded, open markets with close and often squalid conditions (Bale,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Xiao et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Pangolins are similar to bat species as mammals that are known to be able to be infected with viruses such as coronaviruses (Bale,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Morens et al., <xref rid="phn12866-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Xiao et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Emerging evidence may support that in our climate&#8208;changing world, there is encroachment on animal habitats which may impact health and risk for infectious diseases; thus there is a need for urgent efforts to limit climate change to address the emergence of new pandemics in the future (Bernstein,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).</p>