<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Global Environmental Health Day was held on July 1, 2020 and Columbia University's Earth Institute released a State of the Planet report on <italic toggle="yes">COVID&#8208;19&#8217;s Long&#8208;Term Effects on Climate Change&#8212;For Better or Worse</italic> (Cho,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Furthermore, because of recommendations for lockdowns, social distancing, and work from home advisories, significant decreases in transportation occurred globally and limited industrial activity resulted in a 17% decrease in daily carbon emissions in April (Cho,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Cho's commentary suggested that there have been opportunities to both improve and detract from improving public health in the time of COVID&#8208;19 with a lens on climate change. Areas of concern included plans to withdraw from the Paris Climate Accord of 2015, delays in international negotiations regarding climate change and the planned climate meeting of November 2020, deforestation in the Amazon accelerating during the pandemic, weakening of climate policies in the US and rollback of US measures. Additional areas of concern identified by Cho are disruption of science research during the pandemic, less funding for climate resilience and renewable energy, and an increase in use of plastic to prevent spread of COVID&#8208;19. However, Cho notes that there are areas of improvement amidst COVID&#8208;19 that may positively impact public health including a green recovery in other countries with funding for renewable energy sources, more biking and walking as a COVID/climate change co&#8208;benefit, less international travel since transportation represents 23% off global carbon emissions and 11% reduction by aviation (Cho,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). It is important to note that the pandemic has led to simpler living and increased engagement of many in the important role of science in both public health and pandemic response.</p>