<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Manzanedo and Manning (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) analyzed the intersection of COVID&#8208;19 and the urgent climate crisis addressing the unique areas of overlap and differences between the two crises and the key lessons that can be learned. These lessons include &#8220;<italic toggle="yes">high momentum trends; irreversible changes; social and spatial inequality; weakening of international solidarity, and less costly to prevent than to cure&#8221;</italic> (p. 1). Notably, they view one critical difference: since the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic emerged rapidly while the climate crisis has had a decades&#8208;long emergence with a looming crisis by 2030 if urgent action is not taken. Regarding lessons of COVID&#8208;19 and climate change, <italic toggle="yes">high momentum trends</italic> also identified as time lags refer to the delayed response to the pandemic and to climate change science. The authors noted that ignoring calls to action are costlier in the long run. <italic toggle="yes">Irreversible changes</italic> are pressing for the climate crisis since unless greenhouse gases are reduced, there will be planetary changes that are irreparable with significant damage that may negatively impact health. <italic toggle="yes">Social and spatial inequality</italic> refers to aspects of social determinants of health including poverty, inequity between wealthy and poor nations, lack of access to care by many of the world's people, and increased risk by race/ethnicity for black/brown populations. This is significant for both COVID&#8208;19 whereby African&#8208;American and Hispanic populations are disproportionately affected by the pandemic in the US and have significantly poorer outcomes (Azar et&#160;al.,&#160;<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">weakening of international solidarity</italic> since the Paris Agreement and the US withdrawal from the treaty is another key area of international weakening in the global commitment to address climate change. The fact that both the pandemic and climate change are less costly to prevent rather than to cure is a significant outcome of both challenges that we face. As Kerry (<xref rid="phn12866-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) wrote &#8220;climate change and COVID&#8208;19&#8230;.[are] truly the tale of two pandemics deferred, denied, and distorted, one with catastrophic consequences [COVID&#8208;19], the other with even greater risk if we don't reverse course [climate change]&#8221; (p. A8).</p>