<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par38">The argument of Bou-Habib and Olsaretti is very interesting, but it is quite different from the arguments advanced in this paper. The first difference relates to concepts, language, and style. In this paper, the question of the environmental justice of procreative parenting is analyzed using a different conceptual language and starting from a different methodology, which is less theory driven.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn21">21</xref> Methodologically, this approach will make it possible to use the outcomes of this analysis for a subsequent step that moves from theoretical analysis of abstract principles to their consequences in the real world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn22">22</xref> Second, Bou-Habib and Olsaretti&#8217;s argument is a conditional argument: to the extent that people would be willing to hypothetically insure themselves to keep open the option that they would like to be a parent in the future, the modified luck-egalitarian account can justify parental subsidies. In this paper, by contrast, I bite the bullet, and develop an argument why people should be willing to keep open the option of being a parent when designing a just society and why distributive justice does not morally permit the nonprocreator to use more resources from the ecosystems through consumption. The argument in this paper gives a phenomenological account of why parenting is morally distinct from overconsumption and uses this in an argument about distributive justice. And third, the ultimate reasons for socializing some of the costs of procreative parenting are different. One could argue, as Bou-Habib and Olsaretti do, that combining equality of resources with hypothetical insurance will make people want to support procreative parenting. If this is applied to the case of ecological resources, it would imply that parents would not have to suffer lower levels of consumption because of their procreative choices. Similarly, in more recent work, Olsaretti has rejected the view that the costs of procreative parenting should not be shared between parents and nonparents. Olsaretti has developed an analysis within the framework of liberal egalitarianism, using resources as the appropriate metric.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn23">23</xref> Yet it is disputed that matters of distributive justice should be decided using the distributive metric of resources. What difference would it make if one were to endorse another metric of justice, such as capabilities? That is what is investigated next, by first describing how the capability approach would conceptualize procreative parenting (section&#160;<xref rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref>) and then asking what difference the capability approach makes for the plausibility of the Moral Equivalence Thesis (section&#160;<xref rid="Sec5" ref-type="sec">5</xref>).</p>