<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">During the wave of <italic toggle="yes">urban optimism</italic>, this line of research emerged through attempts to, on the one hand, explain the distribution of authority across multiple sectors and levels of government in governing the climate, and, on the other hand, support a celebration of cities in international networks as a new form of transnational governance. Within the former theme, Bulkeley and Kern's (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0076" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) study on modes of governance drew attention to the need for local governments to draw on capacities and resources of other actors to realize emission reductions, in a context of limited reliance on regulatory instruments and an increasing use of &#8220;enabling&#8221; approaches (an insight that was again highlighted a decade later by Elofsson, Smedby, Larsson, and Nassen (<xref rid="wcc643-bib-0124" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)). Multilevel governance research within this theme has focused on understanding collaboration and institutional partnerships between government departments (Roberts, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0238" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), local government and private sector actors (Lund, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0193" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), with societal actors (Barton, Krellenberg, &amp; Harris, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0058" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Vella, Butler, Sipe, Chapin, &amp; Murley, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0286" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), or with boundary&#8208;spanning organizations (Hodson, Marvin, &amp; Bulkeley, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0151" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The underlying assumption is that multilevel governance mechanisms enhance the ability of municipal government to formulate and implement climate plans and supports institutional learning (Benz, Kemmerzell, Knodt, &amp; Tews, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0063" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Lee, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0185" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).</p>