<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The second wave has also fostered in&#8208;depth critiques of the role of TNMs. Local autonomy may paradoxically be limited by transnational authority, and thus, there is interest in how global networks reinforce hegemonic structures of power (Chu, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0096" ref-type="bibr">2018a</xref>). Other scholars have been skeptical of the ability of TMNs to facilitate action. For example, participation in TMNs may have little effect on actual greenhouse emission reductions (Bansard, Pattberg, &amp; Widerberg, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0055" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Krause, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0178" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) or on national politics (Gore, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0134" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), and participation in these networks continues to be skewed towards the Global North (Bansard et al., <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0055" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). While TMNs offer opportunities for introducing new planning rationales at the local level (Davidson &amp; Gleeson, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0104" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), the ability of global dynamics to change local administrative logics may be limited (Hickmann, Fuhr, Hohne, Lederer, &amp; Stehle, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0148" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). It is also not clear how cities can be held accountable in transnational regimes (Gordon, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0132" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Warnings emphasize the lack of international climate funding on the one hand (Ayers, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), and the negative consequences of the involvement of cities in international institutions on the other (Cohen, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0100" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Fraundorfer, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0130" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Lef&#232;vre, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0187" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). A return to theories of centralized forms of steering has ensued: the notion of orchestration purports to close the gap between the fragmentation caused by transnational governance and the coordination required to meet emission reduction targets (Chan, Ellinger, &amp; Widerberg, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0089" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Gordon &amp; Johnson, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0133" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Hale &amp; Roger, <xref rid="wcc643-bib-0139" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p>