<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0010">For decades, gender equality and inclusion have been central to discussions and points of action in development policy and practice. As pointed out by the UN Women (<xref rid="bb0545" ref-type="bibr">UN-Women, 2021</xref>), achieving all the 17 Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) necessitates addressing issues of gender inequality and promoting women's empowerment. Recently, organizations have increasingly called for a recognition of the importance of gender equality and women's empowerment in improving food systems (<xref rid="bb0580" ref-type="bibr">WFP, 2021a</xref>; <xref rid="bb0415" ref-type="bibr">Njuki et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">GAIN, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">CARE, 2021</xref>). Despite widespread agreement on the importance of gender equality in food systems, there continues to be a lack of a strong gender lens in efforts that seek to improve local food systems. Based on CARE (<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">CARE, 2020a</xref>), 46% of 73 global reports offering potential solutions to hunger during the COVID-19 pandemic &#8216;[&#8230;] do not refer to women and girls at all, and only five (under 7%) &#8216;[&#8230;] propose concrete actions to resolve the gender inequalities crippling food systems'. Many responses to COVID-19, both in policy and analysis, fail to consider how gender interacts with implemented measures and their implications for food security in Africa (<xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Doss et al., 2020</xref>). Furthermore, it has been argued that gender equality is central to food systems transformation and that it must be a key subject in the upcoming food systems dialogues, such as UN food systems summits, implying an existing gap in the past food systems discourse (<xref rid="bb0415" ref-type="bibr">Njuki et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0530" ref-type="bibr">UN, 2021b</xref>; <xref rid="bb0330" ref-type="bibr">IFPRI, 2021</xref>).</p>