<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Five of our independent variables were derived from the 2011 Primary Census Enumeration data. This included population density, or the total number of people per square km in each ward, which was used as a control variable in our multivariable models. Previous studies on the social distribution of urban heat have found population density to be positively associated with the UHRI in U.S. urban areas and also used it as a control variable [<xref rid="B3-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B53-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The proportion of individuals aged 6 years or less was included to examine the relationship between urban heat and presence of young children. Children were considered to be a relatively powerless group in home location decisions and more susceptible to heat illness than adults for multiple reasons, including their greater surface area to body mass ratio, lower rate of sweating, and slower rate of acclimatization [<xref rid="B64-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. The proportion of the ward population classified as Scheduled Caste (SC) was used as a measure of social marginalization, since this classification refers to caste groups within Hindu, Buddhist, and Sikh religions who have faced social discrimination due to their lower status and associated occupational roles. This variable has been utilized to denote social marginalization in environmental justice studies in India [<xref rid="B30-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B31-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B32-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. We also used literacy rate, defined as the proportion of the population aged 7 years or more that was literate, to represent ward socioeconomic status. Since the Census of India does not provide data on annual income, poverty, or wages, literacy rate can be used to denote employability and hence as proxy for socioeconomic status [<xref rid="B30-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The fifth variable included the proportion of workers in the ward who were involved in agricultural activities. This was estimated as the sum of main and marginal cultivators and agricultural laborers, divided by the total number of workers in the ward. Wards with higher values of this variable can be expected to have more residents involved in outdoor agricultural labor and hence be more vulnerable to the adverse effects of heat exposure [<xref rid="B21-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22-ijerph-18-04800" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p>