<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Without dismissing the significance of the IPCC report&#8217;s brave treatment of land tenure issues, we offer some critical observations. First, while the report claims that land grabbing is &#8216;imperfectly&#8217; understood (we agree), it does not offer a way to understand it better. The report simply repeats the well-known drivers of land grabs, namely, the 2007&#8211;2008 food price spike and the rush for biofuel production. During the last decade, there has been a &#8216;literature rush&#8217; on land grabs (Oya, <xref rid="CIT0075" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) resulting in the currently huge body of work on the topic.<xref rid="EN0002" ref-type="fn"><sup>2</sup></xref> There is a significant cluster within this literature dedicated to &#8216;green grabbing&#8217;, i.e. land grabbing in the name of the environment (Benjaminsen &amp; Bryceson, <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Fairhead et al., <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Ojeda, <xref rid="CIT0073" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Yet, the report&#8217;s engagement with the scientific literature on land grabs is thin, and there is no engagement with the cluster on &#8216;green grabbling&#8217;, even though this is the form of land grabbing which is most directly related to the relationship between climate change and land. The report&#8217;s treatment of the land grabbing issue falls far short of the state of the art. How do climate change mitigation and adaptation measures result in land grabbing, and how do land grabs result in deepening the climate crisis? These questions are at the heart of the relationship between climate change and land, with emerging evidence suggesting that recent land grabs are contributing significantly to greenhouse gas emissions. For instance, Liao et al. (<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, p. 15) studied 36.7 million hectares of large-scale land deals and found that, &#8216;clearing lands transacted between 2000 and 2016 (36.7 Mha) could have emitted &#8764;2.26 GtC, but constraining land clearing to historical deforestation rates would reduce emissions related to large-scale land transactions to &#8764;0.81 GtC&#8217;. But these questions are not addressed in the IPCC report. But even the so-called &#8216;green solutions&#8217; &#8211; even if these help save or reduce emissions &#8211; can lead to deeply unjust social outcomes. For example, the shift to renewable energy may, under certain conditions, entail committing larger areas of land to produce energy (at best at the same given level now), given the lower power density of renewables, such that energy production becomes a key driver of land use change under a low-carbon scenario (see Scheidel &amp; Sorman, <xref rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, p. 588).<xref rid="EN0003" ref-type="fn"><sup>3</sup></xref> Recent corporate plans to pursue carbon offsetting based on trees and lands are likely to combine the two dimensions of green grabbing just cited. In its estimates, Oxfam reported that: &#8216;Shell would need about 28.6 mmillion hectares by 2050&#8201;&#8230;&#8201;while TotalEnergies plans to offset about 7% of its emissions, needing about 2.6 million hectares by 2050&#8217; (Harvey, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, n.p.). Moreover, the report claims that &#8216;BP has not set out its plans in detail, but is likely to require as much as 22.5 million hectares for offsetting as much as 15% of its emissions&#8217; (Harvey, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, n.p.). These all sound like Tsing&#8217;s notion of &#8216;economy of appearances&#8217; (Tsing, <xref rid="CIT0099" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>), and so, whether or not these plans materialize, their implications for recasting access to land can be palpable in the real world.</p>