<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">On the other hand, there are working people who need land and who still have a degree of access to a range of land and resources, but whose access is under constant threat from the social forces driving global land grabs. Land tenure security through formal recognition may be relevant to them, but there are four problematical aspects of formal recognition as a strategy which need to be considered. (1) In societies marked by pre-existing land-based inequalities, formalizing land tenure <italic toggle="yes">without</italic> prior or accompanying redistributive or restitutive reforms is likely to result in the formalization of inequalities. Those who were previously differentiated out or expelled from their lands are excluded from even making claims for tenure security, because they do not have existing land tenure to secure, as in the cases of the related land policies carried out in Myanmar from 2012 to 2020 (Ra et al., <xref rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Ra &amp; Ju, <xref rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). (2) Formalization in the context of relatively mobile systems of production almost always means sedentarization: from shifting cultivation to sedentary farming, from mobile pastoralism to ranching, from artisanal fishing to industrial fishpond production. It is a shift from an extensive land/nature-based system to an intensive capitalized system in which very few will socio-economically survive, let alone flourish (Woods, <xref rid="CIT0108" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). And once mobile producers are sedentarized, what happens to the land resources freed up by the formalization process? These are almost always converted into exclusionary capital-intensive, industrial-production systems of farming, ranching or aquaculture. (3) Land claims, like laws and policies, do not self-interpret nor self-implement (Franco, <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Claims are interpreted and implemented in messy political struggles within and between social classes and groups within the state and society. There is nothing inherently pro-poor in land registration and formal recognition of land tenure. The actual balance of social forces that act for or against working people&#8217;s interests ultimately shapes the character and trajectory of public action on tenure recognition, and in virtually all cases, the political power of working people tends to be weaker. (4) The assumption that formal land titles shield land-dependent working people from the differentiating currents of commoditization or expulsion through extra-economic coercion is questionable. The differentiating effects of capitalist market relations or the expelling power of extra-economic coercion cut across institutional status of land claims &#8211; with or without land titles, as many previous land reform beneficiaries in different countries who later gave up their lands show (Adam, <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Moyo, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In many settings, powerful economic forces even prefer lands with formal land titles because land deals look more legitimate; in such cases, deals are more secure, not for working people, but for corporations &#8211; as Deininger explicitly suggested (noted elsewhere in this paper).</p>