<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Our third critical observation is that the IPCC report tends to idealize indigenous peoples&#8217; production systems and customary land tenure. In other words, these societies and their lands &#8211; accounting for around half a billion hectares of land globally &#8211; are assumed not only to be intact, but to be inherently democratic in political character (that is, not socially differentiated), and ecologically sustainable as sources of production inputs and as waste sinks. Yet, there is ample evidence to show that the territories claimed by indigenous peoples have been significantly transformed over time and across space, marked by social differentiation, commodification and agroecological diminution and degradation. It is not uncommon to find indigenous communities that managed to get formal certification of their land rights, only to lease these out to agribusiness corporations or mining companies. In many other cases, while indigenous peoples continue to claim a territory and the central state formally classifies it as indigenous peoples&#8217; territory, in reality it could have already been transformed, in its entirety or in part, into a plantation or commercial real estate hub. The case of Davao&#8217;s Unified Bagobo-Tagabawa Tribe (UBTT) in the Philippines that got ancestral land title to their 38,000 hectares land is relevant: AgriNurture Inc. (ANI), a big agribusiness, signed a long-term lease contract a huge portion of this land for 25 years, renewable for another 25 years, to develop agricultural plantations.<xref rid="EN0004" ref-type="fn"><sup>4</sup></xref> This is not the first time that ANI engaged in such an activity in southern Philippines. There are several mining operations in the Philippines that operate in similar ancestral lands. The study by Vidal (<xref rid="CIT0102" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) shows how a mining company deployed the classic divide-and-conquer tactic to secure free, prior and informed consent from the indigenous community that holds an ancestral land title in order to carry out extensive mining operations inside the indigenous territory. Contemporary communities under customary land tenure are also known to be subject to dynamic social differentiation and class conflict (Peters, <xref rid="CIT0079" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). We are not being dismissive of the importance of indigenous peoples&#8217; production systems and customary land tenure. We believe that whatever their state of being at the current conjuncture, they must be taken seriously because indeed they have important contributions to make to a positive alternative future. What we are less convinced about is by an idealized view of these communities and spaces.</p>