<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par28">Electricity made the second largest contribution to total energy consumption in Australia during the reviewed period. The share of electricity in total energy consumption was equal to 19.6% (in 1990), and it increased to 22.1% (in 2017) as indicated by IEA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>) data. The country&#8217;s total electricity production increased by 63.1% from 11,110 to 18,115 GWh between 1990 and 2017 (IEA, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). Electricity is a type of secondary energy, and it is produced by using both renewable and nonrenewable energy sources. Therefore, it is necessary to analyze electricity generation based on the type of the sources that are used in production. A report by the EIA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>) showed that coal was the leading source in Australia&#8217;s electricity production sector. The share of coal was 62.7% in 2017 (IEA, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). Natural gas followed coal in this respect. According to IEA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>) data, the share of natural gas in electricity generation reached 19.6%, in 2017. Australia began to use solar and wind in its electricity production in 1993 and 1994, respectively. As a result, the total share of these two renewable sources reached 8% in power production at the end of the studied period. Lastly, the shares of hydro, oil, and biofuels in electricity generation were 6.3%, 2%, and 1.4% in 2017, respectively (IEA, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>). The share of renewable energies in Australia&#8217;s total electricity output was 15.7% at the end of the studied period due to the substantial efforts made to increase the consumption of renewable energy sources. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the electricity production of Australia from 1990 to 2017 according to the fuel types utilized.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Australia&#8217;s electricity production based on the fuel types over 1990&#8211;2017</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12053_2021_10014_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>