<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Today, civic space is as much digital as it is physical, and it is under threat. There is concern that restrictions on civic space will continue after the COVID-19 pandemic, with negative implications for civil society responses to other global challenges, including the climate crisis. In 2020, Voule noted that &#8220;active citizenship is key in times of crisis&#8221; and warned that &#8220;democracy cannot be indefinitely postponed.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> Also in 2020, noting the &#8220;gratuitous toll being inflicted on democracy, civil liberties, fundamental freedoms, healthcare ethics, and human dignity&#8221; by unjustified limitations on civil and political rights, Stephen Thomson and Eric Ip warned that COVID-19 emergency measures may herald an &#8220;authoritarian pandemic.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup> In 2021, Voule directly addressed threats to the freedoms of peaceful assembly and of association in the context of the climate change and noted that &#8220;addressing the climate crisis and ensuring a just transition requires the existence of a vibrant and dynamic civic society.&#8221; He added that the freedoms of peaceful assembly and of association are inextricably linked with the right to take part in public affairs. His report challenges us to consider the limits of peaceful dissent in the face of state intransigence. Voule argues that states should recognize and provide space for civil disobedience and nonviolent direct action campaigns, &#8220;which are employed by many climate justice activists around the world who are following in the footsteps of other major transnational social movements.&#8221; He notes that &#8220;States must exercise great restraint on imposing restrictions on [these] forms of peaceful protest, including when taking decisions on whether to arrest, prosecute, impose pre-trial detention, convict or award damages against climate justice activists for engaging in such actions.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup></p>