<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0035">Courthouses can reflect, perpetuate and reproduce forms of colonialism in a myriad of ways. Some may be visible in the arrangement of courthouses themselves (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Faria et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Jeffrey, 2019</xref>), others through the relations, &#8220;performative use of categorisation&#8221; (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Blomley, 2015</xref>) and &#8220;spatial tactics&#8221; (<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Sylvestre et al., 2020</xref>) in particular cases and decisions rendered. In Vancouver, Canada, there is a corridor in the British Columbia (BC) Supreme Court building where more than seventy portraits of white male judges appear on the wall, uninterrupted by female or non-white faces. Near the middle of the hall, a few women's faces eventually appear, reflecting some judiciary changes, before the remaining portraits show more white male judges. The building sits on the unceded territory of the Musqueam, Squamish and Tsleil-Waututh peoples. In the basement of the building, which was designed by a famous architect, a special room, built years ago for the Air India bombing terrorism case, has bullet-proof glass dividing the public gallery from the court. On August 15th, 2018, as part of a research programme on intergenerational environmental justice, I sat in this gallery with other courtroom observers as a seventeen-year old Indigenous boy was sentenced by a white male judge for violating an injunction against impeding construction of an oil pipeline expansion project on his ancestral territory. The injunction had been established in March 2018 by the same judge, a justice in the BC Supreme Court who was formerly a lawyer for the tobacco industry (<xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 2018</xref>). The boy's alleged offence was standing on a road on Burnaby Mountain, in front of a vehicle, and praying there a few days after the injunction was established.</p>