<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0055">In this article, I unpack some of the dramas that ensued over the next 15 months in this courtroom &#8211; a critical setting for grounding debate on what it means to contest interlinked climate, environmental, legal and sociocultural injustices (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Chatterton et al., 2013</xref>) &#8211; and for reflecting on what some judges preclude from articulation. A plethora of legal manoeuvres, including surprises and inconsistent rationales, would be mobilised to penalise peaceful land and water protectors, while entertaining only narrowly circumscribed legal arguments. Diverse resistance strategies would also be cultivated and diverse affects experienced. Despite Indigenous-led movements seeking to bring respect to Indigenous laws (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Borrows, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Napoleon, 2013</xref>), courtrooms in Canada are routinely places of asserting settler-colonial power over Indigenous laws and values, denying Indigenous claims, controlling Indigenous bodies and defining &#8211; with colonial law &#8211; what is relevant or irrelevant about Indigenous land, governance systems and life (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Coulthard, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Crosby &amp; Monaghan, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Daigle, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Hunt, 2014</xref>, p. 234; <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">McKibben, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Nunn, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Palmater, 2016</xref>). While courts have been normalising this violence, courtrooms may simultaneously be places of emotional support, anti-colonial solidarity, critical expression, and intergenerational relation-building in the face of neo-colonial capitalism and colonial legal systems. Below I reflect on being part of one such diverse multi-generational and multi-cultural group, seeing relations of care built between defendants and observers-in-solidarity, as prosecutors and judges punish pipeline protestors using jarring arguments to keep climate issues and Indigenous rights &#8211; and truths &#8211; out of the legal calculus.</p>