<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0060">Linked to the above, this article explores what courtroom ethnography might generate as a vantage point for interpreting wider hegemonic arrangements and counter-hegemonic solidarities. <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">LeQuesne (2019)</xref> advanced notions of &#8220;petro-hegemony&#8221; using Gramsci's theory on hegemony to explore dynamics of consent, compliance, coercion and resistance, exploring the Standing Rock Sioux's fight against the Dakota Access Pipeline (DAPL) in North Dakota. <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Estes and Dhillon (2019)</xref> also argue that unpacking hegemony in the Standing Rock case requires grappling with complex issues of Indigenous sovereignty, gender violence and environmental destruction that have all been implicated in threats of pipelines, seeing the more-than-localized nature of protests and their wider politics. In the case of the Kinder Morgan Pipeline &#8211; branded the &#8220;Trans Mountain Pipeline Expansion&#8221; (TMX) project &#8211; millions of Canadian taxpayer dollars have been spent on security and court costs, and like in the DAPL case, taxpayer money has been used to fund secret police infiltration campaigns among peaceful activists, which police spoke about proudly while on the witness stand in the TMX hearings. While participants in the courthouse shared support and prayer, including praying for the prosecutors, wider developments would also be quietly discussed in the corridors and outside. Courtroom ethnography offers fertile terrain for exploring the affective and political landscapes in and around a judicial setting, allowing an in-depth examination of colonial performance. It provides a nexus for critically linking a court injunction imposing the hegemony of oil with deep struggles for a &#8216;just transition&#8217; from fossil fuels (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Brown &amp; Spiegel, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Le Billon &amp; Kristoffersen, 2019</xref>), valuing life, &#8216;place&#8217; and approaches to solidarity. While fossil fuel extractivism continues to flourish in Canada and globally, exacerbating injustices of settler-colonial violence (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Bosworth, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Simpson, 2019</xref>), my overarching objective here is to further critiques of such violence by paying attention to how colonial legal authority is performed and enacted, but also challenged and contested in the space of the courtroom, courthouse corridors and beyond. I argue for the value of courtroom ethnographies to explore politics around oil and ontologies of caring, learning from land defenders and contrasting spectacles of aggressively imposed (neo)colonial order (and their narrative frames) with different affects and values.</p>