<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0065">In addressing blockades and civil disobedience, emphasis in political geography has been on social dynamics around <italic>zones of extraction</italic> (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Brock &amp; Dunlap, 2018</xref>) and collective <italic>street spaces</italic> as sites of policing, protest and solidarity-building (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Daphi, 2017</xref>). <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Walenta (2020)</xref> argues that, broadly speaking, geography as a field has only very minimally engaged <italic>courtroom ethnography</italic> as a method, despite its considerable potential for interrogating intersections of legal space, political geographies of power and lived experiences. Likewise, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Faria et al. (2019)</xref> call for more attention by geographers to the &#8220;spatial work of power in and through the legal system, connecting everyday legal goings-on and the transscalar structural machinations of state violence.&#8221; Contextualising the political geographies of one particularly symbolic set of court proceedings &#8211; connected to a highly controversial oil pipeline expansion &#8211; provides a way of building upon this. I also extend arguments by <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Simpson (2019)</xref>, who, drawing from Deleuze and Guattari, suggests thinking about the relation between settler colonialism and bitumen as a &#8220;resource desiring machine&#8221;; describing the violence of the Alberta oil/bitumen story, Simpson argues: &#8220;the remaking of bitumen as a resource in the Athabasca region served a purpose even more immediate than capitalist accumulation &#8211; it served to consolidate a nascent settler colonial state's claims to authority over territory.&#8221; This discussion is furthered by <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Schmidt (2020)</xref>, unpacking setter-colonial discourses around bitumen, its political geology and temporality, and its dominance. Increasingly central to all this, I would add, is the ongoing proliferation of colonial court proceedings and contestable logics to quell civil disobedience and Indigenous resistance, involving an elaborate and understudied array of actors, processes and spaces in the use and abuse of court &#8216;injunction&#8217; tools.</p>