<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par4">Considering the case of the European Union, while all large installations are regulated within the EU Emission Trading System (ETS) under an EU-wide cap, the majority of greenhouse gas emissions is tackled under the EU &#8216;effort-sharing&#8217; approach, which consists of individual binding emission reduction targets for Member States. Basically, the EU has implemented the regulatory approach of the Kyoto Protocol&#8212;which included individual emission reduction commitments as well as various emission trading options (flexibility instruments)&#8212;among its Member States<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Initially, the so-called Triptych sectoral approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> differentiated three economic segments: (i) the power sector, (ii) the energy-intensive industry exposed to international trade and (iii) the remaining domestically-oriented sectors, with emission reductions for each calculated by application of different rules (see Supplementary Information section&#160;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> for details). For the domestic sectors, a per capita emission allowance approach was used. Building upon this experience (considered to have successfully contributed to political acceptance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>) the regulatory effort-sharing framework to cover emissions outside the EU ETS was further developed by the Effort Sharing Decision and the Effort Sharing Regulation, adopted in 2009 and 2018, respectively. In terms of the criterion used to set differential national targets, both mainly relied on economic performance, i.e. capability as measured in terms of GDP/capita. In 2021 an overall target of 55% reduction by 2030 compared to 1990 was established<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, but the distribution of that effort among Member States is undecided and under negotiation in 2022.</p>