<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par5">In this work, we present an approach that can contribute to a transparent decision process when partitioning an overall emissions target among subsidiary entities by aligning disparate views and defining an allocation space where different parties could agree to an equitable compromise. It builds upon the categorization of equity principles used in the effort-sharing literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. For negotiation processes heavily influenced by a range of factors, such as historical path dependencies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, side deals, power struggles, different cultures, or domestic politics, such transparency in terms of equity may be a significant factor contributing to success, given the increasing weight of the equity dimension in such negotiations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. We assess the implications of the proposed approach&#8212;in terms of the resulting emissions budget allocation and corresponding reduction targets&#8212;in the context of the European Union (EU) negotiations in 2022 to raise the 2030 effort-sharing target<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. We first explore the implications of different effort-sharing mechanisms and interpretations of equity or justice on a singular, country level, finding that the resulting ranges of possible emissions reduction burden can vary widely. In such a case, if each country were to favor a different equity interpretation, the overall target of the EU in 2030 would most likely remain unmet<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. However, our proposed framework allows for systematically combining different interpretations of equity or justice on the basis of three major principles&#8212;capability, equality, and responsibility&#8212;and allows us to explore situations where country targets are the result of a weighted combination of interpretations of those principles, where member state reductions add up to the overall EU reduction target. In doing so we distinguish interpretations of equity or justice that reflect considerations of equality, capability and responsibility. By identifying weighted combinations of interpretations of these principles that minimize the changes in emission reduction effort required by countries compared to their (i) upper bounds of equity-compatible emissions or, given the practical importance of negotiation history, (ii) previous commitments in the earlier less ambitious effort-sharing agreement, we identify a possible space for decision-making which combines multiple equity interpretations. We find that the possible combinations of equity interpretations, and the strength at which they are applied, result in a wide range of space for decision-making which comprises a richer set of ethical considerations than the 2021 proposed EU approach. We conclude with a discussion of the described framework and its applicability in specific negotiation and policymaking processes, also in other international contexts.</p>