<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">This study, taking place through two academic years (September 2020 to April 2022) in the School of Social Work at Dalhousie University, Halifax, NS, Canada, focuses on the teaching&#8211;learning interaction between the two authors, namely a junior social work faculty member with research expertise in GSW and resilience, and a Master of Social Work (MSW) program student with rich practice specialization in child welfare. During the first academic year (September 2020 to April 2021), both authors featured an instructor-student relationship in an MSW-level required course (online), entitled Social Work Practice Research Methods. During this academic year, the multi-disaster societal background (see the societal context section below) encouraged the instructor to integrate the GSW component into weekly student engagement throughout this course. From September 2021 to April 2022, the two authors&#8217; relationship became a supervisor&#8211;trainee relationship, when the student began engagement in research-based social work field education. As various disasters swiftly unfolded at home and abroad, these supervisor&#8211;trainee interactions continually concentrated on GSW-specific research projects in Canada and internationally. During this virtual field education, the trainee participated in a complete research development cycle for several GSW-specific research projects, including the activities of developing a new research project proposal, data collection and data analysis, drafting academic publications, and conducting related knowledge mobilization activities (e.g., conference presentations, invited talks, and guest presentation in MSW courses). During these two academic years, the two authors communicated through emails and virtual weekly meetings. Both authors&#8217; social work-related expertise and partial demographic information, which inform their critical reflections, are presented in <xref rid="healthcare-10-01245-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>