<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par14">In international climate politics, climate justice is a &#8216;discursive battlefield&#8217; where states define themselves and others (Audet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>: 370). While the concept of climate justice does not exclusively look at states, the main discourses surrounding climate justice in international climate negotiations are rooted in a fundamental truth that developed countries have historically caused the climate change problem, the consequences of climate change on different countries and regions are uneven, and the ability of rich and poor countries to bear the cost of addressing climate change is immensely different (Audet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>; Harris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2013</xref>; Okereke and Coventry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2016</xref>). Despite a wide range of definitions and typologies of global climate justice, questions of fairness and equity in addressing climate change have dominated international climate negotiations for decades. But the perceptions of what constitutes a fair/just way to deal with climate change are often quite different between for instance the EU/the North and developing countries (Okereke and Coventry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2016</xref>; von Lucke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2021</xref>). Contestations for fairness and equity are also entangled with other factors such as economic interests and climate science (Okereke and Coventry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2016</xref>). Shaping the design and evolution of the climate governance regime is largely about addressing the issues regarding &#8216;what to do, who should do it and how, and who would pay for it&#8217; (Dimitrov <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2010</xref>: 800). States socially construct global climate justice through debating what global climate justice entails and how it can be achieved in solving these key issues. Within this social construction process of global climate justice, states communicate themselves to each other and define their identities.</p>