<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><?QA-only?><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clim Action</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Climate Action</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2731-3263</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9461415</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">22</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s44168-022-00022-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sustainability and social transformation: the role of ecovillages in confluence with the <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led alternatives</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5056-2114</contrib-id><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>Renata Amorim Almeida</given-names></name><address><email>renata.a.a.fonseca@ufrj.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2677-818X</contrib-id><name><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>Marta de Azevedo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9679-9157</contrib-id><name><surname>Nasri</surname><given-names>Yasmin Xavier Guimar&#x000e3;es</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9075-5180</contrib-id><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>Graciella Faico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8536.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2294 473X</institution-id><institution>Postgraduate Program on Community Psychosociology and Social Ecology (PPG EICOS), Institute of Psychology (IP), </institution><institution>Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), </institution></institution-wrap>Av. Pasteur, 250, Pavilh&#x000e3;o Milton Campos, Praia Vermelha, Rio de Janeiro, RJ CEP 22290-240 Brazil </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>23</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Amidst the uncertainties of a climate emergency scenario, sustainable and counter-hegemonic alternatives of social and productive organization are being developed by several grassroots local communities. Thus, this essay aims to critically discuss the role of ecovillages within the <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led alternatives, understood as a plural set of socially and environmentally transformative possibilities. Adopting a decolonial perspective, this study was carried out through an exploratory qualitative approach, based on a bibliographic and documentary survey. According to the adopted premises, it is possible to recognize that communal territorial innovations, as illustrated by ecovillages&#x02019; practices, may expand the horizon of solutions to face contemporary multiple crises. In line with the Paris Agreement and the 2030 Agenda, confluences between diverse community-led alternatives can contribute to deconstruct rooted development premises and to potentialize climate actions toward a just and sustainable transition, in tune with the triune dimensions of cultural identity, social equity, and ecological sustainability of the <italic>Buen Vivir</italic> communal ethics.</p><sec><title>Graphical abstract</title><p id="Par2">
<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="44168_2022_22_Figa_HTML" id="MO1"/></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Sustainability</kwd><kwd>Ecovillages</kwd><kwd>Pluriverse</kwd><kwd>Buen Vivir</kwd><kwd>2030 Agenda</kwd><kwd>Climate emergency</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2022</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">On a global scale, diverse peoples and communities have been facing numerous pressures arising from the development geopolitics, as illustrated by the Covid-19 pandemic reality. As a strategy of resistance and (re)existence, many counter-hegemonic production and social organizations are being built within the <italic>pluriverse</italic>, which is understood as a wide range of social and environmental transformative possibilities, involving a pluralism of concepts, cosmovisions, and practices in tune with the principles of social and ecological justice. <italic>Pluriversal</italic> community-led alternatives are engaged in the construction of &#x0201c;a world where other worlds fit,&#x0201d; according to Zapatista&#x02019;s principles, in contrast to the ethnocentrism and universalism propagated by Western and modern worldviews (Illich <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1973</xref>; Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>; De la Cadena and Blaser <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2018</xref>; Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">Connected to their own lifestyles, territorialities, cultures, and social struggles, the confrontation of countless daily challenges, especially by the marginalized minoritarian<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1">1</xref> social groups (Porto Gon&#x000e7;alves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2002</xref>; Haesbaert <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2007</xref>; Kothari <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2021</xref>), is generating learning opportunities about resilience and hope that contribute to rethinking the complex scenario of the ongoing transformations, also regarding climate change. Addressing contemporary complexities, inspiring systemic alternatives are being created to face economic, ecological, social, cultural, and ethical-political structural problems (Dilger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2016</xref>; Sol&#x000f3;n et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2019</xref>; Norberg-Hodge <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2019</xref>; Kothari <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2021</xref>). Besides, by being developed within the framework of capitalism itself, these grassroots innovations can thus be understood as &#x0201c;interstitial&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;prefigurative&#x0201d; of a postcapitalist society (Monticelli <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par5">Joining the emergent set of civil society regenerative and localized solutions (Wahl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2019</xref>; Norberg-Hodge <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2019</xref>), the ecovillage movement proposes a feasible whole system design toward sustainable ways of living (Global Ecovillage Network &#x02013; GEN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>). Meanwhile embodying potential pathways to promote greater connection with oneself, with others, and with nature itself, ecovillages are being recognized for prefiguring small-scale transition possibilities toward a resilient, equitable, and ecological society (Trainer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2000</xref>). Therefore, grassroots initiatives are increasingly receiving attention from the international scientific community, although they are still being neglected by public policies to address such objectives (Roysen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par6">Ecovillages are configured through autonomous, local, and direct participatory processes, aiming to integrate several dimensions of sustainability (including the ecological, economic, social, cultural) (Gaia Education <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2005</xref>). But to achieve environmental bioregional regeneration purposes depends also on attempting to the diverse sociocultural and historical backgrounds involved in local dynamics (Dawson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2006</xref>; Liftin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2014</xref>; Mattos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2018</xref>; Roysen and Mertens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2019</xref>; Wahl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par7">Emerging from the &#x0201c;Global North,&#x0201d; as intentional communities guided by sustainability principles, nowadays, ecovillages have acquired new contours with the movement&#x02019;s transposition to the &#x0201c;Global South,&#x0201d; influenced by traditional communities&#x02019;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref> values and ways of living, intrinsically connected to nature&#x02019;s vital cycles. So, as they are currently spread over all continents and interlinked through the Global Ecovillage Network (GEN), it is important to scrutinize the development geopolitics and the &#x0201c;north-south&#x0201d; relations (Santos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2007</xref>) permeating ecovillages&#x02019; approaches (Fotopoulos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2000</xref>; Silva <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2014</xref>).</p><p id="Par8">In this context, reflecting on the interconnections between the socio-economic inequalities<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn3">3</xref> and the ecological and climatic collapses, as results of the colonial exploitative socio-historic process, this essay aims to critically discuss the role of ecovillages within the <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led alternatives, facing the climate emergency on the horizon of the 2030 Agenda. Based on a Latin American decolonial perspective (Quijano <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2000</xref>; Castro-G&#x000f3;mez and Grosfoguel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2007</xref>), recognizing the coloniality of power that is still being deeply perpetuated by western cultural values, this essay seeks to break through the dominant discourses and to open possibilities for other references, ontologies, and epistemologies beyond the Eurocentric ones. For that, it was inspired by the <italic>Buen Vivir</italic> paradigm (Acosta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>; Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2010</xref>; Gudynas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>), based on the Kichwa term <italic>sumak kawsay</italic> and the Aymara <italic>suma qama&#x000f1;a</italic>, which is one of the alternatives to modern development brought forward by <italic>pluriverse</italic> literature (Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>;&#x000a0;Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>; Lang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par9">From this perspective, the essay is structured in three sections, in addition to this introduction. The first one proposes a brief discussion about the ecovillages as a global movement and the development notion itself. In the second one, transition horizons are discussed from a post-development and intercultural perspective, focusing on ecovillages&#x02019; social meanings and practices in relation to systemic alternatives principles of the <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led initiatives. A synthesis of this reflection, constitutes the last third section.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Ecovillages as a global movement and the development paradigm at stake</title><p id="Par10">As briefly introduced, amidst contemporary social and environmental complex challenges, civil society itself is developing innovative solutions aiming to achieve sustainable livelihoods. Among this <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led alternatives, there are human settlements known as ecovillages and described as &#x0201c;niches of grassroots innovation&#x0201d; (Roysen and Mertens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2019</xref>; Boyer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2015</xref>), as well as &#x0201c;demonstrative centers in sustainable practices&#x0201d; (Salazar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2013</xref>), or even as &#x0201c;alternative development paradigm&#x0201d; (Veteto and Lockyer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2008</xref>). The emergence of these communities in the &#x0201c;Global North&#x0201d; is inspired by the counterculture movements of the 1960s/1970s as alternative ways of living in moments of crisis, gathering those&#x000a0;people who did not identify with the dominant ways of thinking-being (Dawson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2013</xref>; Silva <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2014</xref>; Santos-J&#x000fa;nior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2016</xref>; Roysen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par11">But since its origins, in the 1990s&#x000a0;(Gilman and Gilman, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1991</xref>), the ecovillage concept has undergone important redefinitions, especially in recent years, when traditional communities and their perspectives were encompassed by the proposal. Nowadays, ecovillage is institutionally defined by the Global Ecovillage Network as &#x0201c;intentional, traditional, or urban community that is consciously designed through locally owned participatory processes in all four dimensions of sustainability (social, culture, ecology, and economy) to regenerate social and natural environments&#x0201d; (Global Ecovillage Network &#x02013; GEN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par12">So, the ecovillages&#x02019; movement encompasses heterogeneous projects, developed by a plurality of social groups expressing different subjectivities concerning community and nature. According to Dawson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2006</xref>), on the margins of capitalism, ecovillages, in general, aim to rescue ancestral values and local practices threatened by modernity, while at the core of the capitalist society, they stand out due to their pursuit of lifestyle changes, human values rescue, reconnection with nature, and, above all, with each other. Joubert and Alfred (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2007</xref>) reaffirm this perspective, emphasizing the communal ties reconstruction as a central aspect for mitigating environmental impacts on ecovillages in the &#x0201c;Global North.&#x0201d; In turn, ecovillages in the &#x0201c;Global South,&#x0201d; according to these authors, seek improvements in life conditions based on solidary relationships and on the sense of belonging to nature, experienced not as a resource but, actually, as a living organism that represents the mother of the all-embracing interconnected community from whom everyone depends.</p><p id="Par13">Whereas neoliberal capitalism advances, in the context of globalization, socio-environmental problems are amplified, with social inequalities and environmental degradation worsening worldwide, and the ecovillages&#x02019; movement emerges in response. While a &#x0201c;North in the South&#x0201d; is configured by a reduced number of privileged people, and a &#x0201c;South in the North&#x0201d; is constituted by a growing marginalized contingent, the current levels of socioeconomic inequality are close to those registered at the beginning of the twentieth century, at the height of Western imperialism, with the richest 10% holding 78% of global wealth and half of the population holding only 2% of it, as reported by <italic>The World Inequality Report 2022</italic> (Chancel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2022</xref>). According to this source, the overcoming of twenty-first century challenges, including the climate emergency and the massive biodiversity loss, will not be possible without addressing such socioeconomic inequality levels. The <italic>Global Risk Perception Survey</italic> published this year by the World Economic Forum (World Economic Forum - WEF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2022</xref>) also emphasizes global inequalities and polarization, threats to livelihoods, and mental health deterioration as the main challenges in the short term, while it refers to failures in climate actions and noncompliance with the Paris Agreement (United Nations &#x02013; UN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2015</xref>) as the greatest long-term global threats.</p><p id="Par14">Thus, on the intersectionality of the convergent <italic>polycrisis</italic> (Morin and Kern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">1999</xref>) &#x02014; ecological, climatic, economic, social, ethical, political, psychological, and so on &#x02014; the limitations of the hegemonic societal model to address such complexity are revealed. Therefore, the search for alternatives to face these interconnected challenges deserves broader analytical scrutiny from multiple angles and perspectives over the usual power devices and the meaning of development itself. As argued by post-development scholars, like Escobar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1995</xref>) and Sachs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1992</xref>), development, as we know it, is unjust, never worked, and at this point has clearly failed.</p><p id="Par15">Regarding the &#x0201c;top-down&#x0201d; approaches to the ongoing debate on the 2030 Agenda (United Nations &#x02013; UN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2015</xref>), a global action plan for people, planet, prosperity, and peacebuilding, it still focuses on the ecological, economic, and social tripod of the polysemic notion of sustainability (Irving and Oliveira <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2012</xref>; Irving <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2014</xref>). Otherwise, the additional fourth &#x0201c;hidden&#x0201d; and subjective dimension of culture is also considered fundamental in &#x0201c;bottom-up&#x0201d; perspectives from community-led initiatives at the local level of ecovillages (Liftin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2014</xref>). Embodying human values and worldviews that reflect more sustainable lifestyles, ecovillages can contribute to reducing negative environmental impacts and producing positive ones as indicated by several studies (Daly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>; Sherry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2019</xref>; Roysen and Mertens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2019</xref>; Roysen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2021</xref>), including the environmental impact assessment conducted by the Global Ecovillage Network (Global Ecovillage Network -&#x000a0;GEN,&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2022</xref>). Thus, they can contribute to promoting regenerative paradigm shifts concerning the capitalist production and consumption model, disseminated under the aegis of development.</p><p id="Par16">Dawson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2013</xref>) emphasizes the resumption of self-management over common goods and the cultural and economic renewal with respect to the Earth&#x02019;s vital cycles as the guiding premises of community-led practices in ecovillages. The author also stresses that both intentional and traditional communities criticize the current development paradigm, which links economic growth to well-being. As mentioned by Liftin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2014</xref>, p.190), &#x0201c;these communities have been creating parallel structures for self-government within the prevailing social order while demonstrating how to live well with less.&#x0201d; For some traditional communities, becoming an ecovillage also means claiming spiritual and cultural integrity as well as safeguarding respect for communal tradition and self-determination threatened by colonization and modernization (Dawson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2006</xref>; Simas&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2013</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">Although feasible solutions and politics for a just and sustainable transition to a low-carbon society can be inspired by the heterogeneous grassroots innovations of ecovillages &#x02014; as signalized by the image of the Findhorn Ecovillage featuring the cover of the Third Part of the Sixth Assessment Report of the International Panel for Climate Change (Mitigation of Climate Change ) (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change - IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2022b</xref>) &#x02014; it is still important to consider the political ideology concerning cultural values on the ecovillages&#x02019; approaches. This is because the alignment of some contesting initiatives with the current dominant societal frameworks, which do not seek the structural transformation of society (such as the economic or political-institutional order), can represent a &#x0201c;functional adaptation&#x0201d; to the capitalist game rules (Silva <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2014</xref>). Under the aegis of capital, the leading role of counterculture movements can be co-opted by the market logic, interpreted in many situations as the only and inevitable pathway to solve development problems, including socio-environmental issues. Thus, the oppositional trait of counterculture movements can be lost by becoming innocuous for the needed social transformation and, also, convenient with other &#x0201c;sustainabilities&#x0201d;: those of the capital and the <italic>status quo</italic> (Leff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2006</xref>; Silva <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2014</xref>).</p><p id="Par18">Therefore, due to frustrations with the unfulfilled development well-being promises, in the current challenging times, new possibilities are open to alternative ethical-political projects, based on more inclusive and diverse proposals (Hidalgo-Capit&#x000e1;n et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2019</xref>; De la Cadena and Blaser <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2018</xref>). In different sociocultural contexts from those that originated the ecovillage movement, in Latin America, for example, ecovillages have been increasingly associated with ancestral cosmogonies of the Andean and Amazonian regions and the biocentric societal paradigm of <italic>Buen Vivir</italic>, connected to the recognition of the rights of nature as a living being (Acosta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>; Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2010</xref>; L&#x000f3;pez and Prada <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2015</xref>; Chaves et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2017</xref>; Gudynas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2019</xref>; Mu&#x000f1;oz-Villarreal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2018</xref>). The commitment of the ecovillage movement to community-led alternatives based on different worldviews and horizontal relationships, in this way, tends to strengthen their countercultural nature, enabling emancipatory organizations and new productive arrangements and territorialities to emerge (Silva <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2014</xref>).</p><p id="Par19">Meanwhile, in the Brazilian context, for instance, as highlighted by Dias et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2017</xref>), most communities interlinked to the ecovillage movement, resemble those of the &#x0201c;Global North,&#x0201d; and composed of privileged social groups with a homogenous profile, which is mainly middle or upper middle class, ethnically &#x0201c;white,&#x0201d; with higher education levels. Despite the frequently expressed interest in diversity, &#x0201c;apparently, there is no significant link between traditional communities and the ecovillage movement in Brazil, although it is possible to consider them &#x02018;entities&#x02019; that are alike in many aspects&#x0201d; (Dias et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2017</xref>, p. 83). Maybe this shows that, in some ways, there is room for future agencies and straightening relationships between ecovillages and other grassroots community-led alternatives in the &#x0201c;Global South&#x0201d; at the local and regional levels, as illustrated by the confluence between the Instituto Biorregional do Cerrado (IBC), an Ecovillage and Permaculture Center, and the largest Quilombola<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn4">4</xref> territory in Brazil called Kalunga. Both are located in a Brazilian rural area in the Cerrado<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn5">5</xref> biome, a biodiversity world hotspot endangered by the advance of the agribusiness frontier for large-scale monoculture commodities production (mostly soybean and corn) and are together engaging in the local political struggles in the decision-making arena, resisting along 20 years, against the construction of a hydroelectric power plant in the traditional territory (Roysen and Schwab <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Transition horizons: post-development, interculturality, and the confluence within the <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led alternatives</title><p id="Par20">Based on the previous discussion, whereas different social groups face socio-environmental collapses and the convergence of multiple crises in the frontline of their territories, they also promote propositive movements and innovative political practices of collectivization and localization, germinating transformative alternatives.</p><p id="Par21">Looking into ecovillages as laboratories of innovations and social technologies for sustainability, developing and testing solutions adaptable to each territorial context at the microscale of the communities open up a range of new possibilities that may be appropriated by the broader debate on building more sustainable futures (Seyfang and Smith <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2007</xref>; Norberg-Hodge <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2019</xref>; Roysen and Schwab <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2021</xref>). On the other hand, several indigenous, black peoples, rural smallholders, and other local communities are working toward autonomy and self-determination, solidary economy, and reclaiming human, territorial, and nature rights. Along with sustainable food production through agroecology and agroforest restorative practices, rural development based on sociobiodiversity conservation and decentralized governance for economic democracy, they are leading innovations in several fields, also inspiring sustainable transition horizons (Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>; Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>; Kothari <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2021</xref>; Ferreira and Fel&#x000ed;cio <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2021</xref>; Lang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par22">By developing feasible solutions to many of the contemporary challenges, this <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led alternatives should deserve greater attention from public policies, especially the redistributive ones, at a time when humanity is facing the risk of an average global temperature increase of 2.7 &#x000b0;C by the end of this century (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change - IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2021</xref>). In this sense, as a &#x0201c;red alert for humanity,&#x0201d; the first part of the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (The Physical Science Basis) (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change - IPCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2021</xref>) emphasizes that a radical civilizational transformation is needed in this decade to avoid unpredictable changes, in the case of an average increase in temperature greater than 1.5 &#x000b0;C. However, even if the carbon emission neutrality and the net-zero goals of the Paris Agreement are achieved, according to the same report, this increase is most likely to reach 2.2 &#x000b0;C, which further reinforces the need for transformative transitions to radical systemic changes.</p><p id="Par23">Furthermore, to face the panorama of uncertainties regarding climate change adaptation (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change - IPCC&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2022a</xref>)&#x000a0;and mitigation&#x000a0;strategies&#x000a0;(Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change - IPCC&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2022b</xref>), as well as for targeting the 17 SDGs of the 2030 Agenda (even considering the contradictions of this global agreement), it seems essential to strengthen and expand the bonds of collaboration with&#x000a0;those social actors that are regenerating life conditions based on communal micropolitics. But even though the role of civil society is crucial for resilience and territorial autonomy, from a post-development perspective (Sachs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1992</xref>; Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1995</xref>), broader alliances with governments and other decision-makers are determinants to address climate justice, eradicate poverty, and restore the natural environment, safeguarding human and planetary needs.</p><p id="Par24">In order to achieve these transformations, for instance, ancestral knowledge and principles of conviviality (Illich <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1973</xref>), like <italic>Buen Vivir</italic> (Acosta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>; Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2010</xref>; Gudynas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>), can confluate with selective modern dimensions or institutions &#x0201c;in a self-determined way,&#x0201d; as shown by Lang (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2022</xref>) in a study conducted with the Kayambi Kichwa people around their engagement in municipality politics in the northern Ecuadorian Andes. In this way, bringing theory into practice implies reducing the gap between the abstract and ambiguous concepts of sustainability and the concrete transformations that are being undertaken at the territorial level. For that, a real predisposition to an intercultural dialogue of knowledge and practices is fundamental, which implies tensions, conflicts, and pacts based on ethical relationships of respect for differences (Leff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2006</xref>; Santos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2007</xref>; Cusicanqui <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2018</xref>; Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2009</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">It is also important to stress that the lack of openness to the other&#x02019;s knowledge can hinder potential dialogues even between the social movements themselves, as well as between the ecovillage movements and other counter-hegemonic community-led alternatives, such as those led by the landless rural workers, indigenous peoples, or connected to urban and agrarian land reforms, for example. In this sense, agencies and network collaboration based on territorial articulations tend to be of great value, especially if accompanied by an ethical-political perspective committed to a new sustainable order (Porto-Gon&#x000e7;alves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2002</xref>; Haesbaert <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2007</xref>; Silva <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2014</xref>). According to Leff (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2006</xref>, p. 232), &#x0201c;such transformation processes will imply the encounter of multiple rationalities, something much more complex and complicated, but more viable as a sustainability strategy than what dictates the market.&#x0201d;</p><p id="Par26">Understood as an ideology and social vision intrinsic to the ideals of modernization, development holds western economic structure and society as a universal model for others to inevitably follow and emulate (Sachs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1992</xref>). Like a &#x0201c;ruin in the intellectual landscape,&#x0201d; as highlighted by the leading post-development scholar Wolfgang Sachs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1992</xref>), it is time to &#x0201c;dismantle this mental structure.&#x0201d; So, to decolonize the imaginaries from development concepts, post-development theorists promote more plural ideas about well-being based on interculturality (Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2009</xref>). Instead of an unsustainable and also ineffective model of industrialization (due to their ignorance of the local, cultural, and historical contexts of the peoples to which they are applied), cross-cultural dialogues and interactions move beyond a passive acceptance of the multiple coexisting cultures to promote a set of relations grounded in values of mutual respect between indigenous and western ideals (Lang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">To illustrate and push forward this debate on the possible confluences<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn6">6</xref> within the <italic>pluriverse</italic> of the community-led alternatives, as horizon solutions for a just and sustainable transition, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> didactically articulates the dimensions of sustainability, social meanings and practices in ecovillages, and the guiding principles of systemic alternatives, based on a post-development and intercultural perspective of analysis.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Synthesis matrix to articulate sustainability dimensions, social meanings and practices in ecovillages, and the guiding principles of systemic alternatives. Source: developed by the authors based on Roysen et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2021</xref>) and Kothari (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2021</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="44168_2022_22_Fig1_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">Reflecting on the social meanings and practices in ecovillages, connected to the sustainability dimensions, it is possible to recognize that they align with systemic alternative principles in many ways, regarding the economic, ecological, social, cultural, and ethical-political aspects. This is because the <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led alternatives engages in an important variety of projects and actions connected to the commitments of ecological integrity, social equity and justice, meaningful participation, collective responsibility, cultural diversity recognition, and solidarity values (Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>; Roysen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2021</xref>; Kothari <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2021</xref>; Sol&#x000f3;n et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par29">Some of these processes concern subsistence economies and local commerce, alternative health practices, oral and hands-on learning, and other practices, mostly considered outdated or &#x0201c;primitive&#x0201d; nowadays by the modern-development mindset. Otherwise, from a post-development and intercultural perspective, based on the <italic>Buen Vivir</italic> paradigm, within which nature and society are inseparable and the utmost respect for <italic>Pachamama</italic> (Mother Nature) is required, they reveal that human well-being and intergenerational sustainability can be achieved without endangering Earth&#x02019;s biodiversity, including ourselves.</p><p id="Par30">This resignification of well-being itself, not as a result of increasing material accumulation but as a way to safely meet livelihood needs, access satisfying learning and working opportunities, and share good social relationships, without generating ecological degradation and social exclusion, leads to profound cultural values review, regarding the relationships with oneself, the others, and the whole nature. This does not imply an unconditional acceptance of traditions or &#x0201c;a return to the past&#x0201d; but a recognition of the creative potential which results from mixing traditions and innovations linked through values that inspire better forms of conviviality (Illich <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1973</xref>). On these bases, as extensively discussed by De la Cadena and Blaser (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2018</xref>), Kothari, Escobar, and several authors (Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>), rooted in ethical principles of interconnectedness and nurtured by the rich global biocultural heritage, different life territories integrate a <italic>pluriverse</italic> of possibilities based on territorial autonomies and in arrangements among local economies, configuring a &#x0201c;global tapestry of alternatives&#x0201d; (Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>) to ailing contemporaneous lifestyles.</p><p id="Par31">In this debate, it is fundamental to recognize the contribution of the daily life struggles of vulnerable social groups mobilized by environmental justice and land rights to reconfiguring the geopolitics of knowledge. By challenging the abstract theories of the dominant Eurocentric episteme divorced from territorial realities, they turn these &#x0201c;living utopias&#x0201d; possible to emerge, questioning and refusing the colonial, racist, patriarchal, and anthropocentric premises, intrinsic to modern hegemonic social meanings and practices underlying current power structures (Dilger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2016</xref>; Dinerstein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2017</xref>; Quijano <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2000</xref>; Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2010</xref>; Ferreira and Fel&#x000ed;cio <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par32">Therefore, overcoming conventional sustainability perspectives implies the recognition of other worldviews and environmental rationalities (Leff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2006</xref>), diverse in the ways of being-knowing-living. While instrumental narratives based on a fragmented and disenchanted worldview lead to the present scenario of uncertainties, plural narratives can contribute to re-enchantment, &#x0201c;suspending the sky&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;postponing the end of the world&#x0201d; (Krenak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2019</xref>). Consequently, shedding light on the <italic>pluriverse</italic> might inspire hope and expand horizons for regenerative possibilities toward desirable futures. Nature-based solutions to face climate change and biodiversity loss, thus, require narratives that transcend the disjunctive and reductionist thinking and binary splits between nature and culture, like <italic>Buen Vivir</italic>. From a systemic perspective, climate actions should result from a deep process of sociocultural transformations, presupposing the overcoming of the coloniality intrinsic to the materialist and accumulative logic (Quijano <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2000</xref>).</p><p id="Par33">From this analytical perspective, post-development proposals from the &#x0201c;Global North,&#x0201d; such as deep ecology, degrowth, and ecofeminism (Beling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2019</xref>;&#x000a0;Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>), seem to converge with the Epistemologies of the South (Santos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2007</xref>). Therefore, some of the results from the industrialization process and technological development (such as information and communication technologies) can contribute forward to the emergence of plural transition horizons, converging on complementary relations in a synthesis between &#x0201c;organic and synthetic knowledge&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn7">7</xref> (Santos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>).</p><p id="Par34">As a post-development (re)existence strategy, built in the confluence of indigenous cosmovisions and the critical thinking against extractivism, through the dispossession of territories in Latin America (Svampa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2019</xref>), for instance, <italic>Buen Vivir</italic> is becoming an emergent platform for new socio-political and environmental praxis (Acosta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>; Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2010</xref>; Gudynas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2019</xref>; Lang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2022</xref>). In this sense, as an inspiring &#x0201c;North-South&#x0201d; confluence, ecovillages can represent a translocal empowerment strategy through which the meanings of &#x0201c;good coexistence&#x0201d; can recreate living worlds, in tune with the triune dimensions of cultural identity, social equity, and ecological sustainability of the <italic>Buen Vivir</italic> communal ethics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Concluding remarks</title><p id="Par35">A context of multiple crises arises from sociohistorical processes concerning the current development model. For this reason, the ethical-political debate on post-development scrutinizes the notion of development itself, inspired by territorialized and community-led alternatives that can promote more sustainable, resilient, and equitable ways of being-knowing. Although diverse in socio-environmental practices and meanings, the <italic>pluriverse</italic> of community-led alternatives is oriented by premises that rely on safeguarding the &#x0201c;commons&#x0201d; governance based on the recognition of the profound ties of interdependence between humans and nonhumans, which transcend the modern utilitarian rationality of the capitalist, colonial, patriarchal, and anthropocentric world-system view (Porto-Gon&#x000e7;alves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2002</xref>; Escobar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>; Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>; Lang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par36">In this regard, by experiencing sensitive pathways to respectfully inhabit the planet, ecovillages can be understood as &#x0201c;living laboratories&#x0201d; (Santos-J&#x000fa;nior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2016</xref>; Mattos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2018</xref>) where the integration of the various areas of human life (education, health, economy, construction, agriculture, energy, management, politics, etc.) is often conceptualized around four interconnected dimensions: ecological, social, economic, and cultural/spiritual (Gaia Education <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2005</xref>). Nevertheless, it is essential to understand ecovillages as a process in which collective learning can be continuously (re)constructed, and not as a pre-formatted small-scale model of society. Primordial learning from these experiences, for instance, relies on ethical-political principles guided by diverse epistemological and ontological basis. This is because broader and inclusive cross-cultural alliances with diverse and marginalized social groups, together with the empirical knowledge and innovations interconnected to Earth&#x02019;s life cycles, can contribute to expanding transition horizons for resistance and (re)existence, facing the complex contemporary challenges.</p><p id="Par37">Therefore, in contrast to current catastrophic projections, resulting from the unlimited and unidirectional progress beliefs, richer subjectivities emerging from these community-led confluences help to decolonize imaginaries and deconstruct rooted development premises, expanding the fields of possibilities for desirable futures and inspiring public policies, from the very basis of society, to address the Paris Agreement and the 2030 Agenda commitments. Rather than becoming a radically opposing ideology, the <italic>Buen Vivir</italic> approach in these cases provides opportunities to meet the core aims of sustainable development through the <italic>pluriverse</italic>, as possible alternatives that go beyond the conventional anthropocentric development model.</p><p id="Par38">Whereas there is now an impetus toward alternatives to face the countless ongoing uncertainties and predicted collapses &#x02014; materialized by the tragic context of the Covid-19 pandemic, the climate emergency, and the geopolitical insecurities &#x02014; it is essential to deploy &#x0201c;colorful parachutes&#x0201d; (Krenak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2019</xref>) and to be open to the inventive capacity of the Earth&#x02019;s intertwined living intelligences.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="Fn1"><label>1</label><p id="Par41">Minoritarian social groups do not refer to an amount but to the discrimination suffered by some social groups such as indigenous, native, women and poorer people due to racial, socioeconomic, cultural, or gender issues, highlighting their insufficient representativeness in power spaces.</p></fn><fn id="Fn2"><label>2</label><p id="Par42">Different connotations and definitions regard traditional communities. In the Brazilian legislation, they are conceived as &#x0201c;culturally diverse groups that recognize themselves as such, that have their own forms of social organization, that occupy and use territories and natural resources as a condition for their cultural, social, religious, ancestral, and economic reproduction, using knowledge, innovations, and practices generated and transmitted by tradition&#x0201d; (Brasil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2007</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="Fn3"><label>3</label><p id="Par43">Between the privileged and the marginalized by the capitalist system</p></fn><fn id="Fn4"><label>4</label><p id="Par44">Traditional, legally recognized, Afro-descent self-sufficient communities that were created in hidden remote rural areas by ancestors escaping from slavery, most of them with some help of native indigenous people, whose both ancestral lifestyles are closely connected to their environments (Brasil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2007</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="Fn5"><label>5</label><p id="Par45">Cerrado is the second largest biome of the South American continent, considered the world&#x02019;s most biodiverse savanna. Known as &#x0201c;the cradle of the waters&#x0201d; in Central Brazil, it &#x0201c;gives birth&#x0201d; to two-thirds of the hydrographic basins in the Brazilian territory (Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estat&#x000ed;stica &#x02013; IBGE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2007</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="Fn6"><label>6</label><p id="Par46">Confluence is designed as &#x0201c;possible connections for strengthening trajectories, a lesson learned from the waters as they expand their courses in flow and power when they meet&#x0201d; by Ant&#x000f4;nio Bispo dos Santos, a Brazilian intellectual of a Quilombola traditional community (Santos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>). The environmental sociologist Ashish Kothari also adopts the term in a similar sense, in the context of the &#x0201c;Global Tapestry of Alternatives&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Radical Ecological Democracy&#x0201d; networks (Kothari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="Fn7"><label>7</label><p id="Par47">According to Santos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>, p. 101), &#x0201c;there is an organic knowledge and a synthetic knowledge. While organic knowledge develops being, synthetic knowledge develops owning. We are operators of organic knowledge and colonialists are operators of the synthetic.&#x0201d;</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was financed in part by the Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior &#x02014; Brasil (CAPES) &#x02014; Finance Code 001, by the Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico &#x02014; Brasil (CNPq), and the &#x0201c;Sustainability and Social Transformation: Towards the 2030 Agenda Project,&#x0201d; Internationalization Program (CAPES/PrInt/UFRJ).</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Code availability</title><p id="Par39">Not applicable</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>The authors wrote, read, revised and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>Not applicable</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par40">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>El buen vivir en el camino del postdesarrollo: una lectura desde la Constituci&#x000f3;n de Montecristi</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Quito</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Friedrich Ebert Stiftung</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sinergias Sur-Norte para una &#x0201c;transici&#x000f3;n civilizatoria&#x0201d; hacia la sustentabilidad: di&#x000e1;logos de saberes entre buen vivir, decrecimiento, y desarrollo humano</article-title><source>Rev Colomb Sociol</source><year>2019</year><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15446/rcs.v42n2.73250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grassroots innovation for urban sustainability: comparing the diffusion pathways of three ecovillage projects</article-title><source>Environ Plan A Econ Space</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1068/a140250p</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brasil (2007). Decreto n&#x000b0; 6.040, de 7 de fevereiro de 2007. Pol&#x000ed;tica Nacional de Desenvolvimento Sustent&#x000e1;vel dos Povos e Comunidades Tradicionais.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castro-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosfoguel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>El giro decolonial: reflexiones para una diversidad epist&#x000e9;mica m&#x000e1;s all&#x000e1; del capitalismo global</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Bogot&#x000e1;</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Siglo del Hombre Editores; Universidad Central, Instituto de Estudios Sociales Contempor&#x000e1;neos y Pontificia Universidad Javeriana, Instituto Pensar</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chancel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Piketty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zucman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>World Inequality Report 2022</source><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chaves M, Macintyre T, Verschoor G, Wals A (2017) Radical ruralities in practice: negotiating buen vivir in a Colombian network of sustainability. J Rural Stud 58:153&#x02013;162</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cusicanqui</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Un mundo ch&#x02019;ixi es posible: ensayos desde un presente en crisis</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Buenos Aires</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Tinta Lim&#x000f3;n</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying the environmental impact of ecovillages and cohousing communities: a systematic literature review</article-title><source>Local Environ</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13549839.2017.1348342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ecovillages: new frontiers for sustainability</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Green Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lockyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Veteto</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From islands to networks: the history and future of the ecovillage movement</article-title><source>Environmental anthropology engaging ecotopia: bioregionalism, permaculture, ecovillage</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De la Cadena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>De la Cadena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pluriverse. Proposals for a world of many worlds</article-title><source>A world of many worlds</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Durham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Loureiro</surname><given-names>CFB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevitarese</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>CDME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The meaning and relevance of ecovillages for the construction of sustainable societal alternatives</article-title><source>Ambiente Soc</source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1809-4422asoc0083v2032017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dilger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira Filho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Descolonizar o imagin&#x000e1;rio: debates sobre p&#x000f3;s-extrativismo e alternativas ao desenvolvimento</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Rosa Luxemburgo</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dinerstein</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Concrete utopia: (re)producing life in, against and beyond the open veins of capital</source><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Encountering development: the making and unmaking of the Third World</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Escobar A (2018) Designs for the pluriverse: radical interdependence, autonomy, and the making of worlds (New Ecologies for the Twenty-First Century). Duke University Press, Durham</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fel&#x000ed;cio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Por terra e territ&#x000f3;rio: caminhos da revolu&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o dos povos no Brasil</source><year>2021</year><publisher-loc>Arataca</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Teia dos Povos</publisher-name><fpage>439</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fotopoulos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The limitations of life-style strategies: the Ecovillage &#x02018;Movement&#x02019; is NOT the Way Towards a New Democratic Society</article-title><source>Democ Nat</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>308</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gaia Education (2005) EDE: ecovillage design education, 3th edn. Global Ecovillage Network,&#x000a0;Findhorn</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ecovillages and sustainable communities. A report for Gaia Trust by Context Institute</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>Bainbridge Island</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Context Institute</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Global Ecovillage Network &#x02013; GEN. (2020). The ecovillage map of regeneration. Retrieved on 23 May 2022, in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gen.ecovillage.org/projects/map-of-regenaration/">http://gen.ecovillage.org/projects/map-of-regenaration/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Global Ecovillage Network &#x02013; GEN (2022). GEN Website. Retrieved on 23 May 2022, in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gen.ecovillage.org/">http://gen.ecovillage.org/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gudynas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Buen vivir: Germinando alternativas al desarrollo. Am&#x000e9;rica Latina em Movimento - ALAI, n&#x000b0; 462</source><year>2011</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gudynas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Direitos da natureza: &#x000e9;tica bioc&#x000ea;ntrica e pol&#x000ed;ticas ambientais</source><year>2019</year><edition>1</edition><publisher-loc>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Editora Elefante</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haesbaert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Territ&#x000f3;rio e multiterritorialidade: um debate</article-title><source>GEOgraphia</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hidalgo-Capit&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubillo-Guevara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina Carranco</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Los Objetivos del Buen Vivir Una propuesta alternativa a los Objetivos de Desarrollo Sostenible</article-title><source>Iberoamerican J Dev Stud</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Illich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><source>Tools for conviviality</source><year>1973</year><publisher-loc>New York, Evanston, San Francisco, London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harper &#x00026; Row</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estat&#x000ed;stica &#x02013; IBGE</collab></person-group><source>Invent&#x000e1;rios da Biodiversidade do Bioma Cerrado: Biogeografia de Plantas</source><year>2007</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change - IPCC (2021) Summary for policymakers. In: Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis. Cambridge University Press,&#x000a0;Cambridge</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change - IPCC (2022a) Summary for policymakers. In: Climate Change 2022: Impacts, Adaptation and Vulnerability. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change - IPCC (2022b) Summary for policymakers. In: Climate Change 2022: Mitigation of Climate Change. Cambridge University Press,&#x000a0;Cambridge</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustentabilidade e o futuro que n&#x000e3;o queremos: polissemias, controv&#x000e9;rsias e a constru&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de sociedades sustent&#x000e1;veis</article-title><source>Sinais Soc</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>26</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Irving MA, Oliveira E (2012) Sustentabilidade e transforma&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o social. Rio de Janeiro, Ed. Senac</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joubert</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfred</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Beyond you and me: inspirations and wisdom for building community</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Hampshire</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Permanent Publications</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>These alternative economies are inspirations for a sustainable world</article-title><source>Sci Am</source><year>2021</year><volume>324</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salleh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Demaria</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pluriverse: a post-development dictionary</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Tamil Nadu</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Tulika Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krenak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ideias para adiar o fim do mundo</source><year>2019</year><edition>1</edition><publisher-loc>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Companhia das Letras</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lang M (2022) Buen vivir as a territorial practice. Building a more just and sustainable life through interculturality. Sustain Sci Springer 17:1287&#x02013;1299</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Racionalidade ambiental: a reapropria&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o social da natureza</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Civiliza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Brasileira</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liftin</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ecovillages: lessons for sustainable community</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Malden</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Prada</surname><given-names>DFS</given-names></name></person-group><source>El movimiento de ecoaldeas como experiencia alternativa de Buen Vivir, <italic>Polis</italic> [En l&#x000ed;nea]</source><year>2015</year><fpage>40</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattos</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ecovilas: a constru&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de uma cultura regenerativa. Uma etnografia de Findhorn</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Esc&#x000f3;cia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Novas Edi&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es Acad&#x000ea;micas</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monticelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Embodying alternatives to capitalism in the 21st century</article-title><source>TripleC Commun Capit Critique</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>517</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Homeland earth: a manifesto for the new millennium</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Hampton Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz-Villarreal</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecoaldeas en Colombia transitando hacia el buen vivir</article-title><source>Entramado</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18041/1900-3803/entramado.2.4754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norberg-Hodge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>Local is our future: steps to an economics of happiness. Ed: Local Futures</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porto-Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sader</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cece&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Da geografia &#x000e0;s geo-grafias: um mundo em busca de novas territorialidades</article-title><source>La Guerra Infinita: Hegemon&#x000ed;a y terror mundial</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Buenos Aires</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CLACSO</publisher-name><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>256</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quijano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colonialidad del poder, eurocentrismo y America Latina</article-title><source>La colonialidad del saber</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Buenos Aires</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CLACSO</publisher-name><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>246</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roysen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>RAA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarenga</surname><given-names>MAA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>LGMF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zonas de agroecologia e ecovilas: uma proposta para os planos diretores municipais</article-title><source>Sustentabilidade</source><year>2021</year><volume>2</volume><issue>e215527</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24220/2675-7885v2e2021a5527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roysen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New normalities in grassroots innovations: the reconfiguration and normalization of social practices in an ecovillage</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2019</year><volume>236</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.117647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roysen R, Schwab AK (2021) The potential of ecovillages for transitions in rural areas: a comparison of ecovillages in Germany and Brazil. In: Climate Adaptation: Accounts of Resilience, Self-Sufficiency and Systems Change. Arkbound Foundation, Glasgow</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><source>The development dictionary: a guide to knowledge as power</source><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Bloomsbury Academic</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>CAP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Participaci&#x000f3;n y acci&#x000f3;n colectiva en los movimientos globales de ecoaldeas y permacultura</article-title><source>Rev Latinoamer Psicol</source><year>2013</year><volume>45</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>413</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Coloniza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o, Quilombos: Modos e Significa&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Bras&#x000ed;lia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>INCTI</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Para al&#x000e9;m do pensamento abissal: das linhas globais a uma ecologia de saberes</article-title><source>Rev Cr&#x000ed;t Ci&#x000ea;ncias Soc</source><year>2007</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos-J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Zelosamente habitando a Terra: ecovilas genu&#x000ed;nas, espa&#x000e7;o geogr&#x000e1;fico e a constru&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de lugares zelosos em contextos contempor&#x000e2;neos de fronteiras paradigm&#x000e1;ticas</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Salvador</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Tese (Doutorado em Geografia) &#x02013; Universidade Federal da Bahia</publisher-name><fpage>443</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seyfang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grassroots innovations for sustainable development: towards a new research and policy agenda</article-title><source>Environ Politics</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644010701419121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of community sustainability: a life cycle assessment of three ecovillages</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2019</year><volume>237</volume><issue>117830</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva LFDM (2014) Viver de forma sustent&#x000e1;vel ou contribuir para a sustentabilidade do capital? As contradi&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es que permeiam a pr&#x000e1;xis das ecovilas em tempos neoliberais. Geografias 10(1):41&#x02013;53</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Simas ACBF (2013) Comunica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o e Diferen&#x000e7;a: estrat&#x000e9;gias de comunica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o colaborativa para a sustentabilidade comunit&#x000e1;ria. Tese (Doutorado em Comunica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Social) - Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sol&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Alternativas sist&#x000ea;micas: Bem Viver, decrescimento, comuns, ecofeminismo, direitos da M&#x000e3;e Terra e desglobaliza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Editora Elefante</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svampa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>As fronteiras do neoextrativismo na Am&#x000e9;rica Latina: conflitos socioambientais, giro ecoterritorial e novas depend&#x000ea;ncias</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elefante</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trainer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The global ecovillage movement: the simpler way for a sustainable society</article-title><source>Soc Altern</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United Nations &#x02013; UN</collab></person-group><source>Transforming our world: the 2030 agenda for sustainable development</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc><publisher-name>UN</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veteto</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental anthropology engaging permaculture: moving theory and practice toward sustainability</article-title><source>Agriculture</source><year>2008</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Design de Culturas Regenerativas</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Bambual Editora</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Candau</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critical interculturality and decolonial pedagogy: In-Surgir, Re-existing and re-living</article-title><source>Intercultural education in Latin America: between conceptions, tensions and proposals</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc><publisher-name>7 Letras</publisher-name><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Desenvolvimento como Buen Vivir: acordos institucionais e (des)envolvimentos coloniais</article-title><source>Desenvolvimento</source><year>2010</year><volume>53</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Economic Forum - WEF</collab></person-group><source>The Global Risks Report 2022</source><year>2022</year><edition>17</edition></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>