<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">It should be clarified here, for those unfamiliar with ecosophies, that while they are expressions of one&#8217;s values, they are also based in evidence and are subject to change as new evidence comes to light (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_083" ref-type="bibr">Stibbe 2021b</xref>). As briefly described at the outset of this article, there is currently significant evidence to suggest that the production, consumption, and disposal of plastics is a major source of harm to our planet and its inhabitants (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_072" ref-type="bibr">Rochman et&#160;al. 2013</xref>), whether in the form of carbon emissions from petrochemical industries (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_102" ref-type="bibr">Zheng and Suh 2019</xref>) and the social injustices this pollution creates (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_088" ref-type="bibr">UNEP 2021</xref>); plastic&#8217;s implications for the climate (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_078" ref-type="bibr">Shen et&#160;al. 2020</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_084" ref-type="bibr">Stoett and Vince 2019</xref>); plastic waste overwhelming communities around the world (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_042" ref-type="bibr">Letcher 2020</xref>), constituting, some have argued, colonialism (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_044" ref-type="bibr">Liboiron 2021</xref>); or harmful chemicals and microplastics entering ecosystems (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_071" ref-type="bibr">Rochman et&#160;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_089" ref-type="bibr">Verma et&#160;al. 2016</xref>), nonhuman bodies (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_029" ref-type="bibr">Haave et&#160;al. 2021</xref>) and our bodies (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_068" ref-type="bibr">Ragusa et&#160;al. 2021</xref>), the consequences of which are still relatively poorly understood (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_057" ref-type="bibr">Nava and Leoni 2021</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_090" ref-type="bibr">Vethaak and Legler 2021</xref>). These harms and hazards are to be weighed against plastic&#8217;s benefits, such as its convenience and affordability; its light weight for transport; its vast contributions to food provision, safety, hygiene, and medical care; and its central role as a flexible construction material in everyday artifacts such as technology and clothing (<xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_004" ref-type="bibr">Andrady and Neal 2009</xref>; <xref rid="j_jwl-2022-0017_ref_021" ref-type="bibr">George 2020</xref>). With all of these factors in mind, we have designed our ecosophy around the values that we deem to be logically and morally relevant for the wellbeing of our planet as a whole when considering the supply and use of plastics, particularly single-use plastics.</p>