<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par14">However, the evolution of the concept of Climate Change has undergone changes over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Together with the deterministic conceptions that accept the reality of climate change, discrepant and critical voices have arisen that call into question its existence or even reject the concept altogether (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Definitions of climate change</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Author</th><th>Definition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Todorov, A.V. (1986) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]</td><td>The concept of climate change is both complex and controversial. There is no unanimous opinion and agreement among climatologists on the definition of the term climate, not to mention climate change, the trend or climatic fluctuation.</td></tr><tr><td>United Nations (Bodansky, 1993) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td><td>A variation in the climate attributed directly or indirectly to human activity that alters the composition of the world&#8217;s atmosphere and that adds to the natural variability of the climate observed in comparable periods of time.</td></tr><tr><td>Lorenz, E. (1995) [Lorenz EN: Climate is what you expect. Unpublished]</td><td>Climate is the current distribution of a climate system over time that extends indefinitely into the future, so there is no talk of the existence of climate change.</td></tr><tr><td>IPCC (Parry et al., 2007) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td><td>A change in the state of climate that can be identified (for example, by statistical tests) by changes in the average and / or the variability of its properties, and that persists for a prolonged period, usually of decades or more.</td></tr><tr><td>Werndl, C. (2014)</td><td>Different climatic distributions in two successive periods of time.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>