<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">UCL Open Environ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">UCL Open Environ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">UCLOE</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>UCL Open Environment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2632-0886</issn><publisher><publisher-name>UCL Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10171430</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14324/111.444/ucloe.000015</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The geographic, environmental and phylogenetic evolution of the Alveolinoidea from the Cretaceous to the present day</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2339-2444</contrib-id><name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>Marcelle K.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/00000-0001-8232-6853</contrib-id><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>Geoffrey David</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Office of the Vice-Provost (Research), University College London, 2 Taviton Street, London WC1H 0BT, UK</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>m.fadel@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>08</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e015</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution Licence (CC BY) 4.0</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The superfamily Alveolinoidea is a member of the Order Miliolida, and comprises three main families, the Alveolinidae, the Fabulariidae and the Rhapydioninidae. They are examples of Larger benthic foraminifera (LBF), which are single-celled organisms with specific characteristic endoskeletons. Alveolinoids are found globally from the Cretaceous to the present day, and are important biostratigraphic index fossils in shallow-marine carbonates. They are often associated with hydrocarbon reservoirs, and exhibit provincialism with characteristic genera often confined to one of the American, Tethyan or Indo-Pacific provinces. Previously, the systematic study of the global interrelationship between the various alveolinoid lineages has not been possible because of the absence of biostratigraphic correlation between the geographically scattered assemblages, and the scarcity of described material from the Indo-Pacific province. Here we use the literature and new material from the Americas, the French Alps, Iran, Tibet, India and South East Asia, coupled with the use of the planktonic foraminiferal zonal (PZ) correlation scheme to propose a comprehensive, global, systematic analysis of the biostratigraphic, phylogenetic and paleogeographic evolution of the alveolinoids. The alveolinoids originated in the Cretaceous in the Tethyan province. During a global sea-level low stand, a westward migration of some alveolinoids species to the Americas occurred, a behaviour previously reported in contemporaneous orbitolinid LBF. After the Cretaceous/Palaeogene (K&#x02013;P) event, which saw the extinction of all Cretaceous alveolinoids, rare new forms of alveolinoids evolved again, first in the Americas and later independently in Tethys. As was found in previous studies of rotalid LBF, sea-level low stands in the Paleocene also allowed some alveolinoid forms to migrate, but this time in an eastward direction from the Americas to Tethys, and from Tethys on to the Indo-Pacific province. Alveolinoids still exist today (<italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic>), the former of which is cosmopolitan, while the latter is restricted to the Indo-Pacific province. Throughout their phylogenetic history, alveolinoids characteristically exhibit convergent evolution, with the repeated re-occurrence of certain morphological features. Understanding this propensity to homoplasy is essential in understanding and constructing the phylogenetic relationships within the alveolinoid superfamily.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>foraminifera</kwd><kwd>alveolinoids</kwd><kwd>Cretaceous</kwd><kwd>Paleogene</kwd><kwd>Neogene</kwd><kwd>Holocene</kwd><kwd>biostratigraphy</kwd><kwd>phylogeny</kwd><kwd>palaeoenvironment</kwd><kwd>palaeogeographic distribution</kwd><kwd>extinction</kwd><kwd>evolution</kwd><kwd>sea-level change</kwd><kwd>homoplasy</kwd><kwd>the environment</kwd><kwd>climate</kwd><kwd>ecology</kwd></kwd-group><counts><ref-count count="150"/><page-count count="34"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Larger benthic foraminifera (LBF) are single-celled organisms, with an internal, characteristic test, that have acted as major reef-forming organisms from the Paleozoic to the present day (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). Within the geological record, there are 14 taxonomically defined orders of LBF. They are widely used as key biostratigraphic and palaeoenvironmental indicators. Although they were generally limited to warmer, shallower marine environments, their fossil forms are globally distributed, but frequently exhibit provincialism at the family or generic level.</p><p>Our previous work has established that global marine regressions correlate with the migration of some LBF genera from one province to another. The inter-provincial migration of a genus is characterised and defined by the contemporaneous occurrence of the same species (although they may have been given different names, which are therefore synonyms) in two previously isolated provinces. In the Cretaceous, for example, we inferred that, during a global sea-level low stand, some orbitolinids (agglutinated foraminifera, members of the Order Textulariida) underwent a westward trans-oceanic migration from their Tethyan province of origin to the American province (see [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]). Although subsequently the Tethyan province remained the hotspot for orbitolinid speciation, parallel lineages evolved in the again isolated American province, but were extremely rare. Later in the Cenozoic, the American province became the hot spot for speciation of other LBF families (including members of the Order Rotaliida, studied previously by BouDagher-Fadel and Price [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]). Again during global sea-level regressions, trans-Atlantic migrations occurred, but in these cases in an eastward direction into Tethys and then on to the Indo-Pacific, and at times to southern Africa.</p><p>These previous studies, therefore, have led to the hypothesis that periodic, sea-level low stand enabled, inter-provincial migration is a characteristic global dispersal mechanism of many LBF families. As suggested by Pignatti [<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] however, this hypothesis needs further testing. In this study, therefore, we investigate the phylogenetic evolution and palaeogeographic distribution of the main genera of the porcelaneous Alveolinoidea superfamily (members of the Order Miliolida), to establish whether they too exhibit an evolutionary and dispersal behaviour similar to the previously studied LBF groups.</p><p>The Alveolinoidea comprise three families, the Alveolinidae, the Fabulariidae and the Rhapydioninidae (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). They range from the Cretaceous to the present day. Throughout their evolutionary lineages, the alveolinoids exhibited relatively rapid rates of evolution and developed complex tests, which make them an important biostratigraphic index fossil group for the shallow-marine environments of the later Mesozoic and the Cenozoic. Today, alveolinoid-bearing limestones occur globally from the Americas, through the Mediterranean and the Gulf, Tibet, and on to the Indo-Pacific province. They are often associated with significant hydrocarbon reservoirs. The study of the Alveolinoidea and the definition of their stratigraphic ranges has been the subject of many regional micropaleontological investigations, especially those of the Tethyan and American provinces [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], but the most recent revisions of <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> from Indonesia are by Bakx [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Until now, however, it has not been possible to develop an effective global view of their evolution and inter-relationships, because the systematic study of the links between the American, Tethys and Indo-Pacific lineages has been hampered by the lack of biostratigraphic correlation between the geographically scattered alveolinoid assemblages described in the literature, and by the scarcity of described material from the Indo-Pacific province.</p><p>In this paper, we revise some of the analysis presented in BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], and present results from material recently obtained as a result of various investigations of LBF-bearing carbonate facies from two Atlantic basins, one from offshore Brazil (the Campos Basin), and the other off Venezuela (the Matacaibo Basin). These are augmented by studies of new material from several localities including from Saint Barth&#x000e9;lemy (Lesser Antilles); Cardenas, San Luis Potosi, Mexico; the shallow marine sequences of the Ainsa Basin, Spain; Iles Madam and Audignon, France; Les Scaffarels sections from the Western Alps; the Circum-Troodos Massif sedimentary succession, northern Cyprus; the island of Paxos, Greece; Latakia, northwest Syria; Lebanon; the Kuh-I-Bingistan section and Savark formation, Iran; the Red Sea; the Pila Spi formations in Jabal Hiebat Sultan, Iraq; the Ladakh region, India; the Tingri and Gamba regions of southern Tibet; the Sekau formation, Indonesia; Port Moresby, New Guinea; the Sarawak Basin (onshore carbonates from Tinjar Province); and the Baden-Brickyard, Baden, Australia. The detailed locations of the materials studied can be found in associated cited references below. As a result, by combining our observations with those in the literature, we are able to propose a comprehensive, global, systematic analysis of the biostratigraphic, phylogenetic and palaeogeographic evolution of the alveolinoids. In our definitions of stratigraphic ranges, we primarily use the planktonic foraminiferal zonal (PZ) scheme of BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], which is tied to the time scale of Gradstein et al. [<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In this paper, the PZ scheme is also correlated with the LBF &#x02018;letter stages&#x02019; of the Far East, as defined by BouDagher-Fadel and Banner [<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and later revised by BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] (see <xref rid="fg001" ref-type="fig">Figs 1</xref> and <xref rid="fg002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), and with the biogeographic zonation of shallow benthic larger foraminifera as defined by Serra-Kiel et al. [<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], which incorporates a series of biozones proposed for the Paleogene of Western Tethys based on species of <italic toggle="yes">Alvceolina, Nummulites</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Assilina</italic> [<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. These biozones have been integrated into the shallow benthic zones (SBZ) covering the Paleocene to Eocene of the Mediterranean region by Serra-Kiel et al. [<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], as a system of numbered units for the &#x02018;Tertiary&#x02019;, with SBZ 1&#x02013;23 covering the Paleogene (see <xref rid="fg001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Alveolinoids Paleogene biozones with diagnostic first and last occurrences, calibrated against the PZ, the &#x02018;letter stages&#x02019; of the Far East, and the &#x02018;SB&#x02019; zones of the Mediterranean, modified after BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Alveolinoids Neogene biozones with diagnostic first and last occurrences, calibrated to the &#x02018;letter stages&#x02019; of the Far East.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>As described below, our analysis of the evolution and distribution of the alveolinoids will show that our previously developed hypothesis (i.e. that periodic, sea-level low stands enable inter-provincial migration of LBF [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]) is again strongly supported, and that the behaviour and directions of migration of the alveolinoids is resonant with those of the orbitolinids [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], the orthophragminids [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], the nummulitoids [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], the miogypsinids [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and the lepidocyclinids [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The alveolinoids originated in the Cretaceous in the Tethyan province. We conclude here for the first time that during a global sea-level low stand, migration of some alveolinoid species to the Americas occurred. As this province again became isolated as sea levels rose, parallel evolutionary trends between related forms of alveolinoids in the two re-isolated provinces subsequently occurred. After the end-Maastrichtian mass extinction, rare new forms of alveolinoids reappeared first in the Americas. Previous studies also suggested that the Americas were the region of the post-K&#x02013;P appearance of the rotaliid LBF. As also previously inferred from our studies of a number of rotaliid LBFs, sea-level low stands in the Paleocene allowed some alveolinoid forms to migrate from the Americas to Tethys, where again later sea-level rises led to provincial isolation and parallel provincial evolutionary trends. As also occurred for the previously studied rotaliids, the alveolinoids flourished in Tethys and subsequently migrated from Tethys to the Indo-Pacific province, where they further diversified. With the closure of the Tethys seaway in the Miocene (late Burdigalian), the Mediterranean alveolinoids became isolated from their Indo-Pacific descendants and exhibited parallel evolutionary trends with more evolved, different lineages in the Indo-Pacific province showing morphological convergent trends similar to previous Cretaceous stock. Alveolinoids still exist today (<italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic>), the former of which is cosmopolitan, while the latter is restricted to the Indo-Pacific province.</p><p>The Alveolinoidea throughout their phylogenetic history evolved morphologically divergent features, giving rise to identifiably distinct genera. As in previous biogeographical studies, however, we also confirm spatial and temporal gaps in their phylogenetic/stratigraphic distributions [<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. We find that these gaps are best explained by homoplasy, in which convergent and characteristic features reappear as a result of either similar ecological evolutionary selection pressures, or a genetic predisposition to the repetition of specific mutations that produce morphological characteristics that are used to define a genus.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Morphological and paleoenvironmental characteristics of the Alveolinoidea</title><p>The Alveolinoidea made their first appearance in the Early Cretaceous (<xref rid="fg003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) exhibiting a fusiform morphology. As is characteristic of miliolids, they have a porcelaneous, imperforate wall structure, with fine, randomly oriented crystals of high-magnesium calcite. Their tests are enrolled along an elongate axis, being initially planispiral or streptospiral, or &#x02018;miliolid&#x02019;, with chambers added in varying planes (<xref rid="fg004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). In an extreme example of ecologically driven convergent evolution involving forms from different orders, the external appearance of alveolinoids closely resembles the planispiral, fusiform fusulinides of the late Paleozoic. This example of homoplasy is the result of ecological selection pressures acting on forms from different orders filling equivalent niches but in different stratigraphic periods. Many alveolinoids attained the same centrimetric scale as the fusulinides, but differ fundamentally in their imperforate, porcelaneous wall structure, and are indeed very distinct when studied in axial and equatorial (median) sections (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). The basic morphology of the alveolinoids is shown in <xref rid="fg004" ref-type="fig">Figs 4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="fg007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>. Unlike the fusulinides, septal folding does not occur and the spiral septula reach the floor across the chamber. Deposition of secondary calcite (flosculinisation, <xref rid="fg004" ref-type="fig">Figs 4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="fg006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) occurs more evenly across the floor of the chamber or may be restricted to a specific period of ontogenesis, rather than being almost entirely concentrated in the axial zone as in the fusulinides. The embryonic apparatus consists of a spherical proloculus followed by a spiral tube (flexostyle), succeeded in some genera by a miliolid nepion (pre-adult stage). In the adult, numerous chambers are planispirally coiled around an elongate axis, each chamber being broken into tubular chamberlets by secondary septa (septula) that run in the direction of coiling. Connectivity between the chambers is enabled through the vertical septula (canals/passages). These may be situated in front of the septum (post-septal) or behind it (pre-septal) (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]).</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Ranges of the main genera of the Cretaceous Alveolinoidea in the three provinces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>A) The evolution of the Alveolinidae from a simple streptospiral origin, such as <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic>; B) The evolution of the Rhapydioninidae from the lenticular compressed <italic toggle="yes">Pseudedomia;</italic> C) The evolution of the Fabulariidae from a completely overlapping form with vertical incomplete partitions, <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Basal layers and flosculinisation in <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> (modified from [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg006" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Alveolina globosa</italic> (Leymerie), A) equatorial section, B) axial section. Early Eocene, Meting Limestone, Laki group, Pakistan, UCL coll. Scale bars = 1 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g006" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg007" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>A) <italic toggle="yes">Fabularia hanzawai</italic> Robinson, co-type, Eocene, Saint Andrew Claremont Formation, Jamaica, NHM P52840; B&#x02013;C) <italic toggle="yes">Fabularia discolithus</italic> Defrance, Lutetian middle calcaire grossier, Chaumont-en-Vexin, Paris Basin, NHM P33071. Scale bars: A) = 0.5 mm; B&#x02013;C) = 1 mm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g007" position="float"/></fig><p>In the Cenozoic, the alveolinoids re-appeared in the Paleocene seemingly independently from their Cretaceous relatives (<xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>), but evolving from a common simple, long-ranging miliolid ancestor, in an example of homoplasy driven by a predisposition towards the occurrence of a repeated set of mutations that produce generic characteristics. The Paleocene forms share morphological characteristics with their Cretaceous relatives, and evolved separate parallel lineages in both the Tethyan province and the American province. As will be discussed in detail below, this repeated evolution from a simple miliolid common ancestor, such as <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic> caused homoplasic generic characteristics, such as alveoles, to reappear on numerous occasions in the Paleogene and in the Neogene.</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg008" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Ranges of the main genera of the Paleogene Alveolinoidea in the three provinces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g008" position="float"/></fig><p>In the Middle Eocene, alveolinoids reached morphologically large sizes (e.g. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina prorrecta</italic> Hottinger) growing up to 3.5 cm in the diameter of the axial section [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Their sizes were made achievable as a result of the evolutionary development of a variety of morphological structures that had the effect of mechanically strengthening the alveolinoid test, such as by the thickened basal layer (which is subdivided by pillars or secondary partitions in the Fabulariidae), the canaliculation and thickening of the central zone except for a pre-septal space with buttresses or residual pillars (as in the Rhapydioninidae), and the flosculinisation with thick deposition of secondary calcite (as in the Alveolinidae [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). The basal layer of the larger foraminiferal test, when thickened by flosculinisation [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] or perforated by canalicular passages [<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], exists only in the porcelaneous forms (<xref rid="fg005" ref-type="fig">Figs 5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="fg007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).</p><p>The development of alveoles (blind recesses separated by septula; e.g. see <xref rid="fg006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) in some alveolinoids may have allowed them to harbour photosymbionts (e.g. diatom symbionts in living <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic> Douvill&#x000e9; [<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], see <xref rid="fg009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>). Endosymbiosis apparently played a major role in the evolution and diversification of the alveolinoids, and appears to be a key innovation that facilitated a change in habitat from an epifaunal, free-living mode of life, to one of living attached to phytal and non-phytal substrata.</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg009" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella quoyi</italic> (d&#x02019;Orbigny), Port Moresby, Coral Sea, New Guinea, solid specimen figured by BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], showing a parasite-symbiont(s) completely enclosed by the whorls, <italic toggle="yes">Planorbulinopsis parasitica</italic> Banner, embedded in the test. Scale bar = 0.25 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g009" position="float"/></fig><p>On the other hand, the development of pillars in the fabulariids (see <xref rid="fg007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>) and rhapydioninids may also be seen as providing mechanical strength to the test. For example, in discoidal forms, heavily pillared endoskeletons, as a rule, occur in forms living in very shallow, turbulent water. In the present day, robust and fusiform tests (as seen in <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic>) are adapted to a life in environments of moderate hydrodynamic energy, characteristic of water depths of less than 30 m, usually not in mobile sands, but rather on phytal or hard substrates such as reef rubble [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. At Lizard Island, Australia, sand patches at ~15&#x02013;20 m seemed to be the best habitat to collect <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic> (Hallock, personal comment). According to Hottinger [<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], in <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> the function of the elongated fusiform test is related to motility, the test growing in the equatorial direction but moving in the polar direction. The living alveolinids (such as the elongate <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic>) appear to be confined to shallow-marine (down to depths of 80 m), clear, well-oxygenated, tropical and subtropical waters. They can hide or shelter under shallow layers of coral sand, in order to regulate the illumination that they require. Therefore, in comparing the occurrences of the extinct alveolinids with their Holocene descendants, we can safely deduce that these fusiform types, with large alveoles, thrived in sediments deposited in warm, shallow water. In fact, all alveolinoids are regarded as neritic (inner shelf) by Reichel [<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], restricted to littoral, tropical, protected shelf and reef shoals [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], or moderate energy zones of the shallow ramp [<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and some genera are epiphytic [<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Phylogeny and palaeogeographic distribution of the Alveolinoidea</title><p>In this section, we will review the phylogenetic development and taxonomic relationships of the alveolinoids of the Cretaceous, Paleogene and Neogene. Furthermore, we clarify their provincial distributions, based around the Tethyan, American and Indo-Pacific provinces. We discuss the development of the three alveolinoid families, the Alveolinidae, the Fabulariidae and the Rhapydioninidae, which in the Cretaceous occurred in the Tethyan and American provinces, and then the later Cenozoic forms, of which the Alveolinidae and the Fabulariidae occurred in all three provinces (Tethys, American and the Indo-Pacific), while the Rhapydioninidae were constrained to the Americas.</p><sec id="s3a"><title>The Cretaceous Alveolinoidea</title><sec id="s3a1"><title>The Tethyan Province</title><p>The limestones of the Tethyan province range from what is today the Western Mediterranean, through the Middle East to the carbonate platforms of Tibet. This province saw the first development of the alveolinoids from small simple miliolids, such as <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic> (see <xref rid="fg003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). This latter is a simple small streptospiral-involute porcelaneous form, with an apertural slit or with a row of multiple apertures. It made its first appearance in the latest Hauterivian (PZ Hauterivian 2 [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]). It was widely distributed in the Tethyan province from the Albian until the early Paleogene [<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], and is the ancestral form for many of the Alveolinoidea.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Archaealveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg019" ref-type="fig">Plate 1, a</xref>) is the earliest defined <bold>Alveolinidae</bold>. It is subglobular with an early streptospiral stage, pre-septal passages and a single row of apertures at the base of the apertural face. This genus first appeared at the beginning of the Aptian and disappeared at the end of PZ Albian 1 [<xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Archaealveolina</italic> gave rise to and was replaced in the Albian by <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg019" ref-type="fig">Plate 1, b&#x02013;c</xref>), a globular form with planispiral coiling and large pre-septal passages [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina</italic> is recorded from many Tethyan localities ranging from PZ Albian 1 to PZ Cenomanian 3, but as discussed below, is not found in the American province until the beginning of PZ Cenomanian 2.</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg019" fig-type="figure"><label>Plate 1</label><caption><p>Scale bars: a, c, f, h = 0.5 mm; b, d, e, g, i, j = 1 mm.</p><p>a. <italic toggle="yes">Archaealveolina reicheli</italic> (de Castro), figured by Loeblich and Tappan [<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], Aptian, Italy.</p><p>b. <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina</italic> sp., Cenomanian, France, UCL collection.</p><p>c. <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina crassa</italic> Castro, Cenomanian, Iles Madam, UCL collection.</p><p>d. <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina cretacea</italic> Reichel, Cenomanian, Iles Madam, UCL collection.</p><p>e&#x02013;f. <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina tenuis</italic> Reichel, Cenomanian, e) oblique equatorial section; f) oblique axial section, Audignon, near Saint-Sever, UCL collection.</p><p>g&#x02013;j. <italic toggle="yes">Simplalveolina simplex</italic> (Reichel), Cenomanian, Audignon, near Saint-Sever, UCL collection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g019" position="float"/></fig><p>In PZ Albian 4, the planispiral <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina</italic> gave rise to subglobular/fusiform <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg019" ref-type="fig">Plate 1, e&#x02013;f</xref>) with much lower and narrower chamberlets. The apertural face of <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic> has, as does <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina</italic>, a single row of pores near the equator, however, the pores increase poleward to many rows of openings. <italic toggle="yes">Simplalveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg019" ref-type="fig">Plate 1, g&#x02013;j</xref>) which also appeared at PZ Cenomanian 1, is small and ovoid with numerous aligned septula, but lacks secondary chamberlets. The aperture is a single row of pores in the apertural face. In PZ Cenomanian 1, <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic> gave rise to the spherical <italic toggle="yes">Multispirina</italic> (<xref rid="fg020" ref-type="fig">Plate 2, a</xref>), with large, numerous chambers, interleaved by spires [<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The aperture is formed by a row of pores in the apertural face of each of the multiple spires. The growth of <italic toggle="yes">Multispirina</italic> is an example of an alternative to elongate growth, where the multiple spires are a means of accelerating its growth [<xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The multiple spires also enhance the internal inter-connectedness of the pore spaces, as the numerous small apertures along the sutures connect the whorls in an irregular manner, thus making for short radial lines of interconnectedness throughout the test [<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg020" fig-type="figure"><label>Plate 2</label><caption><p>Scale bars: a = 0.15 mm; b&#x02013;g, i, k = 0.5 mm; h, j = 1 mm.</p><p>a. <italic toggle="yes">Multispirina</italic> sp., Cenomanian, Qatar, NHM M2425.</p><p>b. <italic toggle="yes">Streptalveolina</italic> sp., Cenomanian, Iles Madam, UCL collection.</p><p>c&#x02013;f. <italic toggle="yes">Cisalveolina lehneri</italic> Reichel, Cenomanian, India, UCL coll.</p><p>g. <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic> sp. Cenomanian, Paxos, Greece, P. Scholle coll.</p><p>h. <italic toggle="yes">Pseudedomia persica</italic> Rahaghi, Cenomanian, Iran, Nanjing University coll.</p><p>i. <italic toggle="yes">Helenalveolina tappanae</italic> Hottinger, Drobne and Caus, Cenomanian, Iles Madam, UCL collection.</p><p>j&#x02013;k. <italic toggle="yes">Pseudochubbina globularis</italic> (Smout) (= <italic toggle="yes">Pseudedomia globularis</italic> Smout), paratypes, Campanian, Iraq, NHM P42646.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g020" position="float"/></fig><p>Parallel to the <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic> lineage, <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina</italic> also gave rise to the small to medium size globular, streptospirally coiled <italic toggle="yes">Streptalveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg020" ref-type="fig">Plate 2, b</xref>; PZ Albian 4&#x02013;Cenomanian 2). The latter also has large pre-septal passages and a single row of apertures on the apertural face. The trend in this lineage is to evolve planispiral later whorls, as in <italic toggle="yes">Cisalveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg020" ref-type="fig">Plate 2, c&#x02013;f</xref>; PZ Cenomanian 1&#x02013;3), which has alternating septula with a simple narrow, slit-like aperture extending from pole to pole. <italic toggle="yes">Cisalveolina</italic>, unlike all the Cretaceous genera with pre-septal canals, has post-septal passages.</p><p>Of the early alveolinids, 85% did not survive the widespread oceanic anoxic event (OAE) at the Cenomanian&#x02013;Turonian boundary (93.9 Ma), which may in turn have been triggered by the Madagascar and Caribbean volcanic provinces events (<xref rid="fg010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>). The only survivor was <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic>, which in turn went extinct at the end of the Turonian.</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg010" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>The major tectonic, oceanic and climatic events in the Cretaceous affecting alveolinoids and orbitolinid migration, evolution and extinction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g010" position="float"/></fig><p>The alveolinids re-appeared in the Late Cretaceous of the Tethyan province, but notably those that did appear had a streptospiral early stage and a planispiral-involute adult stage. It has been proposed that they are again phylogenetically linked to <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic> (<xref rid="fg020" ref-type="fig">Plate 2, g</xref>), and are an example of the homoplasic, re-appearance of morphologically identical form from a long ranging, robust small-form common ancestor [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. They include the spherical <italic toggle="yes">Helenalveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg020" ref-type="fig">Plate 2, i</xref>; PZ Coniacian 2&#x02013;Santonian 2), <italic toggle="yes">Subalveolina</italic> (PZ Santonian 2&#x02013;Maastrichian 3), and the axially elongated <italic toggle="yes">Senalveolina</italic> in the early Campanian. <italic toggle="yes">Helenalveolina</italic> is distinguished from the Fabulariidae by the absence of pillars subdividing the chambers, by its streptospiral coiling, and by the lack of a trematophore in its apertural face.</p><p>The earliest <bold>Rhapydioninidae</bold> originated in Tethys at the end of the Albian. The axially compressed rhapydioninids have homologous features to the alveolinids, and occupied similar niches, but developed separate parallel lineages. They evolved, as did the alveolinids, from the streptospiral <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic>, but did so later than the first appearance of the alveolinids [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. They had a planispiral to streptospiral early stage, but diverged from the alveolinids lineages by becoming uncoiled, compressed, peneropliform-flaring, or cylindrical in later stages. The basal layer of the rhapydioninids is pierced by tubular supplementary passages as part of the &#x02018;central thickening&#x02019; [<xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The rhapydioninid are comparable to modern peneroplid foraminifera, which commonly are found in shallow-water epifaunal habitats or on epiphytal hard substrates, including seagrasses and algal thalli [<xref rid="r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg021" ref-type="fig">Plate 3, a&#x02013;b</xref>), was the most primitive rhapydioninid and occurred across Tethys between PZ Albian 4&#x02013;Cenomanian 4 [<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]), colonising the carbonate platforms from the Middle East to the Iberian Peninsula. Unusually, it is a cosmopolitan rhapydioninid, and is reported from the American province from PZ Cenomanian 2&#x02013;Turonian 2 (n.b. in the Maastrichtian, <italic toggle="yes">Rhapydionina</italic> becomes the only other example of a cosmopolitan rhapydioninid). <italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic> has a lenticular, planispirally-enrolled test, where the chamber lumen is subdivided into numerous chamberlets by septula. <italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic> species increased in overall test size and complexity of internal structures during their stratigraphic evolution.</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg021" fig-type="figure"><label>Plate 3</label><caption><p>Scale bars: a&#x02013;i, k&#x02013;l = 0.5 mm; j = 1 mm.</p><p>a&#x02013;b. <italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina viallii</italic> Colalongo, Cenomanian, Xinyu, Nanjing University coll.</p><p>c. <italic toggle="yes">Murciella cuvillieri</italic> Fourcade, figured by Fourcade [<xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], Campanian, Spain.</p><p>d&#x02013;e. <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina iranica</italic> Rahaghi, Cenomanian, Iran, Nanjing University coll.</p><p>f. <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> sp., Coniacian, India, UCL coll.</p><p>g&#x02013;h. <italic toggle="yes">Chubbina cardenasensis</italic> (Barker and Grimsdale), g) Late Cretaceous, Cardenas, San Luis Potosi, Mexico, NHM P33044; h) figured by Robinson [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] as a co-type megalospheric specimen of <italic toggle="yes">Chubbina jamaicensis</italic> Robinson, Campanian, Jamaica, NHM P48053.</p><p>i. <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina pilula</italic> Hottinger, Ypresian, Lower Laki Formation, Pakistan, UCL coll.</p><p>j. <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina</italic> sp., Eocene, Libya, UCL coll.</p><p>k. <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina lepidula</italic> (Schwager), Early Eocene, Longjiang section, Tibet, Nanjing University coll.</p><p>l. <italic toggle="yes">Pseudofabularia matleyi</italic> (Vaughan), figured by Loeblich and Tappan [<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], Middle Eocene, Chapelton Formation, Jamaica.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g021" position="float"/></fig><p>Tethyan rhapydioninids are provincially characterised by <italic toggle="yes">Pseudedomia</italic> (<xref rid="fg020" ref-type="fig">Plate 2, h</xref>) and its descendants, which evolved from <italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic> in PZ Cenomanian 1. They are common in the Late Cretaceous deposits of the European&#x02013;North African region [<xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. This lineage exhibits an evolutionary trend with an increasing diameter of the megalospheric form, a reduction in the streptospiral nepionic stage, and an increase in the differentiation and regularity of the peripheral chamberlets in comparison with the median chamberlets in the same chamber [<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudedomia</italic> both resemble <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina</italic> in their globular initial part, but develop compressed, curved chambers in their final whorls. The chambers in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudedomia</italic> become progressively longer, strongly overlapping the preceding chambers. The evolutionary lineage from <italic toggle="yes">Pseudedomia</italic> showed progressive uncoiling and cylindrical development through <italic toggle="yes">Rhapydionina, Murciella</italic> (<xref rid="fg021" ref-type="fig">Plate 3, c</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">Cyclopseudedomia</italic> (see <xref rid="fg007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). The &#x02018;central thickening&#x02019; of <italic toggle="yes">Rhapydionina</italic> compares with the thickened basal layer in the polar area of <italic toggle="yes">Subalveolina</italic> [<xref rid="r64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic> has crosswise, oblique, median tubular chamberlets (the &#x02018;helicoidal&#x02019; structures of Fleury [<xref rid="r65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]), while <italic toggle="yes">Cyclopseudedomia</italic> is cyclical with compressed arched chambers in its final whorls.</p><p>We believe that the Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic> has sometimes been misidentified as a <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic>, which in fact is an American Paleocene form (see below). For example, the Late Cretaceous Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> [e.g. <italic toggle="yes">R. salentina</italic> (Papetti and Tedeschi)] has the same advanced early planispiral-involute nepiont as <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic>, and the two genera were considered synonyms by De Castro [<xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. We agree with this analysis and contend that all Cretaceous, Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> are in fact synonyms of <italic toggle="yes">Murciella.</italic></p><p>All Tethyan rhapydioninids, including <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic>, went extinct at the end of the Maastrichtian. The true <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> appeared in the Paleogene of the American province. There are no records of <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> from the Paleocene of the Tethyan province. <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> has a streptospiral nepiont in both megalospheric and microspheric generations, and characteristically has a smaller test than <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> evolved in different times on the two sides of the Atlantic. They are again an example of homoplasic evolution, rather than representing a single genus that survived the events at the Cretaceous&#x02013;Paleogene boundary while simultaneously moving provinces.</p><p>The <bold>Fabulariidae</bold> are also common in similar ecological niches as the alveolinids, but they did not appear before the Late Cretaceous and were endemic to the Tethyan province, with no record from the Cretaceous deposits of the American province. They arose directly and independently from the alveolinids and the rhapydioninids, either from the simple <italic toggle="yes">Quinqueloculina</italic> group [<xref rid="r66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], or they had a true miliolid origin from, for example, the simple-form <italic toggle="yes">Idalina</italic> (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). The fabulariid test is large, dimorphic, multi-chambered with miliolid coiling, tending to become reduced in subsequent growth stages, either to bilocular or to monolocular chamber cycles, with a trematophore as the aperture. According to Hottinger ([<xref rid="r67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], p. 4) &#x02018;A trematophore, or a sieve constituting the face of many porcelaneous larger foraminifera, is in miliolids produced by the coalescence of teeth, covering a large pre-septal space. It may be supported by residual pillars&#x02019;. Chambers have a thickened basal layer, subdivided by pillars or secondary partitions. Foraminifera in the adult growth stages have a fixed apertural axis. For the terminology and the orientation of sections needed for detailed structural analysis see Drobne [<xref rid="r68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] and Hottinger et al. [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Idalina</italic>, a simple miliolid with a quinqueloculine to biloculine test, gave rise to <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina</italic> (<xref rid="fg021" ref-type="fig">Plate 3, d&#x02013;e</xref>; see [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]), which has incomplete partitions and an aperture consisting of a round trematophore with a bar-like tooth. Also, in the Coniacian, <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> (<xref rid="fg021" ref-type="fig">Plate 3, f</xref>) appeared, with chambers that overlap throughout, with a concentric growth pattern, and with an annular trematophore (<xref rid="fg003" ref-type="fig">Figs 3</xref> and <xref rid="fg007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> is reported from many places in the Tethyan province, for example, from Southern Europe [<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], France [<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="r60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="r70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], Spain [<xref rid="r70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>], Sardinia [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], and Israel [<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="r71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,<xref rid="r72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. In <italic toggle="yes">Pseudolacazina</italic> the chambers are subdivided by longitudinal partitions or by pillars supporting the chamber roof, while in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudochubbina</italic> (<xref rid="fg020" ref-type="fig">Plate 2, j&#x02013;k</xref>) parallel anastomising passages are present in the basal layer. Correcting BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], we now believe that all Cretaceous fabulariids, except the small, primitive, robust <italic toggle="yes">Idalina</italic>, went extinct at the K&#x02013;P boundary.</p></sec><sec id="s3a2"><title>The American Province</title><p>The mid-Cretaceous <bold>Alveolinidae</bold> were extremely rare in the American province, and post-date the Tethyan forms. It is inferred that they migrated from the Tethyan province after their first appearance there. The pre-existing Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic> appeared in the Americas together with some Tethyan orbitolinds (see [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]; <xref rid="fg003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) during the sea-level low stand of the Aptian&#x02013;Albian boundary (migration 1 in <xref rid="fg011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>), and is represented in both provinces by <italic toggle="yes">P. heimi</italic> (Bonet). This species is widely distributed in the Albian&#x02013;Cenomanian of both Western Tethys and the Gulf Coast [<xref rid="r74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. It has also been recorded from Texas, Florida and Louisiana in the United States [<xref rid="r77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg011" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Variation in sea level during the mid to Late Cretaceous based on Miller et al. [<xref rid="r73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The red diamonds represent the planktonic foraminiferal zones, while the numbers signify the main migration events of the alveolinids.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g011" position="float"/></fig><p>The streptospiral alveolinids appeared in the American province, in PZ Albian 4b, and are represented by <italic toggle="yes">Streptalveolina mexicana</italic> Fourcade, Tardy and Vila [<xref rid="r78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. This species initially described from the early Cenomanian, Mexican Aurora Formation, has also been recorded in some localities from PZ Albian 4 to Cenomanian 2 of the Gulf Coast [<xref rid="r79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,<xref rid="r80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. It is endemic to the American province, but appears to be virtually identical to the PZ Albian 4a, Mediterranean species <italic toggle="yes">S. peybernesi</italic> [<xref rid="r81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>], and seems to have appeared in America after the late Albian sea-level low stand (migration 2 in <xref rid="fg011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>). Finally, the pre-existing Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina maccagnoae</italic> De Castro is reported from the Americas from PZ Cenomanian 2 [<xref rid="r82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] from the mid-late Cenomanian deposits of the Manantlan Range in Colima State, Mexico, which again correlates with a global sea-level low stand (migration 3 in <xref rid="fg011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>).</p><p>In the American province, the <bold>Rhapydioninidae</bold> are of two types, represented by the mid-Cretaceous <italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic>, and the distinct, later Cretaceous <italic toggle="yes">Chubbina</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Chubbinella, Praechubbina, Caribalveolina</italic> lineage.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic> is the most primitive genus of the axially compressed Alveolinoidea, and is the only genus of the Rhapydioninidae that is found in the mid-Cretaceous of the American province. It first appeared as a Tethyan form in PZ Albian 4, but it is reported in the Americas 3.4 Ma later (in PZ Cenomanian 2) as <italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic> sp. and <italic toggle="yes">Sellialveolina</italic> cf. <italic toggle="yes">drorimensis</italic> (a Tethyan form) from northern Peru [<xref rid="r83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. This appearance in the Americans coincides with that of <italic toggle="yes">Ovalveolina</italic>, which as noted above correlates with a global PZ Cenomanian 2, sea-level low stand (migration 3 in <xref rid="fg011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>).</p><p>The later American rhapydioninids forms have no Tethyan equivalents, and seem to have evolved directly from the American <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina.</italic> They are described from several localities in southern Mexico, Guatemala and in the Caribbean [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].</p><p>They appear in PZ Campanian 1, and rapidly develop the <italic toggle="yes">Chubbina</italic> (<xref rid="fg021" ref-type="fig">Plate 3, g&#x02013;h</xref>) lineage, which is endemic to the American province. The most primitive genus of this lineage, <italic toggle="yes">Praechubbina</italic>, with a poorly developed endoskeleton, formed by short, incomplete septula and floors, is characterised by a single aperture in its early stages. It differs from the ancestor genus <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic> by the presence of endoskeletal elements and multiple apertures in adult stages of growth [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. The septula in <italic toggle="yes">Chubbinella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Chubbina</italic> are complete, and divide the chambers into long tubular chamberlets. The septula of <italic toggle="yes">Chubbinella</italic> form chamberlets of equal calibre within the same chamber, while in <italic toggle="yes">Chubbina</italic> the chamberlets are unequal and the median chamberlets are parallel to the peripheral chamberlets. In <italic toggle="yes">Chubbina</italic> the subdivision of the chambers begins in the early stages of growth, whereas in <italic toggle="yes">Chubbinella</italic> the early parts are undivided [<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. On the other hand, the axially elongated <italic toggle="yes">Caribalveolina</italic> has alveoles and chubbinid features in the poles that are similar but less regular than the polar features of <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic> [<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p><p>A Late Cretaceous migration of the rhapydioninids from the American province to Tethys never occurred. However, towards the middle Maastrichtian (PZ Maastrichtian 2), migration of the Tethyan form <italic toggle="yes">Rhapydionina</italic> to the American province did occur, with <italic toggle="yes">Rhapydionina cf. R. liburnica</italic> (Stache) reported from PZ Maastrichtian 4 of south east Mexico [<xref rid="r86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. The early Maastrichtian low sea-level stands (migration 4 in <xref rid="fg011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>) correlate with the timing of this apparent trans-oceanic migration (<xref rid="fg012" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg012" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>Schematic migration of alveolinoids during Late Cretaceous, shown by red arrows, from the Tethyan province to the American province.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g012" position="float"/></fig><p>All American rhapydioninids went extinct at the K&#x02013;P boundary.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>The Paleogene Alveolinoidea</title><p>No complex Alveolinoidea survived the Cretaceous/Palaeogene (K&#x02013;P) extinction, however their ancestral small and simple miliolids were robust enough to continue (<xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). In the Paleogene, these ancestral forms again gave rise to new members of all three of the Alveolinoidea families, which closely echoed their Cretaceous predecessors. The alveolinids of the Paleogene show a complex history of regeneration from the simple <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic> (which survived the end Cretaceous event and only went extinct in the late Thanetian, P4), with new forms occurring independently in both the Americas and Tethys. In the Eocene, migration of alveolinids again occurred, but as previously seen in our studies of the rotaliids, now in a west to east direction, with migration of forms from Tethys to the Indo-Pacific.</p><p>In the Paleocene, the rhapydioninids also re-appeared from a small miliolid after the K&#x02013;P extinction, but are only found in the Americas (<xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). In Tethys the fabulariid ancestral form <italic toggle="yes">Idalina</italic> survived the Maastrichtian extinction, and gave rise to a second wave of Paleocene forms. They gave rise in the Middle Paleocene to a <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina</italic> lineage, which echoes the homomorphic Late Cretaceous lineage, but which is separated by a stratigraphic interval of over 6 Ma. In yet another example of homoplasy, <italic toggle="yes">Fabularia</italic> evolved in the Americas independently of the other Tethyan fabulariids, and migrated during an early Ypresian sea-level low stand to Tethys (<xref rid="fg013" ref-type="fig">Figs 13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="fg015" ref-type="fig">15</xref>). All rhapydioninids and fabulariids went extinct before the end of the Paleogene, and only an alveolinid, <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic>, survived into the Neogene (<xref rid="fg016" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg013" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p>The major tectonic, oceanic and climatic events in the Neogene affecting alveolinoids migration, evolution and extinction. WPP, I-P = Indo-Pacific; WT = Western Tethys; A-P = American province.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g013" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg014" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p>Schematic migration of alveolinoids during Early Paleogene, shown by red arrows, from the American province to the Tethyan province.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g014" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg015" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 15</label><caption><p>Variation in sea level during the Paleogene based on Miller et al. [<xref rid="r73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The red diamonds represent the planktonic foraminiferal zones, while the numbers signify the main migration events of the alveolinids.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g015" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg016" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 16</label><caption><p>Ranges of the main genera of the Neogene Alveolinoidea in the three provinces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g016" position="float"/></fig><sec id="s3b1"><title>The American Province</title><p>The <bold>alveolinids</bold>, except for a couple of primitive genera (not discussed in [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]), are rare in the Paleogene of the American province. A primitive small globular planispirally, coiled form, <italic toggle="yes">Quasiborelis</italic> Hanzawa [e.g. <italic toggle="yes">Q. gunteri</italic> (Cole)] with streptospiral early chambers, was reported by Hanzawa [<xref rid="r87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>] from Florida (<xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). It has a simple internal structure, consisting of a poorly developed endoskeleton divided by few septula and floors, and high pre-septal canals, and it must have evolved from a small miliolid that survived the K&#x02013;P event. <italic toggle="yes">Quasiborelis</italic> was short ranged, but was followed directly by forms similar to the later Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> (see [<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]). The American <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> is subglobular in shape with only one row of chamberlets and a planispiral later stage, and has been reported from the Middle Paleocene to the Early Eocene (PZ P3&#x02013;P9) of the American province [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="r88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. The American <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> occupies similar niches as the Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg021" ref-type="fig">Plate 3, i&#x02013;j</xref>; [<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]), which is abundant in the very low hydrodynamic energy back-reef environments of Tethys, but is absent from the American province. The American <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> has aligned septula and pre-septal passages, but they are generally smaller in size than those of the Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic>. American <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> and Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> are probably examples of homoplasy, as they do not co-exist, and are in fact separated by 6.6 Ma in the geological column.</p><p>The <bold>Rhapydioninidae</bold> were common and mainly endemic to the Late Cretaceous low-latitude shallow-water reefal and lagoonal settings of the American province. All of them, however, went extinct at the end of the Cretaceous. The rhapydioninids of the Paleogene are also distinct from those described from the Cretaceous of the Tethyan province, and are only found in the American province. The genus <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia (R. guatemalensis</italic> van den Bold) was originally established by van den Bold [<xref rid="r91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>] from the Eocene of Guatemala, however, as discussed above, it is different from the <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> misidentified in the Tethys, which are in fact <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic>. As is also discussed above, the appearance of <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> in the Paleocene&#x02013;Eocene of the American province is therefore yet another example of homoplasy, where similar characters arose by convergent evolution. True <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> has been reported from Mexico [<xref rid="r92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,<xref rid="r93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] and Guatemala [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. There are no Paleocene records of <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> from the Tethyan province.</p><p>The American <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> gave rise to <italic toggle="yes">Neomurciella</italic>, which made its first appearance in the Selandian of the American province (PZ P3a [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]). <italic toggle="yes">Neomurciella</italic> show a crosswise development of the central and marginal chamberlets, as was found in the Campanian&#x02013;Maastrichtian <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic> gr. <italic toggle="yes">M. renzi</italic> Fleury (see [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]), but this reappearance is 4.4 Ma later than the disappearance of <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Neomurciella</italic> survived the Paleocene&#x02013;Eocene boundary only to disappear within the Early Eocene.</p><p>The American <bold>Fabulariidae</bold> are represented by members of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Fabularia</italic>. This genus evolved for the first time in the American province from the small, primitive form <italic toggle="yes">Miliola</italic> in the Early Eocene (Ypresian, PZ P5b) by developing an involute, biloculine last stage after the early quinqueloculine stage, and thickened vertical partitions, which subdivide the chambers into elongated chamberlets with two tiers in the outer whorls. The two chambers per whorl is a key characteristic of the megalospheric forms (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). The fabulariids were represented in the American province by endemic species, such as <italic toggle="yes">F. vaughani</italic> Cole, <italic toggle="yes">F. cassis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">F. colei</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">F. verseyi</italic>. These species are only found in the Caribbean region [<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="r95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,<xref rid="r96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>] from the Early to Middle Eocene (PZ P6&#x02013;P12a). In the Middle Eocene, Lutetian (PZ P10), the biloculine <italic toggle="yes">Fabularia</italic> (<xref rid="fg007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>) gave rise to <italic toggle="yes">Pseudofabularia</italic> (<xref rid="fg021" ref-type="fig">Plate 3, l</xref>) by developing alveolinid-like pre-septal passages [<xref rid="r97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. The Bartonian&#x02013;Priabonian fabulariid assemblages manifested gigantism, however, they all disappear at the end of the Eocene, except for <italic toggle="yes">Fabularia verseyi</italic>, which survived the Eocene&#x02013;Oligocene extinction, only to die out in the Rupelian [<xref rid="r98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,<xref rid="r99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3b2"><title>The Tethyan Province</title><p>Although the Tethyan province was still the hotspot for <bold>Alveolinidae</bold> diversity, the Paleocene forms evolved independently from their Late Cretaceous relatives (<xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). In the Tethyan province, they re-appeared during the warm Late Paleocene (Thanetian), where they colonised reefal and backreef environments. During the Eocene, they became large and abundant in forereef environments, only to largely disappear by the end of the Eocene.</p><p>Paleogene alveolinids presumably evolved, as did the Cretaceous forms, from <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic> (see [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]). They subsequently develop lineages that are spherical to fusiform in shape, and planispiral in the adult part, exhibiting morphological convergence (homoplasy) with the fusiform/globular alveolinids of the mid-Cretaceous (e.g. the <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic> group). A considerable gap, however, of about 20 Ma exists in the fossil record between the Alveolinidae of the Paleocene and the mid-Cretaceous <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic> group.</p><p>The evolutionary lineages of the Paleogene alveolinids show an incremental increase in the length of the test from pole to pole, from globular through ovoid to elongate, and spindle-shaped. The oldest Paleogene form, <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg021" ref-type="fig">Plate 3, i&#x02013;k</xref>), with a streptoloculine origin and with a fixed axial coiling throughout its ontogeny, is considered the ancestor of <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina</italic> is small, globular and non-flosculinised, with a spherical proloculus in a streptospiral coil and a later planispiral stage. The streptospiral coil still exists in the microspheric forms of <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina. Alveolina</italic> (<xref rid="fg022" ref-type="fig">Plate 4, a&#x02013;j</xref>; <xref rid="fg023" ref-type="fig">Plate 5, a&#x02013;j</xref>; <xref rid="fg024" ref-type="fig">Plate 6, a</xref>) is planispiral&#x02013;fusiform with a single tier of chamberlets in each chamber and, unlike <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina</italic>, shows considerable thickening of the basal layer in the equatorial zone (flosculinisation). Pre-septal and post-septal passages are present in both <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina.</italic></p><fig position="anchor" id="fg022" fig-type="figure"><label>Plate 4</label><caption><p>Scale bars: a&#x02013;j = 1 mm.</p><p>a&#x02013;c. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina globosa</italic> (Leymerie), Ypresian, Eocene, Laki Limestone (Laki Formation), Sakesar Peak in the Salt Range, Pakistan, a) UCL coll.; b) NHM Davies coll.; c) Toraja Formation (Sulawesi), SEA coll., Royal Holloway.</p><p>d&#x02013;f. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina oblonga</italic> d&#x02019;Orbigny, Early Eocene, d&#x02013;e) Dunghan, Siah Koh, UCL coll; f) Chaussy, Val-d&#x02019;Oise, France, UCL coll.</p><p>g. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina leupoldi</italic> Hottinger, Early Eocene, Qumiba section, Tingri, Tibet, Nanjing University.</p><p>h. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina elliptica</italic> (Sowerby), Eocene, Afghanistan, NHM Skinner coll. P7404.</p><p>i. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina corbarica</italic> Hottinger, Early Eocene, Longjiang section, Tibet, Nanjing.</p><p>j. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina daniensis</italic> Drobne, Early Eocene, Ladakh region, India. Sagar Damania, Indian Institute of Technology coll.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g022" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg023" fig-type="figure"><label>Plate 5</label><caption><p>Scale bars: a&#x02013;j = 1 mm.</p><p>a. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina vredenburgi</italic> Davies 1937 (= <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina cucumiformis</italic> Hottinger), topotype, axial section, Late Paleocene, Aquitaine, France, UCL coll.</p><p>b. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina pasticillata</italic> Schwager, Early Eocene, Ladakh region, India, Sagar Damania, Indian Institute of Technology coll.</p><p>c&#x02013;d. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina stipes</italic> Hottinger, Middle Eocene, Ainsa, Spain, UCL coll.</p><p>e. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina solida</italic> Hottinger, Early Eocene, Ladakh region, India, Sagar Damania, Indian Institute of Technology coll.</p><p>f. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina leupoldi</italic>, Hottinger, Early Eocene, Coustouge, France, UCL coll.</p><p>g. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina palermitana</italic> Hottinger, Middle Eocene, Middle Khirthar, Pakistan, UCL coll.</p><p>h. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina vredenburgi</italic> Davies, topotype, equatorial section, Late Paleocene, Aquitaine, France, UCL coll.</p><p>i&#x02013;j. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina subpyrenaica</italic> Leymerie, Early Eocene, Zagros, Iran, UCL coll.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g023" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" id="fg024" fig-type="figure"><label>Plate 6</label><caption><p>Scale bars: a&#x02013;j = 1 mm.</p><p>a&#x02013;b. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina laxa</italic> Fottinger, Early Eocene, Egypt, UCL coll.</p><p>c. <italic toggle="yes">Globoreticulina iranica</italic> Rahaghi, figured by Hottinger [<xref rid="r67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], Middle Eocene, Shiraz, Iran.</p><p>d. <italic toggle="yes">Borelis pygmaeus</italic> Hanzawa, Oligocene, Borneo, 65/9 Loc.205, UCL coll.</p><p>e. <italic toggle="yes">Borelis vonderschmitti</italic> (Schweighauser), Late Eocene, Syria, UCL coll.</p><p>f. <italic toggle="yes">Borelis curdica</italic> (Reichel), Miocene, Turkey, NHM coll.</p><p>g. <italic toggle="yes">Borelis melo</italic> (Fichtel and Moll), Middle Miocene, Turkey, NHM P49087.</p><p>h. <italic toggle="yes">Borelis haueri</italic> (d&#x02019;Orbigny), Middle Miocene, Baden-Brickyard, Baden, Australia, UCL coll.</p><p>i. <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella wichmanni</italic> (Schlumberger), Late Eocene, Indonesia, UCL coll.</p><p>j. <italic toggle="yes">Fabularia discolithus</italic> Defrance, Eocene, calcaire grosier de Rennes, France, NHM Brady coll. P41603.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g024" position="float"/></fig><p>In the Eocene the amount of flosculinisation varies in different species of <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic>, and might be considered to be of specific value only. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> evolve into larger forms through the Eocene, and more than 90 species of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> have been reported in the Mediterranean [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Many of the species reached gigantic sizes (up to 20 mm long [<xref rid="r100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]) before the end of the Middle Eocene, where they become essential members of Eocene carbonate fossil assemblages. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> species, however, became smaller again before completely disappearing at the end of Eocene (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]).</p><p>In the Eocene <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> gave rise to new genera, such as <italic toggle="yes">Globoreticulina</italic> (<xref rid="fg024" ref-type="fig">Plate 6, c</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">Malatyna</italic>, which exhibited similar trends of evolution to the Cretaceous <italic toggle="yes">Subalveolina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Praebullalveolina.</italic> They developed streptospiral nepionts in both generations and a planispiral-involute chamber arrangement in the adult stage of growth [<xref rid="r67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="r101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Both these genera became extinct at the end of the Lutetian.</p><p>Paleoclimatic evidence shows a trend of cooling during late Middle Eocene and at the Eocene&#x02013;Oligocene (E&#x02013;O) boundary ([<xref rid="r102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]; <xref rid="fg013" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>). At the Middle to Late Eocene boundary (37.8 Ma) major changes in global climate and ocean circulation [<xref rid="r102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>] were likely responsible for the disappearance of the gigantic alveolinid species seen at the end of the Bartonian (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). The E&#x02013;O boundary cooling period followed the onset of the Late Eocene rapid sea-level changes, which led to the disappearance of vast carbonate platform and lagoonal environments, and the final extinction of <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic>, and indeed of 85% of all Alveolinoidea. The move into an &#x02018;ice house&#x02019; climate may have been triggered at this time by the opening of the Tasmanian gateway [<xref rid="r103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>].</p><p>The only alveolinid survivors of the E&#x02013;O cooling event were forms related to <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> (<xref rid="fg024" ref-type="fig">Plate 6, d&#x02013;h</xref>), which is in fact an extant alveolinid, and the only one to survive into the Neogene. The appearance of <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> in the Tethyan province in the Bartonian was 6.6 Ma years after the last recorded <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> species in the Paleogene of the American province. Given the magnitude of this gap in the stratigraphic column, we suggest that it is unlikely that this appearance in Tethys was the result of a migration event. We suggest that it is more probable that this appearance in Tethys is yet another example of homoplasy, where re-evolution from a primitive form gave rise to a form in Tethys that was generically similar to the extinct American form, and that it filled the Tethyan niche previously occupied by <italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina.</italic></p><p>In the Tethyan Eocene, <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> is represented by the spheroidal <italic toggle="yes">B. vonderschmitti</italic> (Schweighauser), which was widespread throughout the Bartonian and Priabonian of Western Tethys [<xref rid="r104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> is common in deposits laid down in Early Oligocene, low-latitude, shallow-marine environments, and differs from <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> in having only a pre-septal passage and a secondary small tier of chamberlets, which alternate with the larger ones producing &#x02018;Y&#x02019; shaped septa in the axial section [<xref rid="r106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. In the Oligocene, the sub-spheroidal, small (0.5&#x02013;1.5 mm in diameter and 0.4&#x02013;1.2 mm long), tightly coiled <italic toggle="yes">Borelis inflata</italic> (a form with no Y-shaped septula, see [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]) is also recorded from the Oligocene to the Tortonian of the Western Tethys [<xref rid="r107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>].</p><p>In the Early Oligocene (from about 33.9 Ma), the Drake Passage opened and there was further climatic cooling and ice volume increase ([<xref rid="r102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]; see <xref rid="fg013" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> species, which survived the E&#x02013;O boundary, became adapted to globally cooler environments, while others migrated to the warmer Tethys, such as <italic toggle="yes">B. inflata.</italic></p><p>The Oligocene continue to witness an evolutionary trend of small alveolinids in the Mediterranean, such as <italic toggle="yes">Bullalveolina.</italic> This form evolved from being streptospiral to having a planispiral quinqueloculine test, but unlike the extant <italic toggle="yes">Borelis, Bullalveolina</italic> disappeared at the end of the Oligocene. Generally, however, there were very few notable extinctions of LBF at the end of the Oligocene (see [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). This stratigraphic boundary is probably connected to plate tectonic events, such the development of the Alpine&#x02013;Himalayan orogeny, which were more gradual events and did not seem to trigger major extinctions, or to gradual changes in climate caused by the growing thermal isolation of Antarctica as Australia drifted northwards [<xref rid="r102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>].</p><p>As in the Cretaceous, the Paleogene <bold>Fabulariidae</bold> (mainly the lacazinoform genera, <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella</italic>) are directly derived from the small primitive <italic toggle="yes">Idalina</italic> which survived across the K&#x02013;P boundary (see <xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). Further to the ranges listed in BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], it now seems that the Fabulariidae re-appeared, independently from their Cretaceous counterparts. In doing so, they developed morphologically convergent, homoplasic lineages, which has led to these lineages being given the same generic names as their Cretaceous counterparts. However, we again contend that the considerable stratigraphic gap between their reappearance in the Middle&#x02013;Late Paleocene and the end Cretaceous forms excludes any chance of a direct phylogenetic relationship, other than via a homoplasic repeated evolution from the same <italic toggle="yes">Idalina</italic> common ancestor. There are notable differences between Cretaceous and Paleogene genera, so for example, all Paleogene representatives of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudolacazina</italic> are distinguished from the Cretaceous forms in having lower in shape chambers, subdivided by continuous chamber partitions (septula) (see [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]).</p><p>In the Paleocene, <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudolacazina</italic> echoed the Cretaceous forms, but they uniquely gave rise to Paleogene <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella</italic> by gradual ontogenetic transformation from pluri- to unilocular, completely overlapping growth. The two chambers per whorl is a key characteristic of the megalospheric forms in the fabulariid, however, in <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella</italic>, the microspheric tests have a small initial biloculine stage, followed by uniloculine growth, while their megalospheric tests only show uniloculine development, with a large proloculus. The basal layer of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudolacazina</italic> bears radial pillars supporting the chamber roof that evolve into low longitudinal septula, which do not reach the chamber floor in <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella</italic>, to continuous septula supporting the external chamber wall in <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>].</p><p>The re-appeared <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> is first recorded in Tethys from the Selandian (PZ P4a), while <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella</italic>, having completely overlapping chambers, is rare in the Tethyan province and has not been found in Europe, but is only recorded from Oman and other parts of the Middle East [<xref rid="r113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>].</p><p>On the other hand, the American <italic toggle="yes">Fabularia</italic> spp., which first appeared in the American province in PZ P5b [<xref rid="r96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], appears in Tethys (<xref rid="fg024" ref-type="fig">Plate 6, j</xref>) in the PZ P6b [<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="r111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,<xref rid="r114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. This west to east trans-Atlantic migration coincides with one of two global sea-level low stand in the early Ypresian (migration 5 in <xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Figs 8</xref>, <xref rid="fg013" ref-type="fig">13</xref> and <xref rid="fg014" ref-type="fig">14</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3b3"><title>The Indo-Pacific Province</title><p>We found in our earlier studies of Paleogene rotaliids that migration from Tethys to the Indo-Pacific commonly occurred. Likewise, here we find examples of eastward migration in the Eocene of some <bold>Alveolinidae</bold> into the Indo-Pacific province after their first appearance in Tethys (<xref rid="fg014" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14</xref>). Thus, the first species of <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> appears in the late Ypresian (PZ P9; migration 6 on <xref rid="fg015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15</xref>) in the Indo-Pacific province, compared with its occurrence at the base of Thanetian (PZ P4b) in the Tethys. The Indo-Pacific alveolinids of the Paleogene remained of lower diversity than those of their Tethyan ancestors. Their sizes were smaller (ranging between 7 and 10 mm [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]) and they showed less internal morphological variation. Only a few species have been reported from Indonesia, and many of them are of the <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina oblonga</italic> group of Hottinger [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The Indo-Pacific alveolinids range from the latest Ypresian (P9) to Bartonian [<xref rid="r115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. Other species reported from the Indo-Pacific province include <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina timorensis</italic> Verbeek and <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina ovicula</italic> Nuttall [<xref rid="r116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic>, which first appeared in the Bartonian in Tethyan province, migrated towards the Indo-Pacific through the Tethyan corridor (<xref rid="fg017" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17</xref>), but did not appear in the Indo-Pacific province (migration event 9 in <xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,<xref rid="r117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]) before the Priabonian (PZ P15b; letter stage, Tb). For example, the Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Borelis vonderschmitti</italic> (Schweighauser), which was widespread throughout the Middle&#x02013;Late Eocene in the Western Tethys [<xref rid="r104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>], appeared in the Late Eocene of the Indo-Pacific province [<xref rid="r118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. The Tethyan Oligocene species of <italic toggle="yes">B. inflata</italic> are recorded also from the Oligocene&#x02013;Miocene of Sarawak (Borneo) in the Indo-Pacific area [<xref rid="r118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,<xref rid="r119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. A gradual stratigraphic succession of Indo-Pacific species marked its very slow evolution throughout the Oligocene.</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg017" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 17</label><caption><p>Schematic migration of alveolinoids during Late Paleogene, shown by red arrows, from the Tethyan province to the Indo-Pacific province.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g017" position="float"/></fig><p>Some Tethyan <bold>Fabulariidae</bold> forms also migrated into the Indo-Pacific province [<xref rid="r120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>], where they are represented by <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella. Lacazina</italic> reached the Indo-Pacific (migration 8 in <xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>) in the Bartonian (late P12a) and settled there by the late Eocene. <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> representatives are confined to the northern margin of the Indo-Pacific realm and are found only on an isolated platform of Moluccas [<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella</italic>, restricted to the southern part of the Tethyan province in the early Eocene (Somalia, Oman), first appears in the Lutetian in the Indo-Pacific province (migration 7 in <xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>) and in the Late Eocene (Papua New Guinea). This genus is recorded from Mindoro and Timor, and on remnants of the Australian craton in Indonesia [<xref rid="r122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella</italic> did not survive the E&#x02013;O extinction. <italic toggle="yes">Neolacazopsis</italic>, the representative of the Fabulariidae in the Middle to Late Eocene of Japan, evolved from <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> by developing turtleneck, bottle-like chamberlets and alveolar inner wall instead of arcuate chamberlets [<xref rid="r123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>The Neogene Alveolinoidea</title><p>Only <bold>Alveolinidae</bold> survived into the Neogene. The eastward migration towards the Indo-Pacific province along the Tethyan corridor previously seen in the Paleogene continued into the early Neogene. As species became geographically isolated, the alveolinid distribution showed a distinct provincialism. They colonised new areas in the Indo-Pacific and evolved similar but distinct parallel lineages, taking advantage of empty niches and optimal conditions.</p><sec id="s3c1"><title>The Tethyan/Mediterranean Province</title><p>In the Miocene, the Tethyan alveolinids were represented by species, such as <italic toggle="yes">B. inflata</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Borelis melo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Borelis curdica. Borelis inflata</italic> is recorded as ranging from the Oligocene to the Miocene (Tortonian) of the Western Tethys [<xref rid="r107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,<xref rid="r110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,<xref rid="r124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>], and Zakynthos in Greece [<xref rid="r108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,<xref rid="r109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Borelis melo</italic> with a spheroidal shape and relatively large proloculus (60&#x02013;65 &#x003bc;m) has been reported from the Aquitanian to Messinian in the Tethyan province [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,<xref rid="r106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,<xref rid="r125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. According to Bassi et al. [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>], in <italic toggle="yes">B. melo</italic> the Y-shaped septula occur only in the adult growth stage, while in <italic toggle="yes">B. curdica</italic>, the proloculus is smaller (30&#x02013;50 &#x003bc;m) and the Y-shaped septula occur in all whorls. These authors also postulated that all reliable records of <italic toggle="yes">B. melo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. curdica</italic> are only from Western Tethys, and <italic toggle="yes">B. curdica is</italic> restricted to the Tethyan province. <italic toggle="yes">Borelis melo</italic> ranges from the Aquitanian to the earliest Messinian, while <italic toggle="yes">B. curdica</italic> ranges from the Burdigalian to the Tortonian [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,<xref rid="r106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,<xref rid="r126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>,<xref rid="r128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. For a comprehensive study and complete references to <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> species, the reader is referred to Jones et al. [<xref rid="r133" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>] and Bassi et al. [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>].</p><p>Tethyan alveolinid species became isolated from the Indo-Pacific by the final eastern closure of the Mediterranean basin (<xref rid="fg018" ref-type="fig">Fig. 18</xref>), and finally disappeared from the Mediterranean during the Messinian salinity crisis. However, living <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> species have been reported from the shallow (less than 40 m) continental shelf off Israel [<xref rid="r134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Their re-occurrence in the Eastern Mediterranean with other LBF is attributed by Hyams et al. [<xref rid="r134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>] either to migration from the Atlantic during warm periods of the Pleistocene or Holocene, or to modern migration from the Atlantic, or to modern (Lessepsian) migration from the Red Sea via the Suez Canal. Since the opening of the Suez Canal in 1869, the flow of Lessepsian species (i.e. Indo-Pacific species introduced into the Mediterranean Sea via the canal) has been continuous [<xref rid="r135" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. We suggest that a Lessepsian migration is the most likely way that <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> has recently been introduced to the Eastern Mediterranean, as it is not found in the Western Mediterranean, which would be expected had the migration been from the Atlantic. Furthermore, Hyams et al. [<xref rid="r134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>] figured solid, sub-ellipsoidal specimens morphologically similar to the Indo-Pacific <italic toggle="yes">Borelis schlumbergeri</italic> (Reichel). The Lessepsian origin of this finding is further supported by the fact that <italic toggle="yes">B. schlumbergeri</italic> (Reichel) is to be found in the Northern Bay of Safaga, in the Red sea, close to the southern entrance to the Suez Canal [<xref rid="r136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>].</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg018" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 18</label><caption><p>Schematic distribution of the reported alveolinoids during the Miocene in the Indo-Pacific province.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g018" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c2"><title>The Indo-Pacific Province</title><p>In contrast to the apparent isolation of Tethys forms from the Americas in the Middle and Late Paleogene, migration towards the Indo-Pacific continued in the Oligocene and Early Miocene through the Tethyan seaway (see [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]). In the late Langhian&#x02013;early Serravallian (13&#x02013;14 Ma), a time of several regressions, the short-lived marine reconnection between the Mediterranean and Indian Ocean again closed [<xref rid="r137" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. This final closure brought all migration towards the Indo-Pacific province to an end, and coincided with the onset of a global cooling period. By the time the East Antarctic Ice Sheet was established (12 Ma), the forereef LBF such as the miogypsinids and lepidocyclinids had become extinct or very rare in the Indo-Pacific sub-province [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], while the isolated backreef LBF in the Indo-Pacific developed new survival characters. The small primitive <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> in Middle to Late Miocene shallow-water settings became rare and was gradually replaced by forms with more evolved characters [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], such as <italic toggle="yes">Flosculinella</italic> (<xref rid="fg025" ref-type="fig">Plate 7, a&#x02013;b</xref>) with double rows of chamberlets on the floor of each chamber, and the elongated fusiform <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic> with several rows of chamberlets in axial section. The superposed regular layers of chamberlets separated by floors in <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic> (<xref rid="fg025" ref-type="fig">Plate 7, c&#x02013;g</xref>) are analogous structures found in the mid-Cretaceous <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic>, and are different from the irregular, tubular, supplementary chamberlets present in the thickened basal layers of the Paleogene <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> [<xref rid="r67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. They re-appear, through convergent evolution (homoplasy), millions of years after their earlier extinction, as they are selected for by the changed ecological conditions developed in the Middle Miocene.</p><fig position="anchor" id="fg025" fig-type="figure"><label>Plate 7</label><caption><p>Scale bars: a&#x02013;g = 1 mm.</p><p>a. <italic toggle="yes">Flosculinella globulosa</italic> (Rutten), Early Miocene (lowermost Burdigalian), Indonesia, UCL coll.</p><p>b. <italic toggle="yes">Flosculinella bontangensis</italic> (Rutten), late Early Miocene (Burdigalian, lower Tf1), Borneo, UCL coll.</p><p>c. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella praequoyi</italic> Wonders and Adams, holotype, early Middle Miocene (upper Tf1&#x02013;Tf2), Darai Limestone, Papua New Guinea, NHM P52658.</p><p>d. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella fennemai</italic> Checchia-Rispoli, late Early Miocene (Burdigalian), Borneo, UCL coll.</p><p>e&#x02013;g. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella quoyi</italic> (d Orbigny), Holocene, e) Sekau, formation SEA coll., Royal Holloway; f) Port Moresby, Coral Sea, New Guinea, UCL coll; g) Pacific, UCL coll.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ucloe-03-015-g025" position="float"/></fig><p>Over the Neogene Period, Indo-Pacific alveolinids underwent a very slow evolution, but notably include <italic toggle="yes">Borelis pygmaeus</italic> (which persists to the top of the Te stage [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]). This species is recorded from Oligocene to Lower Miocene deposits [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="r118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,<xref rid="r119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>], but is suddenly replaced by a more advanced form <italic toggle="yes">Flosculinella bontangensis</italic> (<xref rid="fg025" ref-type="fig">Plate 7, b</xref>), with an incremental increase in the length of the test from pole to pole, changing from globular, to ovoid, to elongated spindle-shaped, and with an equally incremental increase in the number of secondary chamberlets (&#x02018;mansardes&#x02019;) from zero in <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> through to one in <italic toggle="yes">Flosculinella</italic> to several rows of chamberlets in <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella.</italic> Parallel lineages have each developed with the acquisition of an additional row of chamberlets in the <italic toggle="yes">Borelis&#x02013;Flosculinella</italic> lineage. This must have occurred at least twice during Te&#x02013;Tf interval (Early&#x02013;Middle Miocene). An example of one of these lineages is seen with the appearance of <italic toggle="yes">Flosculinella reicheli</italic> within the Early Miocene (upper Te) and of <italic toggle="yes">F. bontangensis</italic> (<xref rid="fg025" ref-type="fig">Plate 7, b</xref>) in the early Middle Miocene (just at the top of the Te stage). The latter gave rise to <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella praequoyi</italic> (<xref rid="fg025" ref-type="fig">Plate 7, c</xref>) in the Serravallian, at the base of Tf2 stage. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella praequoyi</italic> has early whorls akin to <italic toggle="yes">F. bontangensis</italic>, but in the latter the chamberlets of each whorl are covered by at least two layers of smaller chamberlets. In <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella quoyi</italic> (<xref rid="fg009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>; <xref rid="fg025" ref-type="fig">Plate 7, e&#x02013;g</xref>), in the Tf3 stage, all of the whorls have a multiple layer of chamberlets. <italic toggle="yes">Flosculinella bontangensis</italic> grades into forms of <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic> at about the same time as the onset of the global cooling. <italic toggle="yes">Alveolinella</italic> today appear to be confined to normal shallow marine (down to depths of 80 m), clear, well-oxygenated, tropical and subtropical waters [<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="r138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>].</p><p>Different parallel lineages of <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> spp. evolved in the Indo-Pacific area. Those with Y-shaped septula such as <italic toggle="yes">B. pygmaeus</italic> are recorded in the Indo-Pacific from the Rupelian to latest Burdigalian (uppermost upper Te [<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]), while other lineages without the Y-shaped septula in the juvenile stage, such as <italic toggle="yes">B. schlumbergeri</italic>, are recorded from the Tortonian to Holocene [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,<xref rid="r139" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,<xref rid="r140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>].</p><p>Bassi et al. [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>] assigned the Indo-Pacific Oligocene to Early Miocene species of <italic toggle="yes">Borelis primitiva</italic> (described from an Upper Oligocene limestone from Eniwetok [<xref rid="r141" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>]), <italic toggle="yes">Borelis globose, Borelis boninensis</italic> (described from the Rupelian of east Mindanao and from the the Bonin Islands [<xref rid="r118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,<xref rid="r142" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]), and the specimen of <italic toggle="yes">B. melo</italic> (reported by BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] from the Serravallian of Australia), to <italic toggle="yes">Borelis pulchra</italic>. They based their conclusion on the absence of Y-shaped septula and the proloculus size of <italic toggle="yes">B. pulchra</italic>. In our opinion, however, these species all have specific characteristics and are separated by time and space from <italic toggle="yes">B. pulchra.</italic> We suggest, therefore, that they should still be treated as separate species.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Borelis inflata</italic>, which first appeared in the Oligocene of Tethys, migrated rapidly into the Indo-Pacific province, and has been described from the Oligocene to Lower Miocene of Sarawak (Borneo) in the Indo-Pacific area [<xref rid="r118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,<xref rid="r119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3c3"><title>The American Province</title><p>The alveolinids were absent from the Neogene of the American province before the early Piacenzian closure of the Central America seaway (<xref rid="fg013" ref-type="fig">Figs 13</xref> and <xref rid="fg016" ref-type="fig">16</xref>). Today, they are represented by <italic toggle="yes">B. pulchra</italic> (d&#x02019;Orbigny), which is recorded from present-day sands of Cuba, Florida and from Jarvis Island [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,<xref rid="r138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,<xref rid="r143" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>].</p><p>There are no records for this species from the Mediterranean, nor would we contend from the Indo-Pacific (see above). Bassi et al. [<xref rid="r105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>], however, suggest that Indo-Pacific forms are synonyms of <italic toggle="yes">B. pulchra</italic> and proposed that there was a migration eastwards from the Indo-Pacific across the Pacific and through the Central America Seaway, before its closure in the Pliocene (<xref rid="fg013" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>). However, despite being strong advocates for the dispersal of LBFs by trans-oceanic migration, because in our opinion the Pacific species are distinct from the American <italic toggle="yes">B. pulchra</italic>, we favour the suggestion that <italic toggle="yes">B. pulchra</italic> is another example of homoplasy, just as we suggest that the Middle Eocene Tethyan origin of <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> was distinct from that of the early Paleogene American forms.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The synthesis described here of the alveolinoids, over an expanded, globally comprehensive geographic area and stratigraphic range, has enabled a more coherent view of their phylogenetic and palaeogeographic evolution to be established, and provides an update to the description presented in BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Two significant characteristics of their evolution and development will be discussed below in further detail, namely those of homoplasy, and of provincialism punctuated by trans-oceanic migration.</p><p>The traits of convergent evolution exhibited by the alveolinoids fall into two distinct types: those in which gross external morphology of forms echo the shape of previous LBF forms, and those in which the internal test morphology is reproduced in forms that are not directly consanguineous. As noted above, an extreme example of ecologically driven convergent evolution involving forms from different orders is exhibited in the external appearance of alveolinoids that closely resemble the planispiral, fusiform fusulinides of the late Paleozoic.</p><p>More confusingly from the taxonomic and phylogenetic viewpoint, however, are the second type of homoplasy, where due to a predisposition to repeated genetic mutations, forms with the same or similar generic characteristics repeatedly appear within a family over time. When these characteristics are similar but not identical, they can lead to the misidentification of forms, as for example, in the rhapydioninids, where some Cretaceous Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic> have been misidentified as <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic>. As noted above, true <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic> appeared only in the Paleogene of the American, and can be characterised by having a streptospiral nepiont in both megalospheric and microspheric generations, and by being smaller than <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic>.</p><p>Another example of homoplasy is one that gives rise to very similar forms within the same family, but which are separated by a larger stratigraphic interval. So, for example, following their Cretaceous predecessors, Paleogene alveolinids re-appeared from <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonummuloculina</italic>, giving rise to the <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> lineage. These Paleogene forms are morphologically convergent with the fusiform/globular alveolinids of the mid-Cretaceous characterised by the <italic toggle="yes">Praealveolina</italic> group. There are generic differences to the detailed test structure of these two lineages, as well as a considerable gap of about 20 Ma in the fossil record, so there is no doubt that they represent distinct, homoplasic stages of evolution within the Alveolinidae. The same is not true, however, for the Late Cretaceous and Early Paleogene fabulariids. Here, the Paleocene <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina</italic> lineage (including <italic toggle="yes">Pseudolacazina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic>) echoed the Cretaceous forms so closely that they are generically indistinguishable. There is however a gap of over 6 Ma between the K&#x02013;P boundary and the first Paleogene occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina</italic> in the Selandian. These Paleogene genera could be considered to be Lazarus taxa, which Wignall and Benton [<xref rid="r146" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>] explain thus, &#x02018;At times of biotic crisis many taxa go extinct, but others only temporarily disappeared from the fossil record, often for intervals measured in millions of years, before reappearing unchanged.&#x02019; Wignall and Benton [<xref rid="r146" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>] suggest that the reappearance of Lazarus taxa in the fossil record probably reflects the rebound after a period of extreme rarity during the aftermath of a global extinction. Here, however, we prefer another explanation, namely that, as with the <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> lineage, the Paleogene <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina</italic> lineage is an example of homoplasic re-evolution from a small, simple form that survived the K&#x02013;P extinction. However, unlike <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> we suggest that, for the Paleogene <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina</italic> lineage, the homoplasy produced forms so close to the previous Cretaceous forms as to be generically indistinguishable.</p><p>A further example of a form that could be a Lazarus taxa or an example of homoplasy, is given by <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic>. The American <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> is reported from the Middle Paleocene to the Early Eocene (PZ P&#x02013;P9), while the first occurrence of the Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> is in the Bartonian of Western Tethys. These occurrences are separated by 6.6 Ma in the geological column, and by an ocean. American <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> has aligned septula and pre-septal passages, and they are in general smaller in size than those of the Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic>. This, and the challenge of the concept of &#x02018;the rebound after a period of extreme rarity&#x02019; of a form into a province displaced from its original realm, leads us to propose that American <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> and Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> are likely also to be examples of homoplasy. This potential tension between the concepts of Lazarus taxa and of homoplasy is worthy of further exploration elsewhere.</p><p>We now turn to the second notable feature of the development of the Alveolinoidea, namely their distinct global pattern of provincialism and the episodes of trans-oceanic migration, similar to behaviour previously observed in other LBFs (e.g. [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r147" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,<xref rid="r148" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]). The three main alveolinoid provinces were those of the Americas, Tethys and the Indo-Pacific. We have previously demonstrated that the Cretaceous agglutinated orbitolinids originated in Tethys, but underwent periodic westward trans-oceanic migration to the Americas during periods of global sea-level low stands [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In this study, we have confirmed that the Tethyan province also remained the palaeogeographic centre for the porcelaneous alveolinids, and that they inhabited similar ecological habitats throughout the Cretaceous and Paleogene. It has been inferred here for the first time that a westward palaeogeographic migration of some alveolinid genera also occurred in the mid-Cretaceous from the Tethys to the Americas (migrations 1&#x02013;3, <xref rid="fg011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>), while the Late Cretaceous alveolinids remained mainly isolated (migration 4, <xref rid="fg011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>). On the other hand, in the Paleogene we saw limited eastward migration from the American province towards Tethys (<italic toggle="yes">Fabularia</italic> in the Ypresian, PZ P6b; migration 5, <xref rid="fg015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15</xref>). On the other hand, migrations from Tethys towards the Indo-Pacific region continued till the closure of the Tethyan corridor and the isolation of the Mediterranean in the Serravallian (migrations 6&#x02013;9, <xref rid="fg008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). As noted, we have shown that most cosmopolitan alveolinoids appeared in Tethys before migrating to other provinces. Likewise, we have seen that once established in the American and Indo-Pacific provinces, local provincial forms evolved, indicating that they were periodically effectively isolated from the Tethyan province. These characteristics have been observed in previous studies of Mesozoic [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and Cenozoic LBF, specifically the lepidocyclinids [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], the miogypsinids [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], the nummulitoids [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r149" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>] and the orthophragminids [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r150" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. The periods of migration from one province to another were often followed by subsequent isolation and development of local provincial lineages. These migrations were often associated with major sea-level regressions, while the subsequent provincial isolation coincided with global sea-level transgressions. This study has, therefore, further tested the migration hypothesis highlighted by Pignatti [<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], and has confirmed the wider application of the ideas initially put forward by BouDagher-Fadel and Price [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We have resynthesised the literature on the occurrence and distribution of the alveolinoids, and augmented this information with observations on new materials from the Americas, Europe, the Middle East, Tibet and South-East Asia. We have produced a global correlation and integration of the occurrences and stratigraphic ranges of members of the three alveolinoid families, namely the Alveolinidae, the Fabulariidae and the Rhapydioninidae, based upon the planktonic foraminiferal zonal scheme of BouDagher-Fadel [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In the Cretaceous, alveolinoids are found in the Tethyan and American provinces, while of the later Cenozoic forms, Alveolinidae and Fabulariidae are found in three provinces (Tethys, American and the Indo-Pacific), while the Rhapydioninidae are constrained to the Americas.</p><p>Alveolinoids characteristically exhibit convergent evolution, with the repeated re-occurrence of certain morphological features. This homoplasy is predominantly of two types, one which recapitulates the gross external morphology of forms, and one in which the internal test morphology is also reproduced, even to the level of regenerating forms with the same generic characteristics.</p><p>We have shown that no alveolinoid survived the K&#x02013;P extinction, but that members of all three families re-appeared from small miliolids that were resilient enough to pass into the Paleogene. Specifically, we have concluded that:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Cretaceous Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic> has on occasion been misidentified as a <italic toggle="yes">Raadshoovenia</italic>, which in fact is an American Paleocene form.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">Fabularia</italic> originated in the Americas at the beginning of the Ypresian, but soon thereafter migrated to Tethys.</p></list-item><list-item><p>There is a gap of over 6 Ma between the last occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">Periloculina, Pseudolacazina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lacazina</italic> in the Cretaceous and their re-appearance in the Paleogene, and that these taxa are most likely to be examples of homoplasic evolution from a small, simple form that survived the K&#x02013;P extinction.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The 6.6 Ma gap between American <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> and Tethyan <italic toggle="yes">Borelis</italic> suggests that they are likely also to be examples of homoplasy.</p></list-item></list><p>Finally, our previously developed hypothesis that periodic, sea-level lows enable inter-provincial migration of LBF is strongly supported, and that the behaviour and directions of migration of the alveolinoids is resonant with those of the orbitolinids, the orthophragminids, the nummulitoids, the miogypsinids and the lepidocyclinids. Migration occurred from East to West in the Cretaceous, but was dominated by migration from West to East in the Cenozoic.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Prof. Hu Xumian and Jingxin Jiang, Yiwei Xu, Gaoyuan Sun, Wen Lai, PhD students, School of Earth Sciences and Engineering and Engineering, Nanjing University, for their assistance in sampling theTibetian and Iranian sections; Sagar Damania, National Stable Isotope Facility, Indian Institute of Technology; Dr. Peter Scholle, Scholle Petrographic, LLC, Greece; and Prof. S&#x000e9;bastien Castelltort, Department of Earth Sciences, University of Geneva, Switzerland, for their collaboration and in providing us with samples from India, Greece and Spain. We are also grateful to the South East Asia Research Group, Royal Holloway College, and the Natural History Museum for allowing us access to their material. We are indebted to Prof Johann Hohenegger, University of Vienna, and Prof. Pamela Hallock, University of South Florida for carefully and thoroughly reviewing our paper.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declarations and conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest in connection to this article.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Open data and data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article (and its supplementary information files).</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>[1]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Evolution and geological significance of larger Benthic Foraminifera</source><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>UCL Press</publisher-name><year>2018a</year><size units="page">p. 704</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>[2]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Global evolution and paleogeographic distribution of mid-Cretaceous orbitolinids</article-title><source>UCL Open &#x02013; Environment</source><year>2019</year><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14324/111.444/ucloe.000001</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>[3]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Evolution and paleogeographic distribution of the lepidocyclinids</article-title><source>J Foraminiferal Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2113/gsjfr.40.1.79</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>[4]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The phylogenetic and palaeogeographic evolution of the miogypsinid larger benthic foraminifera</article-title><source>J Geol Soc</source><year>2013</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/jgs2011-149</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>[5]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The phylogenetic and palaeogeographic evolution of the nummulitoid larger benthic foraminifera</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>2014</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>508</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>[6]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The paleogeographic evolution of the orthophragminids of the paleogene</article-title><source>J Foraminiferal Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2113/gsjfr.47.4.337</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>[7]</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pignatti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Review. Global evolution and paleogeographic distribution of mid-Cretaceous orbitolinids</source><year>2019</year><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14293/S2199-1006.1.SOR-EARTH.AZZFBB.v1.RVGYLO</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>[8]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Uber paleocaene und eocaene Alveolinen</article-title><source>Eclogae Geol Helv</source><year>1960</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>[9]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ciry</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>&#x000c0; propos de Meandropsina larrazeti Mun.-Chalm., generotype d&#x02019;un genre nouveau Larrazetia Ciry</article-title><source>Rev de Micropaleontol</source><year>1964</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>[10]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Chubbina</italic>, a new Cretaceous alveolinid genus from Jamaica and Mexico</article-title><source>Palaeontology</source><year>1968</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>[11]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Viallard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Recherches sur le cycle alpin dans la Chaine iberique sud-occidentale</part-title><source>Th&#x000e8;se, Travaux du laboratorie de g&#x000e9;ologie m&#x000e9;diterran&#x000e9;enne</source><publisher-name>Univ&#x000e9;rsit&#x000e9; Paul Sabatier</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Tolouse</publisher-loc><year>1973</year><size units="page">p. 445</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>[12]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Contribution a la connaissance des Rhapydionininae (Foraminif&#x000e9;res, Alveolinidae) cr&#x000e9;tac&#x000e9;s</article-title><source>Geobios</source><year>1974</year><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0016-6995(74)80013-6</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>[13]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chaproniere</surname><given-names>GCH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Neogene larger foraminiferal sequence in the Australian and New Zealand regions, and its relevance to the East Indies letter stage classification</article-title><source>Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol</source><year>1984</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-0182(84)90023-3</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>[14]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leppig</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Biostratigraphy of larger foraminifera and facies development from the Upper Albian to the Middle Paleocene in the Sierra de Cantabria and the Montes Obarenes (Northwestern Spain)</article-title><source>Neues Jahrb Geol Pal&#x000e4;ontol &#x02013; Monatshefte Jg</source><year>1987</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1127/njgpm/1987/1987/647</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>[15]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Late cretaceous, larger, complex miliolids (foraminifera) endemic in the Pyrenean faunal province</article-title><source>Facies</source><year>1989</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf02536833</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>[16]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Serra-Kiel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferr&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaurhi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Larger foraminiferal biostratigraphy of the Tethyan Paleocene and Eocene</article-title><source>Bull Soc Geol Fr</source><year>1998</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>[17]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vicedo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calonge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Cenomanian rhapydioninids (Foraminiferida): architecture of the shell and stratigraphy</article-title><source>J Foraminiferal Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2113/gsjfr.41.1.41</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>[18]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vicedo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frijia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Late Cretaceous alveolinaceans (larger foraminifera) of the Caribbean palaeobioprovince and their stratigraphic distribution</article-title><source>J Syst Palaeontol</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14772019.2011.637517</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>[19]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vicedo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berlanga</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Serra-Kiel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Paleocene larger foraminifera from the Yucat&#x000e1;n Peninsula (SE Mexico)</article-title><source>Brest, <italic toggle="yes">Carnets de G&#x000e9;ologie</italic> [<italic toggle="yes">Notebooks on Geology</italic>]</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4267/2042/53527</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>[20]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vicedo V and Piuz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Evolutionary trends and biostratigraphical application of new Cenomanian alveolinoids (Foraminifera) from the Natih Formation of Oman</article-title><source>J Syst Palaeontol</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14772019.2016.1244709</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>[21]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Acar</surname><given-names>&#x0015e;</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Descriptions, systematics and revisions of the subgenera <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Glomalveolina</italic>) Hottinger, 1960 and <italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Alveolina</italic>) d&#x02019;Orbigny, 1826 (Foraminiferida)</article-title><source>Bull Min Res Exp</source><year>2019</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>[22]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bozkurt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gormus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Description criteria for eocene alveolinids: examples from inner Western Anatolia</article-title><source>IOP Conf Ser: Earth Environ Sci</source><year>2019</year><fpage>362</fpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1755-1315/362/1/012019</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>[23]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bakx</surname><given-names>LAJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>De genera <italic toggle="yes">Fasciolites</italic> en <italic toggle="yes">Neoalveolina</italic> in het Indo-Pacifische gebied</article-title><source>Verhandelingen van het Koninklijk Nederlandsch Geologisch en Mijnbouwkundig Genootschap voor Nederland en Koloni&#x000eb;n</source><year>1932</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>[24]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Biostratigraphic and geological significance of planktonic foraminifera</source><edition>2nd ed</edition><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>UCL Press</publisher-name><year>2015</year><size units="page">p. 320</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>[25]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Revised diagnostic first and last occurrences of Mesozoic and Cenozoic planktonic foraminifera</source><publisher-name>UCL Office of the Vice-Provost Research, Professional Papers Series, UCL Press</publisher-name><year>2018b</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>[26]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gradstein</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ogg</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ogg</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>The geologic time scale</source><publisher-loc>Amsterdam, Boston</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>2012</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>[27]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boudagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Revision of the stratigraphic significance of the Oligocene&#x02013;Miocene &#x0201c;Letter-Stages&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Rev de Micropaleontol</source><year>1999</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0035-1598(99)90095-8</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>[28]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schaub</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Nummulites et Assilines de la Tethys pal&#x000e9;ogene. Taxonomy, phylogen&#x000e8;se et biostratigraphie</article-title><source>Schweiz Pal&#x000e4;ontol Abh</source><year>1981</year><volume>104&#x02013;106</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>236</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>[29]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Some tertiary foraminifera</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Atlas of Paleobiogeography</source><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>1973</year><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>[30]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Selected Paleogene larger foraminifera</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Atlas of Palaeobiogeography</source><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>1973</year><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>[31]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Larger miliolid foraminifera in time and space. Academie Serbe Sciences et Arts, Bulletin T</article-title><source>CXXVIII; Sciences Naturelles</source><year>2004</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>[32]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x00106;osovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Palaeobiogeography of the Late Cretaceous to Paleogene larger miliolids from tropical to subtropical-sea belts (Neotethys to Caribbean)</article-title><source>Bull Soc Geol Fr</source><year>2009</year><volume>180</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2113/gssgfbull.180.4.317</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>[33]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Comparative anatomy of selected foraminiferal shell structures</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Headley</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>Foraminifera III</source><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><year>1978</year><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>[34]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lipps</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Photosymbiosis: the driving force for reef success and failure</article-title><source>Corals and Reefs: Crises, Collapse and Change</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s1089332600002436</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>[35]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hallock</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Why are larger foraminifera large?</article-title><source>Paleobiology</source><year>1985</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0094837300011507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>[36]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Functional morphology of benthic foraminiferal shells, envelopes of cells beyond measure</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>2000</year><volume>46</volume><issue>Suppl. 1</issue><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>[37]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Alveolinidae</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Treatise on Invertebrate Paleontology, C (Protista 2)</source><publisher-loc>Boulder/Lawrence</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Geological Society of America/University of Kansas Press</publisher-name><year>1964</year><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>[38]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dilley</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Cretaceous larger foraminifera</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Atlas of Palaeobiogeography</source><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>1973</year><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>[39]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hohenegger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Coenoclines of larger foraminifera</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>2000</year><volume>46</volume><issue>Suppl. 1</issue><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>[40]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>The Gulf of Aqaba: ecological micropaleontology</part-title><source>Ecological Studies</source><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><year>1984</year><volume>p. 50</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>354</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>[41]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Veli&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Stratigraphy and Palaeobiogeography of Mesozoic Benthic Foraminifera of the Karst Dinarides (SE Europe) &#x02013; PART 1</article-title><source>Geol Croat</source><year>2007</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>113</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><label>[42]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luperto-Sinni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Microfaune del Cretaceo delle Murge baresi</article-title><source>Geol Romana</source><year>1966</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r43"><label>[43]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calvez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Deux Foraminif&#x000e8;res nouveaux de l&#x02019;Albien calcaire des Pyr&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;es franco-espagnoles Pseudonummoloculina aurigerica n. gen., n. sp. et Dobrogelina? angulata n. sp. <italic toggle="yes">Benthos &#x02018;86</italic>. R&#x000e9;sum&#x000e9;s Abstracts</article-title><source>Gen&#x000e8;ve: Museum d&#x02019;Histoire Naturelle</source><year>1988</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><label>[44]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Husinec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veli&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vlahovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mati&#x0010d;ec</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O&#x00161;tri&#x00107;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korbar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mid Cretaceous orbitolinid (Foraminiferida) record from the islands of Cres and Lo&#x00161;inj (Croatia) and its regional stratigraphic correlation</article-title><source>Cretac Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/cres.2000.0203</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><label>[45]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krobicki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olszewska</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Urgonian-type microfossils in exotic pebbles of the Late Cretaceous and Palaeogene gravel stones from the Sromowce and Jarmuta formations (Pieniny Klippen Belt, Polish Carpathians)</article-title><source>Studia Geologica Polonica, Krak&#x000f3;w</source><year>2005</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><label>[46]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mancinelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiocchini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Cretaceous benthic foraminifers and calcareous algae from Monte Cairo (Southern Latium, Italy)</article-title><source>Boll Soc Paleontol Ital</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>113</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><label>[47]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schlagintweit</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rashidi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Some new and poorly known benthic foraminifera from late Maastrichtian shallow-water carbonates of the Zagros zone, SW Iran</article-title><source>Acta Palaeontol Roman</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r48"><label>[48]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loeblich</surname><given-names>AR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Tappan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Foraminiferal genera and their classification</source><comment>two volumes</comment><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Van Nostrand Reinhold</publisher-name><year>1988</year><size units="page">p. 2047</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r49"><label>[49]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brasier</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Some geometrical aspects of fusiform planispiral shape in larger foraminifera</article-title><source>J Micropalaeontol</source><year>1984</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/jm.3.1.11</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r50"><label>[50]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vicedo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Fusiform and laterally compressed alveolinaceans (Foraminiferida) from both sides of the Late Cretaceous Atlantic</article-title><source>Neues Jahrb Geol Pal&#x000e4;ontol</source><year>2009</year><volume>253</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1127/0077-7749/2009/0253-0229</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r51"><label>[51]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamaoui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fourcade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>R&#x000e9;vision de Rhapydionimae (alveolinidae, foraminif&#x000e8;res)</article-title><source>Bulletin des Centres de Recherches Exploration &#x02013; Production Elf-Aquitaine</source><year>1973</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>435</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r52"><label>[52]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Distribution, Diversity and Functional Morphology of Benthic Foraminifera from Vulcano (Mediterranean Sea)</part-title><source>Unpublished Ph.D. Thesis</source><publisher-name>University of Basel</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Switzerland</publisher-loc><year>1989</year><size units="page">p. 159</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r53"><label>[53]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Epiphytic foraminifera</article-title><source>Mar Micropaleontol</source><year>1993</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0377-8398(93)90035-V</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r54"><label>[54]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silk</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Photophile and sciaphile foraminifera from Lavezzi Island, Corsica</article-title><source>Rev Pal&#x000e9;obiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r55"><label>[55]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldbeck</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Biogeographic provinces and patterns of diversity in selected upper Cretaceous (Santonian&#x02013;Maastrichtian) larger foraminifera</source><publisher-name>SEPM (Society for Sedimentary Geology)</publisher-name><year>2009</year><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>232</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r56"><label>[56]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Castro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title><italic toggle="yes">Pseudorhapydionina dubia</italic> (De Castro, 1965). <italic toggle="yes">Pseudorhapydionina laurinensis</italic> (De Castro, 1965). <italic toggle="yes">Pseudorhipidionina casertana</italic> (De Castro, 1965)</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Les grands Foraminif&#x000e8;res du Cr&#x000e9;tac&#x000e9; moyen de la region m&#x000e9;diterran&#x000e9;enne. Geobios, M&#x000e9;moire sp&#x000e9;ciale</source><year>1985</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r57"><label>[57]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Castro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Osservazioni su Raadshoovenia van den Bold, e i suoi col nuovo genere Scandonea (Foraminiferida, Miliolacea)</article-title><source>Boll Soc Nat Napoli</source><year>1971</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>235</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r58"><label>[58]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Deux Rhapydionininae (Foraminif&#x000e8;res, Alveolinidae) d&#x02019;affinit&#x000e9;s am&#x000e9;ricaines dans le Cr&#x000e9;tac&#x000e9; sup&#x000e9;rieur de Gr&#x000e8;ce (zone de Gavrovo-Tripolitza)</article-title><source>Rev de Micropal&#x000e9;ontol</source><year>1977</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r59"><label>[59]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luperto Sinni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ricchetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Studio micropaleontologicostratigrafico di una successione carbonatica del Cretac&#x000e8;o superior rilevata nel sottosuolo delle Murge sud-orientali</article-title><source>Riv Italiana di Paleontologia e Stratigrafia</source><year>1978</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>666</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r60"><label>[60]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bignot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blondeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poignant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Biogeographie de Foraminif&#x000e8;res tethysiens du S&#x000e9;nonien a l&#x02019;Eoc&#x000e8;ne sup&#x000e9;rieur</article-title><source>Bull Soc Geol Fr</source><year>1985</year><volume>I</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r61"><label>[61]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caffau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plenicar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pugliese</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Late Maastrichtian rudists and microfossils in the Karst region (NE Italy and Slovenia)</article-title><source>Geobios</source><year>1998</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0016-6995(98)80063-6</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r62"><label>[62]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldbeck</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Biogeographic provinces and patterns of diversity in selected Upper Cretaceous (Santonian-Maastrichtian) larger foraminifera</source><publisher-name>SEPM (Society for Sedimentary Geology)</publisher-name><year>2009</year><comment>SEPM Special Publication No. 93</comment><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>232</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r63"><label>[63]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fourcade</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Murciella cuvillieri</italic> n. gen. n. sp. nouveau foraminif&#x000e8;re du S&#x000e9;nonien sup&#x000e9;rieur du sud-est de l&#x02019;Espagne</article-title><source>Rev de Micropal&#x000e9;ontol</source><year>1966</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r64"><label>[64]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Le crible apertural de <italic toggle="yes">Rhapydionina liburnica</italic> Stache du Maastrichtien de Vremski-Britof, Yugoslavie</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Oertli</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Benthos&#x02019; 83</source><publisher-loc>Paris, France</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elf-Aquitaine</publisher-name><year>1984</year><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r65"><label>[65]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Le genre <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic> (Foraminif&#x000e8;re, Rhapydionininae), dans le Cr&#x000e9;tac&#x000e9; sup&#x000e9;rieur de Gr&#x000e8;ce (zone de Gavrovo-Tripolitza)</article-title><source>Geobios</source><year>1979</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0016-6995(79)80078-9</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r66"><label>[66]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Foraminifera</source><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>MacMillan</publisher-name><year>1981</year><size units="page">p. 433</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r67"><label>[67]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Illustrated glossary of terms used in foraminiferal research</article-title><source>Carnets de G&#x000e9;ologie/Notebooks on Geology, Memoir</source><year>2006/02</year><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4267/2042/5832</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r68"><label>[68]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Les grandes Miliolids des couches paleocenes de la Yougoslavie du Nord-Ouest (<italic toggle="yes">Idalina, Fabularia, Lacazina, Periloculina</italic>)</article-title><source>Razprave IV, razr, SAZU</source><year>1974</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r69"><label>[69]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Shallow benthic foraminiferal assemblages as signals for depth of their deposition and their limitations</article-title><source>Bull Soc G&#x000e9;ol Fr</source><year>1997</year><volume>168/4</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>505</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r70"><label>[70]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Foraminif&#x000e8;res rotaliformes et Orbito&#x000ef;des du S&#x000e9;nonien Inf&#x000e9;rieur Pyr&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;en</article-title><source>Eclogae Geol Helv</source><year>1966</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>301</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r71"><label>[71]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Particularidades de la fauna (foramin&#x000ec;feros) del Cret&#x000e1;cico superior pirenaico</article-title><source>Paleontolgia &#x000ec; Evoluci&#x000f3;</source><year>1986</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r72"><label>[72]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Upper Cretaceous larger foraminifera: paleoecological distribution</article-title><source>Rev Pal&#x000e9;obiol</source><year>1988</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r73"><label>[73]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kominz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mountain</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>The phanerozoic record of global sea-level change</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1116412</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16311326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r74"><label>[74]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bonet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Zonificacion microfaunistica de las calizas Cretacicas del este de Mexico</article-title><source>Bolet&#x000ed;n de la Asociaci&#x000f3;n Mexicana de Ge&#x000f3;logos Petroleros</source><year>1956</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r75"><label>[75]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Cretaceous stratigraphy, paleontology, petrography, depositional environments, and cycle stratigraphy at Cerro de Cristo Rey, Do&#x000f1;a Ana County</article-title><source>New Mexico Geology</source><year>2015</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r76"><label>[76]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oma&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Doncel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alencaster</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Caballero</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mid&#x02013;late Cenomanian larger benthic foraminifers from the El Abra Formation W Valles-San Luis Potosi Platform, central&#x02013;eastern Mexico: taxonomy, biostratigraphy and paleoenvironmental implications</article-title><source>Boletin de la Soc Geol Mex</source><year>2019</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18268/bsgm2019v71n3a5</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r77"><label>[77]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conkin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Revision of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Nummoloculina</italic> and emendation of <italic toggle="yes">Nummoloculina heimi</italic> Bonet</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>1958</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1484300</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r78"><label>[78]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fourcade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tardy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vila</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Streptalveolina mexicana</italic> n. gen. n. sp., un Alveolinidae nouveau (Foraminif&#x000e8;re) du C&#x000e9;nomanien du Mexique</article-title><source>Rev de Micropaleontol</source><year>1975</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r79"><label>[79]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Upper Albian benthic foraminifers new in West Texas</article-title><source>J Foraminiferal Re</source><year>2002</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2113/0320043</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r80"><label>[80]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Sequence stratigraphy of comanchean cretaceous outcrop strata of Northeast and South-Central Texas: implications for enhanced petroleum exploration</article-title><source>Transactions Gulf Coast Association of Geological Societies</source><year>2006</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r81"><label>[81]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Castro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Cisalveolina fraasi</italic> (G&#x000fc;mbel) Reichel: diffusione geografica e problemi stratigrafici</article-title><source>Boll Soc Nat Napoli</source><year>1983</year><volume>9091981</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>129</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r82"><label>[82]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oma&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Doncel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torres-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alenc&#x000e1;ster</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Biostratigraphy and paleoenvironment of the Cenomanian/Turonian boundary interval based on foraminifera from W Valles&#x02013;San Luis Potos&#x000ed; Platform, Mexico</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>2012</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r83"><label>[83]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaillard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arnaud-Vanneau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Cenomanian&#x02013;Turonian transition on the Peruvian margin</article-title><source>Cretac Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/cres.1993.1041</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r84"><label>[84]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fourcade</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Origine, evolution et syst&#x000e9;matique de <italic toggle="yes">Praechubbina</italic> n. gen., foraminif&#x000e8;re Alveolinacea de Cr&#x000e9;tac&#x000e9; sup&#x000e9;rieur du Guatemala et du Mexique</article-title><source>Rev de Micropaleontol, Paris</source><year>2001</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0035-1598(01)90153-9</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r85"><label>[85]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Rhapydioninid&#x000e9;s du Campanien-Maastrichtien en region m&#x000e9;diterran&#x000e9;enne: Les genres <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Sigalveolina</italic> n. gen. et <italic toggle="yes">Cyclopseudedomia</italic></article-title><source>Carnets de G&#x000e9;ologie</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4267/2042/68382</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r86"><label>[86]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oma&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alenc&#x000e1;ster</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Late-latest Maastrichtian foraminiferal assemblage from the Angostura Platform, Chiapas, SE Mexico: biostratigraphic, paleoenvironmental and paleobiogeographic significance</article-title><source>J S Am Earth Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsames.2019.02.004</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r87"><label>[87]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Three New Tertiary Foraminiferal Genera from Florida, Saipan and Guam</part-title><source>Transactions and Proceedings of the Palaeontological Society of Japan</source><year>1967</year><comment>New Series, no.65</comment><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r88"><label>[88]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Stratigraphic and paleontologic studies of wells in Florida &#x02013; no 1</article-title><source>Florida Geological Survey</source><year>1941</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>91</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r89"><label>[89]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Micropaleontology of the Oldsmar Limestone (Eocene) of Florida</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>1957</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1484194</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r90"><label>[90]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Butterlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Microfauna del Eoceno Inferior de la Pen&#x000ed;nsula de Yucatan</article-title><source>Paleontologia Mexicana, Instituto de Geolog&#x000ed;a, Mexico</source><year>1960</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r91"><label>[91]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van den Bold</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Contribution to the study of Ostracoda with special reference to the tertiary and cretaceous microfauna of the Caribbean region</source><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>DeBussy</publisher-name><year>1946</year><size units="page">p. 167</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r92"><label>[92]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Butterlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Claves para la determinaci&#x000f3;n de macroforamin&#x000ed;feros de Mexico y del Caribe del Cretacico Superior al Mioceno Medio</source><publisher-name>Instituto Mexicano de Petr&#x000f3;leo</publisher-name><year>1981</year><volume>p. 29</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r93"><label>[93]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>P&#x000ea;cheux</surname><given-names>MJF</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Le Senonien superieur-Tertiaire du Chiapas (S.E. Mexique) et ses Macroforaminiferes</source><comment>These 3<sup>e</sup> Cycle, Univ. Nice</comment><year>1984</year><size units="page">p. 154</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r94"><label>[94]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fourcade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Un nouvel Alveolinidae du Pal&#x000e9;oc&#x000e8;ne &#x02013; Eocene inf&#x000e9;rieur du Mexique. Ses affinit&#x000e9;s avec les genres <italic toggle="yes">Murciella</italic> et <italic toggle="yes">Yaberinella</italic></article-title><source>Rev Micropal&#x000e9;ontol</source><year>1987</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>110</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r95"><label>[95]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Larger foraminiferal biostratigraphy, systematics and paleoenvironments of the Avon Park Formation and Ocala Limestone, Highlands County, Florida</source><publisher-name>Florida International University, ProQuest Dissertations Publishing</publisher-name><year>2010</year><fpage>3447806</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r96"><label>[96]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fentona</surname><given-names>JPG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casas-Gallegoa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Novaka</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Rodr&#x000ed;gueza</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ceteana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>The biostratigraphic record of Cretaceous to Paleogene tectono-eustatic relative sea-level change in Jamaica</article-title><source>J South Am Earth Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsames.2018.06.011</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r97"><label>[97]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Some larger foraminifera from the Eocene limestones at Red Gal Ring, Jamaica</article-title><source>Verh Naturforsch Ges Basel</source><year>1974</year><volume>84</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r98"><label>[98]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Middle Eocene to Oligocene stratigraphy and palaeogeography in Jamaica: a window on the Nicaragua Rise (UNESCO/IUGS IGCP 393)</article-title><source>Contrib Geol UWI Mona</source><year>1999</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r99"><label>[99]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paytan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Broach</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Dating the White Limestone of Jamaica using Sr isotope stratigraphy: a progress report</article-title><source>Caribb J Earth Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r100"><label>[100]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brasier</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Fossil indicators of nutrient levels. 1: Eutrophication and climate change</article-title><source>Geol Soc Spec Publ</source><year>1995</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r101"><label>[101]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Revision of the foraminiferal genus <italic toggle="yes">Globoreticulina</italic> RAHAGHI, 1978, and of its associated fauna of larger foraminifera from the late Middle Eocene of Iran</article-title><source>Notebooks on Geology. (Brest), CG2007-A06</source><year>2007</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4267/2042/9213</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r102"><label>[102]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berggren</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prothero</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group><part-title>Eocene&#x02013;Oligocene climatic and biotic evolution: an overview</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Prothero</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berggren</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Eocene&#x02013;oligocene climatic and biotic evolution</source><publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name><year>1992</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r103"><label>[103]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Oceanic gateways as a critical factor to initiate icehouse earth</article-title><source>J Geol Soc London</source><year>2003</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/0016-764902-115</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r104"><label>[104]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bassi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loriga Broglio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Alveolinids and Middle-Upper Eocene boundary in Northeastern Italy (Veneto, Colli Berici)</article-title><source>J Foraminifer Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r105"><label>[105]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bassi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Di Domenico</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pignatti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abramovich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hallock</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koenen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><source>Data from: Palaeobiogeography and evolutionary patterns of the larger foraminifer Borelis de Montfort (Borelidae)</source><publisher-name>Papers in Palaeontology, Wiley Online Library</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc><year>2019</year><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5061/dryad.st65n12</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r106"><label>[106]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BouDagher-Fadel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noujaim Clark</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Stratigraphy, paleoenvironment and paleogeography of Maritime Lebanon: a key to Eastern Mediterranean Cenozoic history</article-title><source>Stratigraphy</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r107"><label>[107]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sirel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Foraminiferal description and biostratigraphy of the Bartonian, Priabonian and Oligocene shallow-water sediments of the southern and eastern Turkey</article-title><source>Rev Paleobiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>339</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r108"><label>[108]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Di Carlo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Accordi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pignatti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Biostratigraphic analysis of Paleogene lowstand wedge conglomerates of a tectonically active platform margin (Zakynthos Islands, Greece)</article-title><source>J Mediterr Earth Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3304/JMES.2010.004</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r109"><label>[109]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Biostratigraphic remarks on the Caltavuturo Formation (Eocene-Oligocene) cropping out at Portella Colla (Madonie Mts., Sicily)</article-title><source>Rev Pal&#x000e9;obiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>216</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r110"><label>[110]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bassi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Facies and coralline algae from Oligocene limestones in the Malaguide Complex (SE Spain)</article-title><source>Ann Nat Hist Wien Ser A</source><year>2011</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>308</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r111"><label>[111]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Structural elements and stratigraphic distribution of larger Miliolids in the foraminiferal family Fabulariidae</article-title><source>Rev Pal&#x000e9;obiol</source><year>1988</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r112"><label>[112]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x00106;osovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Palaeobiogeography of the Late Cretaceous to Paleogene larger miliolids from tropical to subtropical sea belts (Neotethys to Caribbean)</article-title><source>Bull Soc g&#x000e9;ol Fr</source><year>2009</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r113"><label>[113]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Serra-Kiel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vicedo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Razin</surname><given-names>Ph</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gr&#x000e9;laud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Selandian-Thanetian larger foraminifera from the lower Jafnayn Formation in the Sayq area (eastern Oman Mountains)</article-title><source>Geol Acta</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1344/GeologicaActa2016.14.3.7</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r114"><label>[114]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drobne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Periloculina dalmatina</italic>, a new trematophorid miliolid from the Cuisian of Jugoslavia</article-title><source>Razprave 4 Razreda SAZU</source><year>1985</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r115"><label>[115]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Renema</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Larger foraminifera and their distribution patterns on the Spermonde shelf, South Sulawesi</article-title><source>Scr Geol</source><year>2002</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>263</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r116"><label>[116]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nuttall</surname><given-names>WLF</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Stratigraphy of the Laki Series (Lower Eocene) of parts of Sind and Baluchistan (India); with a Description of the Larger Foraminifera contained in those beds</article-title><source>Q J Geol Soc</source><year>1925</year><volume>81</volume><issue>1-4</issue><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/GSL.JGS.1925.081.01-04.18</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r117"><label>[117]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lunt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Larger foraminifera in Indonesian biostratigraphy, calibrated to isotopic dating</source><publisher-name>GRDC Museum Workshop on Micropaleontology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Bandung</publisher-loc><year>2004</year><size units="page">p. 109</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r118"><label>[118]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matsumaru</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Larger <italic toggle="yes">foraminifera</italic> from east Mindanao, the Philippines</article-title><source>Geol Paleontol Southeast Asia</source><year>1974</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r119"><label>[119]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The foraminifera and stratigraphy of the Melinau Limestone, Sarawak, and its importance in Tertiary correlation</article-title><source>Q J Geol Soc London</source><year>1965</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/gsjgs.121.1.0283</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r120"><label>[120]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Eocene foraminifera from Haha-Jima (Hillsborough Island)</article-title><source>J Paleontol</source><year>1947</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r121"><label>[121]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crespin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Lacazinella</italic>, a new genus of trematophore foraminifera</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>1962</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r122"><label>[122]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lunt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Biogeography of some Eocene larger foraminifera, and their application in distinguishing geological plates</article-title><source>Palaeontol Electronica</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><comment>Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="http://palaeo-electronica.org/paleo/2003_2/geo/issue2_03.htm" ext-link-type="uri">http://palaeo-electronica.org/paleo/2003_2/geo/issue2_03.htm&#x000ef;&#x000bb;&#x000bf;&#x000ef;&#x000bb;&#x000bf;&#x000ef;&#x000bb;&#x000bf;</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r123"><label>[123]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matsumaru</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A new genus of the trematophorate miliolids (Fabulariidae) from the Eocene Setogawa group, Southwest Japan</article-title><source>Trans Proc Palaeontol Soc Jpn NS</source><year>1990</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r124"><label>[124]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bassi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iryu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Palaeobiogeographic patterns of a long living monophyletic lineage: <italic toggle="yes">Lithophyllum pustulatum</italic> species group (Corallinales, Rhodophyta)</article-title><source>Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.palaeo.2009.10.003</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r125"><label>[125]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whybrow</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Dating the terminal Tethyan event. In: Meulenkamp JE, editor. <italic toggle="yes">Reconstruction of Marine Paleoenvironments</italic></article-title><source>Utrecht Micropaleontological Bulletins</source><year>1983</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r126"><label>[126]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Betzler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>First record of <italic toggle="yes">Borelis melo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Dendritina</italic> sp. in the Messinian of SE Spain (Cabo de Gata, Province Almeria)</article-title><source>Pal&#x000e4;ont Z</source><year>1997</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r127"><label>[127]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brandano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomassetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sardella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tinelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Progressive deterioration of trophic conditions in a carbonate ramp environment: the Lithothamnion Limestone, Majella Mountain (Tortonian-early Messinian, Central Apennines, Italy)</article-title><source>Palaios</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2110/palo.2015.022</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r128"><label>[128]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eames</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banner</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Fundamentals of mid-tertiary stratigraphical correlation</source><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><year>1962</year><size units="page">p. 163</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="r129"><label>[129]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bignot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guernet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Sur la pr&#x000e9;sence de <italic toggle="yes">Borelis curdica</italic> (Reichel) dans le Mioc&#x000e9;ne de l&#x02019;ile de Kos (Greece)</article-title><source>G&#x000e9;ol M&#x000e9;dit</source><year>1976</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r130"><label>[130]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buchbinder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinotti</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simantov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zilberman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Temporal and spatial relationships in Miocene reef carbonates in Israel</article-title><source>Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol</source><year>1993</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-0182(93)90154-B</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r131"><label>[131]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cahuzac</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Poignant A. Essai de biozonation de l&#x02019;Oligo-Mioc&#x000e8;ne dans les bassins europ&#x000e9;ens &#x000e0; l&#x02019;aide des grands foraminif&#x000e8;res n&#x000e9;ritiques</article-title><source>Bull Soc G&#x000e9;ol Fr</source><year>1997</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r132"><label>[132]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cicha</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>R&#x000f6;gl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x0010c;tyrok&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rupp</surname><given-names>Ch</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bajraktarevic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><source>Oligocene, miocene foraminifera of the central paratethys</source><comment>Abhandlungen der Senckenbergischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft, 549</comment><publisher-loc>Frankfurt am Main</publisher-loc><publisher-name>W. Kramer</publisher-name><year>1998</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>325</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r133"><label>[133]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>On the stratigraphical and palaeobiogeographical significance of Borelis melo melo (Fichtel &#x00026; Moll, 1798) and B. melo curdica (Reichel, 1937) (Foraminifera, Miliolida, Alveolinidae)</article-title><source>J Micropalaeontol</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r134"><label>[134]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyams</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almogi-Labin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Larger foraminifera of the southeastern Mediterranean shallow continental shelf off Israel</article-title><source>Isr J Earth Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>79</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r135"><label>[135]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katsanevakis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zenetos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Gateways to alien invasions in the European seas</article-title><source>Aquat Invasions</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3391/ai.2014.9.2.02</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r136"><label>[136]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haunold</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Piller</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Benthic foraminiferal associations in the Northern Bay of Safaga, Red Sea, Egypt</article-title><source>Mar Micropaleontol</source><year>1997</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0377-8398(96)00031-X</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r137"><label>[137]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Von R&#x000f6;gl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Palaeogeographic considerations for Mediterranean and Paratethys Seaways (oligocene to Miocene)</article-title><source>Ann Nat Hist Mus Wien</source><year>1998</year><volume>99A</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>310</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r138"><label>[138]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Biogeography of selected &#x02018;larger&#x02019; foraminifera</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>2000</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r139"><label>[139]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Larger foraminifera from Guam</article-title><source>J Paleontol</source><year>1954</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r140"><label>[140]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hottinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halicz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Recent foraminifera from the Gulf of Aqaba, Red Sea</article-title><source>SAZU</source><year>1993</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>179</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r141"><label>[141]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Larger foraminifera from Eniwetok Atoll</article-title><source>U S Geol Surv Prof Pap</source><year>1957</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r142"><label>[142]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matsumaru</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Tertiary larger foraminifera (Foraminiferida) from the Ogasawara Islands, Japan</article-title><source>Paleontol Soc Jpn Spec Pap</source><year>1996</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>239</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r143"><label>[143]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Javaux</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Illustration of modern benthic foraminifera from Bermuda and remarks on distribution in other subtropical/tropical areas</article-title><source>Palaeontologia Electronica</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>29</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r144"><label>[144]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lipps</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Foraminiferal distribution and diversity, Madang Reef and Lagoon, Papua New Guinea</article-title><source>Coral Reefs</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00338-003-0298-1</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r145"><label>[145]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>F&#x000f6;rderer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Atlas of benthic Foraminifera from coral reefs of the Raja Ampat Archipelago (Irian Jaya, Indonesia)</article-title><source>Micropaleontology</source><year>2018</year><volume>64</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>170</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r146"><label>[146]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wignall</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Lazarus taxa and fossil abundance at times of biotic crisis</article-title><source>J Geol Soc</source><year>1999</year><volume>156</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><comment> Bibcode:1999JGSoc.156.453W. Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/gsjgs.156.3.0453</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r147"><label>[147]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Tertiary foraminifera in the Tethyan, American, and Indo-Pacific Provinces. In: Adams CG, Ager, D, editors. <italic toggle="yes">Aspects of tethyan biogeography, systematics association</italic></article-title><source>London: Publication, special publication</source><year>1967</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>217</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r148"><label>[148]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Progress, problems and patterns in the biogeography of reef corals and other tropical marine organisms</article-title><source>Helgol&#x000e4;nder Meeresuntersuchungen</source><year>1988</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02366046</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r149"><label>[149]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pichezzi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Paleocene to lower Eocene larger foraminiferal assemblages from Central Italy: new remarks on biostratigraphy</article-title><source>Riv Ital Paleontol Stratigr</source><year>2018</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13130/2039-4942/9627</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="r150"><label>[150]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>&#x000d6;zcan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Less</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pignatti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>A revised suprageneric classification of American orthophragminids with emphasis on late Paleocene representatives from Jamaica and Alabama</article-title><source>J Syst Palaeontol</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1551</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><comment>Available from</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14772019.2018.1539778</pub-id><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 26 February 2021</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>