<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par28">Making democracy work will require a mass movement with durable organization and a clear focus on addressing fundamental social contradictions, capable of capturing the public imagination and channeling social antagonism to reclaim democracy from corporations. This movement must be strong enough to pressure the government to fund universal health care, renewable energy, public education, green public housing, public transportation, sustainable agriculture, food assistance, green jobs, and climate adaptation, and more, with equal access for everyone. Such policies are increasingly popular across traditional political divides, and could be more popular, but are blocked and maligned by powerful interests who work to mask systemic harms&#160;and use zero sum logics to&#160;divide working people. Constructing an economy based in economic and racial justice that operates within ecological limits requires displacing economic growth and capitalist wealth accumulation as central goals (Bellamy Foster <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2000</xref>). Capitalist growth (profit) disproportionately benefits the hyper-wealthy, while producing immense environmental destruction and waste, and is incompatible with the rapid decarbonization needed to arrest warming (Raworth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2017</xref>; Hickel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2020</xref>; Kallis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2020</xref>). The global capitalist economy was founded on colonialism, dispossession, and slavery, and requires military, prisons, and police to maintain endemic economic and racial inequality, nationally and internationally, stripping poor and racialized populations and nature of inherent rights in the quest to artificially cheapen labor and resources for capital (Bellamy Foster <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2000</xref>; Moore <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2015</xref>; Haraway et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>; Yamahtta-Taylor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">2016</xref>). The fights for economic, racial, and environmental justice, and a future where everyone fits are all intertwined.</p>