<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The mental health impacts of climate change are direct and indirect, and not all impacts are felt equally. Emerging Australian and international evidence suggests that children and young people who are directly exposed to rapid onset extreme weather events (e.g. bushfires, floods, cyclones) and slow&#8208;onset extreme weather events (e.g. droughts) are at risk of various psychological effects: feelings of fear, overwhelm, worry, distress, hopelessness and anger; stress; PTSD; depression; anxiety; phobias; panic disorder; sleep disturbances; attachment disorders; learning difficulties; substance abuse; shock and trauma symptoms; adjustment problems; behavioural problems; and, suicidal thinking.<xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref> Furthermore, level of risk may be amplified by pre&#8208; and post&#8208;disaster factors including pre&#8208;trauma circumstances such as personality and coping styles and skills; stage of development; pre&#8208;existing vulnerabilities due to Indigeneity, rurality, socio&#8208;economic status, gender, sexuality and ability; trauma&#8208;related factors such as intensity of the event and proximity and exposure to the event; post&#8208;trauma factors such as access to social support and social structure; and, environmental and family context, community disruption and violence.<xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="jpc15649-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>
</p>