<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0010">The discrepancy between the stated need for adaptation and the amount of adaptation that takes place has been explained by a dominance of technical fixes and a desire for accurate risk assessments in the adaptation discourse. There has been a tendency to neglect that adaptation is a social process in terms of values, ethics, justice, and different ways of knowing (<xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Nightingale et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Castree et al., 2014</xref>). Co-production and other participatory approaches have emerged in research on adaptation partially as a response to such criticism, and in recognizing that local and traditional knowledge matters for developing adaptation strategies (e.g., <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">Westskog et al., 2017</xref>). At the same time, the scholarly discourses on sustainable development, and increasingly on adaptation, are being shaped by the UN 2030 agenda and the 17 sustainable development goals (SDGs) and the associated targets and indicators. The SDGs are the latest attempt by the UN to shape the global development agenda, following the Local Agenda 21 and then the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs). The SDGs are designed to represent the full range of sustainability issues on a global scale, and every country&#8212;rich and poor&#8212;is urged to address and achieve them. Climate change-related challenges are addressed in SDG 13, with several targets tied to adaptation. SDG 13.1 calls for &#8220;[s]trengthen[ing] resilience and adaptive capacity to climate-related hazards and natural disasters in all countries&#8221;; SDG 13.2 calls for the &#8220;institutionalization of mitigation and adaptation,&#8221; and SDG 13.2 for &#8220;improv[ing] education, awareness-raising and human and institutional capacity on climate change mitigation, adaptation, impact reduction and early warning&#8221;. In addition, efforts and measures to achieve other and potentially conflicting SDGs will likely create synergies and/or tradeoffs for the SDG 13 targets related to adaptation. Furthermore, the SDGs and the targets need to be localized, contextualized, and adapted for successful implementation in local and regional governance agendas (<xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">GTLRG, 2016</xref>). This is also made clear by the UN. Unmasking the tradeoffs and synergies, based on broad stakeholder participation, will likely allow for a more successful implementation of the SDGs (<xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">GTLRG, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">Nilsson et al., 2018</xref>). However, there are major challenges associated with implementing the SDGs, including a lack of knowledge about how this should or could be done (<xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">Nilsson et al., 2018</xref>). In addition, there is limited focus on the role of participatory approaches and knowledge co-production in such processes (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Glass and Newig, 2019</xref>). Given the need for participation and user involvement in localizing the SDG targets for adaptation and for resolving tradeoffs and synergies, there is a need for systematizing knowledge about how processes of co-production may contribute.</p>