<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Primary care is the first point of contact intended to provide comprehensive and coordinated health services; growing climate-related stresses could create breaking-point conditions on such care and affect key parts of primary care services such as facilities, human resources and supply chains.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> The health response to the climate crisis will be delivered by primary health-care workers, who are equally affected by climate-related threats to housing, food prices, exposure to extreme weather events and vector- and waterborne diseases.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Primary care providers must contribute to both climate change adaptation and mitigation via preventive and promotive health measures (such as healthy diets) and integrated health services.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> For example, in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, nurses and their associations across all levels are addressing climate change by raising awareness and calling for greater climate justice as well as advocating for and implementing climate adaptation and mitigation strategies.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> The National Health Service recently announced its goal to become net carbon zero by 2040. While professional associations can make positive changes and create awareness, many aspects of climate change adaptation and mitigation can only be addressed by national and subnational policy-makers, for example in the way that health facilities and workers consume energy and food, and use transport and logistics to procure supplies. In terms of mitigation, policy-makers (especially in high-income, high-carbon emitting countries) could move towards local procurement of supplies to reduce the carbon footprint from transport, orient health facility-based food services towards more locally produced plant-based diets and use renewable energy. In terms of adaptation (especially in low- and middle-income countries that are likely to be most affected by climate change), policy-makers must anticipate likely local disruptions, both in terms of health needs and the ability to deliver them. Policy-makers must also plan for these disruptions in every aspect of primary care and public health interventions.</p>