<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par30">The European Union (EU) ETS is particularly relevant to this paper, given that it is set to include maritime transport from 2023. The EU ETS was established in 2003 and has proceeded through several periods: 2005&#8211;7, 2008&#8211;12, 2013&#8211;2020, and the current period will run 2021&#8211;2030. While strengths identified included simply establishing the system, the plans to steadily reduce the cap and the earning of &#8364;17bn in auctions during 2012&#8211;2016 to spend on carbon reduction (Narassimhan et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2018</xref>), the majority of issues highlighted in previous studies have been negative. These include the fact that it only covers 50% of EU emissions, the allocation of far too many free permits that amounted to a windfall of billions of euros for emitters such as power companies, trades of permits for profit and financialisation of the system, the collapse of the carbon price in 2013, and many instances of fraud (Corporate Europe Observatory, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2014</xref>; Lohmann, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2010</xref>; Narassimhan et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2018</xref>; Vlachou &amp; Pantelias, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2016</xref>). Larger structural issues concerned the fact that in the first and second phases, in which emission allowances were determined bottom-up from each country, and 97% of permits were given for free, which they could then sell, the result was a large transfer of wealth to these large emitters (Moore &amp; Jordan, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2020</xref>), which amounted to continued subsidies to polluters which disincentivised emissions reduction (Corporate Europe Observatory, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2014</xref>). Some studies suggest that the EU ETS saved 1.2 billion tonnes of CO<sub>2</sub> between 2008 and 2016, amounting to 3.8% of EU emissions (Bayer &amp; Acklin, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020</xref>), while others claim that such reductions were not due to the ETS but to the global financial crisis and existing regulations (e.g. engine standards) (Corporate Europe Observatory, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2014</xref>). The EU ETS carbon price dropped to its lowest value of &#8364;2.81 per tonne of carbon in 2013 due to oversupply of free permits but recovered after the 2018 reform and anticipation of stricter caps in the future to reach over &#8364;50 for the first time in 2021.</p>