<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par8">In three key respects, the Covid-19 pandemic and the climate crisis seemed to unfold in different ways, which, at first sight, may help to explain divergent threat perceptions and responses. First, with respect to climate change, it is often argued that the effects of the ongoing temperature rise unfold gradually over a longer period of time due to the inertia of the climate system (Victor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2011</xref>, p. 40). Future generations will thus be much more affected by current political decisions than people living today. This may be especially true for inhabitants of the northern hemisphere, who have been much less severely impacted so far. In contrast, the emergence of SARS-CoV-2 type occurred in the form of a sudden rupture, following its rapid spread across a globalized planet. The dangers quickly became omnipresent in the media through images of ventilated patients in overcrowded hospitals, and were later felt by many in their own lives as well. Second, and relatedly, the effects are distributed unevenly in geographical terms. While societies in the global North are less affected by the consequences of the global rise in temperature and are potentially better able to adapt to it because of greater material resources, global warming affects societies in the global South much more severely. Some Pacific Island states are even threatened in their very existence (Fletcher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2009</xref>). In the case of the Covid-19 pandemic, the situation was just the opposite: After the virus spread in China and Iran, Europe, at a very early stage, became the epicenter of the pandemic. Malm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2020</xref>, pp. 20&#8211;23) regards this as a reason for the decisive action taken by Western governments, which they are lacking in the case of the climate crisis. Third, the effects of the climate crisis take very different forms, such as extreme weather, the decline of habitable conditions and fertile soils, and the destruction of entire ecosystems on land and in the sea. It is impossible to point a finger at the multifaceted phenomenon of the climate crisis. Literary scholar and publicist Timothy Morton coined the term &#8216;hyperobjects&#8217; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2013</xref>) for phenomena that span time and space to such an extent that they are difficult for humans to fully understand or experience. A new virus causing a particular pandemically spreading disease, by contrast, is much more tangible.</p>