<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0025">The main goal of sustainability sciences and adaptation research is for scientific knowledge to result in action and policy change. The failure of the so-called &#8220;linear science to policy model&#8221; to solve complex societal challenges has led to various approaches for increasing the usability of research-based knowledge through the engagement of other knowledge holders and users. Co-production has become the dominant model for such processes (<xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Mach et al., 2020</xref>), but there are other related participatory approaches, such as &#8220;mode 2 knowledge production&#8221; (<xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Gibbons, 1994</xref>), post-normal science (<xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Funtowicz and Ravetz, 1994</xref>), and boundary work (<xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Gieryn, 1983</xref>). There are several definitions, applications, and understandings of the co-production of knowledge, primarily falling into two groups. The first and most widely applied understanding of co-production of knowledge efforts is when scientists and stakeholders deliberately collaborate to produce useful knowledge. This aligns well with the abovementioned objectives and with the works of Maria Carmen Lemos and colleagues (<xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Dilling and Lemos, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Lemos, 2015</xref>). The second application is associated with Sheila <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Jasanoff (2004)</xref> and other scholars in the field of science technology studies (STS) and pertains to the co-production of social order that takes place when new knowledge emerges. In their review of co-production in climate research, Bremer and Meisch call the Jasanoff interpretation of co-production a descriptive lens, while the normative lens refer to approaches where co-production is deliberately facilitated to instigate action (2017). We acknowledge that the co-production of knowledge, in any shape or form, is not without challenges and pitfalls, but this discussion is beyond the scope of this paper.</p>