<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="p0035">A substantial body of literature about researcher-stakeholder collaborations applies the terms &#8220;participatory methods&#8221; or &#8220;participatory approaches.&#8221; The purpose is to include stakeholders and knowledge users and holders in the research process, not as study objects, but as active co-producers of knowledge (<xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Cvitanovic et al., 2019</xref>). The terms are nearly identical to the normative interpretation of co-production (e.g., <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Cvitanovic et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">Turnhout et al., 2020</xref>). However, there is a distinction in the literature between co-production of knowledge approaches where the intended outcome is usable knowledge, and processes of co-production that aim for system change or change in practices as part of the process (e.g., <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Mach et al., 2020</xref>). The latter approach would rely on interventions in the system of interest, mostly in the form of action research (e.g., <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Kindon et al., 2007</xref>), but also labs, policy dialogue platforms, and citizen science approaches may take the form of interventions and instigate system or policy change as part of a co-production process. The outcome of such processes is thus both usable knowledge and system change. We, therefore, designate these types of co-production approaches as &#8220;co-production interventions.&#8221; Inspired by <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Mach and colleagues (2020)</xref>, we categorize processes of co-production for adaptation and the SDGs based on the model below&#8212;on a scale from &#8220;applied research&#8221;&#8212;using co-production to produce usable knowledge for &#8220;transformative co-production interventions&#8221; that lead to system or policy change. <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> illustrates the methods for co-production found in this review on a scale from applied research to transformative co-production interventions.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Methods of co-production found in the corpus with the least interventionist approaches to the left and the most interventionist to the right.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p>