<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The principal intent of this study is to add to the understanding of the dynamic nature of inequitable urban thermal exposure. As of summer 2022, there were no readily available studies investigating this issue through time. The aforementioned cross-sectional studies are very important and shed light on the significant disparity in urban temperature exposure in the U.S. However, a major limitation is they are &#8220;snapshots&#8221; in time. Longitudinal examinations allow for the investigation of trends in the data and offer further validity of observations through a number of temporal periods. Such an investigation can offer clues to whether or not these thermal exposure inequities are increasing or decreasing through time. Furthermore, longitudinal investigations that contain an element of space (or geography) require complex methodologies that can account for spatial and temporal autocorrelation within the data, considerations of which methods such as ordinary least squares regression cannot account for. Methodological techniques must account for spatial, temporal and spatial&#8211;temporal interactions. There are often high degrees of spatial structure or spatial autocorrelation (a grouping or clustering of similar values) within these types of data. Similarly, the temporal structure can exist from one time period to the next. There may even be structures in neighboring areas during a previous temporal period that interact through space and time. Such interactions, when not accounted for, can lead to a number of issues (it is also often interesting to explore these interconnections). Potential issues include the inflation of variance that can impact coefficients, leading to erroneous calculations of statistical significance. Bayesian hierarchical spatial temporal methods can account for these considerations in a robust and elegant manner. These techniques are often employed in disease mapping studies and the procedure outlined in the methods section is primed, with some procedural modifications, for the inclusion of heat health data and should allow future investigators to modify the technique with the inclusion of such data.</p>