<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par13">Not only these risks ranked highly on the likelihood and impact scales, all five environmental risks have direct (e.g., failures of climate change mitigation and adaptation) and/or indirect (e.g., extreme weather events and temperatures) linkages to climate change (Martin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2018</xref>). Similarly, if one were to look at the six transformations that are needed to achieve the SDGs as highlighted (see Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) in the Stockholm Resilience Centre report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2018</xref>), one can see to what degree the conceptualization of climate change and environment/sustainable development domains has been blurred. In terms of conceptualizing global solutions, it is very difficult to see what meaningful differences exist between the climate change and the broader SDG domain.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Six transformations needed to achieve the UN sustainable development goals</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">&#9679; Sustainable development is a societal rather than an environmental challenge</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#9679; Responsible consumption and production cut across several of the other transitions so adopting some sort of a circular economy approach and reducing demand is important</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#9679; It is possible to decarbonize the energy system around 2050 while providing clean and affordable energy for all, including through energy efficiency, more renewables, and electrification</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#9679; Achieving access to nutritional food and clean water for all, while protecting the biosphere and the oceans, requires more efficient and sustainable food systems</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#9679; Transforming our settlement patterns will benefit the majority of the world population&#8212;such as through &#8220;smart&#8221; infrastructure, decent housing, and high connectivity</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#9679; Science, technology, and innovations is a powerful driver, but the direction of change needs to support sustainable development. In particular, much depends on the way the world will put the information technology revolution to use</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Source: Adapted from Stockholm Resilience Centre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2018</xref>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>