<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par25">Studies on decoupling factor methods have become relatively popular in the extant literature. Some researchers established new methods for decoupling, whereas others directly used Tapio&#8217;s decoupling factor. For instance, based on the LMDI approach, Song and Zhang (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2017</xref>) developed a new decoupling method to examine the link between energy-deriving factors and energy-saving factors. The researchers used China&#8217;s energy use as a case study to test the new method. Zhang et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2017</xref>) also analyzed China as a case study; however, they tested the possible decoupling between CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and GDP instead of the decoupling between energy use and GDP. The researchers reported that China&#8217;s dependence on coal for primary energy consumption reduced its potential to have a strong decoupling between CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and GDP. Recent studies have focused on economic sectors, such as residential buildings and transport (Zhang and Bai, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2018</xref>; Song et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>). Zhang and Bai (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2018</xref>) used Tapio&#8217;s decoupling factor to examine the decoupling state of residential energy use in Shandong province, China, for the period between 1995 and 2013. On the other hand, Song et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>) focused on China&#8217;s transport sector and reported that related CO<sub>2</sub> emissions have some mitigation potential. Song et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2019</xref>) reached this conclusion using the LMDI approach and the decoupling factor. Another interesting study combined gravity movement and Tapio&#8217;s decoupling for the analysis of global-level energy-related CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (Zhang and Song, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2019</xref>). The researchers concluded that strong decoupling was rarely observed in developing nations over the 2010&#8211;2015 period. Finally,&#160;Zhang et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2020</xref>)&#160;proposed a new two-dimensional decoupling model to evaluate the decoupling state of the energy footprint of 39 countries for the period between 1995 and 2014. The results of the study demonstrated that 57% of the countries exhibited weak decoupling between energy footprint and GDP, whereas the proportion of countries with a strong decoupling stage was 36%.</p>