<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">This decade, the world is facing structural environmental and socioeconomic challenges. Together, these fundamental challenges, overlayed with wars and conflicts, as well as increased pandemic risks, will shape population health, the structure and function of the Earth&#8217;s natural systems, and the trend of growing economic and health inequities. The health and social care workforce (health workforce) can play a vital role in tackling these challenges (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">WHO Commission on the Social Determinants of Health, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2021b</xref>). Over a decade ago, the World Health Organization&#8217;s (WHO) global Commission on Social Determinants of Health recommended the development of a health workforce &#8216;that is trained in the social determinants of health&#8217; (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">WHO Commission on the Social Determinants of Health, 2008</xref>) and in an understanding of how health inequities are created. Since then, the knowledge on social determinants and health equity has expanded, as has the evidence on the health impacts of environmental pollution that are damaging simultaneously population and planetary health. While the Commission&#8217;s main recommendations are still relevant today, there is little sign that the Commission&#8217;s central messages on the actions needed to promote population health and reduce health inequities have been well implemented. On the contrary, health inequities are increasing in many instances and life expectancies are declining in some countries (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Vos <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). While the problem of increasing health inequities cannot solely be blamed entirely on poor education and training on the social determinants of health and health equity, having a well-trained health workforce is essential if we are to realize the Commission&#8217;s goal of closing the health inequities gap in a generation.</p>