<notes xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><fn-group><fn fn-type="participating-researchers"><p><?igo-nc?>Contributors and sources:<?igo-nc?> This article draws from the work of the background paper, &#8220;Adolescent well-being and the climate crisis,&#8221; which was one of a series of background papers on adolescent wellbeing, commissioned by the Partnership for Maternal, Newborn and Child Health (PMNCH). AMcG is a health and climate change expert. She was programme manager of the Lancet Countdown: Tracking Progress on Health and Climate Change and is coauthor of its reports and other research articles. GG works on the intersection between climate change and women&#8217;s, children&#8217;s, and adolescents&#8217; wellbeing and rights. She is an advocate and researcher within climate youth networks including YOUNGO, the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change youth constituency. VG works at the interface of mental health, psychosocial wellbeing, and climate change. She supports research activities at the MHPSS Collaborative (hosted by Save the Children Denmark). CN is a Rwandan medical doctor and global health expert focusing on climate health advocacy, particularly to do with air pollution and non-communicable diseases. ST is an intern doctor at Tribhuvan University Teaching Hospital, Kathmandu, with a keen interest in climate health. FB is a leading physician, public health professional, and advocate for the health and human rights of women, children, adolescents, and elderly people. She is vice president of Fondation Botnar and is the former assistant director general for family, women&#8217;s, and children&#8217;s health for the World Health Organization. AC is a paediatrician and co-chair of the Lancet Countdown on Health and Climate Change and led the development of Children in All Policies 2030. AMcG is the guarantor.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Competing interests: We have read and understood the BMJ policy on declaration of interests and have no interests to declare.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Provenance and peer review: Commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>This article is part of collection proposed by the Partnership for Maternal Newborn and Child Health. Open access fees are funded by the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation. <italic toggle="yes">The BMJ</italic> commissioned, peer reviewed, edited, and made the decision to publish these articles. Emma Veitch was the lead editor for <italic toggle="yes">The BMJ</italic>.</p></fn></fn-group></notes>