<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="Par17">Additionally, measures to reduce wealth inequality are urgently required, including reforms to ensure that taxes, prices and incentive systems consider the actual ecological and social costs of current consumption patterns (Ripple et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2017</xref>). The argument for large-scale mobilisation of public sector resources is also now overwhelming, given the scale of emissions reductions required over the coming 2 decades. Green New Deal (GND) ideas propose to achieve an ecological restructuring of the economy through sustained investment (Bauhardt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2014</xref>). Central to GND concepts are a commitment to radical economic restructuring and investment in the public realm at scale (Galvin and Healy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2020</xref>), required to deliver the large-scale, expensive and systemwide infrastructure required for a no carbon economy. Newell and Simms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>) argue that an imperative to mobilise finance, both public and private, is &#8220;almost a given&#8221; when considering socio-technical transitions. We argue that a massive investment effort is required to deliver a no-carbon socio-technical regime, including, renewable energy technologies developed at sufficient scale to deliver decarbonized electricity grids; public transport networks which displace reliance on private motor vehicles; so-called green infrastructure, land-use reserved for biodiversity and ecosystem services; dedicated forestry for carbon sequestration; investment in adaptation and climate resilience infrastructure, including for instance flood defence schemes; R&amp;D investment in sustainable and resilient agri-food systems; and at a fundamental level, investment in the so-called low hanging fruit of building retrofit and energy efficiency measures. GND ideas are not without precedent. As argued by Newell and Simms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2021</xref>) &#8220;historically states have played a key role in managing adaptations to external shocks or re-wiring their economies in line with shifting domestic needs and global demands within short periods of time&#8221;. If designed appropriately, GND based policies can accelerate sustainability transitions, within a context of social protection (Allam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2022</xref>). The post-Covid rebuild therefore needs to keep sight of the pressing imperatives of the climate crisis, just transitions and the no carbon economy when designing stimulus packages.</p>