<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The various axes of inequality, such as social class, gender, age, ethnicity and geographical origin or place of residence, among others, as well as their intersections, stratify society, creating hierarchies of power between different social groups. These unequal power relations have repercussions on modes of life of different social groups which are related to: (1) higher or lower GHG emissions; and (2) greater or lesser access to social and material resources that affect a person&#8217;s chances of enjoying good health and ability to adapt to climate change and avoid its health impacts. For example, people with more economic resources have a larger ecological footprint due to, among other things, greater use of air and private land transport or greater consumerism and waste generation [<xref rid="B42-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="B43-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. At the same time, however, it is the people with the least social and economic resources who are most exposed to the effects of climate change and who face the greatest difficulties in adapting to and recovering from these effects. For example, Mediterranean cities are characterised by old housing stock and low energy efficiency. In Barcelona, people from the most disadvantaged social classes have been found to live in dwellings with poorer housing conditions and experience more energy poverty [<xref rid="B44-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. This increases their exposure to rising temperatures and heat waves and reduces their capacity to adapt. Contextual factors of the neighbourhood of residence such as urban planning also have an impact on people&#8217;s health. In Haifa, the greatest exposure to heat and heat waves is downtown because it is hotter due to the topography, but also because it is home to the most deprived neighbourhoods, where there are fewer trees, the heat island effect is greater, and there is more energy poverty [<xref rid="B45-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Adaptive interventions through urban greening in compact cities such as those in the Mediterranean are essential, but they must be prevented from leading to further gentrification and creating new dynamics of exclusion [<xref rid="B46-ijerph-19-12764" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</p>